Genesis 1

1 In the beginning of God's preparing the heavens and the earth--

2 the earth hath existed waste and void, and darkness [is] on the face of the deep, and the Spirit of God fluttering on the face of the waters,

3 and God saith, `Let light be;' and light is.

4 And God seeth the light that [it is] good, and God separateth between the light and the darkness,

5 and God calleth to the light `Day,' and to the darkness He hath called `Night;' and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day one.

6 And God saith, `Let an expanse be in the midst of the waters, and let it be separating between waters and waters.'

7 And God maketh the expanse, and it separateth between the waters which [are] under the expanse, and the waters which [are] above the expanse: and it is so.

8 And God calleth to the expanse `Heavens;' and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day second.

9 And God saith, `Let the waters under the heavens be collected unto one place, and let the dry land be seen:' and it is so.

10 And God calleth to the dry land `Earth,' and to the collection of the waters He hath called `Seas;' and God seeth that [it is] good.

11 And God saith, `Let the earth yield tender grass, herb sowing seed, fruit-tree (whose seed [is] in itself) making fruit after its kind, on the earth:' and it is so.

12 And the earth bringeth forth tender grass, herb sowing seed after its kind, and tree making fruit (whose seed [is] in itself) after its kind; and God seeth that [it is] good;

13 and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day third.

14 And God saith, `Let luminaries be in the expanse of the heavens, to make a separation between the day and the night, then they have been for signs, and for seasons, and for days and years,

15 and they have been for luminaries in the expanse of the heavens to give light upon the earth:' and it is so.

16 And God maketh the two great luminaries, the great luminary for the rule of the day, and the small luminary--and the stars--for the rule of the night;

17 and God giveth them in the expanse of the heavens to give light upon the earth,

18 and to rule over day and over night, and to make a separation between the light and the darkness; and God seeth that [it is] good;

19 and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day fourth.

20 And God saith, `Let the waters teem with the teeming living creature, and fowl let fly on the earth on the face of the expanse of the heavens.'

21 And God prepareth the great monsters, and every living creature that is creeping, which the waters have teemed with, after their kind, and every fowl with wing, after its kind, and God seeth that [it is] good.

22 And God blesseth them, saying, `Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the waters in the seas, and the fowl let multiply in the earth:'

23 and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day fifth.

24 And God saith, `Let the earth bring forth the living creature after its kind, cattle and creeping thing, and beast of the earth after its kind:' and it is so.

25 And God maketh the beast of the earth after its kind, and the cattle after their kind, and every creeping thing of the ground after its kind, and God seeth that [it is] good.

26 And God saith, `Let Us make man in Our image, according to Our likeness, and let them rule over fish of the sea, and over fowl of the heavens, and over cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that is creeping on the earth.'

27 And God prepareth the man in His image; in the image of God He prepared him, a male and a female He prepared them.

28 And God blesseth them, and God saith to them, `Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the earth, and subdue it, and rule over fish of the sea, and over fowl of the heavens, and over every living thing that is creeping upon the earth.'

29 And God saith, `Lo, I have given to you every herb sowing seed, which [is] upon the face of all the earth, and every tree in which [is] the fruit of a tree sowing seed, to you it is for food;

30 and to every beast of the earth, and to every fowl of the heavens, and to every creeping thing on the earth, in which [is] breath of life, every green herb [is] for food:' and it is so.

31 And God seeth all that He hath done, and lo, very good; and there is an evening, and there is a morning--day the sixth.

Genesis 2

1 And the heavens and the earth are completed, and all their host;

2 and God completeth by the seventh day His work which He hath made, and ceaseth by the seventh day from all His work which He hath made.

3 And God blesseth the seventh day, and sanctifieth it, for in it He hath ceased from all His work which God had prepared for making.

4 These [are] births of the heavens and of the earth in their being prepared, in the day of Jehovah God's making earth and heavens;

5 and no shrub of the field is yet in the earth, and no herb of the field yet sprouteth, for Jehovah God hath not rained upon the earth, and a man there is not to serve the ground,

6 and a mist goeth up from the earth, and hath watered the whole face of the ground.

7 And Jehovah God formeth the man--dust from the ground, and breatheth into his nostrils breath of life, and the man becometh a living creature.

8 And Jehovah God planteth a garden in Eden, at the east, and He setteth there the man whom He hath formed;

9 and Jehovah God causeth to sprout from the ground every tree desirable for appearance, and good for food, and the tree of life in the midst of the garden, and the tree of knowledge of good and evil.

10 And a river is going out from Eden to water the garden, and from thence it is parted, and hath become four chief [rivers];

11 the name of the one [is] Pison, it [is] that which is surrounding the whole land of the Havilah where the gold [is],

12 and the gold of that land [is] good, there [is] the bdolach and the shoham stone;

13 and the name of the second river [is] Gibon, it [is] that which is surrounding the whole land of Cush;

14 and the name of the third river [is] Hiddekel, it [is] that which is going east of Asshur; and the fourth river is Phrat.

15 And Jehovah God taketh the man, and causeth him to rest in the garden of Eden, to serve it, and to keep it.

16 And Jehovah God layeth a charge on the man, saying, `Of every tree of the garden eating thou dost eat;

17 and of the tree of knowledge of good and evil, thou dost not eat of it, for in the day of thine eating of it--dying thou dost die.'

18 And Jehovah God saith, `Not good for the man to be alone, I do make to him an helper--as his counterpart.'

19 And Jehovah God formeth from the ground every beast of the field, and every fowl of the heavens, and bringeth in unto the man, to see what he doth call it; and whatever the man calleth a living creature, that [is] its name.

20 And the man calleth names to all the cattle, and to fowl of the heavens, and to every beast of the field; and to man hath not been found an helper--as his counterpart.

21 And Jehovah God causeth a deep sleep to fall upon the man, and he sleepeth, and He taketh one of his ribs, and closeth up flesh in its stead.

22 And Jehovah God buildeth up the rib which He hath taken out of the man into a woman, and bringeth her in unto the man;

23 and the man saith, `This [is] the [proper] step! bone of my bone, and flesh of my flesh!' for this it is called Woman, for from a man hath this been taken;

24 therefore doth a man leave his father and his mother, and hath cleaved unto his wife, and they have become one flesh.

25 And they are both of them naked, the man and his wife, and they are not ashamed of themselves.

Genesis 4

1 And the man knew Eve his wife, and she conceiveth and beareth Cain, and saith, `I have gotten a man by Jehovah;'

2 and she addeth to bear his brother, even Abel. And Abel is feeding a flock, and Cain hath been servant of the ground.

3 And it cometh to pass at the end of days that Cain bringeth from the fruit of the ground a present to Jehovah;

4 and Abel, he hath brought, he also, from the female firstlings of his flock, even from their fat ones; and Jehovah looketh unto Abel and unto his present,

5 and unto Cain and unto his present He hath not looked; and it is very displeasing to Cain, and his countenance is fallen.

6 And Jehovah saith unto Cain, `Why hast thou displeasure? and why hath thy countenance fallen?

7 Is there not, if thou dost well, acceptance? and if thou dost not well, at the opening a sin-offering is crouching, and unto thee its desire, and thou rulest over it.'

8 And Cain saith unto Abel his brother, [`Let us go into the field;'] and it cometh to pass in their being in the field, that Cain riseth up against Abel his brother, and slayeth him.

9 And Jehovah saith unto Cain, `Where [is] Abel thy brother?' and he saith, `I have not known; my brother's keeper--I?'

10 And He saith, `What hast thou done? the voice of thy brother's blood is crying unto Me from the ground;

11 and now, cursed [art] thou from the ground, which hath opened her mouth to receive the blood of thy brother from thy hand;

12 when thou tillest the ground, it doth not add to give its strength to thee--a wanderer, even a trembling one, thou art in the earth.'

13 And Cain saith unto Jehovah, `Greater is my punishment than to be borne;

14 lo, Thou hast driven me to-day from off the face of the ground, and from Thy face I am hid; and I have been a wanderer, even a trembling one, in the earth, and it hath been--every one finding me doth slay me.'

15 And Jehovah saith to him, `Therefore--of any slayer of Cain sevenfold it is required;' and Jehovah setteth to Cain a token that none finding him doth slay him.

16 And Cain goeth out from before Jehovah, and dwelleth in the land, moving about east of Eden;

17 and Cain knoweth his wife, and she conceiveth, and beareth Enoch; and he is building a city, and he calleth the name of the city, according to the name of his son--Enoch.

18 And born to Enoch is Irad; and Irad hath begotten Mehujael; and Mehujael hath begotten Methusael; and Methusael hath begotten Lamech.

19 And Lamech taketh to himself two wives, the name of the one Adah, and the name of the second Zillah.

20 And Adah beareth Jabal, he hath been father of those inhabiting tents and purchased possessions;

21 and the name of his brother [is] Jubal, he hath been father of every one handling harp and organ.

22 And Zillah she also bare Tubal-Cain, an instructor of every artificer in brass and iron; and a sister of Tubal-Cain [is] Naamah.

23 And Lamech saith to his wives: --`Adah and Zillah, hear my voice; Wives of Lamech, give ear [to] my saying: For a man I have slain for my wound, Even a young man for my hurt;

24 For sevenfold is required for Cain, And for Lamech seventy and sevenfold.'

25 And Adam again knoweth his wife, and she beareth a son, and calleth his name Seth, `for God hath appointed for me another seed instead of Abel:' for Cain had slain him.

26 And to Seth, to him also a son hath been born, and he calleth his name Enos; then a beginning was made of preaching in the name of Jehovah.

Genesis 5

1 This [is] an account of the births of Adam: In the day of God's preparing man, in the likeness of God He hath made him;

2 a male and a female He hath prepared them, and He blesseth them, and calleth their name Man, in the day of their being prepared.

3 And Adam liveth an hundred and thirty years, and begetteth [a son] in his likeness, according to his image, and calleth his name Seth.

4 And the days of Adam after his begetting Seth are eight hundred years, and he begetteth sons and daughters.

5 And all the days of Adam which he lived are nine hundred and thirty years, and he dieth.

6 And Seth liveth an hundred and five years, and begetteth Enos.

7 And Seth liveth after his begetting Enos eight hundred and seven years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

8 And all the days of Seth are nine hundred and twelve years, and he dieth.

9 And Enos liveth ninety years, and begetteth Cainan.

10 And Enos liveth after his begetting Cainan eight hundred and fifteen years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

11 And all the days of Enos are nine hundred and five years, and he dieth.

12 And Cainan liveth seventy years, and begetteth Mahalaleel.

13 And Cainan liveth after his begetting Mahalaleel eight hundred and forty years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

14 And all the days of Cainan are nine hundred and ten years, and he dieth.

15 And Mahalaleel liveth five and sixty years, and begetteth Jared.

16 And Mahalaleel liveth after his begetting Jared eight hundred and thirty years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

17 And all the days of Mahalaleel are eight hundred and ninety and five years, and he dieth.

18 And Jared liveth an hundred and sixty and two years, and begetteth Enoch.

19 And Jared liveth after his begetting Enoch eight hundred years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

20 And all the days of Jared are nine hundred and sixty and two years, and he dieth.

21 And Enoch liveth five and sixty years, and begetteth Methuselah.

22 And Enoch walketh habitually with God after his begetting Methuselah three hundred years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

23 And all the days of Enoch are three hundred and sixty and five years.

24 And Enoch walketh habitually with God, and he is not, for God hath taken him.

25 And Methuselah liveth an hundred and eighty and seven years, and begetteth Lamech.

26 And Methuselah liveth after his begetting Lamech seven hundred and eighty and two years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

27 And all the days of Methuselah are nine hundred and sixty and nine years, and he dieth.

28 And Lamech liveth an hundred and eighty and two years, and begetteth a son,

29 and calleth his name Noah, saying, `This [one] doth comfort us concerning our work, and concerning the labour of our hands, because of the ground which Jehovah hath cursed.'

30 And Lamech liveth after his begetting Noah five hundred and ninety and five years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

31 And all the days of Lamech are seven hundred and seventy and seven years, and he dieth.

32 And Noah is a son of five hundred years, and Noah begetteth Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

Genesis 6

1 And it cometh to pass that mankind have begun to multiply on the face of the ground, and daughters have been born to them,

2 and sons of God see the daughters of men that they [are] fair, and they take to themselves women of all whom they have chosen.

3 And Jehovah saith, `My Spirit doth not strive in man--to the age; in their erring they [are] flesh:' and his days have been an hundred and twenty years.

4 The fallen ones were in the earth in those days, and even afterwards when sons of God come in unto daughters of men, and they have borne to them--they [are] the heroes, who, from of old, [are] the men of name.

5 And Jehovah seeth that abundant [is] the wickedness of man in the earth, and every imagination of the thoughts of his heart only evil all the day;

6 and Jehovah repenteth that He hath made man in the earth, and He grieveth Himself-- unto His heart.

7 And Jehovah saith, `I wipe away man whom I have prepared from off the face of the ground, from man unto beast, unto creeping thing, and unto fowl of the heavens, for I have repented that I have made them.'

8 And Noah found grace in the eyes of Jehovah.

9 These [are] births of Noah: Noah [is] a righteous man; perfect he hath been among his generations; with God hath Noah walked habitually.

10 And Noah begetteth three sons, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

11 And the earth is corrupt before God, and the earth is filled [with] violence.

12 And God seeth the earth, and lo, it hath been corrupted, for all flesh hath corrupted its way on the earth.

13 And God said to Noah, `An end of all flesh hath come before Me, for the earth hath been full of violence from their presence; and lo, I am destroying them with the earth.

14 `Make for thyself an ark of gopher-wood; rooms dost thou make with the ark, and thou hast covered it within and without with cypress;

15 and this [is] that which thou dost with it: three hundred cubits [is] the length of the ark, fifty cubits its breadth, and thirty cubits its height;

16 a window dost thou make for the ark, and unto a cubit thou dost restrain it from above; and the opening of the ark thou dost put in its side, --lower, second, and third [stories] dost thou make it.

17 `And I, lo, I am bringing in the deluge of waters on the earth to destroy all flesh, in which [is] a living spirit, from under the heavens; all that [is] in the earth doth expire.

18 `And I have established My covenant with thee, and thou hast come in unto the ark, thou, and thy sons, and thy wife, and thy son's wives with thee;

19 and of all that liveth, of all flesh, two of every [sort] thou dost bring in unto the ark, to keep alive with thee; male and female are they.

20 Of the fowl after its kind, and of the cattle after their kind, of every creeping thing of the ground after its kind, two of every [sort] they come in unto thee, to keep alive.

21 `And thou, take to thyself of all food that is eaten; and thou hast gathered unto thyself, and it hath been to thee and to them for food.'

22 And Noah doth according to all that God hath commanded him; so hath he done.

Genesis 8

1 And God remembereth Noah, and every living thing, and all the cattle which [are] with him in the ark, and God causeth a wind to pass over the earth, and the waters subside,

2 and closed are the fountains of the deep and the net-work of the heavens, and restrained is the shower from the heavens.

3 And turn back do the waters from off the earth, going on and returning; and the waters are lacking at the end of a hundred and fifty days.

4 And the ark resteth, in the seventh month, in the seventeenth day of the month, on mountains of Ararat;

5 and the waters have been going and becoming lacking till the tenth month; in the tenth [month], on the first of the month, appeared the heads of the mountains.

6 And it cometh to pass, at the end of forty days, that Noah openeth the window of the ark which he made,

7 and he sendeth forth the raven, and it goeth out, going out and turning back till the drying of the waters from off the earth.

8 And he sendeth forth the dove from him to see whether the waters have been lightened from off the face of the ground,

9 and the dove hath not found rest for the sole of her foot, and she turneth back unto him, unto the ark, for waters [are] on the face of all the earth, and he putteth out his hand, and taketh her, and bringeth her in unto him, unto the ark.

10 And he stayeth yet other seven days, and addeth to send forth the dove from the ark;

11 and the dove cometh in unto him at even-time, and lo, an olive leaf torn off in her mouth; and Noah knoweth that the waters have been lightened from off the earth.

12 And he stayeth yet other seven days, and sendeth forth the dove, and it added not to turn back unto him any more.

13 And it cometh to pass in the six hundredth and first year, in the first [month], in the first of the month, the waters have been dried from off the earth; and Noah turneth aside the covering of the ark, and looketh, and lo, the face of the ground hath been dried.

14 And in the second month, in the seven and twentieth day of the month, the earth hath become dry.

15 And God speaketh unto Noah, saying, `Go out from the ark, thou, and thy wife, and thy sons, and thy sons' wives with thee;

16 every living thing that [is] with thee, of all flesh, among fowl, and among cattle, and among every creeping thing which is creeping on the earth, bring out with thee;

17 and they have teemed in the earth, and been fruitful, and have multiplied on the earth.'

18 And Noah goeth out, and his sons, and his wife, and his sons' wives with him;

19 every beast, every creeping thing, and every fowl; every creeping thing on the earth, after their families, have gone out from the ark.

20 And Noah buildeth an altar to Jehovah, and taketh of every clean beast, and of every clean fowl, and causeth burnt-offerings to ascend on the altar;

21 and Jehovah smelleth the sweet fragrance, and Jehovah saith unto His heart, `I continue not to disesteem any more the ground because of man, though the imagination of the heart of man [is] evil from his youth; and I continue not to smite anymore all living, as I have done;

22 during all days of the earth, seed-time and harvest, and cold and heat, and summer and winter, and day and night, do not cease.'

Genesis 9

1 And God blesseth Noah, and his sons, and saith to them, `Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the earth;

2 and your fear and your dread is on every beast of the earth, and on every fowl of the heavens, on all that creepeth on the ground, and on all fishes of the sea--into your hand they have been given.

3 Every creeping thing that is alive, to you it is for food; as the green herb I have given to you the whole;

4 only flesh in its life--its blood--ye do not eat.

5 `And only your blood for your lives do I require; from the hand of every living thing I require it, and from the hand of man, from the hand of every man's brother I require the life of man;

6 whoso sheddeth man's blood, by man is his blood shed: for in the image of God hath He made man.

7 And ye, be fruitful and multiply, teem in the earth, and multiply in it.'

8 And God speaketh unto Noah, and unto his sons with him, saying,

9 `And I, lo, I am establishing My covenant with you, and with your seed after you,

10 and with every living creature which [is] with you, among fowl, among cattle, and among every beast of the earth with you, from all who are going out of the ark--to every beast of the earth.

11 And I have established My covenant with you, and all flesh is not any more cut off by waters of a deluge, and there is not any more a deluge to destroy the earth.'

12 And God saith, `This is a token of the covenant which I am giving between Me and you, and every living creature that [is] with you, to generations age-during;

13 My bow I have given in the cloud, and it hath been for a token of a covenant between Me and the earth;

14 and it hath come to pass (in My sending a cloud over the earth) that the bow hath been seen in the cloud,

15 and I have remembered My covenant which is between Me and you, and every living creature among all flesh, and the waters become no more a deluge to destroy all flesh;

16 and the bow hath been in the cloud, and I have seen it--to remember the covenant age-during between God and every living creature among all flesh which [is] on the earth.'

17 And God saith unto Noah, `This [is] a token of the covenant which I have established between Me and all flesh that [is] upon the earth.'

18 And the sons of Noah who are going out of the ark are Shem, and Ham, and Japheth; and Ham is father of Canaan.

19 These three [are] sons of Noah, and from these hath all the earth been overspread.

20 And Noah remaineth a man of the ground, and planteth a vineyard,

21 and drinketh of the wine, and is drunken, and uncovereth himself in the midst of the tent.

22 And Ham, father of Canaan, seeth the nakedness of his father, and declareth to his two brethren without.

23 And Shem taketh--Japheth also--the garment, and they place on the shoulder of them both, and go backward, and cover the nakedness of their father; and their faces [are] backward, and their father's nakedness they have not seen.

24 And Noah awaketh from his wine, and knoweth that which his young son hath done to him,

25 and saith: `Cursed [is] Canaan, Servant of servants he is to his brethren.'

26 And he saith: `Blessed of Jehovah my God [is] Shem, And Canaan is servant to him.

27 God doth give beauty to Japheth, And he dwelleth in tents of Shem, And Canaan is servant to him.'

28 And Noah liveth after the deluge three hundred and fifty years;

29 and all the days of Noah are nine hundred and fifty years, and he dieth.

Genesis 10

1 And these [are] births of the sons of Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth; and born to them are sons after the deluge.

2 `Sons of Japheth [are] Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.

3 And sons of Gomer [are] Ashkenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.

4 And sons of Javan [are] Elishah, and Tarshish, Kittim, and Dodanim.

5 By these have the isles of the nations been parted in their lands, each by his tongue, by their families, in their nations.

6 And sons of Ham [are] Cush, and Mitzraim, and Phut, and Canaan.

7 And sons of Cush [are] Seba, and Havilah, and Sabtah, and Raamah, and Sabtechah; and sons of Raamah [are] Sheba and Dedan.

8 And Cush hath begotten Nimrod;

9 he hath begun to be a hero in the land; he hath been a hero in hunting before Jehovah; therefore it is said, `As Nimrod the hero [in] hunting before Jehovah.'

10 And the first part of his kingdom is Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and Calneh, in the land of Shinar;

11 from that land he hath gone out to Asshur, and buildeth Nineveh, even the broad places of the city, and Calah,

12 and Resen, between Nineveh and Calah; it [is] the great city.

13 And Mitzraim hath begotten the Ludim, and the Anamim, and the Lehabim, and the Naphtuhim,

14 and the Pathrusim, and the Casluhim, (whence have come out Philistim,) and the Caphtorim.

15 And Canaan hath begotten Sidon his first-born, and Heth,

16 and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite,

17 and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite,

18 and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite; and afterwards have the families of the Canaanite been scattered.

19 And the border of the Canaanite is from Sidon, [in] thy coming towards Gerar, unto Gaza; [in] thy coming towards Sodom, and Gomorrah, and Admah, and Zeboim, unto Lasha.

20 These [are] sons of Ham, by their families, by their tongues, in their lands, in their nations.

21 As to Shem, father of all sons of Eber, brother of Japheth the elder, he hath also begotten:

22 Sons of Shem [are] Elam, and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram.

23 And sons of Aram [are] Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Mash.

24 And Arphaxad hath begotten Salah, and Salah hath begotten Eber.

25 And to Eber have two sons been born; the name of the one [is] Peleg (for in his days hath the earth been divided,) and his brother's name [is] Joktan.

26 And Joktan hath begotten Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah,

27 and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah,

28 and Obal, and Abimael, and Sheba,

29 and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab; all these [are] sons of Joktan;

30 and their dwelling is from Mesha, [in] thy coming towards Sephar, a mount of the east.

31 These [are] sons of Shem, by their families, by their tongues, in their lands, by their nations.

32 These [are] families of the sons of Noah, by their births, in their nations, and by these have the nations been parted in the earth after the deluge.

Genesis 11

1 And the whole earth is of one pronunciation, and of the same words,

2 and it cometh to pass, in their journeying from the east, that they find a valley in the land of Shinar, and dwell there;

3 and they say each one to his neighbour, `Give help, let us make bricks, and burn [them] thoroughly:' and the brick is to them for stone, and the bitumen hath been to them for mortar.

4 And they say, `Give help, let us build for ourselves a city and tower, and its head in the heavens, and make for ourselves a name, lest we be scattered over the face of all the earth.'

5 And Jehovah cometh down to see the city and the tower which the sons of men have builded;

6 and Jehovah saith, `Lo, the people [is] one, and one pronunciation [is] to them all, and this it hath dreamed of doing; and now, nothing is restrained from them of that which they have purposed to do.

7 Give help, let us go down, and mingle there their pronunciation, so that a man doth not understand the pronunciation of his companion.'

8 And Jehovah doth scatter them from thence over the face of all the earth, and they cease to build the city;

9 therefore hath [one] called its name Babel, for there hath Jehovah mingled the pronunciation of all the earth, and from thence hath Jehovah scattered them over the face of all the earth.

10 These [are] births of Shem: Shem [is] a son of an hundred years, and begetteth Arphaxad two years after the deluge.

11 And Shem liveth after his begetting Arphaxad five hundred years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

12 And Arphaxad hath lived five and thirty years, and begetteth Salah.

13 And Arphaxad liveth after his begetting Salah four hundred and three years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

14 And Salah hath lived thirty years, and begetteth Eber.

15 And Salah liveth after his begetting Eber four hundred and three years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

16 And Eber liveth four and thirty years, and begetteth Peleg.

17 And Eber liveth after his begetting Peleg four hundred and thirty years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

18 And Peleg liveth thirty years, and begetteth Reu.

19 And Peleg liveth after his begetting Reu two hundred and nine years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

20 And Reu liveth two and thirty years, and begetteth Serug.

21 And Reu liveth after his begetting Serug two hundred and seven years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

22 And Serug liveth thirty years, and begetteth Nahor.

23 And Serug liveth after his begetting Nahor two hundred years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

24 And Nahor liveth nine and twenty years, and begetteth Terah.

25 And Nahor liveth after his begetting Terah an hundred and nineteen years, and begetteth sons and daughters.

26 And Terah liveth seventy years, and begetteth Abram, Nahor, and Haran.

27 And these [are] births of Terah: Terah hath begotten Abram, Nahor, and Haran; and Haran hath begotten Lot;

28 and Haran dieth in the presence of Terah his father, in the land of his birth, in Ur of the Chaldees.

29 And Abram and Nahor take to themselves wives; the name of Abram's wife [is] Sarai, and the name of Nahor's wife [is] Milcah, daughter of Haran, father of Milcah, and father of Iscah.

30 And Sarai is barren--she hath no child.

31 And Terah taketh Abram his son, and Lot, son of Haran, his son's son, and Sarai his daughter-in-law, wife of Abram his son, and they go out with them from Ur of the Chaldees, to go towards the land of Canaan; and they come unto Charan, and dwell there.

32 And the days of Terah are two hundred and five years, and Terah dieth in Charan.

Genesis 12

1 And Jehovah saith unto Abram, `Go for thyself, from thy land, and from thy kindred, and from the house of thy father, unto the land which I shew thee.

2 And I make thee become a great nation, and bless thee, and make thy name great; and be thou a blessing.

3 And I bless those blessing thee, and him who is disesteeming thee I curse, and blessed in thee have been all families of the ground.'

4 And Abram goeth on, as Jehovah hath spoken unto him, and Lot goeth with him, and Abram [is] a son of five and seventy years in his going out from Charan.

5 And Abram taketh Sarai his wife, and Lot his brother's son, and all their substance that they have gained, and the persons that they have obtained in Charan; and they go out to go towards the land of Canaan; and they come in to the land of Canaan.

6 And Abram passeth over into the land, unto the place Shechem, unto the oak of Moreh; and the Canaanite [is] then in the land.

7 And Jehovah appeareth unto Abram, and saith, `To thy seed I give this land;' and he buildeth there an altar to Jehovah, who hath appeared unto him.

8 And he removeth from thence towards a mountain at the east of Beth-El, and stretcheth out the tent (Beth-El at the west, and Hai at the east), and he buildeth there an altar to Jehovah, and preacheth in the name of Jehovah.

9 And Abram journeyeth, going on and journeying towards the south.

10 And there is a famine in the land, and Abram goeth down towards Egypt to sojourn there, for the famine [is] grievous in the land;

11 and it cometh to pass as he hath drawn near to enter Egypt, that he saith unto Sarai his wife, `Lo, I pray thee, I have known that thou [art] a woman of beautiful appearance;

12 and it hath come to pass that the Egyptians see thee, and they have said, `This [is] his wife,' and they have slain me, and thee they keep alive:

13 say, I pray thee, thou [art] my sister, so that it is well with me because of thee, and my soul hath lived for thy sake.'

14 And it cometh to pass, at the entering of Abram into Egypt, that the Egyptians see the woman that she [is] exceeding fair;

15 and princes of Pharaoh see her, and praise her unto Pharaoh, and the woman is taken [to] Pharaoh's house;

16 and to Abram he hath done good because of her, and he hath sheep and oxen, and he-asses, and men-servants, and handmaids, and she-asses, and camels.

17 And Jehovah plagueth Pharaoh and his house--great plagues--for the matter of Sarai, Abram's wife.

18 And Pharaoh calleth for Abram, and saith, `What [is] this thou hast done to me? why hast thou not declared to me that she [is] thy wife?

19 Why hast thou said, She [is] my sister, and I take her to myself for a wife? and now, lo, thy wife, take and go.'

20 And Pharaoh chargeth men concerning him, and they send him away, and his wife, an all that he hath.

Genesis 13

1 And Abram goeth up from Egypt (he and his wife, and all that he hath, and Lot with him) towards the south;

2 and Abram [is] exceedingly wealthy in cattle, in silver, and in gold.

3 And he goeth on his journeyings from the south, even unto Bethel, unto the place where his tent had been at the commencement, between Bethel and Hai--

4 unto the place of the altar which he made there at the first, and there doth Abram preach in the name of Jehovah.

5 And also to Lot, who is going with Abram, there hath been sheep and oxen and tents;

6 and the land hath not suffered them to dwell together, for their substance hath been much, and they have not been able to dwell together;

7 and there is a strife between those feeding Abram's cattle and those feeding Lot's cattle; and the Canaanite and the Perizzite [are] then dwelling in the land.

8 And Abram saith unto Lot, `Let there not, I pray thee, be strife between me and thee, and between my shepherds and thy shepherds, for we [are] men--brethren.

9 Is not all the land before thee? be parted, I pray thee, from me; if to the left, then I to the right; and if to the right, then I to the left.'

10 And Lot lifteth up his eyes, and seeth the whole circuit of the Jordan that it [is] all a watered country (before Jehovah's destroying Sodom and Gomorrah, as Jehovah's garden, as the land of Egypt,) in thy coming toward Zoar,

11 and Lot chooseth for himself the whole circuit of the Jordan; and Lot journeyeth from the east, and they are parted--a man from his companion;

12 Abram hath dwelt in the land of Canaan, and Lot hath dwelt in the cities of the circuit, and tenteth unto Sodom;

13 and the men of Sodom [are] evil, and sinners before Jehovah exceedingly.

14 And Jehovah said unto Abram, after Lot's being parted from him, `Lift up, I pray thee, thine eyes, and look from the place where thou [art], northward, and southward, and eastward, and westward;

15 for the whole of the land which thou are seeing, to thee I give it, and to thy seed--to the age.

16 And I have set thy seed as dust of the earth, so that, if one is able to number the dust of the earth, even thy seed is numbered;

17 rise, go up and down through the land, to its length, and to its breadth, for to thee I give it.'

18 And Abram tenteth, and cometh, and dwelleth among the oaks of Mamre, which [are] in Hebron, and buildeth there an altar to Jehovah.

Genesis 14

1 And it cometh to pass in the days of Amraphel king of Shinar, Arioch king of Ellasar, Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of Goyim,

2 they have made war with Bera king of Sodom, and with Birsha king of Gomorrah, Shinab king of Admah, and Shemeber king of Zeboim, and the king of Bela, which [is] Zoar.

3 All these have been joined together unto the valley of Siddim, which [is] the Salt Sea;

4 twelve years they served Chedorlaomer, and the thirteenth year they rebelled.

5 And in the fourteenth year came Chedorlaomer, and the kings who [are] with him, and they smite the Rephaim in Ashteroth Karnaim, and the Zuzim in Ham, and the Emim in Shaveh Kiriathaim,

6 and the Horites in their mount Seir, unto El-Paran, which [is] by the wilderness;

7 and they turn back and come in unto En-Mishpat, which [is] Kadesh, and smite the whole field of the Amalekite, and also the Amorite who is dwelling in Hazezon-Tamar.

8 And the king of Sodom goeth out, and the king of Gomorrah, and the king of Admah, and the king of Zeboim, and the king of Bela, which [is] Zoar; and they set the battle in array with them in the valley of Siddim,

9 with Chedorlaomer king of Elam, and Tidal king of Goyim, and Amraphel king of Shinar, and Arioch king of Ellasar; four kings with the five.

10 And the valley of Siddim [is] full of bitumen-pits; and the kings of Sodom and Gomorrah flee, and fall there, and those left have fled to the mountain.

11 And they take the whole substance of Sodom and Gomorrah, and the whole of their food, and go away;

12 and they take Lot, Abram's brother's son (seeing he is dwelling in Sodom), and his substance, and go away.

13 And one who is escaping cometh and declareth to Abram the Hebrew, and he is dwelling among the oaks of Mamre the Amorite, brother of Eshcol, and brother of Aner, and they [are] Abram's allies.

14 And Abram heareth that his brother hath been taken captive, and he draweth out his trained domestics, three hundred and eighteen, and pursueth unto Dan.

15 And he divideth himself against them by night, he and his servants, and smiteth them, and pursueth them unto Hobah, which [is] at the left of Damascus;

16 and he bringeth back the whole of the substance, and also Lot his brother and his substance hath he brought back, and also the women and the people.

17 And the king of Sodom goeth out to meet him (after his turning back from the smiting of Chedorlaomer, and of the kings who [are] with him), unto the valley of Shaveh, which [is] the king's valley.

18 And Melchizedek king of Salem hath brought out bread and wine, and he [is] priest of God Most High;

19 and he blesseth him, and saith, `Blessed [is] Abram to God Most High, possessing heaven and earth;

20 and blessed [is] God Most High, who hath delivered thine adversaries into thy hand;' and he giveth to him a tenth of all.

21 And the king of Sodom saith unto Abram, `Give to me the persons, and the substance take to thyself,'

22 and Abram saith unto the king of Sodom, `I have lifted up my hand unto Jehovah, God Most High, possessing heaven and earth--

23 from a thread even unto a shoe-latchet I take not of anything which thou hast, that thou say not, I--I have made Abram rich;

24 save only that which the young men have eaten, and the portion of the men who have gone with me--Aner, Eshcol, and Mamre--they take their portion.'

Genesis 25

1 And Abraham addeth and taketh a wife, and her name [is] Keturah;

2 and she beareth to him Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah.

3 And Jokshan hath begotten Sheba and Dedan; and the sons of Dedan were Asshurim, and Letushim, and Leummim;

4 and the sons of Midian [are] Ephah, and Epher, and Hanoch, and Abidah, and Eldaah: all these [are] sons of Keturah.

5 And Abraham giveth all that he hath to Isaac;

6 and to the sons of the concubines whom Abraham hath, Abraham hath given gifts, and sendeth them away from Isaac his son (in his being yet alive) eastward, unto the east country.

7 And these [are] the days of the years of the life of Abraham, which he lived, a hundred and seventy and five years;

8 and Abraham expireth, and dieth in a good old age, aged and satisfied, and is gathered unto his people.

9 And Isaac and Ishmael his sons bury him at the cave of Machpelah, at the field of Ephron, son of Zoar the Hittite, which [is] before Mamre--

10 the field which Abraham bought from the sons of Heth--there hath Abraham been buried, and Sarah his wife.

11 And it cometh to pass after the death of Abraham, that God blesseth Isaac his son; and Isaac dwelleth by the Well of the Living One, my Beholder.

12 And these [are] births of Ishmael, Abraham's son, whom Hagar the Egyptian, Sarah's handmaid, hath borne to Abraham;

13 and these [are] the names of the sons of Ishmael, by their names, according to their births: first-born of Ishmael, Nebajoth; and Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,

14 and Mishma, and Dumah, and Massa,

15 Hadar, and Tema, Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah:

16 these are sons of Ishmael, and these their names, by their villages, and by their towers; twelve princes according to their peoples.

17 And these [are] the years of the life of Ishmael, a hundred and thirty and seven years; and he expireth, and dieth, and is gathered unto his people;

18 and they tabernacle from Havilah unto Shur, which [is] before Egypt, in [thy] going towards Asshur; in the presence of all his brethren hath he fallen.

19 And these [are] births of Isaac, Abraham's son: Abraham hath begotten Isaac;

20 and Isaac is a son of forty years in his taking Rebekah, daughter of Bethuel the Aramaean, from Padan-Aram, sister of Laban the Aramaean, to him for a wife.

21 And Isaac maketh entreaty to Jehovah before his wife, for she [is] barren: and Jehovah is entreated of him, and Rebekah his wife conceiveth,

22 and the children struggle together within her, and she saith, `If [it is] right--why [am] I thus?' and she goeth to seek Jehovah.

23 And Jehovah saith to her, `Two nations [are] in thy womb, and two peoples from thy bowels are parted; and the [one] people than the [other] people is stronger; and the elder doth serve the younger.'

24 And her days to bear are fulfilled, and lo, twins [are] in her womb;

25 and the first cometh out all red as a hairy robe, and they call his name Esau;

26 and afterwards hath his brother come out, and his hand is taking hold on Esau's heel, and one calleth his name Jacob; and Isaac [is] a son of sixty years in her bearing them.

27 And the youths grew, and Esau is a man acquainted [with] hunting, a man of the field; and Jacob [is] a plain man, inhabiting tents;

28 and Isaac loveth Esau, for [his] hunting [is] in his mouth; and Rebekah is loving Jacob.

29 And Jacob boileth pottage, and Esau cometh in from the field, and he [is] weary;

30 and Esau saith unto Jacob, `Let me eat, I pray thee, some of this red red thing, for I [am] weary;' therefore hath [one] called his name Edom [Red];

31 and Jacob saith, `Sell to-day thy birthright to me.'

32 And Esau saith, `Lo, I am going to die, and what is this to me--birthright?'

33 and Jacob saith, `Swear to me to-day:' and he sweareth to him, and selleth his birthright to Jacob;

34 and Jacob hath given to Esau bread and pottage of lentiles, and he eateth, and drinketh, and riseth, and goeth; and Esau despiseth the birthright.

Genesis 29

1 And Jacob lifteth up his feet, and goeth towards the land of the sons of the east;

2 and he looketh, and lo, a well in the field, and lo, there three droves of a flock crouching by it, for from that well they water the droves, and the great stone [is] on the mouth of the well.

3 (When thither have all the droves been gathered, and they have rolled the stone from off the mouth of the well, and have watered the flock, then they have turned back the stone on the mouth of the well to its place.)

4 And Jacob saith to them, `My brethren, from whence [are] ye?' and they say, `We [are] from Haran.'

5 And he saith to them, `Have ye known Laban, son of Nahor?' and they say, `We have known.'

6 And he saith to them, `Hath he peace?' and they say, `Peace; and lo, Rachel his daughter is coming with the flock.'

7 And he saith, `Lo, the day [is] still great, [it is] not time for the cattle to be gathered; water ye the flock, and go, delight yourselves.'

8 And they say, `We are not able, till that all the droves be gathered together, and they have rolled away the stone from the mouth of the well, and we have watered the flock.'

9 He is yet speaking with them, and Rachel hath come with the flock which her father hath, for she [is] shepherdess;

10 and it cometh to pass when Jacob hath seen Rachel, daughter of Laban his mother's brother, and the flock of Laban his mother's brother, that Jacob cometh nigh and rolleth the stone from off the mouth of the well, and watereth the flock of Laban his mother's brother.

11 And Jacob kisseth Rachel, and lifteth up his voice, and weepeth,

12 and Jacob declareth to Rachel that he [is] her father's brother, and that he [is] Rebekah's son, and she runneth and declareth to her father.

13 And it cometh to pass, when Laban heareth the report of Jacob his sister's son, that he runneth to meet him, and embraceth him, and kisseth him, and bringeth him in unto his house; and he recounteth to Laban all these things,

14 and Laban saith to him, `Only my bone and my flesh [art] thou;' and he dwelleth with him a month of days.

15 And Laban saith to Jacob, `Is it because thou [art] my brother that thou hast served me for nought? declare to me what [is] thy hire.'

16 And Laban hath two daughters, the name of the elder [is] Leah, and the name of the younger Rachel,

17 and the eyes of Leah [are] tender, and Rachel hath been fair of form and fair of appearance.

18 And Jacob loveth Rachel, and saith, `I serve thee seven years for Rachel thy younger daughter:'

19 and Laban saith, `It is better for me to give her to thee than to give her to another man; dwell with me;'

20 and Jacob serveth for Rachel seven years; and they are in his eyes as some days, because of his loving her.

21 And Jacob saith unto Laban, `Give up my wife, for my days have been fulfilled, and I go in unto her;'

22 and Laban gathereth all the men of the place, and maketh a banquet.

23 And it cometh to pass in the evening, that he taketh Leah, his daughter, and bringeth her in unto him, and he goeth in unto her;

24 and Laban giveth to her Zilpah, his maid-servant, to Leah his daughter, a maidservant.

25 And it cometh to pass in the morning, that lo, it [is] Leah; and he saith unto Laban, `What [is] this thou hast done to me? for Rachel have I not served with thee? and why hast thou deceived me?'

26 And Laban saith, `It is not done so in our place, to give the younger before the firstborn;

27 fulfil the week of this one, and we give to thee also this one, for the service which thou dost serve with me yet seven other years.'

28 And Jacob doth so, and fulfilleth the week of this one, and he giveth to him Rachel his daughter, to him for a wife;

29 and Laban giveth to Rachel his daughter Bilhah his maid-servant, for a maid-servant to her.

30 And he goeth in also unto Rachel, and he also loveth Rachel more than Leah; and he serveth with him yet seven other years.

31 And Jehovah seeth that Leah [is] the hated one, and He openeth her womb, and Rachel [is] barren;

32 and Leah conceiveth, and beareth a son, and calleth his name Reuben, for she said, `Because Jehovah hath looked on mine affliction; because now doth my husband love me.'

33 And she conceiveth again, and beareth a son, and saith, `Because Jehovah hath heard that I [am] the hated one, He also giveth to me even this [one];' and she calleth his name Simeon.

34 And she conceiveth again, and beareth a son, and saith, `Now [is] the time, my husband is joined unto me, because I have born to him three sons,' therefore hath [one] called his name Levi.

35 And she conceiveth again, and beareth a son, and saith this time, `I praise Jehovah;' therefore hath she called his name Judah; and she ceaseth from bearing.

Genesis 31

1 And he heareth the words of Laban's sons, saying, `Jacob hath taken all that our father hath; yea, from that which our father hath, he hath made all this honour;'

2 and Jacob seeth the face of Laban, and lo, it is not with him as heretofore.

3 And Jehovah saith unto Jacob, `Turn back unto the land of thy fathers, and to thy kindred, and I am with thee.'

4 And Jacob sendeth and calleth for Rachel and for Leah to the field unto his flock;

5 and saith to them, `I am beholding your father's face--that it is not towards me as heretofore, and the God of my father hath been with me,

6 and ye--ye have known that with all my power I have served your father,

7 and your father hath played upon me, and hath changed my hire ten times; and God hath not suffered him to do evil with me.

8 `If he say thus: The speckled are thy hire, then bare all the flock speckled ones; and if he say thus: The ring-streaked are thy hire, then bare all the flock ring-streaked;

9 and God taketh away the substance of your father, and doth give to me.

10 `And it cometh to pass at the time of the flock conceiving, that I lift up mine eyes and see in a dream, and lo, the he-goats, which are going up on the flock, [are] ring-streaked, speckled, and grisled;

11 and the messenger of God saith unto me in the dream, Jacob, and I say, Here [am] I.

12 `And He saith, Lift up, I pray thee, thine eyes, and see--all the he-goats which are going up on the flock [are] ring-streaked, speckled, and grisled, for I have seen all that Laban is doing to thee;

13 I [am] the God of Bethel where thou hast anointed a standing pillar, where thou hast vowed a vow to me; now, arise, go out from this land, and turn back unto the land of thy birth.'

14 And Rachel answereth--Leah also--and saith to him, `Have we yet a portion and inheritance in the house of our father?

15 have we not been reckoned strangers to him? for he hath sold us, and he also utterly consumeth our money;

16 for all the wealth which God hath taken away from our father, it [is] ours, and our children's; and now, all that God hath said unto thee--do.'

17 And Jacob riseth, and lifteth up his sons and his wives on the camels,

18 and leadeth all his cattle, and all his substance which he hath acquired, the cattle of his getting, which he hath acquired in Padan-Aram, to go unto Isaac his father, to the land of Canaan.

19 And Laban hath gone to shear his flock, and Rachel stealeth the teraphim which her father hath;

20 and Jacob deceiveth the heart of Laban the Aramaean, because he hath not declared to him that he is fleeing;

21 and he fleeth, he and all that he hath, and riseth, and passeth over the River, and setteth his face [toward] the mount of Gilead.

22 And it is told to Laban on the third day that Jacob hath fled,

23 and he taketh his brethren with him, and pursueth after him a journey of seven days, and overtaketh him in the mount of Gilead.

24 And God cometh in unto Laban the Aramaean in a dream of the night, and saith to him, `Take heed to thyself lest thou speak with Jacob from good unto evil.'

25 And Laban overtaketh Jacob; and Jacob hath fixed his tent in the mount; and Laban with his brethren have fixed [theirs] in the mount of Gilead.

26 And Laban saith to Jacob, `What hast thou done that thou dost deceive my heart, and lead away my daughters as captives of the sword?

27 Why hast thou hidden thyself to flee, and deceivest me, and hast not declared to me, and I send thee away with joy and with songs, with tabret and with harp,

28 and hast not suffered me to kiss my sons and my daughters? --now thou hast acted foolishly in doing [so];

29 my hand is to God to do evil with you, but the God of your father yesternight hath spoken unto me, saying, Take heed to thyself from speaking with Jacob from good unto evil.

30 `And now, thou hast certainly gone, because thou hast been very desirous for the house of thy father; why hast thou stolen my gods?'

31 And Jacob answereth and saith to Laban, `Because I was afraid, for I said, Lest thou take violently away thy daughters from me;

32 with whomsoever thou findest thy gods--he doth not live; before our brethren discern for thyself what [is] with me, and take to thyself:' and Jacob hath not known that Rachel hath stolen them.

33 And Laban goeth into the tent of Jacob, and into the tent of Leah, and into the tent of the two handmaidens, and hath not found; and he goeth out from the tent of Leah, and goeth into the tent of Rachel.

34 And Rachel hath taken the teraphim, and putteth them in the furniture of the camel, and sitteth upon them; and Laban feeleth all the tent, and hath not found;

35 and she saith unto her father, `Let it not be displeasing in the eyes of my lord that I am not able to rise at thy presence, for the way of women [is] on me;' and he searcheth, and hath not found the teraphim.

36 And it is displeasing to Jacob, and he striveth with Laban; and Jacob answereth and saith to Laban, `What [is] my transgression? what my sin, that thou hast burned after me?

37 for thou hast felt all my vessels: what hast thou found of all the vessels of thy house? set here before my brethren, and thy brethren, and they decide between us both.

38 `These twenty years I [am] with thee: thy ewes and thy she-goats have not miscarried, and the rams of thy flock I have not eaten;

39 the torn I have not brought in unto thee--I, I repay it--from my hand thou dost seek it; I have been deceived by day, and I have been deceived by night;

40 I have been [thus]: in the day consumed me hath drought, and frost by night, and wander doth my sleep from mine eyes.

41 `This [is] to me twenty years in thy house: I have served thee fourteen years for thy two daughters, and six years for thy flock; and thou changest my hire ten times;

42 unless the God of my father, the God of Abraham, and the Fear of Isaac, had been for me, surely now empty thou hadst sent me away; mine affliction and the labour of my hands hath God seen, and reproveth yesternight.'

43 And Laban answereth and saith unto Jacob, `The daughters [are] my daughters, and the sons my sons, and the flock my flock, and all that thou art seeing [is] mine; and to my daughters--what do I to these to-day, or to their sons whom they have born?

44 and now, come, let us make a covenant, I and thou, and it hath been for a witness between me and thee.'

45 And Jacob taketh a stone, and lifteth it up [for] a standing pillar;

46 and Jacob saith to his brethren, `Gather stones,' and they take stones, and make a heap; and they eat there on the heap;

47 and Laban calleth it Jegar-Sahadutha; and Jacob hath called it Galeed.

48 And Laban saith, `This heap [is] witness between me and thee to-day;' therefore hath he called its name Galeed;

49 Mizpah also, for he said, `Jehovah doth watch between me and thee, for we are hidden one from another;

50 if thou afflict my daughters, or take wives beside my daughters--there is no man with us--see, God [is] witness between me and thee.'

51 And Laban saith to Jacob, `Lo, this heap, and lo, the standing pillar which I have cast between me and thee;

52 this heap [is] witness, and the standing pillar [is] witness, that I do not pass over this heap unto thee, and that thou dost not pass over this heap and this standing pillar unto me--for evil;

53 the God of Abraham and the God of Nahor, doth judge between us--the God of their father,' and Jacob sweareth by the Fear of his father Isaac.

54 And Jacob sacrificeth a sacrifice in the mount, and calleth to his brethren to eat bread, and they eat bread, and lodge in the mount;

55 and Laban riseth early in the morning, and kisseth his sons and his daughters, and blesseth them; and Laban goeth on, and turneth back to his place.

Genesis 35

1 And God saith unto Jacob, `Rise, go up to Bethel, and dwell there, and make there an altar to God, who appeared unto thee in thy fleeing from the face of Esau thy brother.'

2 And Jacob saith unto his household, and unto all who [are] with him, `Turn aside the gods of the stranger which [are] in your midst, and cleanse yourselves, and change your garments;

3 and we rise, and go up to Bethel, and I make there an altar to God, who is answering me in the day of my distress, and is with me in the way that I have gone.'

4 And they give unto Jacob all the gods of the stranger that [are] in their hand, and the rings that [are] in their ears, and Jacob hideth them under the oak which [is] by Shechem;

5 and they journey, and the terror of God is on the cities which [are] round about them, and they have not pursued after the sons of Jacob.

6 And Jacob cometh in to Luz which [is] in the land of Canaan (it [is] Bethel), he and all the people who [are] with him,

7 and he buildeth there an altar, and proclaimeth at the place the God of Bethel: for there had God been revealed unto him, in his fleeing from the face of his brother.

8 And Deborah, Rebekah's nurse, dieth, and she is buried at the lower part of Bethel, under the oak, and he calleth its name `Oak of weeping.'

9 And God appeareth unto Jacob again, in his coming from Padan-Aram, and blesseth him;

10 and God saith to him, `Thy name [is] Jacob: thy name is no more called Jacob, but Israel is thy name;' and He calleth his name Israel.

11 And God saith to him, `I [am] God Almighty; be fruitful and multiply, a nation and an assembly of nations is from thee, and kings from thy loins go out;

12 and the land which I have given to Abraham and to Isaac--to thee I give it, yea to thy seed after thee I give the land.'

13 And God goeth up from him, in the place where He hath spoken with him.

14 And Jacob setteth up a standing pillar in the place where He hath spoken with him, a standing pillar of stone, and he poureth on it an oblation, and he poureth on it oil;

15 and Jacob calleth the name of the place where God spake with him Bethel.

16 And they journey from Bethel, and there is yet a kibrath of land before entering Ephratha, and Rachel beareth, and is sharply pained in her bearing;

17 and it cometh to pass, in her being sharply pained in her bearing, that the midwife saith to her, `Fear not, for this also [is] a son for thee.'

18 And it cometh to pass in the going out of her soul (for she died), that she calleth his name Ben-Oni; and his father called him Benjamin;

19 and Rachel dieth, and is buried in the way to Ephratha, which [is] Bethlehem,

20 and Jacob setteth up a standing pillar over her grave; which [is] the standing pillar of Rachel's grave unto this day.

21 And Israel journeyeth, and stretcheth out his tent beyond the tower of Edar;

22 and it cometh to pass in Israel's dwelling in that land, that Reuben goeth, and lieth with Bilhah his father's concubine; and Israel heareth.

23 And the sons of Jacob are twelve. Sons of Leah: Jacob's first-born Reuben, and Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Zebulun.

24 Sons of Rachel: Joseph and Benjamin.

25 And sons of Bilhah, Rachel's maid-servant: Dan and Naphtali.

26 And sons of Zilpah, Leah's maid-servant: Gad and Asher. These [are] sons of Jacob, who have been born to him in Padan-Aram.

27 And Jacob cometh unto Isaac his father, at Mamre, the city of Arba (which [is] Hebron), where Abraham and Isaac have sojourned.

28 And the days of Isaac are a hundred and eighty years,

29 and Isaac expireth, and dieth, and is gathered unto his people, aged and satisfied with days; and bury him do Esau and Jacob his sons.

Genesis 36

1 And these [are] births of Esau, who [is] Edom.

2 Esau hath taken his wives from the daughters of Canaan: Adah daughter of Elon the Hittite, and Aholibamah daughter of Anah, daughter of Zibeon the Hivite,

3 and Bashemath daughter of Ishmael, sister of Nebajoth.

4 And Adah beareth to Esau, Eliphaz; and Bashemath hath born Reuel;

5 and Aholibamah hath born Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah. These [are] sons of Esau, who were born to him in the land of Canaan.

6 And Esau taketh his wives, and his sons, and his daughters, and all the persons of his house, and his cattle, and all his beasts, and all his substance which he hath acquired in the land of Canaan, and goeth into the country from the face ofJacob his brother;

7 for their substance was more abundant than to dwell together, and the land of their sojournings was not able to bear them because of their cattle;

8 and Esau dwelleth in mount Seir: Esau is Edom.

9 And these [are] births of Esau, father of Edom, in mount Seir.

10 These [are] the names of the sons of Esau: Eliphaz son of Adah, wife of Esau; Reuel son of Bashemath, wife of Esau.

11 And the sons of Eliphaz are Teman, Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, and Kenaz;

12 and Timnath hath been concubine to Eliphaz son of Esau, and she beareth to Eliphaz, Amalek; these [are] sons of Adah wife of Esau.

13 And these [are] sons of Reuel: Nahath and Zerah, Shammah and Mizzah; these were sons of Bashemath wife of Esau.

14 And these have been the sons of Aholibamah daughter of Anah, daughter of Zibeon, wife of Esau; and she beareth to Esau, Jeush and Jaalam and Korah.

15 These [are] chiefs of the sons of Esau: sons of Eliphaz, first-born of Esau: chief Teman, chief Omar, chief Zepho, chief Kenaz,

16 chief Korah, chief Gatam, chief Amalek; these [are] chiefs of Eliphaz, in the land of Edom; these [are] sons of Adah.

17 And these [are] sons of Reuel son of Esau: chief Nahath, chief Zerah, chief Shammah, chief Mizzah; these [are] chiefs of Reuel, in the land of Edom; these [are] sons of Bashemath wife of Esau.

18 And these [are] sons of Aholibamah wife of Esau: chief Jeush, chief Jaalam, chief Korah; these [are] chiefs of Aholibamah daughter of Anah, wife of Esau.

19 These [are] sons of Esau (who [is] Edom), and these their chiefs.

20 These [are] sons of Seir the Horite, the inhabitants of the land: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah,

21 and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan; these [are] chiefs of the Horites, sons of Seir, in the land of Edom.

22 And the sons of Lotan are Hori and Heman; and a sister of Lotan [is] Timna.

23 And these [are] sons of Shobal: Alvan and Manahath, and Ebal, Shepho and Onam.

24 And these [are] sons of Zibeon, both Ajah and Anah: it [is] Anah that hath found the Imim in the wilderness, in his feeding the asses of Zibeon his father.

25 And these [are] sons of Anah: Dishon, and Aholibamah daughter of Anah.

26 And these [are] sons of Dishon: Hemdan, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran.

27 These [are] sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Akan.

28 These [are] sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran.

29 These [are] chiefs of the Horite: chief Lotan, chief Shobal, chief Zibeon, chief Anah,

30 chief Dishon, chief Ezer, chief Dishan: these [are] chiefs of the Horite in reference to their chiefs in the land of Seir.

31 And these [are] the kings who have reigned in the land of Edom before the reigning of a king over the sons of Israel.

32 And Bela son of Beor reigneth in Edom, and the name of his city [is] Dinhabah;

33 and Bela dieth, and reign in his stead doth Jobab son of Zerah from Bozrah;

34 and Jobab dieth, and reign in his stead doth Husham from the land of the Temanite.

35 And Husham dieth, and reign in his stead doth Hadad son of Bedad (who smiteth Midian in the field of Moab), and the name of his city [is] Avith;

36 and Hadad dieth, and reign in his stead doth Samlah of Masrekah;

37 and Samlah dieth, and reign in his stead doth Saul from Rehoboth of the River;

38 and Saul dieth, and reign in his stead doth Baal-hanan son of Achbor;

39 and Baal-hanan son of Achbor dieth, and reign in his stead doth Hadar, and the name of his city [is] Pau; and his wife's name [is] Mehetabel daughter of Matred, daughter of Mezahab.

40 And these [are] the names of the chiefs of Esau, according to their families, according to their places, by their names: chief Timnah, chief Alvah, chief Jetheth,

41 chief Aholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon,

42 chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar,

43 chief Magdiel, chief Iram: these [are] chiefs of Edom, in reference to their dwellings, in the land of their possession; he [is] Esau father of Edom.

Genesis 37

1 And Jacob dwelleth in the land of his father's sojournings--in the land of Canaan.

2 These [are] births of Jacob: Joseph, a son of seventeen years, hath been enjoying himself with his brethren among the flock, (and he [is] a youth,) with the sons of Bilhah, and with the sons of Zilpah, his father's wives, and Joseph bringethin an account of their evil unto their father.

3 And Israel hath loved Joseph more than any of his sons, for he [is] a son of his old age, and hath made for him a long coat;

4 and his brethren see that their father hath loved him more than any of his brethren, and they hate him, and have not been able to speak [to] him peaceably.

5 And Joseph dreameth a dream, and declareth to his brethren, and they add still more to hate him.

6 And he saith unto them, `Hear ye, I pray you, this dream which I have dreamed:

7 that, lo, we are binding bundles in the midst of the field, and lo, my bundle hath arisen, and hath also stood up, and lo, your bundles are round about, and bow themselves to my bundle.'

8 And his brethren say to him, `Dost thou certainly reign over us? dost thou certainly rule over us?' and they add still more to hate him, for his dreams, and for his words.

9 And he dreameth yet another dream, and recounteth it to his brethren, and saith, `Lo, I have dreamed a dream again, and lo, the sun and the moon, and eleven stars, are bowing themselves to me.'

10 And he recounteth unto his father, and unto his brethren; and his father pusheth against him, and saith to him, `What [is] this dream which thou hast dreamt? do we certainly come- -I, and thy mother, and thy brethren--to bow ourselves to thee, to the earth?'

11 and his brethren are zealous against him, and his father hath watched the matter.

12 And his brethren go to feed the flock of their father in Shechem,

13 and Israel saith unto Joseph, `Are not thy brethren feeding in Shechem? come, and I send thee unto them;' and he saith to him, `Here [am] I;'

14 and he saith to him, `Go, I pray thee, see the peace of thy brethren, and the peace of the flock, and bring me back word;' and he sendeth him from the valley of Hebron, and he cometh to Shechem.

15 And a man findeth him, and lo, he is wandering in the field, and the man asketh him, saying, `What seekest thou?'

16 and he saith, `My brethren I am seeking, declare to me, I pray thee, where they are feeding?'

17 And the man saith, `They have journeyed from this, for I have heard some saying, Let us go to Dothan,' and Joseph goeth after his brethren, and findeth them in Dothan.

18 And they see him from afar, even before he draweth near unto them, and they conspire against him to put him to death.

19 And they say one unto another, `Lo, this man of the dreams cometh;

20 and now, come, and we slay him, and cast him into one of the pits, and have said, An evil beast hath devoured him; and we see what his dreams are.'

21 And Reuben heareth, and delivereth him out of their hand, and saith, `Let us not smite the life;'

22 and Reuben saith unto them, `Shed no blood; cast him into this pit which [is] in the wilderness, and put not forth a hand upon him,' --in order to deliver him out of their hand, to bring him back unto his father.

23 And it cometh to pass, when Joseph hath come unto his brethren, that they strip Joseph of his coat, the long coat which [is] upon him,

24 and take him and cast him into the pit, and the pit [is] empty, there is no water in it.

25 And they sit down to eat bread, and they lift up their eyes, and look, and lo, a company of Ishmaelites coming from Gilead, and their camels bearing spices, and balm, and myrrh, going to take [them] down to Egypt.

26 And Judah saith unto his brethren, `What gain when we slay our brother, and have concealed his blood?

27 Come, and we sell him to the Ishmaelites, and our hands are not on him, for he [is] our brother--our flesh;' and his brethren hearken.

28 And Midianite merchantmen pass by and they draw out and bring up Joseph out of the pit, and sell Joseph to the Ishmaelites for twenty silverlings, and they bring Joseph into Egypt.

29 And Reuben returneth unto the pit, and lo, Joseph is not in the pit, and he rendeth his garments,

30 and he returneth unto his brethren, and saith, `The lad is not, and I--whither am I going?'

31 And they take the coat of Joseph, and slaughter a kid of the goats, and dip the coat in the blood,

32 and send the long coat, and they bring [it] in unto their father, and say, `This have we found; discern, we pray thee, whether it [is] thy son's coat or not?'

33 And he discerneth it, and saith, `My son's coat! an evil beast hath devoured him; torn--torn is Joseph!'

34 And Jacob rendeth his raiment, and putteth sackcloth on his loins, and becometh a mourner for his son many days,

35 and all his sons and all his daughters rise to comfort him, and he refuseth to comfort himself, and saith, `For--I go down mourning unto my son, to Sheol,' and his father weepeth for him.

36 And the Medanites have sold him unto Egypt, to Potiphar, a eunuch of Pharaoh, head of the executioners.

Genesis 44

1 And he commandeth him who [is] over his house, saying, `Fill the bags of the men [with] food, as they are able to bear, and put the money of each in the mouth of his bag;

2 and my cup, the silver cup, thou dost put in the mouth of the bag of the young one, and his corn-money;' and he doth according to the word of Joseph which he hath spoken.

3 The morning is bright, and the men have been sent away, they and their asses--

4 they have gone out of the city--they have not gone far off--and Joseph hath said to him who [is] over his house, `Rise, pursue after the men; and thou hast overtaken them, and thou hast said unto them, Why have ye recompensed evil for good?

5 Is not this that with which my lord drinketh? and he observeth diligently with it; ye have done evil [in] that which ye have done.'

6 And he overtaketh them, and speaketh unto them these words,

7 and they say unto him, `Why doth my lord speak according to these words? far be it from thy servants to do according to this word;

8 lo, the money which we found in the mouth of our bags we brought back unto thee from the land of Canaan, and how do we steal from the house of thy lord silver or gold?

9 with whomsoever of thy servants it is found, he hath died, and we also are to my lord for servants.'

10 And he saith, `Now, also, according to your words, so it [is]; he with whom it is found becometh my servant, and ye are acquitted;'

11 and they hasten and take down each his bag to the earth, and each openeth his bag;

12 and he searcheth--at the eldest he hath begun, and at the youngest he hath completed--and the cup is found in the bag of Benjamin;

13 and they rend their garments, and each ladeth his ass, and they turn back to the city.

14 And Judah--his brethren also--cometh in unto the house of Joseph, and he is yet there, and they fall before him to the earth;

15 and Joseph saith to them, `What [is] this deed that ye have done? have ye not known that a man like me doth diligently observe?'

16 And Judah saith, `What do we say to my lord? what do we speak? and what--do we justify ourselves? God hath found out the iniquity of thy servants; lo, we [are] servants to my lord, both we, and he in whose hand the cup hath been found;'

17 and he saith, `Far be it from me to do this; the man in whose hand the cup hath been found, he becometh my servant; and ye, go ye up in peace unto your father.'

18 And Judah cometh nigh unto him, and saith, `O, my lord, let thy servant speak, I pray thee, a word in the ears of my lord, and let not thine anger burn against thy servant--for thou art as Pharaoh.

19 My lord hath asked his servants, saying, Have ye a father or brother?

20 and we say unto my lord, We have a father, an aged one, and a child of old age, a little one; and his brother died, and he is left alone of his mother, and his father hath loved him.

21 `And thou sayest unto thy servants, Bring him down unto me, and I set mine eye upon him;

22 and we say unto my lord, The youth is not able to leave his father, when he hath left his father, then he hath died;

23 and thou sayest unto thy servants, If your young brother come not down with you, ye add not to see my face.

24 `And it cometh to pass, that we have come up unto thy servant my father, that we declare to him the words of my lord;

25 and our father saith, Turn back, buy for us a little food,

26 and we say, We are not able to go down; if our young brother is with us, then we have gone down; for we are not able to see the man's face, and our young brother not with us.

27 `And thy servant my father saith unto us, Ye--ye have known that two did my wife bare to me,

28 and the one goeth out from me, and I say, Surely he is torn--torn! and I have not seen him since;

29 when ye have taken also this from my presence, and mischief hath met him, then ye have brought down my grey hairs with evil to sheol.

30 `And now, at my coming in unto thy servant my father, and the youth not with us (and his soul is bound up in his soul),

31 then it hath come to pass when he seeth that the youth is not, that he hath died, and thy servants have brought down the grey hairs of thy servant our father with sorrow to sheol;

32 for thy servant obtained the youth by surety from my father, saying, If I bring him not in unto thee--then I have sinned against my father all the days.

33 `And now, let thy servant, I pray thee, abide instead of the youth a servant to my lord, and the youth goeth up with his brethren,

34 for how do I go up unto my father, and the youth not with me? lest I look on the evil which doth find my father.'

Genesis 46

1 And Israel journeyeth, and all that he hath, and cometh in to Beer-Sheba, and sacrificeth sacrifices to the God of his father Isaac;

2 and God speaketh to Israel in visions of the night, and saith, `Jacob, Jacob;' and he saith, `Here [am] I.'

3 And He saith, `I [am] God, God of thy father, be not afraid of going down to Egypt, for for a great nation I set thee there;

4 I--I go down with thee to Egypt, and I--I also certainly bring thee up, and Joseph doth put his hand on thine eyes.'

5 And Jacob riseth from Beer-Sheba, and the sons of Israel bear away Jacob their father, And their infants, and their wives, in the waggons which Pharaoh hath sent to bear him,

6 and they take their cattle, and their goods which they have acquired in the land of Canaan, and come into Egypt--Jacob, and all his seed with him,

7 his sons, and his sons' sons with him, his daughters, and his sons' daughters, yea, all his seed he brought with him into Egypt.

8 And these [are] the names of the sons of Israel who are coming into Egypt: Jacob and his sons, Jacob's first-born, Reuben.

9 And sons of Reuben: Hanoch, and Phallu, and Hezron, and Carmi.

10 And sons of Simeon: Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul son of the Canaanitess.

11 And sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

12 And sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, and Pharez, and Zarah, (and Er and Onan die in the land of Canaan.) And sons of Pharez are Hezron and Hamul.

13 And sons of Issachar: Tola, and Phuvah, and Job, and Shimron.

14 And sons of Zebulun: Sered, and Elon, and Jahleel.

15 These [are] sons of Leah whom she bare to Jacob in Padan-Aram, and Dinah his daughter; all the persons of his sons and his daughters [are] thirty and three.

16 And sons of Gad: Ziphion, and Haggi, Shuni, and Ezbon, Eri, and Arodi, and Areli.

17 And sons of Asher: Jimnah, and Ishuah, and Isui, and Beriah, and Serah their sister. And sons of Beriah: Heber and Malchiel.

18 These [are] sons of Zilpah, whom Laban gave to Leah his daughter, and she beareth these to Jacob--sixteen persons.

19 Sons of Rachel, Jacob's wife: Joseph and Benjamin.

20 And born to Joseph in the land of Egypt (whom Asenath daughter of Poti-Pherah, priest of On, hath borne to him) [are] Manasseh and Ephraim.

21 And sons of Benjamin: Belah, and Becher, and Ashbel, Gera, and Naaman, Ehi, and Rosh, Muppim, and Huppim, and Ard.

22 These [are] sons of Rachel, who were born to Jacob; all the persons [are] fourteen.

23 And sons of Dan: Hushim.

24 And sons of Naphtali: Jahzeel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem.

25 These [are] sons of Bilhah, whom Laban gave to Rachel his daughter; and she beareth these to Jacob--all the persons [are] seven.

26 All the persons who are coming to Jacob to Egypt, coming out of his thigh, apart from the wives of Jacob's sons, all the persons [are] sixty and six.

27 And the sons of Joseph who have been born to him in Egypt [are] two persons. All the persons of the house of Jacob who are coming into Egypt [are] seventy.

28 And Judah he hath sent before him unto Joseph, to direct before him to Goshen, and they come into the land of Goshen;

29 and Joseph harnesseth his chariot, and goeth up to meet Israel his father, to Goshen, and appeareth unto him, and falleth on his neck, and weepeth on his neck again;

30 and Israel saith unto Joseph, `Let me die this time, after my seeing thy face, for thou [art] yet alive.'

31 And Joseph saith unto his brethren, and unto the house of his father, `I go up, and declare to Pharaoh, and say unto him, My brethren, and the house of my father who [are] in the land of Canaan have come in unto me;

32 and the men [are] feeders of a flock, for they have been men of cattle; and their flock, and their herd, and all that they have, they have brought.'

33 `And it hath come to pass when Pharaoh calleth for you, and hath said, What [are] your works?

34 that ye have said, Thy servants have been men of cattle from our youth, even until now, both we and our fathers, --in order that ye may dwell in the land of Goshen, for the abomination of the Egyptians is every one feeding a flock.'

Genesis 49

1 And Jacob calleth unto his sons and saith, `Be gathered together, and I declare to you that which doth happen with you in the latter end of the days.

2 `Be assembled, and hear, sons of Jacob, And hearken unto Israel your father.

3 Reuben! my first-born thou, My power, and beginning of my strength, The abundance of exaltation, And the abundance of strength;

4 Unstable as water, thou art not abundant; For thou hast gone up thy father's bed; Then thou hast polluted: My couch he went up!

5 Simeon and Levi [are] brethren! Instruments of violence--their espousals!

6 Into their secret, come not, O my soul! Unto their assembly be not united, O mine honour; For in their anger they slew a man, And in their self-will eradicated a prince.

7 Cursed [is] their anger, for [it is] fierce, And their wrath, for [it is] sharp; I divide them in Jacob, And I scatter them in Israel.

8 Judah! thou--thy brethren praise thee! Thy hand [is] on the neck of thine enemies, Sons of thy father bow themselves to thee.

9 A lion's whelp [is] Judah, For prey, my son, thou hast gone up; He hath bent, he hath crouched as a lion, And as a lioness; who causeth him to arise?

10 The sceptre turneth not aside from Judah, And a lawgiver from between his feet, Till his Seed come; And his [is] the obedience of peoples.

11 Binding to the vine his ass, And to the choice vine the colt of his ass, He hath washed in wine his clothing, And in the blood of grapes his covering;

12 Red [are] eyes with wine, And white [are] teeth with milk!

13 Zebulun at a haven of the seas doth dwell, And he [is] for a haven of ships; And his side [is] unto Zidon.

14 Issacher [is] a strong ass, Crouching between the two folds;

15 And he seeth rest that [it is] good, And the land that [it is] pleasant, And he inclineth his shoulder to bear, And is to tribute a servant.

16 Dan doth judge his people, As one of the tribes of Israel;

17 Dan is a serpent by the way, An adder by the path, Which is biting the horse's heels, And its rider falleth backward.

18 For Thy salvation I have waited, Jehovah!

19 Gad! a troop assaulteth him, But he assaulteth last.

20 Out of Asher his bread [is] fat; And he giveth dainties of a king.

21 Naphtali [is] a hind sent away, Who is giving beauteous young ones.

22 Joseph [is] a fruitful son; A fruitful son by a fountain, Daughters step over the wall;

23 And embitter him--yea, they have striven, Yea, hate him do archers;

24 And his bow abideth in strength, And strengthened are the arms of his hands By the hands of the Mighty One of Jacob, Whence is a shepherd, a son of Israel.

25 By the God of thy father who helpeth thee, And the Mighty One who blesseth thee, Blessings of the heavens from above, Blessings of the deep lying under, Blessings of breasts and womb; --

26 Thy father's blessings have been mighty Above the blessings of my progenitors, Unto the limit of the heights age-during They are for the head of Joseph, And for the crown of the one Separate [from] his brethren.

27 Benjamin! a wolf teareth; In the morning he eateth prey, And at evening he apportioneth spoil.'

28 All these [are] the twelve tribes of Israel, and this [is] that which their father hath spoken unto them, and he blesseth them; each according to his blessing he hath blessed them.

29 And he commandeth them, and saith unto them, `I am being gathered unto my people; bury me by my fathers, at the cave which [is] in the field of Ephron the Hittite;

30 in the cave which [is] in the field of Machpelah, which [is] on the front of Mamre, in the land of Canaan, which Abraham bought with the field from Ephron the Hittite for a possession of a burying-place;

31 (there they buried Abraham and Sarah his wife; there they buried Isaac and Rebekah his wife; and there I buried Leah);

32 the purchase of the field and of the cave which [is] in it, [is] from Sons of Heth.'

33 And Jacob finisheth commanding his sons, and gathereth up his feet unto the bed, and expireth, and is gathered unto his people.

Exodus 2

1 And there goeth a man of the house of Levi, and he taketh the daughter of Levi,

2 and the woman conceiveth, and beareth a son, and she seeth him that he [is] fair, and she hideth him three months,

3 and she hath not been able any more to hide him, and she taketh for him an ark of rushes, and daubeth it with bitumen and with pitch, and putteth the lad in it, and putteth [it] in the weeds by the edge of the River;

4 and his sister stationeth herself afar off, to know what is done to him.

5 And a daughter of Pharaoh cometh down to bathe at the River, and her damsels are walking by the side of the River, and she seeth the ark in the midst of the weeds, and sendeth her handmaid, and she taketh it,

6 and openeth, and seeth him--the lad, and lo, a child weeping! and she hath pity on him, and saith, `This is [one] of the Hebrews' children.'

7 And his sister saith unto the daughter of Pharaoh, `Do I go? when I have called for thee a suckling woman of the Hebrews, then she doth suckle the lad for thee;'

8 and the daughter of Pharaoh saith to her, `Go;' and the virgin goeth, and calleth the mother of the lad,

9 and the daughter of Pharaoh saith to her, `Take this lad away, and suckle him for me, and I--I give thy hire;' and the woman taketh the lad, and suckleth him.

10 And the lad groweth, and she bringeth him in to the daughter of Pharaoh, and he is to her for a son, and she calleth his name Moses, and saith, `Because--from the water I have drawn him.'

11 And it cometh to pass, in those days, that Moses is grown, and he goeth out unto his brethren, and looketh on their burdens, and seeth a man, an Egyptian, smiting a man, a Hebrew, [one] of his brethren,

12 and he turneth hither and thither, and seeth that there is no man, and smiteth the Egyptian, and hideth him in the sand.

13 And he goeth out on the second day, and lo, two men, Hebrews, striving! and he saith to the wrong-doer, `Why dost thou smite thy neighbour?'

14 and he saith, `Who set thee for a head and a judge over us? to slay me art thou saying [it], as thou hast slain the Egyptian?' and Moses feareth, and saith, `Surely the thing hath been known.'

15 And Pharaoh heareth of this thing, and seeketh to slay Moses, and Moses fleeth from the face of Pharaoh, and dwelleth in the land of Midian, and dwelleth by the well.

16 And to a priest of Midian [are] seven daughters, and they come and draw, and fill the troughs, to water the flock of their father,

17 and the shepherds come and drive them away, and Moses ariseth, and saveth them, and watereth their flock.

18 And they come in to Reuel their father, and he saith, `Wherefore have ye hastened to come in to-day?'

19 and they say, `A man, an Egyptian, hath delivered us out of the hand of the shepherds, and also hath diligently drawn for us, and watereth the flock;'

20 and he saith unto his daughters, `And where [is] he? why [is] this? --ye left the man! call for him, and he doth eat bread.'

21 And Moses is willing to dwell with the man, and he giveth Zipporah his daughter to Moses,

22 and she beareth a son, and he calleth his name Gershom, for he said, `A sojourner I have been in a strange land.'

23 And it cometh to pass during these many days, that the king of Egypt dieth, and the sons of Israel sigh because of the service, and cry, and their cry goeth up unto God, because of the service;

24 and God heareth their groaning, and God remembereth His covenant with Abraham, with Isaac, and with Jacob;

25 and God seeth the sons of Israel, and God knoweth.

Exodus 6

1 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Now dost thou see that which I do to Pharaoh, for with a strong hand he doth send them away, yea, with a strong hand he doth cast them out of his land.'

2 And God speaketh unto Moses, and saith unto him, `I [am] Jehovah,

3 and I appear unto Abraham, unto Isaac, and unto Jacob, as God Almighty; as to My name Jehovah, I have not been known to them;

4 and also I have established My covenant with them, to give to them the land of Canaan, the land of their sojournings, wherein they have sojourned;

5 and also I have heard the groaning of the sons of Israel, whom the Egyptians are causing to serve, and I remember My covenant.

6 `Therefore say to the sons of Israel, I [am] Jehovah, and I have brought you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians, and have delivered you from their service, and have redeemed you by a stretched-out arm, and by great judgments,

7 and have taken you to Me for a people, and I have been to you for God, and ye have known that I [am] Jehovah your God, who is bringing you out from under the burdens of the Egyptians;

8 and I have brought you in unto the land which I have lifted up My hand to give it to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, and have given it to you--a possession; I [am] Jehovah.'

9 And Moses speaketh so unto the sons of Israel, and they hearkened not unto Moses, for anguish of spirit, and for harsh service.

10 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

11 `Go in, speak unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he doth send the sons of Israel out of his land;

12 and Moses speaketh before Jehovah, saying, `Lo, the sons of Israel have not hearkened unto me, and how doth Pharaoh hear me, and I of uncircumcised lips?'

13 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, and unto Aaron, and chargeth them for the sons of Israel, and for Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt.

14 These [are] heads of the house of their fathers: Sons of Reuben first-born of Israel [are] Hanoch, and Phallu, Hezron, and Carmi: these [are] families of Reuben.

15 And sons of Simeon [are] Jemuel, and Jamin, and Ohad, and Jachin, and Zohar, and Shaul, son of the Canaanitess: these [are] families of Simeon.

16 And these [are] the names of the sons of Levi, as to their births: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari: and the years of the life of Levi [are] a hundred and thirty and seven years.

17 The sons of Gershon [are] Libni, and Shimi, as to their families.

18 And the sons of Kohath [are] Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel: and the years of the life of Kohath [are] a hundred and thirty and three years.

19 And the sons of Merari [are] Mahli and Mushi: these [are] families of Levi, as to their births.

20 And Amram taketh Jochebed his aunt to himself for a wife, and she beareth to him Aaron and Moses: and the years of the life of Amram [are] a hundred and thirty and seven years.

21 And sons of Izhar [are] Korah, and Nepheg, and Zichri.

22 And sons of Uzziel [are] Mishael, and Elzaphan, and Sithri.

23 And Aaron taketh Elisheba daughter of Amminadab, sister of Naashon, to himself for a wife, and she beareth to him Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.

24 And sons of Korah [are] Assir, and Elkanah, and Abiasaph: these [are] families of the Korhite.

25 And Eleazar, Aaron's son, hath taken to him [one] of the daughters of Putiel for a wife to himself, and she beareth to him Phinehas: these [are] heads of the fathers of the Levites, as to their families.

26 This [is] Aaron--and Moses--to whom Jehovah said, `Bring ye out the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, by their hosts;'

27 these are they who are speaking unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, to bring out the sons of Israel from Egypt, this [is] Moses--and Aaron.

28 And it cometh to pass in the day of Jehovah's speaking unto Moses in the land of Egypt,

29 that Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying, `I [am] Jehovah, speak unto Pharaoh king of Egypt all that I am speaking unto thee.'

30 And Moses saith before Jehovah, `Lo, I [am] of uncircumcised lips, and how doth Pharaoh hearken unto me?'

Exodus 15

1 Then singeth Moses and the sons of Israel this song to Jehovah, and they speak, saying: --`I sing to Jehovah, For triumphing He hath triumphed; The horse and its rider He hath thrown into the sea.

2 My strength and song is JAH, And He is become my salvation: This [is] my God, and I glorify Him; God of my father, and I exalt Him.

3 Jehovah [is] a man of battle; Jehovah [is] His name.

4 Chariots of Pharaoh and his force He hath cast into the sea; And the choice of his captains Have sunk in the Red Sea!

5 The depths do cover them; They went down into the depths as a stone.

6 Thy right hand, O Jehovah, Is become honourable in power; Thy right hand, O Jehovah, Doth crush an enemy.

7 And in the abundance of Thine excellency Thou throwest down Thy withstanders, Thou sendest forth Thy wrath--It consumeth them as stubble.

8 And by the spirit of Thine anger Have waters been heaped together; Stood as a heap have flowings; Congealed have been depths In the heart of a sea.

9 The enemy said, I pursue, I overtake; I apportion spoil; Filled is my soul with them; I draw out my sword; My hand destroyeth them: --

10 Thou hast blown with Thy wind The sea hath covered them; They sank as lead in mighty waters.

11 Who [is] like Thee among the gods, O Jehovah? Who [is] like Thee--honourable in holiness--Fearful in praises--doing wonders?

12 Thou hast stretched out Thy right hand--Earth swalloweth them!

13 Thou hast led forth in Thy kindness The people whom Thou hast redeemed. Thou hast led on in Thy strength Unto Thy holy habitation.

14 Peoples have heard, they are troubled; Pain hath seized inhabitants of Philistia.

15 Then have chiefs of Edom been troubled: Mighty ones of Moab--Trembling doth seize them! Melted have all inhabitants of Canaan!

16 Fall on them doth terror and dread; By the greatness of Thine arm They are still as a stone, Till Thy people pass over, O Jehovah; Till the people pass over Whom Thou hast purchased.

17 Thou dost bring them in, And dost plant them In a mountain of Thine inheritance, A fixed place for Thy dwelling Thou hast made, O Jehovah; A sanctuary, O Lord, Thy hands have established;

18 Jehovah reigneth--to the age, and for ever!'

19 For the horse of Pharaoh hath gone in with his chariots and with his horsemen into the sea, and Jehovah turneth back on them the waters of the sea, and the sons of Israel have gone on dry land in the midst of the sea.

20 And Miriam the inspired one, sister of Aaron, taketh the timbrel in her hand, and all the women go out after her, with timbrels and with choruses;

21 and Miriam answereth to them: --`Sing ye to Jehovah, For Triumphing He hath triumphed; The horse and its rider He hath thrown into the sea!'

22 And Moses causeth Israel to journey from the Red Sea, and they go out unto the wilderness of Shur, and they go three days in the wilderness, and have not found water,

23 and they come in to Marah, and have not been able to drink the waters of Marah, for they [are] bitter; therefore hath [one] called its name Marah.

24 And the people murmur against Moses, saying, `What do we drink?'

25 and he crieth unto Jehovah, and Jehovah sheweth him a tree, and he casteth unto the waters, and the waters become sweet. There He hath made for them a statute, and an ordinance, and there He hath tried them,

26 and He saith, `If thou dost really hearken to the voice of Jehovah thy God, and dost that which is right in His eyes, and hast hearkened to His commands, and kept all His statutes: none of the sickness which I laid on the Egyptians do I lay on thee, for I, Jehovah, am healing thee.

27 And they come to Elim, and there [are] twelve fountains of water, and seventy palm trees; and they encamp there by the waters.

Exodus 20

1 `And God speaketh all these words, saying,

2 I [am] Jehovah thy God, who hath brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants.

3 `Thou hast no other Gods before Me.

4 `Thou dost not make to thyself a graven image, or any likeness which [is] in the heavens above, or which [is] in the earth beneath, or which [is] in the waters under the earth.

5 Thou dost not bow thyself to them, nor serve them: for I, Jehovah thy God, [am] a zealous God, charging iniquity of fathers on sons, on the third [generation], and on the fourth, of those hating Me,

6 and doing kindness to thousands, of those loving Me and keeping My commands.

7 `Thou dost not take up the name of Jehovah thy God for a vain thing, for Jehovah acquitteth not him who taketh up His name for a vain thing.

8 `Remember the Sabbath-day to sanctify it;

9 six days thou dost labour, and hast done all thy work,

10 and the seventh day [is] a Sabbath to Jehovah thy God; thou dost not do any work, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, thy man-servant, and thy handmaid, and thy cattle, and thy sojourner who is within thy gates, --

11 for six days hath Jehovah made the heavens and the earth, the sea, and all that [is] in them, and resteth in the seventh day; therefore hath Jehovah blessed the Sabbath-day, and doth sanctify it.

12 `Honour thy father and thy mother, so that thy days are prolonged on the ground which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee.

13 `Thou dost not murder.

14 `Thou dost not commit adultery.

15 `Thou dost not steal.

16 `Thou dost not answer against thy neighbour a false testimony.

17 `Thou dost not desire the house of thy neighbour, thou dost not desire the wife of thy neighbour, or his man-servant, or his handmaid, or his ox, or his ass, or anything which [is] thy neighbour's.'

18 And all the people are seeing the voices, and the flames, and the sound of the trumpet, and the mount smoking; and the people see, and move, and stand afar off,

19 and say unto Moses, `Speak thou with us, and we hear, and let not God speak with us, lest we die.'

20 And Moses saith unto the people, `Fear not, for to try you hath God come, and in order that His fear may be before your faces--that ye sin not.'

21 And the people stand afar off, and Moses hath drawn nigh unto the thick darkness where God [is].

22 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Thus dost thou say unto the sons of Israel: Ye--ye have seen that from the heavens I have spoken with you;

23 ye do not make with Me gods of silver, even gods of gold ye do not make to yourselves.

24 `An altar of earth thou dost make for Me, and thou hast sacrificed on it thy burntofferings and thy peace-offerings, thy flock and thy herd; in every place where I cause My name to be remembered I come in unto thee, and have blessed thee.

25 `And if an altar of stones thou dost make to Me, thou dost not build them of hewn work; when thy tool thou hast waved over it, then thou dost pollute it;

26 neither dost thou go up by steps on Mine altar, that thy nakedness be not revealed upon it.

Exodus 22

1 `When a man doth steal an ox or sheep, and hath slaughtered it or sold it, five of the herd he doth repay for the ox, and four of the flock for the sheep.

2 `If in the breaking through, the thief is found, and he hath been smitten, and hath died, there is no blood for him;

3 if the sun hath risen upon him, blood [is] for him, he doth certainly repay; if he have nothing, then he hath been sold for his theft;

4 if the theft is certainly found in his hand alive, whether ox, or ass, or sheep--double he repayeth.

5 `When a man depastureth a field or vineyard, and hath sent out his beast, and it hath pastured in the field of another, [of] the best of his field, and the best of his vineyard, he doth repay.

6 `When fire goeth forth, and hath found thorns, and a stack, or the standing corn, or the field, hath been consumed, he who causeth the burning doth certainly repay.

7 `When a man doth give unto his neighbour silver, or vessels to keep, and it hath been stolen out of the man's house; if the thief is found, he repayeth double.

8 `If the thief is not found, then the master of the house hath been brought near unto God, whether he hath not put forth his hand against the work of his neighbour;

9 for every matter of transgression, for ox, for ass, for sheep, for raiment, for any lost thing of which it is said that it is his; unto God cometh the matter of them both; he whom God doth condemn, he repayeth double to his neighbour.

10 `When a man doth give unto his neighbour an ass, or ox, or sheep, or any beast to keep, and it hath died, or hath been hurt, or taken captive, none seeing--

11 an oath of Jehovah is between them both, that he hath not put forth his hand against the work of his neighbour, and its owner hath accepted, and he doth not repay;

12 but if it is certainly stolen from him, he doth repay to its owner;

13 if it is certainly torn, he bringeth it in--a witness; the torn thing he doth not repay.

14 `And when a man doth ask [anything] from his neighbour, and it hath been hurt or hath died--its owner not being with it--he doth certainly repay;

15 if its owner [is] with it, he doth not repay, --if it [is] a hired thing, it hath come for its hire.

16 `And when a man doth entice a virgin who [is] not betrothed, and hath lain with her, he doth certainly endow her to himself for a wife;

17 if her father utterly refuse to give her to him, money he doth weigh out according to the dowry of virgins.

18 `A witch thou dost not keep alive.

19 `Whoever lieth with a beast is certainly put to death.

20 `He who is sacrificing to a god, save to Jehovah alone, is devoted.

21 `And a sojourner thou dost not oppress, nor crush him, for sojourners ye have been in the land of Egypt.

22 `Any widow or orphan ye do not afflict;

23 if thou dost really afflict him, surely if he at all cry unto Me, I certainly hear his cry;

24 and Mine anger hath burned, and I have slain you by the sword, and your wives have been widows, and your sons orphans.

25 `If thou dost lend My poor people with thee money, thou art not to him as a usurer; thou dost not lay on him usury;

26 if thou dost at all take in pledge the garment of thy neighbour, during the going in of the sun thou dost return it to him:

27 for it alone is his covering, it [is] his garment for his skin; wherein doth he lie down? and it hath come to pass, when he doth cry unto Me, that I have heard, for I [am] gracious.

28 `God thou dost not revile, and a prince among thy people thou dost not curse.

29 `Thy fulness and thy liquids thou dost not delay; the first-born of thy sons thou dost give to Me;

30 so thou dost to thine ox, to thy sheep; seven days it is with its dam, on the eighth day thou dost give it to Me.

31 `And ye are holy men to Me, and flesh torn in the field ye do not eat, to a dog ye do cast it.

Exodus 23

1 `Thou dost not lift up a vain report; thou dost not put thy hand with a wicked man to be a violent witness.

2 `Thou art not after many to evil, nor dost thou testify concerning a strife, to turn aside after many to cause [others] to turn aside;

3 and a poor man thou dost not honour in his strife.

4 `When thou meetest thine enemy's ox or his ass going astray, thou dost certainly turn it back to him;

5 when thou seest the ass of him who is hating thee crouching under its burden, then thou hast ceased from leaving [it] to it--thou dost certainly leave [it] with him.

6 `Thou dost not turn aside the judgment of thy needy one in his strife;

7 from a false matter thou dost keep far off, and an innocent and righteous man thou dost not slay; for I do not justify a wicked man.

8 `And a bribe thou dost not take; for the bribe bindeth the open -[eyed], and perverteth the words of the righteous.

9 `And a sojourner thou dost not oppress, and ye--ye have known the soul of the sojourner, for sojourners ye have been in the land of Egypt.

10 `And six years thou dost sow thy land, and hast gathered its increase;

11 and the seventh thou dost release it, and hast left it, and the needy of thy people have eaten, and their leaving doth the beast of the field eat; so dost thou to thy vineyard--to thine oliveyard.

12 `Six days thou dost do thy work, and on the seventh day thou dost rest, so that thine ox and thine ass doth rest, and the son of thine handmaid and the sojourner is refreshed;

13 and in all that which I have said unto you ye do take heed; and the name of other gods ye do not mention; it is not heard on thy mouth.

14 `Three times thou dost keep a feast to Me in a year;

15 the Feast of Unleavened things thou dost keep; seven days thou dost eat unleavened things, as I have commanded thee, at the time appointed [in] the month of Abib; for in it thou hast come forth out of Egypt, and ye do not appear [in] My presence empty;

16 and the Feast of Harvest, the first fruits of thy works which thou sowest in the field; and the Feast of the In-Gathering, in the outgoing of the year, in thy gathering thy works out of the field.

17 `Three times in a year do all thy males appear before the face of the Lord Jehovah.

18 `Thou dost not sacrifice on a fermented thing the blood of My sacrifice, and the fat of My festival doth not remain till morning;

19 the beginning of the first-fruits of thy ground thou dost bring into the house of Jehovah thy God; thou dost not boil a kid in its mother's milk.

20 `Lo, I am sending a messenger before thee to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee in unto the place which I have prepared;

21 be watchful because of his presence, and hearken to his voice, rebel not against him, for he beareth not with your transgression, for My name [is] in his heart;

22 for, if thou diligently hearken to his voice, and hast done all that which I speak, then I have been at enmity with thine enemies, and have distressed those distressing thee.

23 `For My messenger goeth before thee, and hath brought thee in unto the Amorite, and the Hittite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, and I have cut them off.

24 `Thou dost not bow thyself to their gods, nor serve them, nor do according to their doings, but dost utterly devote them, and thoroughly break their standing pillars.

25 `And ye have served Jehovah your God, and He hath blessed thy bread and thy water, and I have turned aside sickness from thine heart;

26 there is not a miscarrying and barren one in thy land; the number of thy days I fulfil:

27 My terror I send before thee, and I have put to death all the people among whom thou comest, and I have given the neck of all thine enemies unto thee.

28 `And I have sent the hornet before thee, and it hath cast out the Hivite, the Canaanite, and the Hittite, from before thee;

29 I cast them not out from before thee in one year, lest the land be a desolation, and the beast of the field hath multiplied against thee;

30 little [by] little I cast them out from before thee, till thou art fruitful, and hast inherited the land.

31 `And I have set thy border from the Red Sea, even unto the sea of the Philistines, and from the wilderness unto the River: for I give into your hand the inhabitants of the land, and thou hast cast them out from before thee;

32 thou dost not make a covenant with them, and with their gods;

33 they do not dwell in thy land, lest they cause thee to sin against Me when thou servest their gods, when it becometh a snare to thee.'

Exodus 26

1 `And thou dost make the tabernacle: ten curtains of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet; [with] cherubs, work of a designer, thou dost make them;

2 the length of the one curtain [is] eight and twenty by the cubit, and the breadth of the one curtain four by the cubit, one measure [is] to all the curtains;

3 five of the curtains are joining one unto another, and five curtains are joining one to another.

4 `And thou hast made loops of blue upon the edge of the one curtain, at the end in the joining; and so thou makest in the edge of the outermost curtain, in the joining of the second.

5 fifty loops thou dost make in the one curtain, and fifty loops thou dost make in the edge of the curtain which [is] in the joining of the second, causing the loops to take hold one unto another;

6 and thou hast made fifty hooks of gold, and hast joined the curtains one to another by the hooks, and the tabernacle hath been one.

7 `And thou hast made curtains of goats' [hair], for a tent over the tabernacle; thou dost make eleven curtains:

8 the length of the one curtain [is] thirty by the cubit, and the breadth of the one curtain four by the cubit; one measure [is] to the eleven curtains;

9 and thou hast joined the five curtains apart, and the six curtains apart, and hast doubled the six curtains over-against the front of the tent.

10 `And thou hast made fifty loops on the edge of the one curtain, the outermost in the joining, and fifty loops on the edge of the curtain which is joining the second;

11 and thou hast made fifty hooks of brass, and hast brought in the hooks into the loops, and hast joined the tent, and it hath been one.

12 `And the superfluity in the curtains of the tent--the half of the curtain which is superfluous--hath spread over the hinder part of the tabernacle;

13 and the cubit on this side, and the cubit on that, in the superfluity in the length of the curtains of the tent, is spread out over the sides of the tabernacle, on this and on that, to cover it;

14 and thou hast made a covering for the tent, of rams' skins made red, and a covering of badgers' skins above.

15 `And thou hast made the boards for the tabernacle, of shittim wood, standing up;

16 ten cubits [is] the length of the board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of the one board;

17 two handles [are] to the one board, joined one unto another; so thou dost make for all the boards of the tabernacle;

18 and thou hast made the boards of the tabernacle: twenty boards for the south side southward;

19 and forty sockets of silver thou dost make under the twenty boards, two sockets under the one board for its two handles, and two sockets under the other board for its two handles.

20 `And for the second side of the tabernacle, for the north side, [are] twenty boards,

21 and their forty sockets of silver, two sockets under the one board, and two sockets under another board.

22 And for the sides of the tabernacle westward, thou dost make six boards.

23 And two boards thou dost make for the corners of the tabernacle in the two sides.

24 And they are pairs beneath, and together they are pairs above its head unto the one ring; so is it for them both, they are for the two corners.

25 And they have been eight boards, and their sockets of silver [are] sixteen sockets, two sockets under the one board, and two sockets under another board.

26 `And thou hast made bars of shittim wood: five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle,

27 and five bars for the boards of the second side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the side of the tabernacle at the two sides, westward;

28 and one hath caused the middle bar in the midst of the boards to reach from end unto end;

29 and the boards thou dost overlay [with] gold, and their rings thou dost make of gold places for bars, and hast overlaid their bars with gold;

30 and thou hast raised up the tabernacle according to its fashion which thou hast been shewn in the mount.

31 `And thou hast made a vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of a designer; he maketh it [with] cherubs;

32 and thou hast put it on four pillars of shittim wood, overlaid [with] gold, their pegs [are] of gold, on four sockets of silver.

33 `And thou hast put the vail under the hooks, and hast brought in thither within the vail the ark of the testimony; and the vail hath made a separation for you between the holy and the holy of holies.

34 `And thou hast put the mercy-seat on the ark of the testimony, in the holy of holies.

35 `And thou hast set the table at the outside of the vail, and the candlestick overagainst the table on the side of the tabernacle southward, and the table thou dost put on the north side.

36 `And thou hast made a covering for the opening of the tent, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of an embroiderer;

37 and thou hast made for the covering five pillars of shittim [wood], and hast overlaid them [with] gold, their pegs [are] of gold, and thou hast cast for them five sockets of brass.

Exodus 27

1 `And thou hast made the altar of shittim wood, five cubits the length, and five cubits the breadth--the altar is square--and three cubits its height.

2 And thou hast made its horns on its four corners, its horns are of the same, and thou hast overlaid it [with] brass.

3 And thou hast made its pots to remove its ashes, and its shovels, and its bowls, and its forks, and its fire-pans, even all its vessels thou dost make of brass.

4 `And thou hast made for it a grate of net-work of brass, and hast made on the net four rings of brass on its four extremities,

5 and hast put it under the compass of the altar beneath, and the net hath been unto the middle of the altar.

6 `And thou hast made staves for the altar, staves of shittim wood, and hast overlaid them [with] brass.

7 And the staves have been brought into the rings, and the staves have been on the two sides of the altar in bearing it.

8 Hollow with boards thou dost make it, as it hath been shewed thee in the mount, so do they make [it].

9 `And thou hast made the court of the tabernacle: for the south side southward, hangings for the court of twined linen, a hundred by the cubit [is] the length for the one side,

10 and its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets [are] of brass, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] of silver;

11 and so for the north side in length, hangings of a hundred [cubits] in length, and its twenty pillars and their twenty sockets [are] of brass, the pegs of the pillars and their fillets [are] of silver.

12 `And [for] the breadth of the court at the west side [are] hangings of fifty cubits, their pillars ten, and their sockets ten.

13 And [for] the breadth of the court at the east side, eastward, [are] fifty cubits.

14 And the hangings at the side [are] fifteen cubits, their pillars three, and their sockets three.

15 And at the second side [are] hangings fifteen [cubits], their pillars three, and their sockets three.

16 `And for the gate of the court a covering of twenty cubits, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of an embroiderer; their pillars four, their sockets four.

17 All the pillars of the court round about [are] filleted [with] silver, their pegs [are] silver, and their sockets brass.

18 `The length of the court [is] a hundred by the cubit, and the breadth fifty by fifty, and the height five cubits, of twined linen, and their sockets [are] brass,

19 even all the vessels of the tabernacle, in all its service, and all its pins, and all the pins of the court, [are] brass.

20 `And thou--thou dost command the sons of Israel, and they bring unto thee pure beaten olive oil for the light, to cause the lamp to go up continually;

21 in the tent of meeting, at the outside of the vail, which [is] over the testimony, doth Aaron--his sons also--arrange it from evening till morning before Jehovah--a statute age-during to their generations, from the sons of Israel.

Exodus 28

1 `And thou, bring thou near unto thee Aaron thy brother, and his sons with him, from the midst of the sons of Israel, for his being priest to Me, [even] Aaron, Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar, sons of Aaron;

2 and thou hast made holy garments for Aaron thy brother, for honour and for beauty;

3 and thou--thou dost speak unto all the wise of heart, whom I have filled [with] a spirit of wisdom, and they have made the garments of Aaron to sanctify him for his being priest to Me.

4 `And these [are] the garments which they make: a breastplate, and an ephod, and an upper robe, and an embroidered coat, a mitre, and a girdle; yea, they have made holy garments for Aaron thy brother, and for his sons, for his being priest to Me.

5 `And they take the gold, and the blue, and the purple, and the scarlet, and the linen,

6 and have made the ephod of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of a designer;

7 it hath two shoulders joining at its two ends, and it is joined.

8 `And the girdle of his ephod which [is] on him, according to its work, is of the same, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen.

9 `And thou hast taken the two shoham stones, and hast opened on them the names of the sons of Israel;

10 six of their names on the one stone, and the names of the remaining six on the second stone, according to their births;

11 the work of an engraver in stone, openings of a signet, thou dost open the two stones by the names of the sons of Israel; turned round, embroidered [with] gold, thou dost make them.

12 `And thou hast set the two stones on the shoulders of the ephod--stones of memorial to the sons of Israel--and Aaron hath borne their names before Jehovah, on his two shoulders, for a memorial.

13 `And thou hast made embroidered things of gold,

14 and two chains of pure gold, wreathed work thou dost make them, work of thick bands, and thou hast put the thick chains on the embroidered things.

15 `And thou hast made a breastplate of judgment, work of a designer; according to the work of the ephod thou dost make it; of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen thou dost make it;

16 it is square, doubled, a span its length, and a span its breadth.

17 `And thou hast set in it settings of stone, four rows of stone; a row of sardius, topaz, and carbuncle [is] the first row;

18 and the second row [is] emerald, sapphire, and diamond;

19 and the third row [is] opal, agate, and amethyst;

20 and the fourth row [is] beryl, and onyx, and jasper; embroidered with gold are they in their settings,

21 and the stones are according to the names of the sons of Israel, twelve, according to their names, openings of a signet, each by his name are they for the twelve tribes.

22 `And thou hast made on the breastplate wreathed chains, work of thick bands, of pure gold;

23 and thou hast made on the breastplate two rings of gold, and hast put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate;

24 and thou hast put the two thick bands of gold on the two rings at the ends of the breastplate;

25 and the two ends of the two thick bands thou dost put on the two embroidered things, and thou hast put [them] on the shoulders of the ephod over-against its face.

26 `And thou hast made two rings of gold, and hast set them on the two ends of the breastplate, on its border, which [is] over-against the ephod within;

27 and thou hast made two rings of gold, and hast put them on the two shoulders of the ephod, beneath, over-against its front, over-against its joining, above the girdle of the ephod,

28 and they bind the breastplate by its rings unto the rings of the ephod with a ribbon of blue, to be above the girdle of the ephod, and the breastplate is not loosed from the ephod.

29 `And Aaron hath borne the names of the sons of Israel in the breastplate of judgment, on his heart, in his going in unto the sanctuary, for a memorial before Jehovah continually.

30 `And thou hast put unto the breastplate of judgment the Lights and the Perfections, and they have been on the heart of Aaron, in his going in before Jehovah, and Aaron hath borne the judgment of the sons of Israel on his heart before Jehovahcontinually.

31 `And thou hast made the upper robe of the ephod completely of blue,

32 and the opening for its head hath been in its midst, a border is to its opening round about, work of a weaver, as the opening of a habergeon there is to it; it is not rent.

33 `And thou hast made on its hem pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, on its hem round about, and bells of gold in their midst round about;

34 a bell of gold and a pomegranate, a bell of gold and a pomegranate [are] on the hems of the upper robe round about.

35 `And it hath been on Aaron to minister in, and its sound hath been heard in his coming in unto the sanctuary before Jehovah, and in his going out, and he doth not die.

36 `And thou hast made a flower of pure gold, and hast opened on it--openings of a signet--`Holy to Jehovah;'

37 and thou hast put it on a blue ribbon, and it hath been on the mitre--over-against the front of the mitre it is;

38 and it hath been on the forehead of Aaron, and Aaron hath borne the iniquity of the holy things which the sons of Israel do hallow, even all their holy gifts; and it hath been on his forehead continually for a pleasing thing for them before Jehovah.

39 `And thou hast embroidered the coat of linen, and hast made a mitre of linen, and a girdle thou dost make--work of an embroiderer.

40 `And for the sons of Aaron thou dost make coats, and thou hast made for them girdles, yea, bonnets thou dost make for them, for honour and for beauty;

41 and thou hast clothed Aaron thy brother with them, and his sons with him, and hast anointed them, and hast consecrated their hand, and hast sanctified them, and they have been priests to Me.

42 `And make thou for them linen trousers to cover the naked flesh: they are from the loins even unto the thighs;

43 and they have been on Aaron and on his sons, in their going in unto the tent of meeting, or in their drawing nigh unto the altar to minister in the sanctuary, and they do not bear iniquity nor have they died; a statute age-during to him, andto his seed after him.

Exodus 36

1 And Bezaleel, and Aholiab, and every wise-hearted man, in whom Jehovah hath given wisdom and understanding to know to do every work of the service of the sanctuary, have done according to all that Jehovah commanded.

2 And Moses calleth unto Bezaleel, and unto Aholiab, and unto every wise-hearted man in whose heart Jehovah hath given wisdom, every one whom his heart lifted up, to come near unto the work to do it.

3 And they take from before Moses all the heave-offering which the sons of Israel have brought in for the work of the service of the sanctuary to do it; and still they have brought in unto him a willing-offering morning by morning.

4 And all the wise men, who are doing all the work of the sanctuary, come each from his work which they are doing,

5 and speak unto Moses, saying, `The people are multiplying to bring in more than sufficient for the service of the work which Jehovah commanded to make.'

6 And Moses commandeth, and they cause a voice to pass over through the camp, saying, `Let not man or woman make any more work for the heave-offering of the sanctuary;' and the people are restrained from bringing,

7 and the work hath been sufficient for them, for all the work, to do it, and to leave.

8 And all the wise-hearted ones among the doers of the work make the tabernacle; ten curtains of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, [with] cherubs, work of a designer, he hath made them.

9 The length of the one curtain [is] eight and twenty by the cubit, and the breadth of the one curtain four by the cubit; one measure [is] to all the curtains.

10 And he joineth the five curtains one unto another, and the [other] five curtains he hath joined one unto another;

11 and he maketh loops of blue on the edge of the one curtain, at the end, in the joining; so he hath made in the edge of the outmost curtain, in the joining of the second;

12 fifty loops he hath made in the one curtain, and fifty loops hath he made in the end of the curtain which [is] in the joining of the second; the loops are taking hold one on another.

13 And he maketh fifty hooks of gold, and joineth the curtains one unto another by the hooks, and the tabernacle is one.

14 And he maketh curtains of goats' [hair] for a tent over the tabernacle; eleven curtains he hath made them;

15 the length of the one curtain [is] thirty by the cubit, and the breadth of the one curtain [is] four cubits; one measure [is] to the eleven curtains;

16 and he joineth the five curtains apart, and the six curtains apart.

17 And he maketh fifty loops on the outer edge of the curtain, in the joining; and fifty loops he hath made on the edge of the curtain which is joining the second;

18 and he maketh fifty hooks of brass to join the tent--to be one;

19 and he maketh a covering for the tent of rams' skins made red, and a covering of badgers' skins above.

20 And he maketh the boards for the tabernacle of shittim wood, standing up;

21 ten cubits [is] the length of the [one] board, and a cubit and a half the breadth of the [one] board;

22 two handles [are] to the one board, joined one unto another; so he hath made for all the boards of the tabernacle.

23 And he maketh the boards for the tabernacle; twenty boards for the south side southward;

24 and forty sockets of silver he hath made under the twenty boards, two sockets under the one board for its two handles, and two sockets under the other board for its two handles.

25 And for the second side of the tabernacle, for the north side, he hath made twenty boards,

26 and their forty sockets of silver, two sockets under the one board, and two sockets under the other board;

27 and for the sides of the tabernacle, westward, hath he made six boards;

28 and two boards hath he made for the corners of the tabernacle, in the two sides;

29 and they have been twins below, and together they are twins at its head, at the one ring; so he hath done to both of them at the two corners;

30 and there have been eight boards; and their sockets of silver [are] sixteen sockets, two sockets under the one board.

31 And he maketh bars of shittim wood, five for the boards of the one side of the tabernacle,

32 and five bars for the boards of the second side of the tabernacle, and five bars for the boards of the tabernacle, for the sides westward;

33 and he maketh the middle bar to enter into the midst of the boards from end to end;

34 and the boards he hath overlaid with gold, and their rings he hath made of gold, places for bars, and he overlayeth the bars with gold.

35 And he maketh the vail of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of a designer he hath made it, [with] cherubs;

36 and he maketh for it four pillars of shittim [wood], and overlayeth them with gold; their pegs [are] of gold; and he casteth for them four sockets of silver.

37 And he maketh a covering for the opening of the tent, of blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, work of an embroiderer,

38 also its five pillars, and their pegs; and he overlaid their tops and their fillets [with] gold, and their five sockets [are] brass.

Exodus 39

1 And of the blue, and the purple, and the scarlet, they made coloured garments, to minister in the sanctuary; and they make the holy garments which [are] for Aaron, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

2 And he maketh the ephod, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen,

3 and they expand the plates of gold, and have cut off wires to work in the midst of the blue, and in the midst of the purple, and in the midst of the scarlet, and in the midst of the linen-- work of a designer;

4 shoulder-pieces they have made for it, joining; at its two ends it is joined.

5 And the girdle of his ephod which [is] on it is of the same, according to its work, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

6 And they prepare the shoham stones, set, embroidered [with] gold, opened with openings of a signet, by the names of the sons of Israel;

7 and he setteth them on the shoulders of the ephod--stones of memorial for the sons of Israel, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

8 And he maketh the breastplate, work of a designer, like the work of the ephod, of gold, blue, and purple, and scarlet, and twined linen;

9 it hath been square; double they have made the breastplate, a span its length, and a span its breadth, doubled.

10 And they fill in it four rows of stones; a row of a sardius, a topaz, and a carbuncle [is] the one row;

11 and the second row an emerald, a sapphire, and a diamond;

12 and the third row an opal, an agate, and an amethyst;

13 and the fourth row a beryl, an onyx, and a jasper--set, embroidered [with] gold, in their settings.

14 And the stones, according to the names of the sons of Israel, are twelve, according to their names, openings of a signet, each according to his name, for the twelve tribes.

15 And they make on the breastplate wreathed chains, work of thick bands, of pure gold;

16 and they make two embroidered things of gold, and two rings of gold, and put the two rings on the two ends of the breastplate,

17 and they put the two thick bands of gold on the two rings on the ends of the breastplate;

18 and the two ends of the two thick bands they have put on the two embroidered things, and they put them on the shoulders of the ephod, over-against its front.

19 And they make two rings of gold, and set [them] on the two ends of the breastplate, on its border, which [is] on the side of the ephod within;

20 and they make two rings of gold, and put them on the two shoulders of the ephod below, over-against its front, over-against its joining, above the girdle of the ephod;

21 and they bind the breastplate by its rings unto the rings of the ephod, with a ribbon of blue, to be above the girdle of the ephod, and the breastplate is not loosed from off the ephod, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

22 And he maketh the upper robe of the ephod, work of a weaver, completely of blue;

23 and the opening of the upper robe [is] in its midst, as the opening of a habergeon, a border [is] to its opening round about, it is not rent;

24 and they make on the hems of the upper robe pomegranates of blue, and purple, and scarlet, twined.

25 And they make bells of pure gold, and put the bells in the midst of the pomegranates, on the hems of the upper robe, round about, in the midst of the pomegranates;

26 a bell and a pomegranate, a bell and a pomegranate, [are] on the hems of the upper robe, round about, to minister in, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

27 And they make the coats of linen, work of a weaver, for Aaron and for his sons,

28 and the mitre of linen, and the beautiful bonnets of linen, and the linen trousers, of twined linen,

29 and the girdle of twined linen, and blue, and purple, and scarlet, work of an embroiderer, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

30 And they make the flower of the holy crown of pure gold, and write on it a writing, openings of a signet, `Holy to Jehovah;'

31 and they put on it a ribbon of blue, to put [it] on the mitre above, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

32 And all the service of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting is completed; and the sons of Israel do according to all that Jehovah hath commanded Moses; so they have done.

33 And they bring in the tabernacle unto Moses, the tent, and all its vessels, its hooks, its boards, its bars, and its pillars, and its sockets;

34 and the covering of rams' skins, which are made red, and the covering of badgers' skins, and the vail of the covering;

35 the ark of the testimony and its staves, and the mercy-seat;

36 the table, all its vessels, and the bread of the presence;

37 the pure candlestick, its lamps, the lamps of arrangement, and all its vessels, and the oil for the light.

38 And the golden altar, and the anointing oil, and the spice-perfume, and the covering of the opening of the tent;

39 the brazen altar and the brazen grate which it hath, its staves, and all its vessels, the laver and its base.

40 The hangings of the court, its pillars, and its sockets; and the covering for the gate of the court, its cords, and its pins; and all the vessels of the service of the tabernacle, for the tent of meeting;

41 the coloured clothes to minister in the sanctuary, the holy garments for Aaron the priest, and the garments of his sons, to act as priest in.

42 According to all that Jehovah hath commanded Moses, so have the sons of Israel done all the service;

43 and Moses seeth all the work, and lo, they have done it as Jehovah hath commanded; so they have done. And Moses doth bless them.

Exodus 40

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `On the first day of the month, in the first month, thou dost raise up the tabernacle of the tent of meeting,

3 and hast set there the ark of the testimony, and hast covered over the ark with the vail,

4 and hast brought in the table, and set its arrangement in order, and hast brought in the candlestick, and caused its lamps to go up.

5 `And thou hast put the golden altar for perfume before the ark of the testimony, and hast put the covering of the opening to the tabernacle,

6 and hast put the altar of the burnt-offering before the opening of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting,

7 and hast put the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and hast put water there.

8 `And thou hast set the court round about, and hast placed the covering of the gate of the court,

9 and hast taken the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle, and all that [is] in it, and hallowed it, and all its vessels, and it hath been holy;

10 and thou hast anointed the altar of the burnt-offering, and all its vessels, and sanctified the altar, and the altar hath been most holy;

11 and thou hast anointed the laver and its base, and sanctified it.

12 `And thou hast brought near Aaron and his sons unto the opening of the tent of meeting, and hast bathed them with water;

13 and thou hast clothed Aaron with the holy garments, and anointed him, and sanctified him, and he hath acted as priest to Me.

14 `And his sons thou dost bring near, and hast clothed them with coats,

15 and anointed them as thou hast anointed their father, and they have acted as priests to Me, and their anointing hath been to be to them for a priesthood age-during, to their generations.'

16 And Moses doth according to all that Jehovah hath commanded him; so he hath done.

17 And it cometh to pass, in the first month, in the second year, in the first of the month, the tabernacle hath been raised up;

18 and Moses raiseth up the tabernacle, and setteth its sockets, and placeth its boards, and placeth its bars, and raiseth its pillars,

19 and spreadeth the tent over the tabernacle, and putteth the covering of the tent upon it above, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

20 And he taketh and putteth the testimony unto the ark, and setteth the staves on the ark, and putteth the mercy-seat on the ark above;

21 and bringeth in the ark unto the tabernacle, and placeth the vail of the covering, and covereth over the ark of the testimony, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

22 And he putteth the table in the tent of meeting, on the side of the tabernacle northward, at the outside of the vail,

23 and setteth in order upon it the arrangement of bread, before Jehovah, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

24 And he putteth the candlestick in the tent of meeting, over-against the table, on the side of the tabernacle southward,

25 and causeth the lamps to go up before Jehovah, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

26 And he setteth the golden altar in the tent of meeting, before the vail,

27 and maketh perfume on it--spice-perfume--as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

28 And he setteth the covering of the opening to the tabernacle,

29 and the altar of the burnt-offering he hath set at the opening of the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, and causeth the burnt-offering to go up upon it, and the present, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

30 And he putteth the laver between the tent of meeting and the altar, and putteth water there for washing,

31 and Moses and Aaron and his sons have washed their hands and their feet at the same;

32 in their going in unto the tent of meeting, and in their drawing near unto the altar, they wash, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

33 And he raiseth up the court round about the tabernacle, and about the altar, and placeth the covering of the gate of the court; and Moses completeth the work.

34 And the cloud covereth the tent of meeting, and the honour of Jehovah hath filled the tabernacle;

35 and Moses hath not been able to go in unto the tent of meeting, for the cloud hath tabernacled on it, and the honour of Jehovah hath filled the tabernacle.

36 And in the going up of the cloud from off the tabernacle the sons of Israel journey in all their journeys;

37 and if the cloud go not up then they journey not, until the day of its going up:

38 for the cloud of Jehovah [is] on the tabernacle by day, and fire is in it by night, before the eyes of all the house of Israel in all their journeys.

Leviticus 2

1 `And when a person bringeth near an offering, a present to Jehovah, of flour is his offering, and he hath poured on it oil, and hath put on it frankincense;

2 and he hath brought it in unto the sons of Aaron, the priests, and he hath taken from thence the fulness of his hand of its flour and of its oil, besides all its frankincense, and the priest hath made perfume with its memorial on the altar,a fire-offering of sweet fragrance to Jehovah;

3 and the remnant of the present [is] for Aaron and for his sons, most holy, of the fireofferings of Jehovah.

4 `And when thou bringest near an offering, a present baked in an oven, [it is of] unleavened cakes of flour mixed with oil, or thin unleavened cakes anointed with oil.

5 `And if thine offering [is] a present [made] on the girdel, it is of flour, mixed with oil, unleavened;

6 divide thou it into parts, and thou hast poured on it oil; it [is] a present.

7 `And if thine offering [is] a present [made] on the frying-pan, of flour with oil it is made,

8 and thou hast brought in the present which is made of these to Jehovah, and [one] hath brought it near unto the priest, and he hath brought it nigh unto the altar,

9 and the priest hath lifted up from the present its memorial, and hath made perfume on the altar, a fire-offering of sweet fragrance to Jehovah;

10 and the remnant of the present [is] for Aaron and for his sons, most holy, of the fireofferings of Jehovah.

11 No present which ye bring near to Jehovah is made fermented, for with any leaven or any honey ye perfume no fire-offering to Jehovah.

12 `An offering of first -[fruits] --ye bring them near to Jehovah, but on the altar they go not up, for sweet fragrance.

13 And every offering--thy present--with salt thou dost season, and thou dost not let the salt of the covenant of thy God cease from thy present; with all thine offerings thou dost bring near salt.

14 `And if thou bring near a present of first-ripe [fruits] to Jehovah, --of green ears, roasted with fire, beaten out [corn] of a fruitful field thou dost bring near the present of thy firstripe [fruits],

15 and thou hast put on it oil, and laid on it frankincense, it [is] a present;

16 and the priest hath made perfume with its memorial from its beaten out [corn], and from its oil, besides all its frankincense--a fire-offering to Jehovah.

Leviticus 13

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, and unto Aaron, saying,

2 `When a man hath in the skin of his flesh a rising, or scab, or bright spot, and it hath become in the skin of his flesh a leprous plague, then he hath been brought in unto Aaron the priest, or unto one of his sons the priests;

3 and the priest hath seen the plague in the skin of the flesh, and the hair in the plague hath turned white, and the appearance of the plague [is] deeper than the skin of his flesh--it [is] a plague of leprosy, and the priest hath seen him,and hath pronounced him unclean.

4 `And if the bright spot is white in the skin of his flesh, and its appearance is not deeper than the skin, and its hair hath not turned white, then hath the priest shut up [him who hath] the plague seven days.

5 `And the priest hath seen him on the seventh day, and lo, the plague hath stood in his eyes, the plague hath not spread in the skin, and the priest hath shut him up a second seven days.

6 `And the priest hath seen him on the second seventh day, and lo, the plague is become weak, and the plague hath not spread in the skin--and the priest hath pronounced him clean, it [is] a scab, and he hath washed his garments, and hath been clean.

7 `And if the scab spread greatly in the skin, after his being seen by the priest for his cleansing, then he hath been seen a second time by the priest;

8 and the priest hath seen, and lo, the scab hath spread in the skin, and the priest hath pronounced him unclean; it [is] leprosy.

9 `When a plague of leprosy is in a man, then he hath been brought in unto the priest,

10 and the priest hath seen, and lo, a white rising in the skin, and it hath turned the hair white, and a quickening of raw flesh [is] in the rising, --

11 an old leprosy it [is] in the skin of his flesh, and the priest hath pronounced him unclean; he doth not shut him up, for he [is] unclean.

12 `And if the leprosy break out greatly in the skin, and the leprosy hath covered all the skin of [him who hath] the plague, from his head even unto his feet, to all that appeareth to the eyes of the priest,

13 then hath the priest seen, and lo, the leprosy hath covered all his flesh, and he hath pronounced [him who hath] the plague clean; it hath all turned white; he [is] clean.

14 `And in the day of raw flesh being seen in him he is unclean;

15 and the priest hath seen the raw flesh, and hath pronounced him unclean; the raw flesh is unclean, it [is] leprosy.

16 Or when the raw flesh turneth back, and hath been turned to white, then he hath come in unto the priest,

17 and the priest hath seen him, and lo, the plague hath been turned to white, and the priest hath pronounced clean [him who hath] the plague; he [is] clean.

18 `And when flesh hath in it, in its skin, an ulcer, and it hath been healed,

19 and there hath been in the place of the ulcer a white rising, or a bright white spot, very red, then it hath been seen by the priest,

20 and the priest hath seen, and lo, its appearance [is] lower than the skin, and its hair hath turned white, and the priest hath pronounced him unclean; it [is] a plague of leprosy--in an ulcer it hath broken out.

21 `And if the priest see it, and lo, there is no white hair in it, and it is not lower than the skin, and is become weak, then hath the priest shut him up seven days;

22 and if it spread greatly in the skin, then hath the priest pronounced him unclean, it [is] a plague;

23 and if in its place the bright spot stay--it hath not spread--it [is] an inflammation of the ulcer; and the priest hath pronounced him clean.

24 `Or when flesh hath in its skin a fiery burning, and the quickening of the burning, the bright white spot, hath been very red or white,

25 and the priest hath seen it, and lo, the hair hath turned white in the bright spot, and its appearance [is] deeper than the skin; leprosy it [is], in the burning it hath broken out, and the priest hath pronounced him unclean; it [is] a plague of leprosy.

26 `And if the priest see it, and lo, there is no white hair on the bright spot, and it is not lower than the skin, and it is become weak, then the priest hath shut him up seven days;

27 and the priest hath seen him on the seventh day, if it spread greatly in the skin, then the priest hath pronounced him unclean; a plague of leprosy it [is].

28 `And if the bright spot stay in its place, it hath not spread in the skin, and is become weak; a rising of the burning it [is], and the priest hath pronounced him clean; for it [is] inflammation of the burning.

29 `And when a man (or a woman) hath in him a plague in the head or in the beard,

30 then hath the priest seen the plague, and lo, its appearance is deeper than the skin, and in it a thin shining hair, and the priest hath pronounced him unclean; it [is] a scall--it [is] a leprosy of the head or of the beard.

31 `And when the priest seeth the plague of the scall, and lo, its appearance is not deeper than the skin, and there is no black hair in it, then hath the priest shut up [him who hath] the plague of the scall seven days.

32 `And the priest hath seen the plague on the seventh day, and lo, the scall hath not spread, and a shining hair hath not been in it, and the appearance of the scall is not deeper than the skin,

33 then he hath shaved himself, but the scall he doth not shave; and the priest hath shut up [him who hath] the scall a second seven days.

34 And the priest hath seen the scall on the seventh day, and lo, the scall hath not spread in the skin, and its appearance is not deeper than the skin, and the priest hath pronounced him clean, and he hath washed his garments, and hath beenclean.

35 `And if the scall spread greatly in the skin after his cleansing,

36 and the priest hath seen him, and lo, the scall hath spread in the skin, the priest seeketh not for the shining hair, he is unclean;

37 and if in his eyes the scall hath stayed, and black hair hath sprung up in it, the scall hath been healed--he [is] clean--and the priest hath pronounced him clean.

38 `And when a man or woman hath in the skin of their flesh bright spots, white bright spots,

39 and the priest hath seen, and lo, in the skin of their flesh white weak bright spots, it [is] a freckled spot broken out in the skin; he [is] clean.

40 `And when a man's head [is] polished, he [is] bald, he [is] clean;

41 and if from the corner of his face his head is polished, he [is] bald of the forehead; he [is] clean.

42 `And when there is in the bald back of the head, or in the bald forehead, a very red white plague, it [is] a leprosy breaking out in the bald back of the head, or in the bald forehead;

43 and the priest hath seen him, and lo, the rising of the very red white plague in the bald back of the head, or in the bald forehead, [is] as the appearance of leprosy, in the skin of the flesh,

44 he [is] a leprous man, he [is] unclean; the priest doth pronounce him utterly unclean; his plague [is] in his head.

45 `As to the leper in whom [is] the plague, his garments are rent, and his head is uncovered, and he covereth over the upper lip, and `Unclean! unclean!' he calleth;

46 all the days that the plague [is] in him he is unclean; he [is] unclean, alone he doth dwell, at the outside of the camp [is] his dwelling.

47 `And when there is in any garment a plague of leprosy, --in a garment of wool, or in a garment of linen,

48 or in the warp, or in the woof, of linen or of wool, or in a skin, or in any work of skin,

49 and the plague hath been very green or very red in the garment, or in the skin, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in any vessel of skin, it [is] a plague of leprosy, and it hath been shewn the priest.

50 `And the priest hath seen the plague, and hath shut up [that which hath] the plague, seven days;

51 and he hath seen the plague on the seventh day, and the plague hath spread in the garment, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in the skin, of all that is made of skin for work; the plague [is] a fretting leprosy, it [is] unclean.

52 `And he hath burnt the garment, or the warp, or the woof, in wool or in linen, or any vessel of skin in which the plague is; for it [is] a fretting leprosy; with fire it is burnt.

53 `And if the priest see, and lo, the plague hath not spread in the garment, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in any vessel of skin,

54 then hath the priest commanded, and they have washed that in which the plague [is], and he hath shut it up a second seven days.

55 And the priest hath seen [that which hath] the plague after it hath been washed, and lo, the plague hath not changed its aspect, and the plague hath not spread, --it [is] unclean; with fire thou dost burn it; it [is] a fretting in its back-part or in its front-part.

56 `And if the priest hath seen, and lo, the plague [is] become weak after it hath been washed, then he hath rent it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof;

57 and if it still be seen in the garment, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in any vessel of skin, it [is] a fretting; with fire thou dost burn it--that in which the plague [is].

58 `And the garment, or the warp, or the woof, or any vessel of skin which thou dost wash when the plague hath turned aside from them, then it hath been washed a second time, and hath been clean.

59 `This [is] the law of a plague of leprosy [in] a garment of wool or of linen, or of the warp or of the woof, or of any vessel of skin, to pronounce it clean or to pronounce it unclean.'

Leviticus 15

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, and unto Aaron, saying,

2 `Speak unto the sons of Israel, and ye have said unto them, When there is an issue out of the flesh of any man, [for] his issue he [is] unclean;

3 and this is his uncleanness in his issue--his flesh hath run with his issue, or his flesh hath stopped from his issue; it [is] his uncleanness.

4 `All the bed on which he lieth who hath the issue is unclean, and all the vessel on which he sitteth is unclean;

5 and any one who cometh against his bed doth wash his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

6 `And he who is sitting on the vessel on which he sitteth who hath the issue, doth wash his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

7 `And he who is coming against the flesh of him who hath the issue, doth wash his garments, and hath bathed with water, and hath been unclean till the evening.

8 `And when he who hath the issue spitteth on him who is clean, then he hath washed his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

9 `And all the saddle on which he rideth who hath the issue is unclean;

10 and any one who is coming against anything which is under him is unclean till the evening, and he who is bearing them doth wash his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

11 `And anyone against whom he cometh who hath the issue (and his hands hath not rinsed with water) hath even washed his garments, and bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

12 `And the earthen vessel which he who hath the issue cometh against is broken; and every wooden vessel is rinsed with water.

13 `And when he who hath the issue is clean from his issue, then he hath numbered to himself seven days for his cleansing, and hath washed his garments, and hath bathed his flesh with running water, and been clean.

14 `And on the eighth day he taketh to himself two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, and hath come in before Jehovah unto the opening of the tent of meeting, and hath given them unto the priest;

15 and the priest hath made them, one a sin-offering, and the one a burnt-offering; and the priest hath made atonement for him before Jehovah, because of his issue.

16 `And when a man's seed of copulation goeth out from him, then he hath bathed with water all his flesh, and been unclean till the evening.

17 `And any garment, or any skin on which there is seed of copulation, hath also been washed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

18 `And a woman with whom a man lieth with seed of copulation, they also have bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

19 `And when a woman hath an issue--blood is her issue in her flesh--seven days she is in her separation, and any one who is coming against her is unclean till the evening.

20 `And anything on which she lieth in her separation is unclean, and anything on which she sitteth is unclean;

21 and any one who is coming against her bed doth wash his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

22 `And any one who is coming against any vessel on which she sitteth doth wash his garments, and hath washed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

23 `And if it [is] on the bed, or on the vessel on which she is sitting, in his coming against it, he is unclean till the evening.

24 `And if a man really lie with her, and her separation is on him, then he hath been unclean seven days, and all the bed on which he lieth is unclean.

25 `And when a woman's issue of blood floweth many days within the time of her separation, or when it floweth over her separation--all the days of the issue of her uncleanness are as the days of her separation; she [is] unclean.

26 `All the bed on which she lieth all the days of her issue is as the bed of her separation to her, and all the vessel on which she sitteth is unclean as the uncleanness of her separation;

27 and any one who is coming against them is unclean, and hath washed his garments, and hath bathed with water, and been unclean till the evening.

28 `And if she hath been clean from her issue, then she hath numbered to herself seven days, and afterwards she is clean;

29 and on the eighth day she taketh to herself two turtle-doves, or two young pigeons, and hath brought them in unto the priest, unto the opening of the tent of meeting;

30 and the priest hath made the one a sin-offering, and the one a burnt-offering, and the priest hath made atonement for her before Jehovah, because of the issue of her uncleanness.

31 `And ye have separated the sons of Israel from their uncleanness, and they die not in their uncleanness, in their defiling My tabernacle which [is] in their midst.

32 `This [is] the law of him who hath an issue, and of him whose seed of copulation goeth out from him, for uncleanness thereby,

33 and of her who is sick in her separation, and of him who hath an issue, the issue of a male or of a female, and of a man who lieth with an unclean woman.'

Leviticus 18

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Speak unto the sons of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, I [am] Jehovah your God;

3 according to the work of the land of Egypt in which ye have dwelt ye do not, and according to the work of the land of Canaan whither I am bringing you in, ye do not, and in their statutes ye walk not.

4 `My judgments ye do, and My statutes ye keep, to walk in them; I [am] Jehovah your God;

5 and ye have kept My statutes and My judgments which man doth and liveth in them; I [am] Jehovah.

6 `None of you unto any relation of his flesh doth draw near to uncover nakedness; I [am] Jehovah.

7 `The nakedness of thy father and the nakedness of thy mother thou dost not uncover, she [is] thy mother; thou dost not uncover her nakedness.

8 `The nakedness of the wife of thy father thou dost not uncover; it [is] the nakedness of thy father.

9 `The nakedness of thy sister, daughter of thy father, or daughter of thy mother, born at home or born without; thou dost not uncover their nakedness.

10 `The nakedness of thy son's daughter, or of thy daughter's daughter: thou dost not uncover their nakedness; for theirs [is] thy nakedness.

11 `The nakedness of a daughter of thy father's wife, begotten of thy father, she [is] thy sister; thou dost not uncover her nakedness.

12 `The nakedness of a sister of thy father thou dost not uncover; she [is] a relation of thy father.

13 `The nakedness of thy mother's sister thou dost not uncover; for she [is] thy mother's relation.

14 `The nakedness of thy father's brother thou dost not uncover; unto his wife thou dost not draw near; she [is] thine aunt.

15 `The nakedness of thy daughter-in-law thou dost not uncover; she [is] thy son's wife; thou dost not uncover her nakedness.

16 `The nakedness of thy brother's wife thou dost not uncover; it [is] thy brother's nakedness.

17 `The nakedness of a woman and her daughter thou dost not uncover; her son's daughter, and her daughter's daughter thou dost not take to uncover her nakedness; they [are] her relations; it [is] wickedness.

18 `And a woman unto another thou dost not take, to be an adversary, to uncover her nakedness beside her, in her life.

19 `And unto a woman in the separation of her uncleanness thou dost not draw near to uncover her nakedness.

20 `And unto the wife of thy fellow thou dost not give thy seed of copulation, for uncleanness with her.

21 `And of thy seed thou dost not give to pass over to the Molech; nor dost thou pollute the name of thy God; I [am] Jehovah.

22 `And with a male thou dost not lie as one lieth with a woman; abomination it [is].

23 `And with any beast thou dost not give thy copulation, for uncleanness with it; and a woman doth not stand before a beast to lie down with it; confusion it [is].

24 `Ye are not defiled with all these, for with all these have the nations been defiled which I am sending away from before you;

25 and the land is defiled, and I charge its iniquity upon it, and the land vomiteth out its inhabitants:

26 and ye--ye have kept My statutes and My judgments, and do not [any] of all these abominations, the native and the sojourner who is sojourning in your midst,

27 (for all these abominations have the men of the land done who [are] before you, and the land is defiled),

28 and the land doth not vomit you out in your defiling it, as it hath vomited out the nation which [is] before you;

29 for any one who doth [any] of all these abominations--even the persons who are doing [so], have been cut off from the midst of their people;

30 and ye have kept My charge, so as not to do [any] of the abominable statutes which have been done before you, and ye do not defile yourselves with them; I [am] Jehovah your God.'

Leviticus 19

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Speak unto all the company of the sons of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, Ye are holy, for holy [am] I, Jehovah, your God.

3 `Each his mother and his father ye do fear, and My sabbaths ye do keep; I [am] Jehovah your God.

4 `Ye do not turn unto the idols, and a molten god ye do not make to yourselves; I [am] Jehovah your God.

5 `And when ye sacrifice a sacrifice of peace-offerings to Jehovah, at your pleasure ye do sacrifice it;

6 in the day of your sacrificing it is eaten, and on the morrow, and that which is left unto the third day with fire is burnt,

7 and if it be really eaten on the third day, it [is] an abomination, it is not pleasing,

8 and he who is eating it his iniquity doth bear, for the holy thing of Jehovah he hath polluted, and that person hath been cut off from his people.

9 `And in your reaping the harvest of your land ye do not completely reap the corner of thy field, and the gleaning of thy harvest thou dost not gather,

10 and thy vineyard thou dost not glean, even the omitted part of thy vineyard thou dost not gather, to the poor and to the sojourner thou dost leave them; I [am] Jehovah your God.

11 `Ye do not steal, nor feign, nor lie one against his fellow.

12 `And ye do not swear by My name to falsehood, or thou hast polluted the name of thy God; I [am] Jehovah.

13 `Thou dost not oppress thy neighbour, nor take plunder; the wages of the hireling doth not remain with thee till morning.

14 `Thou dost not revile the deaf; and before the blind thou dost not put a stumbling block; and thou hast been afraid of thy God; I [am] Jehovah.

15 `Ye do not do perversity in judgment; thou dost not lift up the face of the poor, nor honour the face of the great; in righteousness thou dost judge thy fellow.

16 `Thou dost not go slandering among thy people; thou dost not stand against the blood of thy neighbour; I [am] Jehovah.

17 `Thou dost not hate thy brother in thy heart; thou dost certainly reprove thy fellow, and not suffer sin on him.

18 `Thou dost not take vengeance, nor watch the sons of thy people; and thou hast had love to thy neighbour as thyself; I [am] Jehovah.

19 `My statutes ye do keep: thy cattle thou dost not cause to gender [with] diverse kinds; thy field thou dost not sow with diverse kinds, and a garment of diverse kinds, shaatnez, doth not go up upon thee.

20 `And when a man lieth with a woman with seed of copulation, and she a maidservant, betrothed to a man, and not really ransomed, or freedom hath not been given to her, an investigation there is; they are not put to death, for she [is] notfree.

21 `And he hath brought in his guilt-offering to Jehovah, unto the opening of the tent of meeting, a ram [for] a guilt-offering,

22 and the priest hath made atonement for him with the ram of the guilt-offering before Jehovah, for his sin which he hath sinned, and it hath been forgiven him because of his sin which he hath sinned.

23 `And when ye come in unto the land, and have planted all [kinds] of trees [for] food, then ye have reckoned as uncircumcised its fruit, three years it is to you uncircumcised, it is not eaten,

24 and in the fourth year all its fruit is holy--praises for Jehovah.

25 And in the fifth year ye do eat its fruit--to add to you its increase; I [am] Jehovah your God.

26 `Ye do not eat with the blood; ye do not enchant, nor observe clouds.

27 `Ye do not round the corner of your head, nor destroy the corner of thy beard.

28 `And a cutting for the soul ye do not put in your flesh; and a writing, a cross-mark, ye do not put on you; I [am] Jehovah.

29 `Thou dost not pollute thy daughter to cause her to go a-whoring, that the land go not a-whoring, and the land hath been full of wickedness.

30 `My sabbaths ye do keep, and My sanctuary ye do reverence; I [am] Jehovah.

31 `Ye do not turn unto those having familiar spirits; and unto wizards ye do not seek, for uncleanness by them; I [am] Jehovah your God.

32 `At the presence of grey hairs thou dost rise up, and thou hast honoured the presence of an old man, and hast been afraid of thy God; I [am] Jehovah.

33 `And when a sojourner sojourneth with thee in your land, thou dost not oppress him;

34 as a native among you is the sojourner to you who is sojourning with you, and thou hast had love to him as to thyself, for sojourners ye have been in the land of Egypt; I [am] Jehovah your God.

35 `Ye do not do perversity in judgment, in mete-yard, in weight, or in liquid measure;

36 righteous balances, righteous weights, a righteous ephah, and a righteous hin ye have; I [am] Jehovah your God, who hath brought you out from the land of Egypt;

37 and ye have observed all my statutes, and all my judgments, and have done them; I [am] Jehovah.'

Leviticus 20

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `And unto the sons of Israel thou dost say, Any man of the sons of Israel, and of the sojourners who is sojourning in Israel, who giveth of his seed to the Molech, is certainly put to death; the people of the land do stone him with stones;

3 and I--I set My face against that man, and have cut him off from the midst of his people, for of his seed he hath given to the Molech, so as to defile My sanctuary, and to pollute My holy name.

4 `And if the people of the land really hide their eyes from that man, in his giving of his seed to the Molech, so as not to put him to death,

5 then I have set My face against that man, and against his family, and have cut him off, and all who are going a-whoring after him, even going a-whoring after the Molech, from the midst of their people.

6 `And the person who turneth unto those having familiar spirits, and unto the wizards, to go a-whoring after them, I have even set My face against that person, and cut him off from the midst of his people.

7 `And ye have sanctified yourselves, and ye have been holy, for I [am] Jehovah your God;

8 and ye have kept My statutes and have done them; I [am] Jehovah, sanctifying you.

9 `For any man who revileth his father and his mother is certainly put to death; his father and his mother he hath reviled: his blood [is] on him.

10 `And a man who committeth adultery with a man's wife--who committeth adultery with the wife of his neighbour--the adulterer and the adulteress are surely put to death.

11 `And a man who lieth with his father's wife--the nakedness of his father he hath uncovered--both of them are certainly put to death; their blood [is] on them.

12 `And a man who lieth with his daughter-in-law--both of them are certainly put to death; confusion they have made; their blood [is] on them.

13 `And a man who lieth with a male as one lieth with a woman; abomination both of them have done; they are certainly put to death; their blood [is] on them.

14 `And a man who taketh the woman and her mother--it [is] wickedness; with fire they burn him and them, and there is no wickedness in your midst.

15 `And a man who giveth his lying with a beast is certainly put to death, and the beast ye do slay.

16 `And a woman who draweth near unto any beast to lie with it--thou hast even slain the woman and the beast; they are certainly put to death; their blood [is] on them.

17 `And a man who taketh his sister, a daughter of his father or daughter of his mother, and he hath seen her nakedness, and she seeth his nakedness: it is a shame; and they have been cut off before the eyes of the sons of their people; the nakedness of his sister he hath uncovered; his iniquity he beareth.

18 `And a man who lieth with a sick woman, and hath uncovered her nakedness, her fountain he hath made bare, and she hath uncovered the fountain of her blood, --even both of them have been cut off from the midst of their people.

19 `And the nakedness of thy mother's sister, and of thy father's sister, thou dost not uncover; because his relation he hath made bare; their iniquity they bear.

20 `And a man who lieth with his aunt, the nakedness of his uncle he hath uncovered; their sin they bear; childless they die.

21 `And a man who taketh his brother's wife--it [is] impurity; the nakedness of his brother he hath uncovered; childless they are.

22 `And ye have kept all My statutes, and all My judgments, and have done them, and the land vomiteth you not out whither I am bringing you in to dwell in it;

23 and ye walk not in the statutes of the nation which I am sending away from before you, for all these they have done, and I am wearied with them;

24 and I say to you, Ye--ye do possess their ground, and I--I give it to you to possess it, a land flowing with milk and honey; I [am] Jehovah your God, who hath separated you from the peoples.

25 `And ye have made separation between the pure beasts and the unclean, and between the unclean fowl and the pure, and ye do not make yourselves abominable by beast or by fowl, or by anything which creepeth [on] the ground which I have separated to you for unclean;

26 and ye have been holy to Me; for holy [am] I, Jehovah; and I separate you from the peoples to become Mine.

27 `And a man or woman--when there is in them a familiar spirit, or who [are] wizards--are certainly put to death; with stones they stone them; their blood [is] on them.'

Leviticus 21

1 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Speak unto the priests, sons of Aaron, and thou hast said unto them, For [any] person [a priest] is not defiled among his people,

2 except for his relation who [is] near unto him--for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother.

3 and for his sister, the virgin, who is near unto him, who hath not been to a man; for her he is defiled.

4 `A master [priest] doth not defile himself among his people--to pollute himself;

5 they do not make baldness on their head, and the corner of their beard they do not shave, and in their flesh they do not make a cutting;

6 they are holy to their God, and they pollute not the name of their God, for the fireofferings of Jehovah, bread of their God, they are bringing near, and have been holy.

7 `A woman, a harlot, or polluted, they do not take, and a woman cast out from her husband they do not take, for he [is] holy to his God;

8 and thou hast sanctified him, for the bread of thy God he is bringing near; he is holy to thee; for holy [am] I, Jehovah, sanctifying you.

9 `And a daughter of any priest when she polluteth herself by going a-whoring--her father she is polluting; with fire she is burnt.

10 `And the high priest of his brethren, on whose head is poured the anointing oil, and hath consecrated his hand to put on the garments, his head doth not uncover, nor rend his garments,

11 nor beside any dead person doth he come; for his father and for his mother he doth not defile himself;

12 nor from the sanctuary doth he go out, nor doth he pollute the sanctuary of his God, for the separation of the anointing oil of his God [is] on him; I [am] Jehovah.

13 `And he taketh a wife in her virginity;

14 widow, or cast out, or polluted one--a harlot--these he doth not take, but a virgin of his own people he doth take [for] a wife,

15 and he doth not pollute his seed among his people; for I [am] Jehovah, sanctifying him.'

16 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

17 `Speak unto Aaron, saying, No man of thy seed to their generations in whom there is blemish doth draw near to bring near the bread of his God,

18 for no man in whom [is] blemish doth draw near--a man blind, or lame or dwarfed, or enlarged,

19 or a man in whom there is a breach in the foot, or a breach in the hand,

20 or hump-backed, or a dwarf, or with a mixture in his eye, or a scurvy person, or scabbed, or broken-testicled.

21 `No man in whom is blemish (of the seed of Aaron the priest) doth come nigh to bring near the fire-offerings of Jehovah; blemish [is] in him; the bread of his God he doth not come nigh to bring near.

22 `Bread of his God--of the most holy things, and of the holy things--he doth eat;

23 only, unto the vail he doth not enter, and unto the altar he doth not draw nigh; for blemish [is] in him; and he doth not pollute My sanctuaries; for I [am] Jehovah, sanctifying them.'

24 And Moses speaketh unto Aaron, and unto his sons, and unto all the sons of Israel.

Leviticus 24

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Command the sons of Israel, and they bring unto thee pure olive oil, beaten, for the lamp, to cause a light to go up continually;

3 at the outside of the vail of the testimony in the tent of meeting doth Aaron arrange it from evening till morning before Jehovah continually--a statute age-during to your generations;

4 by the pure candlestick he doth arrange the lights before Jehovah continually.

5 `And thou hast taken flour, and hast baked twelve cakes with it, two tenth deals are in the one cake,

6 and thou hast set them two ranks (six in the rank) on the pure table before Jehovah,

7 and thou hast put on the rank pure frankincense, and it hath been to the bread for a memorial, a fire-offering to Jehovah.

8 `On each sabbath-day he arrangeth it before Jehovah continually, from the sons of Israel--a covenant age-during;

9 and it hath been to Aaron, and to his sons, and they have eaten it in the holy place, for it [is] most holy to him, from the fire-offerings of Jehovah--a statute age-during.'

10 And a son of an Israelitish woman goeth out (and he [is] son of an Egyptian man), in the midst of the sons of Israel, and strive in the camp do the son of the Israelitish woman and a man of Israel,

11 and the son of the Israelitish woman execrateth the Name, and revileth; and they bring him in unto Moses; and his mother's name [is] Shelomith daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan;

12 and he causeth him to rest in charge--to explain to them by the mouth of Jehovah.

13 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

14 `Bring out the reviler unto the outside of the camp; and all those hearing have laid their hands on his head, and all the company have stoned him.

15 `And unto the sons of Israel thou dost speak, saying, When any man revileth his God--then he hath borne his sin;

16 and he who is execrating the name of Jehovah is certainly put to death; all the company do certainly cast stones at him; as a sojourner so a native, in his execrating the Name, is put to death.

17 `And when a man smiteth any soul of man, he is certainly put to death.

18 `And he who smiteth a beast repayeth it, body for body.

19 `And when a man putteth a blemish in his fellow, as he hath done so it is done to him;

20 breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as he putteth a blemish in a man so it is done in him.

21 `And he who smiteth a beast repayeth it, and he who smiteth [the life of] man is put to death;

22 one judgment is to you; as a sojourner so is a native; for I [am] Jehovah your God.'

23 And Moses speaketh unto the sons of Israel, and they bring out the reviler unto the outside of the camp, and stone him with stones; and the sons of Israel have done as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

Leviticus 25

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, in mount Sinai, saying,

2 `Speak unto the sons of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, When ye come in unto the land which I am giving to you, then hath the land kept a sabbath to Jehovah.

3 `Six years thou dost sow thy field, and six years thou dost prune thy vineyard, and hast gathered its increase,

4 and in the seventh year a sabbath of rest is to the land, a sabbath to Jehovah; thy field thou dost not sow, and thy vineyard thou dost not prune;

5 the spontaneous growth of thy harvest thou dost not reap, and the grapes of thy separated thing thou dost not gather, a year of rest it is to the land.

6 `And the sabbath of the land hath been to you for food, to thee, and to thy manservant, and to thy handmaid, and to thy hireling, and to thy settler, who are sojourning with thee;

7 and to thy cattle, and to the beast which [is] in thy land, is all thine increase for food.

8 `And thou hast numbered to thee seven sabbaths of years, seven years seven times, and the days of the seven sabbaths of years have been to thee nine and forty years,

9 and thou hast caused a trumpet of shouting to pass over in the seventh month, in the tenth of the month; in the day of the atonements ye do cause a trumpet to pass over through all your land;

10 and ye have hallowed the year, the fiftieth year; and ye have proclaimed liberty in the land to all its inhabitants; a jubilee it is to you; and ye have turned back each unto his possession; yea, each unto his family ye do turn back.

11 `A jubilee it [is], the fiftieth year, a year it is to you; ye sow not, nor reap its spontaneous growth, nor gather its separated things;

12 for a jubilee it [is], holy it is to you; out of the field ye eat its increase;

13 in the year of this jubilee ye turn back each unto his possession.

14 `And when thou sellest anything to thy fellow, or buyest from the hand of thy fellow, ye do not oppress one another;

15 by the number of years after the jubilee thou dost buy from thy fellow; by the number of the years of increase he doth sell to thee;

16 according to the multitude of the years thou dost multiply its price, and according to the fewness of the years thou dost diminish its price; for a number of increases he is selling to thee;

17 and ye do not oppress one another, and thou hast been afraid of thy God; for I [am] Jehovah your God.

18 `And ye have done My statutes, and My judgments ye keep, and have done them, and ye have dwelt on the land confidently,

19 and the land hath given its fruit, and ye have eaten to satiety, and have dwelt confidently on it.

20 `And when ye say, What do we eat in the seventh year, lo, we do not sow, nor gather our increase?

21 then I have commanded My blessing on you in the sixth year, and it hath made the increase for three years;

22 and ye have sown the eighth year, and have eaten of the old increase; until the ninth year, until the coming in of its increase, ye do eat the old.

23 `And the land is not sold--to extinction, for the land [is] Mine, for sojourners and settlers [are] ye with Me;

24 and in all the land of your possession a redemption ye do give to the land.

25 `When thy brother becometh poor, and hath sold his possession, then hath his redeemer who is near unto him come, and he hath redeemed the sold thing of his brother;

26 and when a man hath no redeemer, and his own hand hath attained, and he hath found as sufficient [for] its redemption,

27 then he hath reckoned the years of its sale, and hath given back that which is over to the man to whom he sold [it], and he hath returned to his possession.

28 `And if his hand hath not found sufficiency to give back to him, then hath his sold thing been in the hand of him who buyeth it till the year of jubilee; and it hath gone out in the jubilee, and he hath returned to his possession.

29 `And when a man selleth a dwelling-house [in] a walled city, then hath his right of redemption been until the completion of a year from its selling; days--is his right of redemption;

30 and if it is not redeemed until the fulness to him of a perfect year, then hath the house which [is] in a walled city been established to extinction to the buyer of it, to his generations; it goeth not out in the jubilee;

31 and a house of the villages which have no wall round about, on the field of the country is reckoned; redemption is to it, and in the jubilee it goeth out.

32 `As to cities of the Levites--houses of the cities of their possession--redemption age-during is to the Levites;

33 as to him who redeemeth from the Levites, both the sale of a house and the city of his possession have gone out in the jubilee, for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession in the midst of the sons of Israel.

34 And a field, a suburb of their cities, is not sold; for a possession age-during it [is] to them.

35 `And when thy brother is become poor, and his hand hath failed with thee, then thou hast kept hold on him, sojourner and settler, and he hath lived with thee;

36 thou takest no usury from him, or increase; and thou hast been afraid of thy God; and thy brother hath lived with thee;

37 thy money thou givest not to him in usury, and for increase thou givest not thy food;

38 I [am] Jehovah your God, who hath brought you out of the land of Egypt, to give to you the land of Canaan, to become your God.

39 `And when thy brother becometh poor with thee, and he hath been sold to thee, thou dost not lay on him servile service;

40 as an hireling, as a settler, he is with thee, till the year of the jubilee he doth serve with thee, --

41 then he hath gone out from thee, he and his sons with him, and hath turned back unto his family; even unto the possession of his fathers he doth turn back.

42 `For they [are] My servants, whom I have brought out from the land of Egypt: they are not sold [with] the sale of a servant;

43 thou rulest not over him with rigour, and thou hast been afraid of thy God.

44 `And thy man-servant and thy handmaid whom thou hast [are] of the nations who [are] round about you; of them ye buy man-servant and handmaid,

45 and also of the sons of the settlers who are sojourning with you, of them ye buy, and of their families who [are] with you, which they have begotten in your land, and they have been to you for a possession;

46 and ye have taken them for inheritance to your sons after you, to occupy [for] a possession; to the age ye lay service upon them, but upon your brethren, the sons of Israel, one with another, thou dost not rule over him with rigour.

47 `And when the hand of a sojourner or settler with thee attaineth [riches], and thy brother with him hath become poor, and he hath been sold to a sojourner, a settler with thee, or to the root of the family of a sojourner,

48 after he hath been sold, there is a right of redemption to him; one of his brethren doth redeem him,

49 or his uncle, or a son of his uncle, doth redeem him, or any of the relations of his flesh, of his family, doth redeem him, or--his own hand hath attained--then he hath been redeemed.

50 `And he hath reckoned with his buyer from the year of his being sold to him till the year of jubilee, and the money of his sale hath been by the number of years; as the days of an hireling it is with him.

51 `If yet many years, according to them he giveth back his redemption [money], from the money of his purchase.

52 `And if few are left of the years till the year of jubilee, then he hath reckoned with him, according to his years he doth give back his redemption [money];

53 as an hireling, year by year, he is with him, and he doth not rule him with rigour before thine eyes.

54 `And if he is not redeemed in these [years], then he hath gone out in the year of jubilee, he and his sons with him.

55 For to Me [are] the sons of Israel servants; My servants they [are], whom I have brought out of the land of Egypt; I, Jehovah, [am] your God.

Leviticus 26

1 `Ye do not make to yourselves idols; and graven image or standing image ye do not set up to yourselves; and a stone of imagery ye do not put in your land, to bow yourselves to it; for I [am] Jehovah your God.

2 `My sabbaths ye do keep, and My sanctuary ye do reverence; I [am] Jehovah.

3 `If in My statutes ye walk, and My commands ye keep, and have done them,

4 then I have given your rains in their season, and the land hath given her produce, and the tree of the field doth give its fruit;

5 and reached to you hath the threshing, the gathering, and the gathering doth reach the sowing -[time]; and ye have eaten your bread to satiety, and have dwelt confidently in your land.

6 `And I have given peace in the land, and ye have lain down, and there is none causing trembling; and I have caused evil beasts to cease out of the land, and the sword doth not pass over into your land.

7 `And ye have pursued your enemies, and they have fallen before you by the sword;

8 and five of you have pursued a hundred, and a hundred of you do pursue a myriad; and your enemies have fallen before you by the sword.

9 `And I have turned unto you, and have made you fruitful, and have multiplied you, and have established My covenant with you;

10 and ye have eaten old [store], and the old because of the new ye bring out.

11 `And I have given My tabernacle in your midst, and My soul doth not loathe you;

12 and I have walked habitually in your midst, and have become your God, and ye-- ye are become My people;

13 I [am] Jehovah your God, who have brought you out of the land of the Egyptians, from being their servants; and I break the bars of your yoke, and cause you to go erect.

14 `And if ye do not hearken to Me, and do not all these commands;

15 and if at My statutes ye kick, and if My judgments your soul loathe, so as not to do all My commands--to your breaking My covenant--

16 I also do this to you, and I have appointed over you trouble, the consumption, and the burning fever, consuming eyes, and causing pain of soul; and your seed in vain ye have sowed, and your enemies have eaten it;

17 and I have set My face against you, and ye have been smitten before your enemies; and those hating you have ruled over you, and ye have fled, and there is none pursuing you.

18 `And if unto these ye hearken not to Me, --then I have added to chastise you seven times for your sins;

19 and I have broken the pride of your strength, and have made your heavens as iron, and your earth as brass;

20 and consumed hath been your strength in vain, and your land doth not give her produce, and the tree of the land doth not give its fruit.

21 `And if ye walk with Me [in] opposition, and are not willing to hearken to Me, then I have added to you a plague seven times, according to your sins,

22 and sent against you the beast of the field, and it hath bereaved you; and I have cut off your cattle, and have made you few, and your ways have been desolate.

23 `And if by these ye are not instructed by Me, and have walked with Me [in] opposition,

24 then I have walked--I also--with you in opposition, and have smitten you, even I, seven times for your sins;

25 and I have brought in on you a sword, executing the vengeance of a covenant; and ye have been gathered unto your cities, and I have sent pestilence into your midst, and ye have been given into the hand of an enemy.

26 `In My breaking to you the staff of bread, then ten women have baked your bread in one oven, and have given back your bread by weight; and ye have eaten, and are not satisfied.

27 `And if for this ye hearken not to Me, and have walked with Me in opposition,

28 then I have walked with you in the fury of opposition, and have chastised you, even I, seven times for your sins.

29 `And ye have eaten the flesh of your sons; even flesh of your daughters ye do eat.

30 And I have destroyed your high places, and cut down your images, and have put your carcases on the carcases of your idols, and My soul hath loathed you;

31 and I have made your cities a waste, and have made desolate your sanctuaries, and I smell not at your sweet fragrances;

32 and I have made desolate the land, and your enemies, who are dwelling in it, have been astonished at it.

33 And you I scatter among nations, and have drawn out after you a sword, and your land hath been a desolation, and your cities are a waste.

34 `Then doth the land enjoy its sabbaths--all the days of the desolation, and ye in the land of your enemies--then doth the land rest, and hath enjoyed its sabbaths;

35 all the days of the desolation it resteth that which it hath not rested in your sabbaths in your dwelling on it.

36 `And those who are left of you--I have also brought a faintness into their heart in the lands of their enemies, and the sound of a leaf driven away hath pursued them, and they have fled--flight from a sword--and they have fallen, and there is none pursuing.

37 And they have stumbled one on another, as from the face of a sword, and there is none pursuing, and ye have no standing before your enemies,

38 and ye have perished among the nations, and the land of your enemies hath consumed you.

39 `And those who are left of you--they consume away in their iniquity, in the lands of your enemies; and also in the iniquities of their fathers, with them they consume away.

40 `And--they have confessed their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, in their trespass which they have trespassed against Me, and also, that they have walked with Me, in opposition,

41 also I walk to them in opposition, and have brought them into the land of their enemies--or then their uncircumcised heart is humbled, and then they accept the punishment of their iniquity, --

42 then I have remembered My covenant [with] Jacob, and also My covenant [with] Isaac, and also My covenant [with] Abraham I remember, and the land I remember.

43 `And--the land is left of them, and doth enjoy its sabbaths, in the desolation without them, and they accept the punishment of their iniquity, because, even because, against My judgments they have kicked, and My statutes hath their soul loathed,

44 and also even this, in their being in the land of their enemies, I have not rejected them, nor have I loathed them, to consume them, to break My covenant with them; for I [am] Jehovah their God; --

45 then I have remembered for them the covenant of the ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt before the eyes of the nations to become their God; I [am] Jehovah.'

46 These [are] the statutes, and the judgments, and the laws, which Jehovah hath given between Him and the sons of Israel, in mount Sinai, by the hand of Moses.

Leviticus 27

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Speak unto the sons of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, When a man maketh a wonderful vow, by thy valuation the persons [are] Jehovah's.

3 When thy valuation hath been of the male from a son of twenty years even unto a son of sixty years, then hath been thy valuation fifty shekels of silver by the shekel of the sanctuary.

4 And if it [is] a female--then hath thy valuation been thirty shekels;

5 and if from a son of five years even unto a son of twenty years--then hath thy valuation been of the male twenty shekels, and for the female, ten shekels;

6 and if from a son of a month even unto a son of five years--then hath thy valuation been of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female thy valuation [is] three shekels of silver;

7 and if from a son of sixty years and above--if a male, then hath thy valuation been fifteen shekels, and for a female, ten shekels.

8 `And if he is poorer than thy valuation, then he hath presented himself before the priest, and the priest hath valued him; according to that which the hand of him who is vowing doth reach doth the priest value him.

9 `And if [it is] a beast of which they bring near an offering to Jehovah, all that [one] giveth of it to Jehovah is holy;

10 he doth not change it nor exchange it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good; and if he really change beast for beast, --then it hath been--it and its exchange is holy.

11 `And if [it is] any unclean beast of which they do not bring near an offering to Jehovah, then he hath presented the beast before the priest,

12 and the priest hath valued it; whether good or bad, according to thy valuation, O priest, so it is;

13 and if he really redeem it, then he hath added its fifth to thy valuation.

14 `And when a man sanctifieth his house, a holy thing to Jehovah, then hath the priest valued it, whether good or bad; as the priest doth value it so it standeth;

15 and if he who is sanctifying doth redeem his house, then he hath added a fifth of the money of thy valuation to it, and it hath become his.

16 `And if of the field of his possession a man sanctify to Jehovah, then hath thy valuation been according to its seed; a homer of barley-seed at fifty shekels of silver;

17 if from the year of the jubilee he sanctify his field, according to thy valuation it standeth;

18 and if after the jubilee he sanctify his field, then hath the priest reckoned to him the money according to the years which are left, unto the year of the jubilee, and it hath been abated from thy valuation.

19 `And if he really redeem the field--he who is sanctifying it--then he hath added a fifth of the money of thy valuation to it, and it hath been established to him;

20 and if he do not redeem the field, or if he hath sold the field to another man, it is not redeemed any more;

21 and the field hath been, in its going out in the jubilee, holy to Jehovah as a field which is devoted; to the priest is its possession.

22 `And if the field of his purchase (which [is] not of the fields of his possession) [one] sanctify to Jehovah--

23 then hath the priest reckoned to him the amount of thy valuation unto the year of jubilee, and he hath given thy valuation in that day--a holy thing to Jehovah;

24 in the year of the jubilee the field returneth to him from whom he bought it, to him whose [is] the possession of the land.

25 And all thy valuation is by the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs is the shekel.

26 `Only, a firstling which is Jehovah's firstling among beasts--no man doth sanctify it, whether ox or sheep; it [is] Jehovah's.

27 And if among the unclean beasts, then he hath ransomed [it] at thy valuation, and he hath added its fifth to it; and if it is not redeemed, then it hath been sold at thy valuation.

28 `Only, no devoted thing which a man devoteth to Jehovah, of all that he hath, of man, and beast, and of the field of his possession, is sold or redeemed; every devoted thing is most holy to Jehovah.

29 `No devoted thing, which is devoted of man, is ransomed, it is surely put to death.

30 And all tithe of the land, of the seed of the land, of the fruit of the tree, is Jehovah's--holy to Jehovah.

31 `And if a man really redeem [any] of his tithe, its fifth he addeth to it.

32 `And all the tithe of the herd and of the flock--all that passeth by under the rod--the tenth is holy to Jehovah;

33 he enquireth not between good and bad, nor doth he change it; and if he really change it--then it hath been--it and its exchange is holy; it is not redeemed.'

34 These [are] the commands which Jehovah hath commanded Moses for the sons of Israel, in mount Sinai.

Numbers 1

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, in the tent of meeting, on the first of the second month, in the second year of their going out of the land of Egypt, saying:

2 `Take ye up the sum of all the company of the sons of Israel by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names--every male by their polls;

3 from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host in Israel, ye do number them by their hosts, thou and Aaron;

4 and with you there is a man for a tribe, each is a head to the house of his fathers.

5 `And these [are] the names of the men who stand with you: `For Reuben--Elizur son of Shedeur.

6 `For Simeon--Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai.

7 `For Judah--Nahshon son of Amminadab.

8 `For Issachar--Nathaneel son of Zuar.

9 `For Zebulun--Eliab son of Helon.

10 `For the sons of Joseph--for Ephraim: Elishama son of Ammihud: for Manasseh-- Gamaliel son of Pedahzur.

11 `For Benjamin--Abidan son of Gideoni.

12 `For Dan--Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai.

13 `For Asher--Pagiel son of Ocran.

14 `For Gad--Eliasaph son of Deuel.

15 `For Naphtali--Ahira son of Enan.'

16 These [are] those called of the company, princes of the tribes of their fathers; they [are] heads of the thousands of Israel.

17 And Moses taketh--Aaron also--these men, who were defined by name,

18 and all the company they assembled on the first of the second month, and they declare their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names from a son of twenty years and upward, by their polls,

19 as Jehovah hath commanded Moses; and he numbereth them in the wilderness of Sinai.

20 And the sons of Reuben, Israel's first-born--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, by their polls, every male from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

21 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Reuben, are six and forty thousand and five hundred.

22 Of the sons of Simeon--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, its numbered ones in the number of names, by their polls, every male from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

23 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Simeon, [are] nine and fifty thousand and three hundred.

24 Of the sons of Gad--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

25 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Gad, [are] five and forty thousand and six hundred and fifty.

26 Of the sons of Judah--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

27 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Judah, [are] four and seventy thousand and six hundred.

28 Of the sons of Issachar--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

29 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Issachar, [are] four and fifty thousand and four hundred.

30 Of the sons of Zebulun--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

31 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Zebulun, [are] seven and fifty thousand and four hundred.

32 Of the sons of Joseph--of the sons of Ephraim--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

33 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Ephraim, [are] forty thousand and five hundred.

34 Of the sons of Manasseh--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

35 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Manasseh, [are] two and thirty thousand and two hundred.

36 Of the sons of Benjamin--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

37 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Benjamin, [are] five and thirty thousand and four hundred.

38 Of the sons of Dan--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

39 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Dan, [are] two and sixty thousand and seven hundred.

40 Of the sons of Asher--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

41 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Asher, [are] one and forty thousand and five hundred.

42 [Of] the sons of Naphtali--their births, by their families, by the house of their fathers, in the number of names, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host--

43 their numbered ones, for the tribe of Naphtali, [are] three and fifty thousand and four hundred.

44 These [are] those numbered, whom Moses numbered--Aaron also, and the princes of Israel, twelve men--each for the house of his fathers, they have been.

45 And they are, all those numbered of the sons of Israel, by the house of their fathers, from a son of twenty years and upward, every one going out to the host in Israel,

46 yea, all those numbered are six hundred thousand, and three thousand, and five hundred and fifty.

47 And the Levites, for the tribe of their fathers, have not numbered themselves in their midst,

48 seeing Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

49 `Only, the tribe of Levi thou dost not number, and their sum thou dost not take up in the midst of the sons of Israel;

50 and thou, appoint the Levites over the tabernacle of the testimony, and over all its vessels, and over all that it hath; they bear the tabernacle, and all its vessels, and they serve it; and round about the tabernacle they encamp.

51 `And in the journeying of the tabernacle, the Levites take it down, and in the encamping of the tabernacle, the Levites raise it up; and the stranger who is coming near is put to death.'

52 And the sons of Israel have encamped, each by his camp, and each by his standard, by their hosts;

53 and the Levites encamp round about the tabernacle of the testimony; and there is no wrath on the company of the sons of Israel, and the Levites have kept the charge of the tabernacle of the testimony.

54 And the sons of Israel do according to all that Jehovah hath commanded Moses; so they have done.

Numbers 2

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, and unto Aaron, saying,

2 `Each by his standard, with ensigns of the house of their fathers, do the sons of Israel encamp; over-against round about the tent of meeting they encamp.'

3 And those encamping eastward towards the sun-rising, [are of] the standard of the camp of Judah, by their hosts; and the prince of the sons of Judah [is] Nahshon, son of Amminadab;

4 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] four and seventy thousand and six hundred.

5 And those encamping by him [are of] the tribe of Issachar; and the prince of the sons of Issachar [is] Nethaneel son of Zuar;

6 and his host, and its numbered ones, [are] four and fifty thousand and four hundred.

7 The tribe of Zebulun; and the prince of the sons of Zebulun [is] Eliab son of Helon;

8 and his host, and its numbered ones, [are] seven and fifty thousand and four hundred;

9 all those numbered of the camp of Judah [are] a hundred thousand, and eighty thousand, and six thousand, and four hundred, by their hosts; they journey first.

10 The standard of the camp of Reuben [is] southward, by their hosts; and the prince of the sons of Reuben [is] Elizur son of Shedeur;

11 and his host, and its numbered ones, [are] six and forty thousand and five hundred.

12 And those encamping by him [are of] the tribe of Simeon; and the prince of the sons of Simeon [is] Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai;

13 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] nine and fifty thousand and three hundred.

14 And the tribe of Gad; and the prince of the sons of Gad [is] Eliasaph son of Reuel;

15 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] five and forty thousand and six hundred and fifty.

16 All those numbered of the camp of Reuben [are] a hundred thousand, and one and fifty thousand, and four hundred and fifty, by their hosts; and they journey second.

17 And the tent of meeting--the camp of the Levites--hath journeyed in the midst of the camps; as they encamp so they journey, each at his station by their standards.

18 The standard of the camp of Ephraim, by their hosts, [is] westward; and the prince of the sons of Ephraim [is] Elishama son of Ammihud;

19 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] forty thousand and five hundred.

20 And by him [is] the tribe of Manasseh; and the prince of the sons of Manasseh [is] Gamaliel son of Pedahzur;

21 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] two and thirty thousand, and two hundred.

22 And the tribe of Benjamin; and the prince of the sons of Benjamin [is] Abidan son of Gideoni;

23 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] five and thirty thousand and four hundred.

24 All those numbered of the camp of Ephraim [are] a hundred thousand, and eight thousand, and a hundred, by their hosts; and they journey third.

25 The standard of the camp of Dan [is] northward, by their hosts; and the prince of the sons of Dan [is] Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai;

26 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] two and sixty thousand and seven hundred.

27 And those encamping by him [are of] the tribe of Asher; and the prince of the sons of Asher [is] Pagiel son of Ocran;

28 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] one and forty thousand and five hundred.

29 And the tribe of Naphtali; and the prince of the sons of Naphtali [is] Ahira son of Enan;

30 and his host, and their numbered ones, [are] three and fifty thousand and four hundred.

31 All those numbered of the camp of Dan [are] a hundred thousand, and seven and fifty thousand, and six hundred; at the rear they journey, by their standards.

32 These [are] those numbered of the sons of Israel by the house of their fathers; all those numbered of the camps by their hosts [are] six hundred thousand, and three thousand, and five hundred and fifty.

33 And the Levites have not numbered themselves in the midst of the sons of Israel, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

34 And the sons of Israel do according to all that Jehovah hath commanded Moses; so they have encamped by their standards, and so they have journeyed; each by his families, by the house of his fathers.

Numbers 3

1 And these [are] births of Aaron and Moses, in the day of Jehovah's speaking with Moses in mount Sinai.

2 And these [are] the names of the sons of Aaron: the first-born Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar;

3 these [are] the names of the sons of Aaron, the anointed priests, whose hand he hath consecrated for acting as priest.

4 And Nadab dieth--Abihu also--before Jehovah, in their bringing near strange fire before Jehovah, in the wilderness of Sinai, and sons they had not; and Eleazar--Ithamar also--acteth as priest in the presence of Aaron their father.

5 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

6 `Bring near the tribe of Levi, and thou hast caused it to stand before Aaron the priest, and they have served him,

7 and kept his charge, and the charge of all the company before the tent of meeting, to do the service of the tabernacle;

8 and they have kept all the vessels of the tent of meeting, and the charge of the sons of Israel, to do the service of the tabernacle;

9 and thou hast given the Levites to Aaron and to his sons; they are surely given to him out of the sons of Israel.

10 `And Aaron and his sons thou dost appoint, and they have kept their priesthood, and the stranger who cometh near is put to death.'

11 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

12 `And I, lo, I have taken the Levites from the midst of the sons of Israel instead of every first-born opening a womb among the sons of Israel, and the Levites have been Mine;

13 for Mine [is] every first-born, in the day of My smiting every first-born in the land of Egypt I have sanctified to Myself every first-born in Israel, from man unto beast; Mine they are; I [am] Jehovah.'

14 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses in the wilderness of Sinai, saying,

15 `Number the sons of Levi by the house of their fathers, by their families; every male from a son of a month and upward thou dost number them.'

16 And Moses numbereth them according to the command of Jehovah, as he hath been commanded.

17 And these are sons of Levi by their names: Gershon, and Kohath, and Merari.

18 And these [are] the names of the sons of Gershon by their families: Libni and Shimei.

19 And the sons of Kohath, by their families, [are] Amram and Izhar, Hebron and Uzziel.

20 And the sons of Merari by their families [are] Mahli and Mushi; these are the families of the Levites, by the house of their fathers.

21 Of Gershon [is] the family of the Libnite, and the family of the Shimite; these are the families of the Gershonite.

22 Their numbered ones, in number, every male from a son of a month and upward, their numbered ones [are] seven thousand and five hundred.

23 The families of the Gershonite, behind the tabernacle, do encamp westward.

24 And the prince of a father's house for the Gershonite [is] Eliasaph son of Lael.

25 And the charge of the sons of Gershon in the tent of meeting [is] the tabernacle, and the tent, its covering, and the vail at the opening of the tent of meeting,

26 and the hangings of the court, and the vail at the opening of the court, which [is] by the tabernacle and by the altar round about, and its cords, to all its service.

27 And of Kohath [is] the family of the Amramite, and the family of the Izharite, and the family of the Hebronite, and the family of the Uzzielite; these are families of the Kohathite.

28 In number, all the males, from a son of a month and upward, [are] eight thousand and six hundred, keeping the charge of the sanctuary.

29 The families of the sons of Kohath encamp by the side of the tabernacle southward.

30 And the prince of a father's house for the families of the Kohathite [is] Elizaphan son of Uzziel.

31 And their charge [is] the ark, and the table, and the candlestick, and the altars, and the vessels of the sanctuary with which they serve, and the vail, and all its service.

32 And [to] the prince of the princes of the Levites, Eleazar son of Aaron the priest, [is] the oversight of the keepers of the charge of the sanctuary.

33 Of Merari [is] the family of the Mahlite, and the family of the Mushite; these [are] the families of Merari.

34 And their numbered ones, in number, all the males from a son of a month and upward, [are] six thousand and two hundred.

35 And the prince of a father's house for the families of Merari [is] Zuriel son of Abihail; by the side of the tabernacle they encamp northward.

36 And the oversight--the charge of the sons of Merari--[is] the boards of the tabernacle, and its bars, and its pillars, and its sockets, and all its vessels, and all its service,

37 and the pillars of the court round about, and their sockets, and their pins, and their cords.

38 And those encamping before the tabernacle eastward, before the tent of meeting, at the east, [are] Moses and Aaron, and his sons, keeping the charge of the sanctuary for the charge of the sons of Israel, and the stranger who cometh near is put to death.

39 All those numbered of the Levites whom Moses numbered--Aaron also--by the command of Jehovah, by their families, every male from a son of a month and upward, [are] two and twenty thousand.

40 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Number every first-born male of the sons of Israel from a son of a month and upward, and take up the number of their names;

41 and thou hast taken the Levites for Me (I [am] Jehovah), instead of every first-born among the sons of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of every firstling among the cattle of the sons of Israel.'

42 And Moses numbereth, as Jehovah hath commanded him, all the first-born among the sons of Israel.

43 And all the first-born--male--by the number of names, from a son of a month and upward, of their numbered ones, are two and twenty thousand two hundred and seventy and three.

44 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

45 `Take the Levites instead of every first-born among the sons of Israel, and the cattle of the Levites instead of their cattle; and the Levites have been Mine; I [am] Jehovah.

46 `And [from] those ransomed of the two hundred and seventy and three (who are more than the Levites) of the first-born of the sons of Israel,

47 thou hast even taken five shekels a-piece by the poll--by the shekel of the sanctuary thou takest; twenty gerahs the shekel [is];

48 and thou hast given the money to Aaron, and to his sons, whereby those over and above are ransomed.'

49 And Moses taketh the ransom money from those over and above those ransomed by the Levites;

50 from the first-born of the sons of Israel he hath taken the money, a thousand and three hundred and sixty and five--by the shekel of the sanctuary;

51 and Moses giveth the money of those ransomed to Aaron, and to his sons, according to the command of Jehovah, as Jehovah hath commanded Moses.

Numbers 10

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Make to thee two trumpets of silver; beaten work thou dost make them, and they have been to thee for the convocation of the company, and for the journeying of the camps;

3 and they have blown with them, and all the company have met together unto thee, unto the opening of the tent of meeting.

4 And if with one they blow, then have the princes, heads of the thousands of Israel, met together unto thee;

5 `And ye have blown--a shout, and the camps which are encamping eastward have journeyed.

6 `And ye have blown--a second shout, and the camps which are encamping southward have journeyed; a shout they blow for their journeys.

7 `And in the assembling of the assembly ye blow, and do not shout;

8 and sons of Aaron, the priests, blow with the trumpets; and they have been to you for a statute age-during to your generations.

9 `And when ye go into battle in your land against the adversary who is distressing you, then ye have shouted with the trumpets, and ye have been remembered before Jehovah your God, and ye have been saved from your enemies.

10 `And in the day of your gladness, and in your appointed seasons, and in the beginnings of your months, ye have blown also with the trumpets over your burnt-offerings, and over the sacrifices of your peace-offerings, and they have been to you for a memorial before your God; I, Jehovah, [am] your God.'

11 And it cometh to pass--in the second year, in the second month, in the twentieth of the month--the cloud hath gone up from off the tabernacle of the testimony,

12 and the sons of Israel journey in their journeyings from the wilderness of Sinai, and the cloud doth tabernacle in the wilderness of Paran;

13 and they journey at first, by the command of Jehovah, in the hand of Moses.

14 And the standard of the camp of the sons of Judah journeyeth in the first [place], by their hosts, and over its host [is] Nahshon son of Amminadab.

15 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Issachar [is] Nathaneel son of Zuar.

16 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Zebulun [is] Eliab son of Helon;

17 And the tabernacle hath been taken down, and the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari have journeyed, bearing the tabernacle.

18 And the standard of the camp of Reuben hath journeyed, by their hosts, and over its host [is] Elizur son of Shedeur.

19 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Simeon [is] Shelumiel son of Zurishaddai.

20 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Gad [is] Eliasaph son of Deuel;

21 And the Kohathites have journeyed, bearing the tabernacle, and the [others] have raised up the tabernacle until their coming in.

22 And the standard of the camp of the sons of Ephraim hath journeyed, by their hosts, and over its host [is] Elishama son of Ammihud.

23 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Manasseh [is] Gamalial son of Pedahzur.

24 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Benjamin [is] Abidan son of Gideoni.

25 And the standard of the camp of the sons of Dan hath journeyed (rearward to all the camps), by their hosts, and over its host [is] Ahiezer son of Ammishaddai.

26 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Asher [is] Pagiel son of Ocran.

27 And over the host of the tribe of the sons of Naphtali [is] Ahira son of Enan.

28 These [are] journeyings of the sons of Israel by their hosts--and they journey.

29 And Moses saith to Hobab son of Raguel the Midianite, father-in-law of Moses, `We are journeying unto the place of which Jehovah hath said, I give it to you; go with us, and we have done good to thee; for Jehovah hath spoken good concerning Israel.'

30 And he saith unto him, `I do not go; but unto my land and unto my kindred do I go.'

31 And he saith, `I pray thee, forsake us not, because thou hast known our encamping in the wilderness, and thou hast been to us for eyes;

32 and it hath come to pass when thou goest with us, yea, it hath come to pass--that good which Jehovah doth kindly with us--it we have done kindly to thee.'

33 And they journey from the mount of Jehovah a journey of three days; and the ark of the covenant of Jehovah is journeying before them the journey of three days, to spy out for them a resting-place;

34 and the cloud of Jehovah [is] on them by day, in their journeying from the camp.

35 And it cometh to pass in the journeying of the ark, that Moses saith, `Rise, O Jehovah, and Thine enemies are scattered, and those hating Thee flee from Thy presence.'

36 And in its resting he saith, `Return, O Jehovah, [to] the myriads, the thousands of Israel.'

Numbers 11

1 And the people is evil, as those sighing habitually in the ears of Jehovah, and Jehovah heareth, and His anger burneth, and the fire of Jehovah burneth among them, and consumeth in the extremity of the camp.

2 And the people cry unto Moses, and Moses prayeth unto Jehovah, and the fire is quenched;

3 and he calleth the name of that place Taberah, for the fire of Jehovah hath `burned' among them.

4 And the rabble who [are] in its midst have lusted greatly, and the sons of Israel also turn back and weep, and say, `Who doth give us flesh?

5 We have remembered the fish which we do eat in Egypt for nought, the cucumbers, and the melons, and the leeks, and the onions, and the garlick;

6 and now our soul [is] dry, there is not anything, save the manna, before our eyes.'

7 And the manna is as coriander seed, and its aspect as the aspect of bdolach;

8 the people have turned aside and gathered [it], and ground [it] with millstones, or beat [it] in a mortar, and boiled [it] in a pan, and made it cakes, and its taste hath been as the taste of the moisture of oil.

9 And in the descending of the dew on the camp by night, the manna descendeth upon it.

10 And Moses heareth the people weeping by its families, each at the opening of his tent, and the anger of Jehovah burneth exceedingly, and in the eyes of Moses [it is] evil.

11 And Moses saith unto Jehovah, `Why hast Thou done evil to Thy servant? and why have I not found grace in Thine eyes--to put the burden of all this people upon me?

12 I--have I conceived all this people? I--have I begotten it, that Thou sayest unto me, Carry it in thy bosom as the nursing father beareth the suckling, unto the ground which Thou hast sworn to its fathers?

13 Whence have I flesh to give to all this people? for they weep unto me, saying, Give to us flesh, and we eat.

14 I am not able--I alone--to bear all this people, for [it is] too heavy for me;

15 and if thus Thou art doing to me--slay me, I pray Thee; slay, if I have found grace in thine eyes, and let me not look on mine affliction.'

16 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Gather to Me seventy men of the elders of Israel, whom thou hast known that they are elders of the people, and its authorities; and thou hast taken them unto the tent of meeting, and they have stationed themselves there with thee,

17 and I have come down and spoken with thee there, and have kept back of the Spirit which [is] upon thee, and have put on them, and they have borne with thee some of the burden of the people, and thou dost not bear [it] thyself alone.

18 `And unto the people thou dost say, Sanctify yourselves for to-morrow, and ye have eaten flesh (for ye have wept in the ears of Jehovah, saying, Who doth give us flesh? for we [had] good in Egypt) --and Jehovah hath given to you flesh, and ye have eaten.

19 Ye do not eat one day, nor two days, nor five days, nor ten days, nor twenty days; --

20 unto a month of days, till that it come out from your nostrils, and it hath become to you an abomination; because that ye have loathed Jehovah, who [is] in your midst, and weep before Him, saying, Why is this? --we have come out of Egypt!'

21 And Moses saith, `Six hundred thousand footmen [are] the people in whose midst I [am]; and Thou, Thou hast said, Flesh I give to them, and they have eaten, a month of days!

22 Is flock and herd slaughtered for them, that one hath found for them? --are all the fishes of the sea gathered for them--that one hath found for them?'

23 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Is the hand of Jehovah become short? now thou dost see whether My word meeteth thee or not.'

24 And Moses goeth out, and speaketh unto the people the words of Jehovah, and gathereth seventy men of the elders of the people, and causeth them to stand round about the tent,

25 and Jehovah cometh down in the cloud, and speaketh unto him, and keepeth back of the Spirit which [is] on him, and putteth on the seventy men of the elders; and it cometh to pass at the resting of the Spirit on them, that they prophesy, anddo not cease.

26 And two of the men are left in the camp, the name of the one [is] Eldad, and the name of the second Medad, and the spirit resteth upon them, (and they are among those written, and have not gone out to the tent), and they prophesy in the camp;

27 and the young man runneth, and declareth to Moses, and saith, `Eldad and Medad are prophesying in the camp.'

28 And Joshua son of Nun, minister of Moses, [one] of his young men, answereth and saith, `My lord Moses, restrain them.'

29 And Moses saith to him, `Art thou zealous for me? O that all Jehovah's people were prophets! that Jehovah would put His Spirit upon them!'

30 And Moses is gathered unto the camp, he and the elders of Israel.

31 And a spirit hath journeyed from Jehovah, and cutteth off quails from the sea, and leaveth by the camp, as a day's journey here, and as a day's journey there, round about the camp, and about two cubits, on the face of the land.

32 And the people rise all that day, and all the night, and all the day after, and gather the quails--he who hath least hath gathered ten homers--and they spread them out for themselves round about the camp.

33 The flesh is yet between their teeth--it is not yet cut off--and the anger of Jehovah hath burned among the people, and Jehovah smiteth among the people--a very great smiting;

34 and [one] calleth the name of that place Kibroth-Hattaavah, for there they have buried the people who lust.

35 From Kibroth-Hattaavah have the people journeyed to Hazeroth, and they are in Hazeroth.

Numbers 12

1 And Miriam speaketh--Aaron also--against Moses concerning the circumstance of the Cushite woman whom he had taken: for a Cushite woman he had taken;

2 and they say, `Only by Moses hath Jehovah spoken? also by us hath he not spoken?' and Jehovah heareth.

3 And the man Moses [is] very humble, more than any of the men who [are] on the face of the ground.

4 And Jehovah saith suddenly unto Moses, and unto Aaron, and unto Miriam, `Come out ye three unto the tent of meeting;' and they three come out.

5 And Jehovah cometh down in the pillar of the cloud, and standeth at the opening of the tent, and calleth Aaron and Miriam, and they come out both of them.

6 And He saith, `Hear, I pray you, My words: If your prophet is of Jehovah--in an appearance unto him I make Myself known; in a dream I speak with him;

7 not so My servant Moses; in all My house he [is] stedfast;

8 mouth unto mouth I speak with him, and [by] an appearance, and not in riddles; and the form of Jehovah he beholdeth attentively; and wherefore have ye not been afraid to speak against My servant--against Moses?'

9 And the anger of Jehovah burneth against them, and He goeth on,

10 and the cloud hath turned aside from off the tent, and lo, Miriam [is] leprous as snow; and Aaron turneth unto Miriam, and lo, leprous!

11 And Aaron saith unto Moses, `O, my lord, I pray thee, lay not upon us sin [in] which we have been foolish, and [in] which we have sinned;

12 let her not, I pray thee, be as [one] dead, when in his coming out from the womb of his mother--the half of his flesh is consumed.'

13 And Moses crieth unto Jehovah, saying, `O God, I pray Thee, give, I pray Thee, healing to her.'

14 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `And her father had but spat in her face--is she not ashamed seven days? she is shut out seven days at the outside of the camp, and afterwards she is gathered.'

15 And Miriam is shut out at the outside of the camp seven days, and the people hath not journeyed till Miriam is gathered;

16 and afterwards have the people journeyed from Hazeroth, and they encamp in the wilderness of Paran.

Numbers 13

1 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

2 `Send for thee men, and they spy the land of Canaan, which I am giving to the sons of Israel; one man, one man for the tribe of his fathers ye do send, every one a prince among them.'

3 And Moses sendeth them from the wilderness of Paran by the command of Jehovah; all of them [are] men, heads of the sons of Israel they are,

4 and these their names: For the tribe of Reuben, Shammua son of Zaccur.

5 For the tribe of Simeon, Shaphat son of Hori.

6 For the tribe of Judah, Caleb son of Jephunneh.

7 For the tribe of Issachar, Igal son of Joseph.

8 For the tribe of Ephraim, Oshea, son of Nun.

9 For the tribe of Benjamin, Palti son of Raphu.

10 For the tribe of Zebulun, Gaddiel son of Sodi.

11 For the tribe of Joseph, (for the tribe of Manasseh,) Gaddi son of Susi.

12 For the tribe of Dan, Ammiel son of Gemalli.

13 For the tribe of Asher, Sethur son of Michael.

14 For the tribe of Naphtali, Nahbi son of Vopshi.

15 For the tribe of Gad, Geuel son of Machi.

16 These [are] the names of the men whom Moses hath sent to spy the land; and Moses calleth Hoshea son of Nun, Jehoshua.

17 And Moses sendeth them to spy the land of Canaan, and saith unto them, `Go ye up this [way] into the south, and ye have gone up the mountain,

18 and have seen the land what it [is], and the people which is dwelling on it, whether it [is] strong or feeble; whether it [is] few or many;

19 and what the land [is] in which it is dwelling, whether it [is] good or bad; and what [are] the cities in which it is dwelling, whether in camps or in fortresses;

20 And what the land [is], whether it [is] fat or lean; whether there is wood in it or not; and ye have strengthened yourselves, and have taken of the fruit of the land;' and the days [are] days of the first-fruits of grapes.

21 And they go up and spy the land, from the wilderness of Zin unto Rehob at the going in to Hamath;

22 and they go up by the south, and come in unto Hebron, and there [are] Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai, children of Anak (and Hebron was built seven years before Zoan in Egypt),

23 and they come in unto the brook of Eshcol, and cut down thence a branch and one cluster of grapes, and they bear it on a staff by two, also [some] of the pomegranates, and of the figs.

24 That place hath [one] called Brook of Eshcol, because of the cluster which the sons of Israel cut from thence.

25 And they turn back from spying the land at the end of forty days.

26 And they go and come in unto Moses, and unto Aaron, and unto all the company of the sons of Israel, unto the wilderness of Paran, to Kadesh; and they bring them and all the company back word, and shew them the fruit of the land.

27 And they recount to him, and say, `We came in unto the land whither thou hast sent us, and also it [is] flowing with milk and honey--and this [is] its fruit;

28 only, surely the people which is dwelling in the land [is] strong; and the cities are fenced, very great; and also children of Anak we have seen there.

29 Amalek is dwelling in the land of the south, and the Hittite, and the Jebusite, and the Amorite is dwelling in the hill country, and the Canaanite is dwelling by the sea, and by the side of the Jordan.'

30 And Caleb stilleth the people concerning Moses, and saith, `Let us certainly go up- -and we have possessed it; for we are thoroughly able for it.'

31 And the men who have gone up with him said, `We are not able to go up against the people, for it [is] stronger than we;'

32 and they bring out an evil account of the land which they have spied unto the sons of Israel, saying, `The land into which we passed over to spy it, is a land eating up its inhabitants; and all the people whom we saw in its midst [are] men of stature;

33 and there we saw the Nephilim, sons of Anak, of the Nephilim; and we are in our own eyes as grasshoppers; and so we were in their eyes.'

Numbers 21

1 And the Canaanite--king Arad--dwelling in the south, heareth that Israel hath come the way of the Atharim, and he fighteth against Israel, and taketh [some] of them captive.

2 And Israel voweth a vow to Jehovah, and saith, `If Thou dost certainly give this people into my hand, then I have devoted their cities;'

3 and Jehovah hearkeneth to the voice of Israel, and giveth up the Canaanite, and he devoteth them and their cities, and calleth the name of the place Hormah.

4 And they journey from mount Hor, the way of the Red Sea, to compass the land of Edom, and the soul of the people is short in the way,

5 and the people speak against God, and against Moses, `Why hast thou brought us up out of Egypt to die in a wilderness? for there is no bread, and there is no water, and our soul hath been weary of this light bread.'

6 And Jehovah sendeth among the people the burning serpents, and they bite the people, and much people of Israel die;

7 and the people come in unto Moses and say, `We have sinned, for we have spoken against Jehovah, and against thee; pray unto Jehovah, and He doth turn aside from us the serpent;' and Moses prayeth in behalf of the people.

8 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Make for thee a burning [serpent], and set it on an ensign; and it hath been, every one who is bitten and hath seen it--he hath lived.

9 And Moses maketh a serpent of brass, and setteth it on the ensign, and it hath been, if the serpent hath bitten any man, and he hath looked expectingly unto the serpent of brass--he hath lived.

10 And the sons of Israel journey, and encamp in Oboth.

11 And they journey from Oboth, and encamp in Ije-Abarim, in the wilderness that [is] on the front of Moab, at the rising of the sun.

12 From thence they have journeyed, and encamp in the valley of Zared.

13 From thence they have journeyed, and encamp beyond Arnon, which [is] in the wilderness which is coming out of the border of the Amorite, for Arnon [is] the border of Moab, between Moab and the Amorite;

14 therefore it is said in a book, `The wars of Jehovah,' --`Waheb in Suphah, And the brooks of Arnon;

15 And the spring of the brooks, Which turned aside to the dwelling of Ar, And hath leaned to the border of Moab.'

16 And from thence [they journeyed] to Beer; it [is] the well [concerning] which Jehovah said to Moses, `Gather the people, and I give to them--water.'

17 Then singeth Israel this song, concerning the well--they have answered to it:

18 `A well--digged it have princes, Prepared it have nobles of the people, With the lawgiver, with their staves.' And from the wilderness [they journeyed] to Mattanah,

19 and from Mattanah to Nahaliel, and from Nahaliel to Bamoth,

20 and from Bamoth in the valley which [is] in the field of Moab [to] the top of Pisgah, which hath looked on the front of the wilderness.

21 And Israel sendeth messengers unto Sihon king of the Amorite, saying,

22 `Let me pass through thy land, we do not turn aside into a field, or into a vineyard, we do not drink waters of a well; in the king's way we go, till that we pass over thy border.'

23 And Sihon hath not suffered Israel to pass through his border, and Sihon gathereth all his people, and cometh out to meet Israel into the wilderness, and cometh in to Jahaz, and fighteth against Israel.

24 And Israel smiteth him by the mouth of the sword, and possesseth his land from Arnon unto Jabbok--unto the sons of Ammon; for the border of the sons of Ammon [is] strong.

25 And Israel taketh all these cities, and Israel dwelleth in all the cities of the Amorite, in Heshbon, and in all its villages;

26 for Heshbon is a city of Sihon king of the Amorite, and he hath fought against the former king of Moab, and taketh all his land out of his hand, unto Arnon;

27 therefore those using similes say--`Enter ye Heshbon, Let the city of Sihon be built and ready,

28 For fire hath gone out from Heshbon, A flame from the city of Sihon, It hath consumed Ar of Moab, Owners of the high places of Arnon.

29 Woe to thee, O Moab, Thou hast perished, O people of Chemosh, He hath given his sons who escape--Also his daughters--Into captivity, to a king of the Amorite--Sihon!

30 And we shoot them, Perished hath Heshbon unto Dibon, And we make desolate unto Nophah, Which [is] unto Medeba.'

31 And Israel dwelleth in the land of the Amorite,

32 and Moses sendeth to spy out Jaazer, and they capture its villages, and dispossess the Amorite who [is] there,

33 and turn and go up the way of Bashan, and Og king of Bashan cometh out to meet them, he and all his people, to battle, [at] Edrei.

34 And Jehovah saith unto Moses, `Fear him not, for into thy hand I have given him, and all his people, and his land, and thou hast done to him as thou hast done to Sihon king of the Amorite, who is dwelling in Heshbon.'

35 And they smite him, and his sons, and all his people, until he hath not left to him a remnant, and they possess his land.

Numbers 23

1 And Balaam saith unto Balak, `Build for me in this [place] seven altars, and make ready for me in this [place] seven bullocks and seven rams.'

2 And Balak doth as Balaam hath spoken, and Balak--Balaam also--offereth a bullock and a ram on the altar,

3 and Balaam saith to Balak, `Station thyself by thy burnt-offering and I go on, it may be Jehovah doth come to meet me, and the thing which He sheweth me--I have declared to thee;' and he goeth [to] a high place.

4 And God cometh unto Balaam, and he saith unto Him, `The seven altars I have arranged, and I offer a bullock and a ram on the altar;'

5 and Jehovah putteth a word in the mouth of Balaam, and saith, `Turn back unto Balak, and thus thou dost speak.'

6 And he turneth back unto him, and lo, he is standing by his burnt-offering, he and all the princes of Moab.

7 And he taketh up his simile, and saith: `From Aram he doth lead me--Balak king of Moab; From mountains of the east: Come--curse for me Jacob, And come--be indignant [with] Israel.

8 What--do I pierce? --God hath not pierced! And what--am I indignant? --Jehovah hath not been indignant!

9 For from the top of rocks I see it, And from heights I behold it; Lo a people! alone it doth tabernacle, And among nations doth not reckon itself.

10 Who hath counted the dust of Jacob, And the number of the fourth of Israel? Let me die the death of upright ones, And let my last end be like his!'

11 And Balak saith unto Balaam, `What hast thou done to me? to pierce mine enemies I have taken thee--and lo, thou hast certainly blessed;'

12 and he answereth and saith, `That which Jehovah doth put in my mouth--it do I not take heed to speak?'

13 And Balak saith unto him, `Come, I pray thee, with me unto another place, whence thou dost see it, only its extremity thou dost see, and all of it thou dost not see, and pierce it for me thence;'

14 and he taketh him [to] the field of Zophim, unto the top of Pisgah, and buildeth seven altars, and offereth a bullock and a ram on the altar.

15 And he saith unto Balak, `Station thyself here by thy burnt-offering, and I--I meet [Him] there;'

16 and Jehovah cometh unto Balaam, and setteth a word in his mouth, and saith, `Turn back unto Balak, and thus thou dost speak.'

17 And he cometh unto him, and lo, he is standing by his burnt-offering, and the princes of Moab with him, and Balak saith to him: `What hath Jehovah spoken?'

18 And he taketh up his simile, and saith: `Rise, Balak, and hear; Give ear unto me, son of Zippor!

19 God [is] not a man--and lieth, And a son of man--and repenteth! Hath He said-- and doth He not do [it]? And spoken--and doth He not confirm it?

20 Lo, to bless I have received: Yea, He blesseth, and I [can]not reverse it.

21 He hath not beheld iniquity in Jacob, Nor hath He seen perverseness in Israel; Jehovah his God [is] with him, And a shout of a king [is] in him.

22 God is bringing them out from Egypt, As the swiftness of a Reem is to him;

23 For no enchantment [is] against Jacob, Nor divination against Israel, At the time it is said of Jacob and Israel, What hath God wrought!

24 Lo, the people as a lioness riseth, And as a lion he lifteth himself up, He lieth not down till he eateth prey, And blood of pierced ones doth drink.'

25 And Balak saith unto Balaam, `Neither pierce it at all, nor bless it at all;'

26 and Balaam answereth and saith unto Balak, `Have I not spoken unto thee, saying, All that Jehovah speaketh--it I do?'

27 And Balak saith unto Balaam, `Come, I pray thee, I take thee unto another place; it may be it is right in the eyes of God--to pierce it for me from thence.'

28 And Balak taketh Balaam to the top of Peor, which is looking on the front of the wilderness,

29 and Balaam saith unto Balak, `Build for me in this [place] seven altars, and make ready for me in this [place] seven bullocks and seven rams;'

30 and Balak doth as Balaam said, and he offereth a bullock and a ram on an altar.

Numbers 26

1 And it cometh to pass, after the plague, that Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, and unto Eleazar son of Aaron the priest, saying,

2 `Take up the sum of all the company of the sons of Israel, from a son of twenty years and upward, by the house of their fathers, every one going out to the host in Israel.'

3 And Moses speaketh--Eleazar the priest also--with them, in the plains of Moab, by Jordan, [near] Jericho, saying,

4 `From a son of twenty years and upward,' as Jehovah hath commanded Moses and the sons of Israel who are coming out from the land of Egypt.

5 Reuben, first-born of Israel--sons of Reuben: [of] Hanoch [is] the family of the Hanochite; of Pallu the family of the Palluite;

6 of Hezron the family of the Hezronite; of Carmi the family of the Carmite.

7 These [are] families of the Reubenite, and their numbered ones are three and forty thousand and seven hundred and thirty.

8 And the son of Pallu [is] Eliab;

9 and the sons of Eliab [are] Nemuel and Dathan and Abiram; this [is that] Dathan and Abiram, called ones of the company, who have striven against Moses and against Aaron in the company of Korah, in their striving against Jehovah,

10 and the earth openeth her mouth, and swalloweth them and Korah, in the death of the company, in the fire consuming the two hundred and fifty men, and they become a sign;

11 and the sons of Korah died not.

12 Sons of Simeon by their families: of Nemuel [is] the family of the Nemuelite; of Jamin the family of the Jaminite; of Jachin the family of the Jachinite;

13 of Zerah the family of the Zarhite; of Shaul the family of the Shaulite.

14 These [are] families of the Simeonite, two and twenty thousand and two hundred.

15 Sons of Gad by their families: of Zephon [is] the family of the Zephonite; of Haggi the family of the Haggite; of Shuni the family of the Shunite;

16 of Ozni the family of the Oznite; of Eri the family of the Erite:

17 of Arod the family of the Arodite; of Areli the family of the Arelite.

18 These [are] families of the sons of Gad, by their numbered ones, forty thousand and five hundred.

19 Sons of Judah [are] Er and Onan; and Er dieth--Onan also--in the land of Canaan.

20 And sons of Judah, by their families, are: of Shelah the family of the Shelanite; of Pharez the family of the Pharzite; of Zerah the family of the Zarhite;

21 and sons of Pharez are: of Hezron the family of the Hezronite; of Hamul the family of the Hamulite.

22 These [are] families of Judah, by their numbered ones, six and seventy thousand and five hundred.

23 Sons of Issachar by their families; [of] Tola [is] the family of the Tolaite; of Pua the family of the Punite;

24 of Jashub the family of the Jashubite; of Shimron the family of the Shimronite.

25 These [are] families of Issachar, by their numbered ones, four and sixty thousand and three hundred.

26 Sons of Zebulun by their families: of Sered [is] the family of the Sardite; of Elon the family of the Elonite; of Jahleel the family of the Jahleelite.

27 These [are] families of the Zebulunite by their numbered ones, sixty thousand and five hundred.

28 Sons of Joseph by their families [are] Manasseh and Ephraim.

29 Sons of Manasseh: of Machir [is] the family of the Machirite; and Machir hath begotten Gilead; of Gilead [is] the family of the Gileadite.

30 These [are] sons of Gilead: [of] Jeezer [is] the family of the Jeezerite; of Helek the family of the Helekite;

31 and [of] Asriel the family of the Asrielite; and [of] Shechem the family of the Shechemite;

32 and [of] Shemida the family of the Shemidaite; and [of] Hepher the family of the Hepherite.

33 And Zelophehad son of Hepher had no sons but daughters, and the names of the daughters of Zelophehad [are] Mahlah, and Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah.

34 These [are] families of Manasseh, and their numbered ones [are] two and fifty thousand and seven hundred.

35 These [are] sons of Ephraim by their families: of Shuthelah [is] the family of the Shuthelhite; of Becher the family of the Bachrite; of Tahan the family of the Tahanite.

36 And these [are] sons of Shuthelah: of Eran the family of the Eranite.

37 These [are] families of the sons of Ephraim, by their numbered ones, two and thirty thousand and five hundred. These [are] sons of Joseph by their families.

38 Sons of Benjamin by their families: of Bela [is] the family of the Belaite; of Ashbel the family of the Ashbelite; of Ahiram the family of the Ahiramite;

39 of Shupham the family of the Shuphamite; of Hupham the family of the Huphamite.

40 And sons of Bela are Ard and Naaman: [of Ard is] the family of the Ardite: of Naaman the family of the Naamite.

41 These [are] sons of Benjamin by their families, and their numbered ones [are] five and forty thousand and six hundred.

42 These [are] sons of Dan by their families: of Shuham [is] the family of the Shuhamite; these [are] families of Dan by their families;

43 all the families of the Shuhamite, by their numbered ones, [are] four and sixty thousand and four hundred.

44 Sons of Asher by their families: of Jimna [is] the family of the Jimnite; of Jesui the family of the Jesuite; of Beriah the family of the Beriite.

45 Of sons of Beriah: of Heber [is] the family of the Heberite; of Malchiel the family of the Malchielite.

46 And the name of the daughter of Asher [is] Sarah.

47 These [are] families of the sons of Asher, by their numbered ones, three and fifty thousand and four hundred.

48 Sons of Naphtali by their families: of Jahzeel [is] the family of the Jahzeelite; of Guni the family of the Gunite;

49 of Jezer the family of the Jezerite; of Shillem the family of the Shillemite.

50 These [are] families of Naphtali by their families, and their numbered ones [are] five and forty thousand and four hundred.

51 These [are] numbered ones of the sons of Israel, six hundred thousand, and a thousand, seven hundred and thirty.

52 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, saying,

53 `To these is the land apportioned by inheritance, by the number of names;

54 to the many thou dost increase their inheritance, and to the few thou dost diminish their inheritance; [to] each according to his numbered ones is given his inheritance.

55 `Only by lot is the land apportioned, by the names of the tribes of their fathers they inherit;

56 according to the lot is their inheritance apportioned between many and few.'

57 And these [are] numbered ones of the Levite by their families: of Gershon [is] the family of the Gershonite; of Kohath the family of the Kohathite; of Merari the family of the Merarite.

58 These [are] families of the Levite: the family of the Libnite, the family of the Hebronite, the family of the Mahlite, the family of the Mushite, the family of the Korathite. And Kohath hath begotten Amram,

59 and the name of Amram's wife is Jochebed, daughter of Levi, whom [one] hath born to Levi in Egypt; and she beareth to Amram Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam their sister.

60 And born to Aaron Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar;

61 and Nadab dieth--Abihu also--in their bringing near strange fire before Jehovah.

62 And their numbered ones are three and twenty thousand, every male from a son of a month and upwards, for they have not numbered themselves in the midst of the sons of Israel; for an inheritance hath not been given to them in the midst of the sons of Israel.

63 These [are] those numbered by Moses and Eleazar the priest, who have numbered the sons of Israel in the plains of Moab, by Jordan, [near] Jericho;

64 and among these there hath not been a man of those numbered by Moses, and Aaron the priest, who numbered the sons of Israel in the wilderness of Sinai,

65 for Jehovah said of them, `They do certainly die in the wilderness;' and there hath not been left of them a man save Caleb son of Jephunneh, and Joshua son of Nun.

Numbers 30

1 And Moses speaketh unto the heads of the tribes of the sons of Israel, saying, `This [is] the thing which Jehovah hath commanded:

2 `When a man voweth a vow to Jehovah, or hath sworn an oath to bind a bond on his soul, he doth not pollute his word; according to all that is going out from his mouth he doth.

3 `And when a woman voweth a vow to Jehovah, and hath bound a bond in the house of her father in her youth,

4 and her father hath heard her vow, and her bond which she hath bound on her soul, and her father hath kept silent at her, then have all her vows been established, and every bond which she hath bound on her soul is established.

5 `And if her father hath disallowed her in the day of his hearing, none of her vows and her bonds which she hath bound on her soul is established, and Jehovah is propitious to her, for her father hath disallowed her.

6 `And if she be at all to a husband, and her vows [are] on her, or a wrongful utterance [on] her lips, which she hath bound on her soul,

7 and her husband hath heard, and in the day of his hearing, he hath kept silent at her, then have her vows been established, and her bonds which she hath bound on her soul are established.

8 `And if in the day of her husband's hearing he disalloweth her, then he hath broken her vow which [is] on her, and the wrongful utterance of her lips which she hath bound on her soul, and Jehovah is propitious to her.

9 `As to the vow of a widow or cast-out woman, all that she hath bound on her soul is established on her.

10 `And if [in] the house of her husband she hath vowed, or hath bound a bond on her soul with an oath,

11 and her husband hath heard, and hath kept silent at her--he hath not disallowed her--then have all her vows been established, and every bond which she hath bound on her soul is established.

12 `And if her husband doth certainly break them in the day of his hearing, none of the outgoing of her lips concerning her vows, or concerning the bond of her soul, is established--her husband hath broken them--and Jehovah is propitious to her.

13 `Every vow and every oath--a bond to humble a soul--her husband doth establish it, or her husband doth break it;

14 and if her husband certainly keep silent at her, from day unto day, then he hath established all her vows, or all her bonds which [are] upon her; he hath established them, for he hath kept silent at her in the day of his hearing;

15 and if he doth at all break them after his hearing, then he hath borne her iniquity.'

16 These [are] the statutes which Jehovah hath commanded Moses between a man and his wife, between a father and his daughter, in her youth, [in] the house of her father.

Numbers 33

1 These [are] journeys of the sons of Israel who have come out of the land of Egypt, by their hosts, by the hand of Moses and Aaron;

2 and Moses writeth their outgoings, by their journeys, by the command of Jehovah; and these [are] their journeys, by their outgoings:

3 And they journey from Rameses in the first month, on the fifteenth day of the first month, on the morrow of the passover have the sons of Israel gone out with a high hand, before the eyes of all the Egyptians--

4 and the Egyptians are burying those whom Jehovah hath smitten among them, every first-born, and on their gods hath Jehovah done judgments--

5 and the sons of Israel journey from Rameses, and encamp in Succoth.

6 And they journey from Succoth, and encamp in Etham, which [is] in the extremity of the wilderness;

7 and they journey from Etham, and turn back on Pi-Hahiroth, which [is] on the front of Baal-Zephon, and they encamp before Migdol.

8 And they journey from Pi-Hahiroth, and pass over through the midst of the sea, into the wilderness, and go a journey of three days in the wilderness of Etham, and encamp in Marah.

9 And they journey from Marah, and come in to Elim, and in Elim [are] twelve fountains of waters, and seventy palm trees, and they encamp there;

10 and they journey from Elim, and encamp by the Red Sea.

11 And they journey from the Red Sea, and encamp in the wilderness of Sin;

12 and they journey from the wilderness of Sin, and encamp in Dophkah.

13 And they journey from Dophkah, and encamp in Alush;

14 and they journey from Alush, and encamp in Rephidim; and there was there no water for the people to drink.

15 And they journey from Rephidim, and encamp in the wilderness of Sinai;

16 and they journey from the wilderness of Sinai, and encamp in Kibroth-Hattaavah.

17 And they journey from Kibroth-Hattaavah, and encamp in Hazeroth;

18 and they journey from Hazeroth, and encamp in Rithmah.

19 And they journey from Rithmah, and encamp in Rimmon-Parez;

20 and they journey from Rimmon-Parez, and encamp in Libnah.

21 And they journey from Libnah, and encamp in Rissah;

22 and they journey from Rissah, and encamp in Kehelathah.

23 And they journey from Kehelathah, and encamp in mount Shapher;

24 and they journey from mount Shapher, and encamp in Haradah.

25 And they journey from Haradah, and encamp in Makheloth;

26 and they journey from Makheloth, and encamp in Tahath.

27 And they journey from Tahath, and encamp in Tarah;

28 and they journey from Tarah, and encamp in Mithcah.

29 And they journey from Mithcah, and encamp in Hashmonah;

30 and they journey from Hashmonah, and encamp in Moseroth.

31 And they journey from Moseroth, and encamp in Bene-Jaakan;

32 and they journey from Bene-Jaakan, and encamp at Hor-Hagidgad.

33 And they journey from Hor-Hagidgad, and encamp in Jotbathah;

34 and they journey from Jotbathah, and encamp in Ebronah.

35 And they journey from Ebronah, and encamp in Ezion-Gaber;

36 and they journey from Ezion-Gaber, and encamp in the wilderness of Zin, which [is] Kadesh.

37 And they journey from Kadesh, and encamp in mount Hor, in the extremity of the land of Edom.

38 And Aaron the priest goeth up unto mount Hor, by the command of Jehovah, and dieth there, in the fortieth year of the going out of the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, in the fifth month, on the first of the month;

39 and Aaron [is] a son of a hundred and twenty and three years in his dying in mount Hor.

40 And the Canaanite--king Arad--who is dwelling in the south, in the land of Canaan, heareth of the coming of the sons of Israel.

41 And they journey from mount Hor, and encamp in Zalmonah;

42 and they journey from Zalmonah, and encamp in Punon.

43 And they journey from Punon, and encamp in Oboth;

44 and they journey from Oboth, and encamp in Ije-Abarim, in the border of Moab.

45 And they journey from Iim, and encamp in Dibon-Gad;

46 and they journey from Dibon-Gad, and encamp in Almon-Diblathaim.

47 And they journey from Almon-Diblathaim, and encamp in the mountains of Abarim, before Nebo;

48 and they journey from the mountains of Abarim, and encamp in the plains of Moab, by Jordan, [near] Jericho.

49 And they encamp by the Jordan from Beth-Jeshimoth, unto Abel-Shittim, in the plains of Moab.

50 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, in the plains of Moab, by Jordan, [near] Jericho, saying,

51 `Speak unto the sons of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, When ye are passing over the Jordan unto the land of Canaan,

52 then ye have dispossessed all the inhabitants of the land from before you, and have destroyed all their imagery, yea, all their molten images ye destroy, and all their high places ye lay waste,

53 and ye have possessed the land, and dwelt in it, for to you I have given the land--to possess it.

54 `And ye have inherited the land by lot, by your families; to the many ye increase their inheritance, and to the few ye diminish their inheritance; whither the lot goeth out to him, it is his; by the tribes of your fathers ye inherit.

55 `And if ye do not dispossess the inhabitants of the land from before you, then it hath been, those whom ye let remain of them, [are] for pricks in your eyes, and for thorns in your sides, and they have distressed you on the land in which yeare dwelling,

56 and it hath come to pass, as I thought to do to them--I do to you.'

Deuteronomy 1

1 These [are] the words which Moses hath spoken unto all Israel, beyond the Jordan, in the wilderness, in the plain over-against Suph, between Paran and Tophel, and Laban, and Hazeroth, and Di-Zahab;

2 eleven days' from Horeb, the way of mount Seir, unto Kadesh-Barnea.

3 And it cometh to pass in the fortieth year, in the eleventh month, on the first of the month hath Moses spoken unto the sons of Israel according to all that Jehovah hath commanded him concerning them;

4 after his smiting Sihon king of the Amorite who is dwelling in Heshbon, and Og king of Bashan who is dwelling in Ashtaroth in Edrei,

5 beyond the Jordan, in the land of Moab, hath Moses begun to explain this law, saying:

6 `Jehovah our God hath spoken unto us in Horeb, saying, Enough to you--of dwelling in this mount;

7 turn ye and journey for you, and enter the mount of the Amorite, and unto all its neighbouring places, in the plain, in the hill-country, and in the low country, and in the south, and in the haven of the sea, the land of the Canaanite, and of Lebanon, unto the great river, the river Phrat;

8 see, I have set before you the land; go in and possess the land which Jehovah hath sworn to your fathers, to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them, and to their seed after them.

9 `And I speak unto you at that time, saying, I am not able by myself to bear you;

10 Jehovah your God hath multiplied you, and lo, ye [are] to-day as the stars of the heavens for multitude;

11 Jehovah, God of your fathers, is adding to you, as ye [are], a thousand times, and doth bless you as He hath spoken to you.

12 `How do I bear by myself your pressure, and your burden, and your strife?

13 Give for yourselves men, wise and intelligent, and known to your tribes, and I set them for your heads;

14 and ye answer me and say, Good [is] the thing which thou hast spoken--to do.

15 `And I take the heads of your tribes, men, wise and known, and I appoint them heads over you, princes of thousands, and princes of hundreds, and princes of fifties, and princes of tens, and authorities, for your tribes.

16 And I command your judges at that time, saying, Hearkening between your brethren--then ye have judged righteousness between a man, and his brother, and his sojourner;

17 ye do not discern faces in judgment; as the little so the great ye do hear; ye are not afraid of the face of any, for the judgment is God's, and the thing which is too hard for you, ye bring near unto me, and I have heard it;

18 and I command you, at that time, all the things which ye do.

19 `And we journey from Horeb, and go [through] all that great and fearful wilderness which ye have seen--the way of the hill-country of the Amorite, as Jehovah our God hath commanded us, and we come in unto Kadesh-Barnea.

20 `And I say unto you, Ye have come in unto the hill-country of the Amorite, which Jehovah our God is giving to us;

21 see, Jehovah thy God hath set before thee the land; go up, possess, as Jehovah, God of thy fathers, hath spoken to thee; fear not, nor be affrighted.

22 `And ye come near unto me, all of you, and say, Let us send men before us, and they search for us the land, and they bring us back word [concerning] the way in which we go up into it, and the cities unto which we come in;

23 and the thing is good in mine eyes, and I take of you twelve men, one man for a tribe.

24 `And they turn and go up to the hill-country, and come in unto the valley of Eshcol, and spy it,

25 and they take with their hand of the fruit of the land, and bring down unto us, and bring us back word, and say, Good is the land which Jehovah our God is giving to us.

26 `And ye have not been willing to go up, and ye provoke the mouth of Jehovah your God,

27 and murmur in your tents, and say, In Jehovah's hating us He hath brought us out of the land of Egypt, to give us into the hand of the Amorite--to destroy us;

28 whither are we going up? our brethren have melted our heart, saying, A people greater and taller than we, cities great and fenced to heaven, and also sons of Anakim--we have seen there.

29 `And I say unto you, Be not terrified, nor be afraid of them;

30 Jehovah your God, who is going before you--He doth fight for you, according to all that He hath done with you in Egypt before your eyes,

31 and in the wilderness, where thou hast seen that Jehovah thy God hath borne thee as a man beareth his son, in all the way which ye have gone, till your coming in unto this place.

32 `And in this thing ye are not stedfast in Jehovah your God,

33 who is going before you in the way to search out to you a place for your encamping, in fire by night, to shew you in the way in which ye go, and in a cloud by day.

34 `And Jehovah heareth the voice of your words, and is wroth, and sweareth, saying,

35 Not one of these men of this evil generation doth see the good land which I have sworn to give to your fathers,

36 save Caleb son of Jephunneh--he doth see it, and to him I give the land on which he hath trodden, and to his sons, because that he hath been fully after Jehovah.

37 `Also with me hath Jehovah been angry for your sake, saying, Also, thou dost not go in thither;

38 Joshua son of Nun, who is standing before thee, he goeth in thither; him strengthen thou; for he doth cause Israel to inherit.

39 `And your infants, of whom ye have said, For a prey they are, and your sons who have not known to-day good and evil, they go in thither, and to them I give it, and they possess it;

40 and ye, turn for yourselves, and journey toward the wilderness, the way of the Red Sea.

41 `And ye answer and say unto me, We have sinned against Jehovah; we--we go up, and we have fought, according to all that which Jehovah our God hath commanded us; and ye gird on each his weapons of war, and ye are ready to go up into the hill-country;

42 and Jehovah saith unto me, Say to them, Ye do not go up, nor fight, for I am not in your midst, and ye are not smitten before your enemies.

43 `And I speak unto you, and ye have not hearkened, and provoke the mouth of Jehovah, and act proudly, and go up into the hill-country;

44 and the Amorite who is dwelling in that hill-country cometh out to meet you, and they pursue you as the bees do, and smite you in Seir--unto Hormah.

45 `And ye turn back and weep before Jehovah, and Jehovah hath not hearkened to your voice, nor hath he given ear unto you;

46 and ye dwell in Kadesh many days, according to the days which ye had dwelt.

Deuteronomy 2

1 `And we turn, and journey into the wilderness, the way of the Red Sea, as Jehovah hath spoken unto me, and we go round the mount of Seir many days.

2 `And Jehovah speaketh unto me, saying,

3 Enough to you--is the going round of this mount; turn for yourselves northward.

4 `And the people command thou, saying, Ye are passing over into the border of your brethren, sons of Esau, who are dwelling in Seir, and they are afraid of you; and ye have been very watchful,

5 ye do not strive with them, for I do not give to you of their land even the treading of the sole of a foot; for a possession to Esau I have given mount Seir.

6 `Food ye buy from them with money, and have eaten; and also water ye buy from them with money, and have drunk,

7 for Jehovah thy God hath blessed thee in all the work of thy hands; He hath known thy walking in this great wilderness these forty years; Jehovah thy God [is] with thee; thou hast not lacked anything.

8 `And we pass by from our brethren, sons of Esau, who are dwelling in Seir, by the way of the plain, by Elath, and by Ezion-Gaber; and we turn, and pass over the way of the wilderness of Moab;

9 and Jehovah saith unto me, Do not distress Moab, nor stir thyself up against them [in] battle, for I do not give to thee of their land [for] a possession; for to the sons of Lot I have given Ar [for] a possession.'

10 `The Emim formerly have dwelt in it, a people great, and numerous, and tall, as the Anakim;

11 Rephaim they are reckoned, they also, as the Anakim; and the Moabites call them Emim.

12 And in Seir have the Horim dwelt formerly; and the sons of Esau dispossess them, and destroy them from before them, and dwell in their stead, as Israel hath done to the land of his possession, which Jehovah hath given to them;

13 now, rise ye, and pass over for yourselves the brook Zered; and we pass over the brook Zered.

14 `And the days which we have walked from Kadesh-Barnea until that we have passed over the brook Zered, [are] thirty and eight years, till the consumption of all the generation of the men of battle from the midst of the camp, as Jehovah hath sworn to them;

15 and also the hand of Jehovah hath been against them, to destroy them from the midst of the camp, till they are consumed.

16 `And it cometh to pass, when all the men of battle have finished dying from the midst of the people,

17 that Jehovah speaketh unto me, saying,

18 Thou art passing over to-day the border of Moab, even Ar,

19 and thou hast come near over-against the sons of Ammon, thou dost not distress them, nor stir up thyself against them, for I do not give [any] of the land of the sons of Ammon to thee [for] a possession; for to the sons of Lot I have given it [for] a possession.

20 `A land of Rephaim it is reckoned, even it; Rephaim dwelt in it formerly, and the Ammonites call them Zamzummim;

21 a people great, and numerous, and tall, as the Anakim, and Jehovah destroyeth them before them, and they dispossess them, and dwell in their stead,

22 as He hath done for the sons of Esau, who are dwelling in Seir, when He destroyed the Horim from before them, and they dispossess them, and dwell in their stead, unto this day.

23 `As to the Avim who are dwelling in Hazerim unto Azzah, the Caphtorim-- who are coming out from Caphtor--have destroyed them, and dwell in their stead.

24 `Rise ye, journey and pass over the brook Arnon; see, I have given into thy hand Sihon king of Heshbon, the Amorite, and his land; begin to possess, and stir up thyself against him [in] battle.

25 This day I begin to put thy dread and thy fear on the face of the peoples under the whole heavens, who hear thy fame, and have trembled and been pained because of thee.

26 `And I send messengers from the wilderness of Kedemoth, unto Sihon king of Heshbon, --words of peace--saying,

27 Let me pass over through thy land; in the several ways I go; I turn not aside-- right or left--

28 food for money thou dost sell me, and I have eaten; and water for money thou dost give to me, and I have drunk; only, let me pass over on my feet, --

29 as the sons of Esau who are dwelling in Seir, and the Moabites who are dwelling in Ar, have done to me--till that I pass over the Jordan, unto the land which Jehovah our God is giving to us.

30 `And Sihon king of Heshbon hath not been willing to let us pass over by him, for Jehovah thy God hath hardened his spirit, and strengthened his heart, so as to give him into thy hand as at this day.

31 `And Jehovah saith unto me, See, I have begun to give before thee Sihon and his land; begin to possess--to possess his land.

32 `And Sihon cometh out to meet us, he and all his people, to battle to Jahaz;

33 and Jehovah our God giveth him before us, and we smite him, and his sons, and all his people;

34 and we capture all his cities at that time, and devote the whole city, men, and the women, and the infants--we have not left a remnant;

35 only, the cattle we have spoiled for ourselves, and the spoil of the cities which we have captured.

36 `From Aroer, which [is] by the edge of the brook Arnon, and the city which [is] by the brook, even unto Gilead there hath not been a city which [is] too high for us; the whole hath Jehovah our God given before us.

37 `Only, unto the land of the sons of Ammon thou hast not drawn near, any part of the brook Jabbok, and cities of the hill-country, and anything which Jehovah our God hath [not] commanded.

Deuteronomy 3

1 `And we turn, and go up the way to Bashan, and Og king of Bashan cometh out to meet us, he and all his people, to battle, [to] Edrei.

2 `And Jehovah saith unto me, Fear him not, for into thy hand I have given him, and all his people, and his land, and thou hast done to him as thou hast done to Sihon king of the Amorite who is dwelling in Heshbon.

3 `And Jehovah our God giveth into our hands also Og king of Bashan, and all his people, and we smite him till there hath not been left to him a remnant;

4 and we capture all his cities at that time, there hath not been a city which we have not taken from them, sixty cities, all the region of Argob, the kingdom of Og in Bashan.

5 All these [are] cities fenced with high walls, two-leaved doors and bar, apart from cities of villages very many;

6 and we devote them, as we have done to Sihon king of Heshbon, devoting every city, men, the women, and the infants;

7 and all the cattle, and the spoil of the cities, we have spoiled for ourselves.

8 `And we take, at that time, the land out of the hand of the two kings of the Amorite, which is beyond the Jordan, from the brook Arnon unto mount Hermon;

9 (Sidonians call Hermon, Sirion; and the Amorites call it Senir,)

10 all the cities of the plain, and all Gilead, and all Bashan, unto Salchah and Edrei, cities of the kingdom of Og in Bashan,

11 for only Og king of Bashan had been left of the remnant of the Rephaim; lo, his bedstead [is] a bedstead of iron; is it not in Rabbath of the sons of Ammon? nine cubits its length, and four cubits its breadth, by the cubit of a man.

12 `And this land we have possessed, at that time; from Aroer, which [is] by the brook Arnon, and the half of mount Gilead, and its cities, I have given to the Reubenite, and to the Gadite;

13 and the rest of Gilead and all Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I have given to the half tribe of Manasseh; all the region of Argob, to all that Bashan, called the land of Rephaim.

14 `Jair son of Manasseh hath taken all the region of Argob, unto the border of Geshuri, and Maachathi, and calleth them by his own name, Bashan-Havoth-Jair, unto this day.

15 And to Machir I have given Gilead.

16 `And to the Reubenite and to the Gadite I have given from Gilead even unto the brook Arnon, the middle of the valley and the border, even unto Jabbok the brook, the border of the sons of Ammon,

17 and the plain, and the Jordan, and the border, from Chinnereth even unto the sea of the plain, the salt sea, under the springs of Pisgah, at the [sun] -rising.

18 `And I command you, at that time, saying, Jehovah your God hath given to you this land to possess it; armed ye pass over before your brethren the sons of Israel, all the sons of might.

19 Only, your wives, and your infants, and your cattle--I have known that ye have much cattle--do dwell in your cities which I have given to you,

20 till that Jehovah give rest to your brethren like yourselves, and they also have possessed the land which Jehovah your God is giving to them beyond the Jordan, then ye have turned back each to his possession, which I have given to you.

21 `And Jehoshua I have commanded at that time, saying, Thine eyes are seeing all that which Jehovah your God hath done to these two kings--so doth Jehovah to all the kingdoms whither thou are passing over;

22 fear them not, for Jehovah your God, He is fighting for you.

23 `And I entreat for grace unto Jehovah, at that time, saying,

24 Lord Jehovah, Thou--Thou hast begun to shew Thy servant Thy greatness, and Thy strong hand; for who [is] a God in the heavens or in earth who doth according to Thy works, and according to Thy might?

25 Let me pass over, I pray Thee, and see the good land which [is] beyond the Jordan, this good hill-country, and Lebanon.

26 `And Jehovah sheweth himself wroth with me, for your sake, and hath not hearkened unto me, and Jehovah saith unto me, Enough for thee; add not to speak unto Me any more about this thing:

27 go up [to] the top of Pisgah, and lift up thine eyes westward, and northward, and southward, and eastward, and see with thine eyes--for thou dost not pass over this Jordan;

28 and charge Jehoshua, and strengthen him, and harden him, for he doth pass over before this people, and he doth cause them to inherit the land which thou seest.

29 `And we dwell in a valley over-against Beth-Peor.

Deuteronomy 5

1 And Moses calleth unto all Israel, and saith unto them, `Hear, Israel, the statutes and the judgments which I am speaking in your ears to-day, and ye have learned them, and have observed to do them.

2 Jehovah our God made with us a covenant in Horeb;

3 not with our fathers hath Jehovah made this covenant, but with us; we--these-- here to-day--all of us alive.

4 Face to face hath Jehovah spoken with you, in the mount, out of the midst of the fire;

5 I am standing between Jehovah and you, at that time, to declare to you the word of Jehovah, for ye have been afraid from the presence of the fire, and ye have not gone up into the mount; saying:

6 `I Jehovah [am] thy God, who hath brought thee out from the land of Egypt, from a house of servants.

7 `Thou hast no other gods in My presence.

8 `Thou dost not make to thee a graven image, any similitude which [is] in the heavens above, and which [is] in the earth beneath, and which [is] in the waters under the earth;

9 thou dost not bow thyself to them nor serve them, for I Jehovah thy God [am] a zealous God, charging iniquity of fathers on children, and on a third [generation], and on a fourth, to those hating Me;

10 and doing kindness to thousands, to those loving Me, and to those keeping My commands.

11 `Thou dost not take up the Name of Jehovah thy God for a vain thing, for Jehovah doth not acquit him who taketh up His Name for a vain thing.

12 `Observe the day of the sabbath--to sanctify it, as Jehovah thy God hath commanded thee;

13 six days thou dost labour, and hast done all thy work,

14 and the seventh day [is] a sabbath to Jehovah thy God; thou dost not do any work, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy handmaid, and thine ox, and thine ass, and all thy cattle, and thy sojourner who [is] within thy gates; so that thy manservant, and thy handmaid doth rest like thyself;

15 and thou hast remembered that a servant thou hast been in the land of Egypt, and Jehovah thy God is bringing thee out thence by a strong hand, and by a stretched-out arm; therefore hath Jehovah thy God commanded thee to keep the day of the sabbath.

16 `Honour thy father and thy mother, as Jehovah thy God hath commanded thee, so that thy days are prolonged, and so that it is well with thee, on the ground which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee.

17 `Thou dost not murder.

18 `Thou dost not commit adultery.

19 `Thou dost not steal.

20 `Thou dost not answer against thy neighbour--a false testimony.

21 `Thou dost not desire thy neighbour's wife; nor dost thou covet thy neighbour's house, his field, and his man-servant, and his handmaid, his ox, and his ass, and anything which [is] thy neighbour's.

22 `These words hath Jehovah spoken unto all your assembly, in the mount out of the midst of the fire, of the cloud, and of the thick darkness--a great voice; and He hath not added, and He writeth them on two tables of stone, and giveth them unto me.

23 `And it cometh to pass as ye hear the voice out of the midst of the darkness, and of the mountain burning with fire, that ye come near unto me, all the heads of your tribes, and your elders,

24 and say, Lo, Jehovah our God hath shewed us His honour, and His greatness; and His voice we have heard out of the midst of the fire; this day we have seen that God doth speak with man--and he hath lived.

25 `And, now, why do we die? for consume us doth this great fire--if we add to hear the voice of Jehovah our God any more--then we have died.

26 For who of all flesh [is] he who hath heard the voice of the living God speaking out of the midst of the fire like us--and doth live?

27 Draw near thou, and hear all that which Jehovah our God saith, and thou, thou dost speak unto us all that which Jehovah our God speaketh unto thee, and we have hearkened, and done it.

28 `And Jehovah heareth the voice of your words, in your speaking unto me, and Jehovah saith unto me, I have heard the voice of the words of this people which they have spoken unto thee; they have done well [in] all that they have spoken.

29 O that their heart had been thus to them, to fear Me, and to keep My commands all the days, that it may be well with them, and with their sons--to the age!

30 `Go, say to them, Turn back for yourselves, to your tents;

31 and thou here stand thou with Me, and let Me speak unto thee all the command, and the statutes, and the judgments which thou dost teach them, and they have done in the land which I am giving to them to possess it.

32 `And ye have observed to do as Jehovah your God hath commanded you, ye turn not aside--right or left;

33 in all the way which Jehovah your God hath commanded you ye walk, so that ye live, and [it is] well with you, and ye have prolonged days in the land which ye possess.

Deuteronomy 10

1 `At that time hath Jehovah said unto me, Grave for thee two tables of stone, like the first, and come up unto Me, into the mount, and thou hast made for thee an ark of wood,

2 and I write on the tables the words which were on the first tables, which thou hast broken, and thou hast placed them in the ark;

3 and I make an ark of shittim wood, and grave two tables of stone like the first, and go up to the mount, and the two tables in my hand.

4 `And He writeth on the tables, according to the first writing, the Ten Matters, which Jehovah hath spoken unto you in the mount, out of the midst of the fire, in the day of the assembly, and Jehovah giveth them unto me,

5 and I turn and come down from the mount, and put the tables in the ark which I had made, and they are there, as Jehovah commanded me.

6 `And the sons of Israel have journeyed from Beeroth of the sons of Jaakan to Mosera, there Aaron died, and he is buried there, and Eleazar his son doth act as priest in his stead;

7 thence they journeyed to Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a land of brooks of water.

8 `At that time hath Jehovah separated the tribe of Levi, to bear the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, to stand before Jehovah, to serve Him, and to bless in His name, unto this day,

9 therefore there hath not been to Levi a portion and inheritance with his brethren; Jehovah Himself [is] his inheritance, as Jehovah thy God hath spoken to him.

10 `And I--I have stood in the mount, as the former days, forty days and forty nights, and Jehovah hearkeneth unto me also at that time; Jehovah hath not willed to destroy thee.

11 `And Jehovah saith unto me, Rise, go to journey before the people, and they go in and possess the land which I have sworn to their fathers to give to them.

12 `And now, Israel, what is Jehovah thy God asking from thee, except to fear Jehovah thy God, to walk in all His ways, and to love Him, and to serve Jehovah thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul,

13 to keep the commands of Jehovah, and His statutes which I am commanding thee to-day, for good to thee?

14 `Lo, to Jehovah thy God [are] the heavens and the heavens of the heavens, the earth and all that [is] in it;

15 only in thy fathers hath Jehovah delighted--to love them, and He doth fix on their seed after them--on you, out of all the peoples as [at] this day;

16 and ye have circumcised the foreskin of your heart, and your neck ye do not harden any more;

17 for Jehovah your God--He [is] God of the gods, and Lord of the lords; God, the great, the mighty, and the fearful; who accepteth not persons, nor taketh a bribe;

18 He is doing the judgment of fatherless and widow, and loving the sojourner, to give to him bread and raiment.

19 `And ye have loved the sojourner, for sojourners ye were in the land of Egypt.

20 `Jehovah thy God thou dost fear, Him thou dost serve, and to Him thou dost cleave, and by His name thou dost swear.

21 He [is] thy praise, and He [is] thy God, who hath done with thee these great and fearful [things] which thine eyes have seen:

22 with seventy persons did thy fathers go down to Egypt, and now hath Jehovah thy God made thee as stars of the heavens for multitude.

Deuteronomy 16

1 `Observe the month of Abib--and thou hast made a passover to Jehovah thy God, for in the month of Abib hath Jehovah thy God brought thee out of Egypt by night;

2 and thou hast sacrificed a passover to Jehovah thy God, of the flock, and of the herd, in the place which Jehovah doth choose to cause His name to tabernacle there.

3 `Thou dost not eat with it any fermented thing, seven days thou dost eat with it unleavened things, bread of affliction; for in haste thou hast come out of the land of Egypt; so that thou dost remember the day of thy coming out of the land of Egypt all days of thy life;

4 and there is not seen with thee leaven in all thy border seven days, and there doth not remain of the flesh which thou dost sacrifice at evening on the first day till morning.

5 `Thou art not able to sacrifice the passover within any of thy gates which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee,

6 except at the place which Jehovah thy God doth choose to cause His name to tabernacle--there thou dost sacrifice the passover in the evening, at the going in of the sun, the season of thy coming out of Egypt;

7 and thou hast cooked and eaten in the place on which Jehovah thy God doth fix, and hast turned in the morning, and gone to thy tents;

8 six days thou dost eat unleavened things, and on the seventh day [is] a restraint to Jehovah thy God; thou dost do no work.

9 `Seven weeks thou dost number to thee; from the beginning of the sickle among the standing corn thou dost begin to number seven weeks,

10 and thou hast made the feast of weeks to Jehovah thy God, a tribute of a freewill offering of thy hand, which thou dost give, as Jehovah thy God doth bless thee.

11 And thou hast rejoiced before Jehovah thy God, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy handmaid, and the Levite who [is] within thy gates, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] in thy midst, in the place which Jehovah thy God doth choose to cause His name to tabernacle there,

12 and thou hast remembered that a servant thou hast been in Egypt, and hast observed and done these statutes.

13 `The feast of booths thou dost make for thee seven days, in thine in-gathering of thy threshing-floor, and of thy wine-vat;

14 and thou hast rejoiced in thy feast, thou, and thy son, and thy daughter, and thy man-servant, and thy handmaid, and the Levite, and the sojourner, and the fatherless, and the widow, who [are] within thy gates.

15 Seven days thou dost feast before Jehovah thy God, in the place which Jehovah doth choose, for Jehovah thy God doth bless thee in all thine increase, and in every work of thy hands, and thou hast been only rejoicing.

16 `Three times in a year doth every one of thy males appear before Jehovah thy God in the place which He doth choose--in the feast of unleavened things, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of booths; and they do not appear before Jehovah empty;

17 each according to the gift of his hand, according to the blessing of Jehovah thy God, which He hath given to thee.

18 `Judges and authorities thou dost make to thee within all thy gates which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee, for thy tribes; and they have judged the people--a righteous judgment.

19 Thou dost not turn aside judgment; thou dost not discern faces, nor take a bribe, for the bribe blindeth the eyes of the wise, and perverteth the words of the righteous.

20 Righteousness--righteousness thou dost pursue, so that thou livest, and hast possessed the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee.

21 `Thou dost not plant for thee a shrine of any trees near the altar of Jehovah thy God, which thou makest for thyself,

22 and thou dost not raise up to thee any standing image which Jehovah thy God is hating.

Deuteronomy 18

1 `There is not to the priests the Levites--all the tribe of Levi--a portion and inheritance with Israel; fire-offerings of Jehovah, even His inheritance, they eat,

2 and he hath no inheritance in the midst of his brethren; Jehovah Himself [is] his inheritance, as He hath spoken to him.

3 `And this is the priest's right from the people, from those sacrificing a sacrifice, whether ox or sheep, he hath even given to the priest the leg, and the two cheeks, and the stomach;

4 the first of thy corn, of thy new wine, and of thine oil, and the first of the fleece of thy flock, thou dost give to him;

5 for on him hath Jehovah thy God fixed, out of all thy tribes, to stand to serve in the name of Jehovah, He and his sons continually.

6 `And when the Levite cometh from one of thy cities out of all Israel, where he hath sojourned, and hath come with all the desire of his soul unto the place which Jehovah doth choose,

7 then he hath ministered in the name of Jehovah his God, like all his brethren, the Levites, who are standing there before Jehovah,

8 portion as portion they do eat, apart from his sold things, with the fathers.

9 `When thou art coming in unto the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee, thou dost not learn to do according to the abominations of those nations:

10 there is not found in thee one causing his son and his daughter to pass over into fire, a user of divinations, an observer of clouds, and an enchanter, and a sorcerer,

11 and a charmer, and one asking at a familiar spirit, and a wizard, and one seeking unto the dead.

12 `For the abomination of Jehovah [is] every one doing these, and because of these abominations is Jehovah thy God dispossessing them from thy presence.

13 Perfect thou art with Jehovah thy God,

14 for these nations whom thou art possessing, unto observers of clouds, and unto diviners, do hearken; and thou--not so hath Jehovah thy God suffered thee.

15 `A prophet out of thy midst, out of thy brethren, like to me, doth Jehovah thy God raise up to thee--unto him ye hearken;

16 according to all that thou didst ask from Jehovah thy God, in Horeb, in the day of the assembly, saying, Let me not add to hear the voice of Jehovah my God, and this great fire let me not see any more, and I die not;

17 and Jehovah saith unto me, They have done well that they have spoken;

18 a prophet I raise up to them, out of the midst of their brethren, like to thee; and I have given my words in his mouth, and he hath spoken unto them all that which I command him;

19 and it hath been--the man who doth not hearken unto My words which he doth speak in My name, I require [it] of him.

20 `Only, the prophet who presumeth to speak a word in My name--that which I have not commanded him to speak--and who speaketh in the name of other gods--even that prophet hath died.

21 `And when thou sayest in thy heart, How do we know the word which Jehovah hath not spoken? --

22 that which the prophet speaketh in the name of Jehovah, and the thing is not, and cometh not--it [is] the word which Jehovah hath not spoken; in presumption hath the prophet spoken it; --thou art not afraid of him.

Deuteronomy 20

1 `When thou goest out to battle against thine enemy, and hast seen horse and chariot--a people more numerous than thou--thou art not afraid of them, for Jehovah thy God [is] with thee, who is bringing thee up out of the land of Egypt;

2 and it hath been, in your drawing near unto the battle, that the priest hath come nigh, and spoken unto the people,

3 and said unto them, Hear, Israel, ye are drawing near to-day to battle against your enemies, let not your hearts be tender, fear not, nor make haste, nor be terrified at their presence,

4 for Jehovah your God [is] He who is going with you, to fight for you with your enemies--to save you.

5 `And the authorities have spoken unto the people, saying, Who [is] the man that hath built a new house, and hath not dedicated it? --let him go and turn back to his house, lest he die in battle, and another man dedicate it.

6 `And who [is] the man that hath planted a vineyard, and hath not made it common? --let him go and turn back to his house, lest he die in battle, and another man make it common.

7 `And who [is] the man that hath betrothed a woman, and hath not taken her? -- let him go and turn back to his house, lest he die in battle, and another man take her.

8 `And the authorities have added to speak unto the people, and said, Who [is] the man that is afraid and tender of heart? --let him go and turn back to his house, and the heart of his brethren doth not melt like his heart;

9 and it hath come to pass as the authorities finish to speak unto the people, that they have appointed princes of the hosts at the head of the people.

10 `When thou drawest near unto a city to fight against it, then thou hast called unto it for Peace,

11 and it hath been, if Peace it answer thee, and hath opened to thee, then it hath come to pass--all the people who are found in it are to thee for tributaries, and have served thee.

12 `And if it doth not make peace with thee, and hath made with thee war, then thou hast laid siege against it,

13 and Jehovah thy God hath given it into thy hand, and thou hast smitten every male of it by the mouth of the sword.

14 Only, the women, and the infants, and the cattle, and all that is in the city, all its spoil, thou dost seize for thyself, and thou hast eaten the spoil of thine enemies which Jehovah thy God hath given to thee.

15 So thou dost do to all the cities which are very far off from thee, which are not of the cities of these nations.

16 `Only, of the cities of these peoples which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee [for] an inheritance, thou dost not keep alive any breathing;

17 for thou dost certainly devote the Hittite, and the Amorite, the Canaanite, and the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, as Jehovah thy God hath commanded thee,

18 so that they teach you not to do according to all their abominations which they have done to their gods, and ye have sinned against Jehovah your God.

19 `When thou layest siege unto a city many days, to fight against it, to capture it, thou dost not destroy its trees to force an axe against them, for of them thou dost eat, and them thou dost not cut down--for man's [is] the tree of the field--to go in at thy presence in the siege.

20 Only, the tree, which thou knowest that it [is] not a fruit-tree, it thou dost destroy, and hast cut down, and hast built a bulwark against the city which is making with thee war till thou hast subdued it.

Deuteronomy 22

1 `Thou dost not see the ox of thy brother or his sheep driven away, and hast hidden thyself from them, thou dost certainly turn them back to thy brother;

2 and if thy brother [is] not near unto thee, and thou hast not known him, then thou hast removed it unto the midst of thy house, and it hath been with thee till thy brother seek it, and thou hast given it back to him;

3 and so thou dost to his ass, and so thou dost to his garment, and so thou dost to any lost thing of thy brother's, which is lost by him, and thou hast found it; thou art not able to hide thyself.

4 `Thou dost not see the ass of thy brother, or his ox, falling in the way, and hast hid thyself from them; thou dost certainly raise [them] up with him.

5 `The habiliments of a man are not on a woman, nor doth a man put on the garment of a woman, for the abomination of Jehovah thy God [is] any one doing these.

6 `When a bird's nest cometh before thee in the way, in any tree, or on the earth, brood or eggs, and the mother sitting on the brood or on the eggs, thou dost not take the mother with the young ones;

7 thou dost certainly send away the mother, and the young ones dost take to thyself, so that it is well with thee, and thou hast prolonged days.

8 `When thou buildest a new house, then thou hast made a parapet to thy roof, and thou dost not put blood on thy house when one falleth from it.

9 `Thou dost not sow thy vineyard [with] divers things, lest the fulness of the seed which thou dost sow, and the increase of the vineyard, be separated.

10 `Thou dost not plow with an ox and with an ass together.

11 `Thou dost not put on a mixed cloth, wool and linen together.

12 `Fringes thou dost make to thee on the four skirts of thy covering with which thou dost cover [thyself].

13 `When a man taketh a wife, and hath gone in unto her, and hated her,

14 and laid against her actions of words, and brought out against her an evil name, and said, This woman I have taken, and I draw near unto her, and I have not found in her tokens of virginity:

15 `Then hath the father of the damsel--and her mother--taken and brought out the tokens of virginity of the damsel unto the elders of the city in the gate,

16 and the father of the damsel hath said unto the elders, My daughter I have given to this man for a wife, and he doth hate her;

17 and lo, he hath laid actions of words, saying, I have not found to thy daughter tokens of virginity--and these [are] the tokens of the virginity of my daughter! and they have spread out the garment before the elders of the city.

18 `And the elders of that city have taken the man, and chastise him,

19 and fined him a hundred silverlings, and given to the father of the damsel, because he hath brought out an evil name on a virgin of Israel, and she is to him for a wife, he is not able to send her away all his days.

20 `And if this thing hath been truth--tokens of virginity have not been found for the damsel--

21 then they have brought out the damsel unto the opening of her father's house, and stoned her have the men of her city with stones, and she hath died, for she hath done folly in Israel, to go a-whoring [in] her father's house; and thou hast put away the evil thing out of thy midst.

22 `When a man is found lying with a woman, married to a husband, then they have died even both of them, the man who is lying with the woman, also the woman; and thou hast put away the evil thing out of Israel.

23 `When there is a damsel, a virgin, betrothed to a man, and a man hath found her in a city, and lain with her;

24 then ye have brought them both out unto the gate of that city, and stoned them with stones, and they have died: --the damsel, because that she hath not cried, [being] in a city; and the man, because that he hath humbled his neighbour's wife; and thou hast put away the evil thing out of thy midst.

25 `And if in a field the man find the damsel who is betrothed, and the man hath laid hold on her, and lain with her, then hath the man who hath lain with her died alone;

26 and to the damsel thou dost not do anything, the damsel hath no deadly sin; for as a man riseth against his neighbour and hath murdered him--the life, so [is] this thing;

27 for in a field he found her, she hath cried--the damsel who is betrothed--and she hath no saviour.

28 `When a man findeth a damsel, a virgin who is not betrothed, and hath caught her, and lain with her, and they have been found,

29 then hath the man who is lying with her given to the father of the damsel fifty silverlings, and to him she is for a wife; because that he hath humbled her, he is not able to send her away all his days.

30 `A man doth not take his father's wife, nor uncover his father's skirt.

Deuteronomy 23

1 `One wounded, bruised, or cut in the member doth not enter into the assembly of Jehovah;

2 a bastard doth not enter into the assembly of Jehovah; even a tenth generation of him doth not enter into the assembly of Jehovah.

3 `An Ammonite and a Moabite doth not enter into the assembly of Jehovah; even a tenth generation of them doth not enter into the assembly of Jehovah--to the age;

4 because that they have not come before you with bread and with water in the way, in your coming out from Egypt, and because he hath hired against thee Balaam son of Beor, of Pethor of Aram-Naharaim, to revile thee;

5 and Jehovah thy God hath not been willing to hearken unto Balaam, and Jehovah thy God doth turn for thee the reviling to a blessing, because Jehovah thy God hath loved thee;

6 thou dost not seek their peace and their good all thy days--to the age.

7 `Thou dost not abominate an Edomite, for thy brother he [is]; thou dost not abominate an Egyptian, for a sojourner thou hast been in his land;

8 sons who are begotten of them, a third generation of them, doth enter into the assembly of Jehovah.

9 `When a camp goeth out against thine enemies, then thou hast kept from every evil thing.

10 `When there is in thee a man who is not clean, from an accident at night--then he hath gone out unto the outside of the camp--he doth not come in unto the midst of the camp--

11 and it hath been, at the turning of the evening, he doth bathe with water, and at the going in of the sun he doth come in unto the midst of the camp.

12 `And a station thou hast at the outside of the camp, and thou hast gone out thither without,

13 and a nail thou hast on thy staff, and it hath been, in thy sitting without, that thou hast digged with it, and turned back, and covered thy filth;

14 for Jehovah thy God is walking up and down in the midst of thy camp, to deliver thee, and to give thine enemies before thee, and thy camp hath been holy, and He doth not see in thee the nakedness of anything, and hath turned back from after thee.

15 `Thou dost not shut up a servant unto his lord, who is delivered unto thee from his lord;

16 with thee he doth dwell, in thy midst, in the place which he chooseth within one of thy gates, where it is pleasing to him; thou dost not oppress him.

17 `There is not a whore among the daughters of Israel, nor is there a whoremonger among the sons of Israel;

18 thou dost not bring a gift of a whore, or a price of a dog, into the house of Jehovah thy God, for any vow; for the abomination of Jehovah thy God [are] even both of them.

19 `Thou dost not lend in usury to thy brother; usury of money, usury of food, usury of anything which is lent on usury.

20 To a stranger thou mayest lend in usury, and to thy brother thou dost not lend in usury, so that Jehovah thy God doth bless thee in every putting forth of thy hand on the land whither thou goest in to possess it.

21 `When thou vowest a vow to Jehovah thy God, thou dost not delay to complete it; for Jehovah thy God doth certainly require it from thee, and it hath been in thee--sin.

22 `And when thou forbearest to vow, it is not in thee a sin.

23 The produce of thy lips thou dost keep, and hast done [it], as thou hast vowed to Jehovah thy God; a free-will-offering, which thou hast spoken with thy mouth.

24 `When thou comest in unto the vineyard of thy neighbour, then thou hast eaten grapes, according to thy desire, thy sufficiency; but into thy vessel thou dost not put [any].

25 When thou comest in among the standing-corn of thy neighbour, then thou hast plucked the ears with thy hand, but a sickle thou dost not wave over the standing-corn of thy neighbour.

Deuteronomy 24

1 `When a man doth take a wife, and hath married her, and it hath been, if she doth not find grace in his eyes (for he hath found in her nakedness of anything), and he hath written for her a writing of divorce, and given [it] into her hand, and sent her out of his house,

2 and she hath gone out of his house, and hath gone and been another man's,

3 and the latter man hath hated her, and written for her a writing of divorce, and given [it] into her hand, and sent her out of his house, or when the latter man dieth, who hath taken her to himself for a wife:

4 `Her former husband who sent her away is not able to turn back to take her to be to him for a wife, after that she hath become defiled; for an abomination it [is] before Jehovah, and thou dost not cause the land to sin which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee--an inheritance.

5 `When a man taketh a new wife, he doth not go out into the host, and [one] doth not pass over unto him for anything; free he is at his own house one year, and hath rejoiced his wife whom he hath taken.

6 `None doth take in pledge millstones, and rider, for life it [is] he is taking in pledge.

7 `When a man is found stealing a person, of his brethren, of the sons of Israel, and hath tyrannized over him, and sold him, then hath that thief died, and thou hast put away the evil thing out of thy midst.

8 `Take heed, in the plague of leprosy, to watch greatly, and to do according to all that the priests, the Levites, teach you; as I have commanded them ye observe to do;

9 remember that which Jehovah thy God hath done to Miriam in the way, in your coming out of Egypt.

10 `When thou liftest up on thy brother a debt of anything, thou dost not go in unto his house to obtain his pledge;

11 at the outside thou dost stand, and the man on whom thou art lifting [it] up is bringing out unto thee the pledge at the outside.

12 `And if he is a poor man, thou dost not lie down with his pledge;

13 thou dost certainly give back to him the pledge at the going in of the sun, and he hath lain down in his own raiment, and hath blessed thee; and to thee it is righteousness before Jehovah thy God.

14 `Thou dost not oppress a hireling, poor and needy, of thy brethren or of thy sojourner who is in thy land within thy gates;

15 in his day thou dost give his hire, and the sun doth not go in upon it, for he [is] poor, and unto it he is lifting up his soul, and he doth not cry against thee unto Jehovah, and it hath been in thee--sin.

16 `Fathers are not put to death for sons, and sons are not put to death for fathers--each for his own sin, they are put to death.

17 `Thou dost not turn aside the judgment of a fatherless sojourner, nor take in pledge the garment of a widow;

18 and thou hast remembered that a servant thou hast been in Egypt, and Jehovah thy God doth ransom thee from thence; therefore I am commanding thee to do this thing.

19 `When thou reapest thy harvest in thy field, and hast forgotten a sheaf in a field, thou dost not turn back to take it; to the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, it is; so that Jehovah thy God doth bless thee in all the work of thy hands.

20 `When thou beatest thine olive, thou dost not examine the branch behind thee; to the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, it is.

21 `When thou cuttest thy vineyard, thou dost not glean behind thee; to the sojourner, to the fatherless, and to the widow, it is;

22 and thou hast remembered that a servant thou hast been in the land of Egypt; therefore I am commanding thee to do this thing.

Deuteronomy 25

1 `When there is a strife between men, and they have come nigh unto the judgment, and they have judged, and declared righteous the righteous, and declared wrong the wrong-doer,

2 then it hath come to pass, if the wrong-doer is to be smitten, that the judge hath caused him to fall down, and [one] hath smitten him in his presence, according to the sufficiency of his wrong-doing, by number;

3 forty [times] he doth smite him--he is not adding, lest, he is adding to smite him above these--many stripes, and thy brother is lightly esteemed in thine eyes.

4 `Thou dost not muzzle an ox in its threshing.

5 `When brethren dwell together, and one of them hath died, and hath no son, the wife of the dead is not without to a strange man; her husband's brother doth go in unto her, and hath taken her to him for a wife, and doth perform the duty of her husband's brother;

6 and it hath been, the first-born which she beareth doth rise for the name of his dead brother, and his name is not wiped away out of Israel.

7 `And if the man doth not delight to take his brother's wife, then hath his brother's wife gone up to the gate, unto the elders, and said, My husband's brother is refusing to raise up to his brother a name in Israel; he hath not been willing to perform the duty of my husband's brother;

8 and the elders of his city have called for him, and spoken unto him, and he hath stood and said, I have no desire to take her;

9 `Then hath his brother's wife drawn nigh unto him, before the eyes of the elders, and drawn his shoe from off his foot, and spat in his face, and answered and said, Thus it is done to the man who doth not build up the house of his brother;

10 and his name hath been called in Israel--The house of him whose shoe is drawn off.

11 `When men strive together, one with another, and the wife of the one hath drawn near to deliver her husband out of the hand of his smiter, and hath put forth her hand, and laid hold on his secrets,

12 then thou hast cut off her hand, thine eye doth not spare.

13 `Thou hast not in thy bag a stone and a stone, a great and a small.

14 Thou hast not in thy house an ephah and an ephah, a great and a small.

15 Thou hast a stone complete and just, thou hast an ephah complete and just, so that they prolong thy days on the ground which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee;

16 for the abomination of Jehovah thy God [is] any one doing these things, any one doing iniquity.

17 `Remember that which Amalek hath done to thee in the way, in your going out from Egypt,

18 that he hath met thee in the way, and smiteth in all those feeble behind thee (and thou wearied and fatigued), and is not fearing God.

19 And it hath been, in Jehovah thy God's giving rest to thee, from all thine enemies round about, in the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee--an inheritance to possess it--thou dost blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens--thou dost not forget.

Deuteronomy 27

1 `And Moses--the elders of Israel also--commandeth the people, saying, Keep all the command which I am commanding you to-day;

2 and it hath been, in the day that ye pass over the Jordan unto the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee, that thou hast raised up for thee great stones, and plaistered them with plaister,

3 and written on them all the words of this law in thy passing over, so that thou goest in unto the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee--a land flowing with milk and honey, as Jehovah, God of thy fathers, hath spoken to thee.

4 `And it hath been, in your passing over the Jordan, ye raise up these stones which I am commanding you to-day, in mount Ebal, and thou hast plaistered them with plaister,

5 and built there an altar to Jehovah thy God, an altar of stones, thou dost not wave over them iron.

6 Of complete stones thou buildest the altar of Jehovah thy God, and hast caused to ascend on it burnt-offerings to Jehovah thy God,

7 and sacrificed peace-offerings, and eaten there, and rejoiced before Jehovah thy God,

8 and written on the stones all the words of this law, well engraved.'

9 And Moses speaketh--the priests, the Levites, also--unto all Israel, saying, `Keep silent, and hear, O Israel, this day thou hast become a people to Jehovah thy God;

10 and thou hast hearkened to the voice of Jehovah thy God, and done His commands, and His statutes, which I am commanding thee to-day.'

11 And Moses commandeth the people on that day, saying,

12 `These do stand, to bless the people, on mount Gerizzim, in your passing over the Jordan: Simeon, and Levi, and Judah, and Issachar, and Joseph, and Benjamin.

13 And these do stand, for the reviling, on mount Ebal: Reuben, Gad, and Asher, and Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali.

14 `And the Levites have answered and said unto every man of Israel--a loud voice:

15 `Cursed [is] the man who maketh a graven and molten image, the abomination of Jehovah, work of the hands of an artificer, and hath put [it] in a secret place, --and all the people have answered and said, Amen.

16 `Cursed [is] He who is making light of his father and his mother, --and all the people have said, Amen.

17 `Cursed [is] he who is removing his neighbour's border, --and all the people have said, Amen.

18 `Cursed [is] he who is causing the blind to err in the way, --and all the people have said, Amen.

19 `Cursed [is] he who is turning aside the judgment of fatherless, sojourner, and widow, --and all the people have said, Amen.

20 `Cursed [is] he who is lying with his father's wife, for he hath uncovered his father's skirt, --and all the people have said, Amen.

21 `Cursed [is] he who is lying with any beast, --and all the people have said, Amen.

22 `Cursed [is] he who is lying with his sister, daughter of his father, or daughter of his mother, --and all the people have said, Amen.

23 `Cursed [is] he who is lying with his mother-in-law, --and all the people have said, Amen.

24 `Cursed [is] he who is smiting his neighbour in secret, --and all the people have said, Amen.

25 `Cursed [is] he who is taking a bribe to smite a person, innocent blood, --and all the people have said, Amen.

26 `Cursed [is] he who doth not establish the words of this law, to do them, --and all the people have said, Amen.

Deuteronomy 28

1 `And it hath been, if thou dost hearken diligently to the voice of Jehovah thy God, to observe to do all His commands which I am commanding thee to-day, that Jehovah thy God hath made thee uppermost above all the nations of the earth,

2 and all these blessings have come upon thee, and overtaken thee, because thou dost hearken to the voice of Jehovah thy God:

3 `Blessed [art] thou in the city, and blessed [art] thou in the field.

4 `Blessed [is] the fruit of thy womb, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit of thy cattle, increase of thine oxen, and wealth of thy flock.

5 `Blessed [is] thy basket and thy kneading-trough.

6 `Blessed [art] thou in thy coming in, and blessed [art] thou in thy going out.

7 `Jehovah giveth thine enemies, who are rising up against thee--smitten before thy face; in one way they come out unto thee, and in seven ways they flee before thee.

8 `Jehovah commandeth with thee the blessing in thy storehouses, and in every putting forth of thy hand, and hath blessed thee in the land which Jehovah thy God is giving to thee.

9 `Jehovah doth establish thee to Himself for a holy people, as He hath sworn to thee, when thou keepest the commands of Jehovah thy God, and hast walked in His ways;

10 and all the peoples of the land have seen that the name of Jehovah is called upon thee, and they have been afraid of thee.

11 `And Jehovah hath made thee abundant in good, in the fruit of the womb, and in the fruit of thy cattle, and in the fruit of thy ground, on the ground which Jehovah hath sworn to thy fathers to give to thee.

12 `Jehovah doth open to thee his good treasure--the heavens--to give the rain of thy land in its season, and to bless all the work of thy hand, and thou hast lent to many nations, and thou--thou dost not borrow.

13 `And Jehovah hath given thee for head, and not for tail; and thou hast been only above, and art not beneath, for thou dost hearken unto the commands of Jehovah thy God, which I am commanding thee to-day, to keep and to do,

14 and thou dost not turn aside from all the words which I am commanding you to-day--right or left--to go after other gods, to serve them.

15 `And it hath been, if thou dost not hearken unto the voice of Jehovah thy God to observe to do all His commands, and His statutes, which I am commanding thee to-day, that all these revilings have come upon thee, and overtaken thee:

16 `Cursed [art] thou in the city, and cursed [art] thou in the field.

17 `Cursed [is] thy basket and thy kneading-trough.

18 `Cursed [is] the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy land, increase of thine oxen, and wealth of thy flock.

19 `Cursed [art] thou in thy coming in, and cursed [art] thou in thy going out.

20 `Jehovah doth send on thee the curse, the trouble, and the rebuke, in every putting forth of thy hand which thou dost, till thou art destroyed, and till thou perish hastily, because of the evil of thy doings [by] which thou hast forsaken Me.

21 `Jehovah doth cause to cleave to thee the pestilence, till He consume thee from off the ground whither thou art going in to possess it.

22 `Jehovah doth smite thee with consumption, and with fever, and with inflammation, and with extreme burning, and with sword, and with blasting, and with mildew, and they have pursued thee till thou perish

23 `And thy heavens which [are] over thy head have been brass, and the earth which [is] under thee iron;

24 Jehovah giveth the rain of thy land--dust and ashes; from the heavens it cometh down on thee till thou art destroyed.

25 `Jehovah giveth thee smitten before thine enemies; in one way thou goest out unto them, and in seven ways dost flee before them, and thou hast been for a trembling to all kingdoms of the earth;

26 and thy carcase hath been for food to every fowl of the heavens, and to the beast of the earth, and there is none causing trembling.

27 `Jehovah doth smite thee with the ulcer of Egypt, and with emerods, and with scurvy, and with itch, of which thou art not able to be healed.

28 `Jehovah doth smite thee with madness, and with blindness, and with astonishment of heart;

29 and thou hast been gropling at noon, as the blind gropeth in darkness; and thou dost not cause thy ways to prosper; and thou hast been only oppressed and plundered all the days, and there is no saviour.

30 `A woman thou dost betroth, and another man doth lie with her; a house thou dost build, and dost not dwell in it; a vineyard thou dost plant, and dost not make it common;

31 thine ox [is] slaughtered before thine eyes, and thou dost not eat of it; thine ass [is] taken violently away from before thee, and it is not given back to thee; thy sheep [are] given to thine enemies, and there is no saviour for thee.

32 `Thy sons and thy daughters [are] given to another people, and thine eyes are looking and consuming for them all the day, and thy hand is not to God!

33 The fruit of thy ground, and all thy labour, eat up doth a people whom thou hast not known; and thou hast been only oppressed and bruised all the days;

34 and thou hast been mad, because of the sight of thine eyes which thou dost see.

35 `Jehovah doth smite thee with an evil ulcer, on the knees, and on the legs (of which thou art not able to be healed), from the sole of thy foot even unto thy crown.

36 `Jehovah doth cause thee to go, and thy king whom thou raisest up over thee, unto a nation which thou hast not known, thou and thy fathers, and thou hast served there other gods, wood and stone;

37 and thou hast been for an astonishment, for a simile, and for a byword among all the peoples whither Jehovah doth lead thee.

38 `Much seed thou dost take out into the field, and little thou dost gather in, for the locust doth consume it;

39 vineyards thou dost plant, and hast laboured, and wine thou dost not drink nor gather, for the worm doth consume it;

40 olives are to thee in all thy border, and oil thou dost not pour out, for thine olive doth fall off.

41 `Sons and daughters thou dost beget, and they are not with thee, for they go into captivity;

42 all thy trees and the fruit of thy ground doth the locust possess;

43 the sojourner who [is] in thy midst goeth up above thee very high, and thou goest down very low;

44 he doth lend [to] thee, and thou dost not lend [to] him; he is for head, and thou art for tail.

45 `And come upon thee have all these curses, and they have pursued thee, and overtaken thee, till thou art destroyed, because thou hast not hearkened to the voice of Jehovah thy God, to keep His commands, and His statutes, which he hath commanded thee;

46 and they have been on thee for a sign and for a wonder, also on thy seed--to the age.

47 `Because that thou hast not served Jehovah thy God with joy, and with gladness of heart, because of the abundance of all things--

48 thou hast served thine enemies, whom Jehovah sendeth against thee, in hunger, and in thirst, and in nakedness, and in lack of all things; and he hath put a yoke of iron on thy neck, till He hath destroyed thee.

49 `Jehovah doth lift up against thee a nation, from afar, from the end of the earth, as the eagle it flieth; a nation whose tongue thou hast not heard,

50 a nation--fierce of countenance--which accepteth not the face of the aged, and the young doth not favour;

51 and it hath eaten the fruit of thy cattle, and the fruit of thy ground, till thou art destroyed; which leaveth not to thee corn, new wine, and oil, increase of thine oxen, and wealth of thy flock, till it hath destroyed thee.

52 `And it hath laid siege to thee in all thy gates, till thy walls come down, the high and the fenced ones in which thou art trusting, in all thy land; yea, it hath laid siege to thee in all thy gates, in all thy land, which Jehovah thy God hath given to thee;

53 and thou hast eaten the fruit of thy body, flesh of thy sons and thy daughters (whom Jehovah thy God hath given to thee), in the siege, and in the straitness with which thine enemies do straiten thee.

54 `The man who is tender in thee, and who [is] very delicate--his eye is evil against his brother, and against the wife of his bosom, and against the remnant of his sons whom he leaveth,

55 against giving to one of them of the flesh of his sons whom he eateth, because he hath nothing left to him, in the siege, and in the straitness with which thine enemy doth straiten thee in all thy gates.

56 `The tender woman in thee, and the delicate, who hath not tried the sole of her foot to place on the ground because of delicateness and because of tenderness--her eye is evil against the husband of her bosom, and against her son, and against her daughter,

57 and against her seed which cometh out from between her feet, even against her sons whom she doth bear, for she doth eat them for the lacking of all things in secret, in the siege and in the straitness with which thine enemy doth straiten thee within thy gates.

58 `If thou dost not observe to do all the words of this law which are written in this book, to fear this honoured and fearful name--Jehovah thy God--

59 then hath Jehovah made wonderful thy strokes, and the strokes of thy seed-- great strokes, and stedfast, and evil sicknesses, and stedfast.

60 `And He hath brought back on thee all the diseases of Egypt, of the presence of which thou hast been afraid, and they have cleaved to thee;

61 also every sickness and every stroke which is not written in the book of this law; Jehovah doth cause them to go up upon thee till thou art destroyed,

62 and ye have been left with few men, instead of which ye have been as stars of the heavens for multitude, because thou hast not hearkened to the voice of Jehovah thy God.

63 `And it hath been, as Jehovah hath rejoiced over you to do you good, and to multiply you, so doth Jehovah rejoice over you to destroy you, and to lay you waste; and ye have been pulled away from off the ground whither thou art going in to possess it;

64 and Jehovah hath scattered thee among all the peoples, from the end of the earth even unto the end of the earth; and thou hast served there other gods which thou hast not known, thou and thy fathers--wood and stone.

65 `And among those nations thou dost not rest, yea, there is no resting-place for the sole of thy foot, and Jehovah hath given to thee there a trembling heart, and failing of eyes, and grief of soul;

66 and thy life hath been hanging in suspense before thee, and thou hast been afraid by night and by day, and dost not believe in thy life;

67 in the morning thou sayest, O that it were evening! and in the evening thou sayest, O that it were morning! from the fear of thy heart, with which thou art afraid, and from the sight of thine eyes which thou seest.

68 `And Jehovah hath brought thee back to Egypt with ships, by a way of which I said to thee, Thou dost not add any more to see it, and ye have sold yourselves there to thine enemies, for men-servants and for maid-servants, and there is nobuyer.'

Deuteronomy 32

1 `Give ear, O heavens, and I speak; And thou dost hear, O earth, sayings of my mouth!

2 Drop as rain doth My doctrine; Flow as dew doth My sayings; As storms on the tender grass, And as showers on the herb,

3 For the Name of Jehovah I proclaim, Ascribe ye greatness to our God!

4 The Rock! --perfect [is] His work, For all His ways [are] just; God of stedfastness, and without iniquity: Righteous and upright [is] He.

5 It hath done corruptly to Him; Their blemish is not His sons', A generation perverse and crooked!

6 To Jehovah do ye act thus, O people foolish and not wise? Is not He thy father- -thy possessor? He made thee, and doth establish thee.

7 Remember days of old--Understand the years of many generations--Ask thy father, and he doth tell thee; Thine elders, and they say to thee:

8 In the Most High causing nations to inherit, In His separating sons of Adam-- He setteth up the borders of the peoples By the number of the sons of Israel.

9 For Jehovah's portion [is] His people, Jacob [is] the line of His inheritance.

10 He findeth him in a land--a desert, And in a void--a howling wilderness, He turneth him round--He causeth him to understand--He keepeth him as the apple of His eye.

11 As an eagle waketh up its nest, Over its young ones fluttereth, Spreadeth its wings--taketh them, Beareth them on its pinions; --

12 Jehovah alone doth lead him, And there is no strange god with him.

13 He maketh him ride on high places of earth, And he eateth increase of the fields, And He maketh him suck honey from a rock, And oil out of the flint of a rock;

14 Butter of the herd, and milk of the flock, With fat of lambs, and rams, sons of Bashan, And he-goats, with fat of kidneys of wheat; And of the blood of the grape thou dost drink wine!

15 And Jeshurun waxeth fat, and doth kick: Thou hast been fat--thou hast been thick, Thou hast been covered. And he leaveth God who made him, And dishonoureth the Rock of his salvation.

16 They make Him zealous with strangers, With abominations they make Him angry.

17 They sacrifice to demons--no god! Gods they have not known--New ones-- from the vicinity they came; Not feared them have your fathers!

18 The Rock that begat thee thou forgettest, And neglectest God who formeth thee.

19 And Jehovah seeth and despiseth--For the provocation of His sons and His daughters.

20 And He saith: I hide My face from them, I see what [is] their latter end; For a froward generation [are] they, Sons in whom is no stedfastness.

21 They have made Me zealous by `no-god,' They made Me angry by their vanities; And I make them zealous by `no-people,' By a foolish nation I make them angry.

22 For a fire hath been kindled in Mine anger, And it burneth unto Sheol--the lowest, And consumeth earth and its increase, And setteth on fire foundations of mountains.

23 I gather upon them evils, Mine arrows I consume upon them.

24 Exhausted by famine, And consumed by heat, and bitter destruction. And the teeth of beasts I send upon them, With poison of fearful things of the dust.

25 Without bereave doth the sword, And at the inner-chambers--fear, Both youth and virgin, Suckling with man of grey hair.

26 I have said: I blow them away, I cause their remembrance to cease from man;

27 If not--the anger of an enemy I fear, Lest their adversaries know--Lest they say, Our hand is high, And Jehovah hath not wrought all this.

28 For a nation lost to counsels [are] they, And there is no understanding in them.

29 If they were wise--They deal wisely [with] this; They attend to their latter end:

30 How doth one pursue a thousand, And two cause a myriad to flee! If not--that their rock hath sold them, And Jehovah hath shut them up?

31 For not as our Rock [is] their rock, (And our enemies [are] judges!)

32 For of the vine of Sodom their vine [is], And of the fields of Gomorrah; Their grapes [are] grapes of gall--They have bitter clusters;

33 The poison of dragons [is] their wine And the fierce venom of asps.

34 Is it not laid up with Me? Sealed among My treasures?

35 Mine [are] vengeance and recompense, At the due time--doth their foot slide; For near is a day of their calamity, And haste do things prepared for them.

36 For Jehovah doth judge His people, And for His servants doth repent Himself. For He seeth--the going away of power, And none is restrained and left.

37 And He hath said, Where [are] their gods--The rock in which they trusted;

38 Which the fat of their sacrifices do eat, They drink the wine of their libation! Let them arise and help you, Let it be for you a hiding-place!

39 See ye, now, that I--I [am] He, And there is no god with Me: I put to death, and I keep alive; I have smitten, and I heal; And there is not from My hand a deliverer,

40 For I lift up unto the heavens My hand, And have said, I live--to the age!

41 If I have sharpened the brightness of My sword, And My hand doth lay hold on judgment, I turn back vengeance to Mine adversaries, And to those hating Me--I repay!

42 I make drunk Mine arrows with blood, And My sword devoureth flesh, From the blood of the pierced and captive, From the head of the freemen of the enemy.

43 Sing ye nations--[with] his people, For the blood of His servants He avengeth, And vengeance He turneth back on His adversaries, And hath pardoned His land--His people.'

44 And Moses cometh and speaketh all the words of this song in the ears of the people, he and Hoshea son of Nun;

45 and Moses finisheth to speak all these words unto all Israel,

46 and saith unto them, `Set your heart to all the words which I am testifying against you to-day, that ye command your sons to observe to do all the words of this law,

47 for it [is] not a vain thing for you, for it [is] your life, and by this thing ye prolong days on the ground whither ye are passing over the Jordan to possess it.'

48 And Jehovah speaketh unto Moses, in this self-same day, saying,

49 `Go up unto this mount Abarim, mount Nebo, which [is] in the land of Moab, which [is] on the front of Jericho, and see the land of Canaan which I am giving to the sons of Israel for a possession;

50 and die in the mount whither thou art going up, and be gathered unto thy people, as Aaron thy brother hath died in the mount Hor, and is gathered unto his people:

51 `Because ye trespassed against me in the midst of the sons of Israel at the waters of Meribath-Kadesh, the wilderness of Zin--because ye sanctified Me not in the midst of the sons of Israel;

52 but over-against thou seest the land, and thither thou dost not go in, unto the land which I am giving to the sons of Israel.'

Deuteronomy 33

1 And this [is] the blessing [with] which Moses the man of God blessed the sons of Israel before his death,

2 and he saith: --`Jehovah from Sinai hath come, And hath risen from Seir for them; He hath shone from mount Paran, And hath come [with] myriads of holy ones; At His right hand [are] springs for them.

3 Also He [is] loving the peoples; All His holy ones [are] in thy hand, And they-- they sat down at thy foot, [Each] He lifteth up at thy words.

4 A law hath Moses commanded us, A possession of the assembly of Jacob.

5 And he is in Jeshurun king, In the heads of the people gathering together, The tribes of Israel!

6 Let Reuben live, and not die, And let his men be a number.

7 And this [is] for Judah; and he saith: --Hear, O Jehovah, the voice of Judah, And unto his people do Thou bring him in; His hand hath striven for him, And an help from his adversaries art Thou.

8 And of Levi he said: --Thy Thummim and thy Urim [are] for thy pious one, Whom Thou hast tried in Massah, Thou dost strive with Him at the waters of Meribah;

9 Who is saying of his father and his mother, I have not seen him; And his brethren he hath not discerned, And his sons he hath not known; For they have observed Thy saying, And Thy covenant they keep.

10 They teach Thy judgments to Jacob, And Thy law to Israel; They put perfume in Thy nose, And whole burnt-offering on Thine altar.

11 Bless, O Jehovah, his strength, And the work of his hands Thou acceptest, Smite the loins of his withstanders, And of those hating him--that they rise not!

12 Of Benjamin he said: --The beloved of Jehovah doth tabernacle confidently by him, Covering him over all the day; Yea, between his shoulders He doth tabernacle.

13 And of Joseph he said: --Blessed of Jehovah [is] his land, By precious things of the heavens, By dew, and by the deep crouching beneath,

14 And by precious things--fruits of the sun, And by precious things--cast forth by the moons,

15 And by chief things--of the ancient mountains, And by precious things--of the age-during heights,

16 And by precious things--of earth and its fulness, And the good pleasure Of Him who is dwelling in the bush, --Let it come for the head of Joseph, And for the crown of him Who is separate from his brethren.

17 His honour [is] a firstling of his ox, And his horns [are] horns of a reem; By them peoples he doth push together To the ends of earth; And they [are] the myriads of Ephraim, And they [are] the thousands of Manasseh.

18 And of Zebulun he said: --Rejoice, O Zebulun, in thy going out, And, O Issachar, in thy tents;

19 Peoples [to] the mountain they call, There they sacrifice righteous sacrifices; For the abundance of the seas they suck, And hidden things hidden in the sand.

20 And of Gad he said: --Blessed of the Enlarger [is] Gad, As a lioness he doth tabernacle, And hath torn the arm--also the crown!

21 And he provideth the first part for himself, For there the portion of the lawgiver is covered, And he cometh [with] the heads of the people; The righteousness of Jehovah he hath done, And His judgments with Israel.

22 And of Dan he said: --Dan [is] a lion's whelp; he doth leap from Bashan.

23 And of Naphtali he said: --O Naphtali, satisfied with pleasure, And full of the blessing of Jehovah, West and south possess thou.

24 And of Asher he said: --Blessed with sons [is] Asher, Let him be accepted by his brethren, And dipping in oil his foot.

25 Iron and brass [are] thy shoes, And as thy days--thy strength.

26 There is none like the God of Jeshurun, Riding the heavens in thy help, And in His excellency the skies.

27 A habitation [is] the eternal God, And beneath [are] arms age-during. And He casteth out from thy presence the enemy, and saith, `Destroy!'

28 And Israel doth tabernacle [in] confidence alone; The eye of Jacob [is] unto a land of corn and wine; Also His heavens drop down dew.

29 O thy happiness, O Israel! who is like thee? A people saved by Jehovah, The shield of thy help, And He who [is] the sword of thine excellency: And thine enemies are subdued for thee, And thou on their high places dost tread.'

Joshua 7

1 And the sons of Israel commit a trespass in the devoted thing, and Achan, son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah, taketh of the devoted thing, and the anger of Jehovah burneth against the sons of Israel.

2 And Joshua sendeth men from Jericho to Ai, which [is] near Beth-Aven, on the east of Bethel, and speaketh unto them, saying, `Go up and spy the land;' and the men go up and spy Ai,

3 and they turn back unto Joshua, and say unto him, `Let not all the people go up; let about two thousand men, or about three thousand men, go up, and they smite Ai; cause not all the people to labour thither; for they [are] few.'

4 And there go up of the people thither about three thousand men, and they flee before the men of Ai,

5 and the men of Ai smite of them about thirty and six men, and pursue them before the gate unto Shebarim, and they smite them in Morad; and the heart of the people is melted, and becometh water.

6 And Joshua rendeth his garments, and falleth on his face to the earth before the ark of Jehovah till the evening, he and the elders of Israel, and they cause dust to go up on their head.

7 And Joshua saith, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, why hast Thou at all caused this people to pass over the Jordan, to give us into the hand of the Amorite to destroy us? --and oh that we had been willing--and we dwell beyond the Jordan!

8 Oh, Lord, what do I say, after that Israel hath turned the neck before its enemies?

9 and the Canaanite and all the inhabitants of the land do hear, and have come round against us, and cut off our name out of the earth; and what dost Thou do for Thy great name?'

10 And Jehovah saith unto Joshua, `Rise for thee, why [is] this? --thou [art] falling on thy face?

11 Israel hath sinned, and also they have transgressed My covenant which I commanded them, and also taken of the devoted thing, and also stolen, and also deceived, and also put [it] among their vessels,

12 and the sons of Israel have not been able to stand before their enemies; the neck they turn before their enemies, for they have become a devoted thing; I add not to be with you--if ye destroy not the devoted thing out of your midst.

13 `Rise, sanctify the people, and thou hast said, Sanctify yourselves for to-morrow; for thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, A devoted thing [is] in thy midst, O Israel, thou art not able to stand before thine enemies till your turning aside of the devoted thing out of your midst;

14 and ye have been brought near in the morning by your tribes, and it hath been, the tribe which Jehovah doth capture doth draw near by families, and the family which Jehovah doth capture doth draw near by households, and the household which Jehovah doth capture doth draw near by men;

15 and it hath been, he who is captured with the devoted thing is burnt with fire, he and all that he hath, because he hath transgressed the covenant of Jehovah, and because he hath done folly in Israel.'

16 And Joshua riseth early in the morning, and bringeth Israel near by its tribes, and the tribe of Judah is captured;

17 and he bringeth near the family of Judah, and he captureth the family of the Zarhite; and he bringeth near the family of the Zarhite by men, and Zabdi is captured;

18 and he bringeth near his household by men, and Achan--son of Carmi, son of Zabdi, son of Zerah, of the tribe of Judah--is captured.

19 And Joshua saith unto Achan, `My son, put, I pray thee, honour on Jehovah, God of Israel, and give to Him thanks, and declare, I pray thee, to me, what thou hast done--hide not from me.'

20 And Achan answereth Joshua, and saith, `Truly I have sinned against Jehovah, God of Israel, and thus and thus I have done;

21 and I see among the spoil a goodly robe of Shinar, and two hundred shekels of silver, and one wedge of gold, whose weight [is] fifty shekels, and I desire them, and take them; and lo, they [are] hid in the earth, in the midst of my tent, and the silver under it.'

22 And Joshua sendeth messengers, and they run unto the tent, and lo, it is hidden in his tent, and the silver under it;

23 and they take them out of the midst of the tent, and bring them in unto Joshua, and unto all the sons of Israel, and pour them out before Jehovah.

24 And Joshua taketh Achan son of Zerah, and the silver, and the robe, and the wedge of gold, and his sons, and his daughters, and his ox, and his ass, and his flock, and his tent, and all that he hath, and all Israel with him, and they cause them to go up the valley of Achor.

25 And Joshua saith, `What! thou hast troubled us! --Jehovah doth trouble thee this day;' and all Israel cast stones at him, and they burn them with fire, and they stone them with stones,

26 and they raise up over him a great heap of stones unto this day, and Jehovah turneth back from the heat of His anger, therefore hath [one] called the name of that place `Valley of Achor' till this day.

Joshua 15

1 And the lot for the tribe of the sons of Judah, for their families, is unto the border of Edom; the wilderness of Zin southward, at the extremity of the south;

2 and to them the south border is at the extremity of the salt sea, from the bay which is looking southward;

3 and it hath gone out unto the south to Maaleh-Akrabbim, and passed over to Zin, and gone up on the south to Kadesh-Barnea, and passed over [to] Hezron, and gone up to Adar, and turned round to Karkaa,

4 and passed over [to] Azmon, and gone out [at] the brook of Egypt, and the outgoings of the border have been at the sea; this is to you the south border.

5 And the east border [is] the salt sea, unto the extremity of the Jordan, and the border at the north quarter [is] from the bay of the sea, at the extremity of the Jordan;

6 and the border hath gone up [to] Beth-Hoglah, and passed over on the north of Beth- Arabah, and the border hath gone up [to] the stone of Bohan son of Reuben:

7 and the border hath gone up towards Debir from the valley of Achor, and northward looking unto Gilgal, which [is] over-against the ascent of Adummim, which [is] on the south of the brook, and the border hath passed over unto the waters of En-Shemesh, and its outgoings have been unto En-Rogel;

8 and the border hath gone up the valley of the son of Hinnom, unto the side of the Jebusite on the south (it [is] Jerusalem), and the border hath gone up unto the top of the hill-country which [is] on the front of the valley of Hinnom westward, which [is] in the extremity of the valley of the Rephaim northward;

9 and the border hath been marked out, from the top of the hill-country unto the fountain of the waters of Nephtoah, and hath gone out unto the cities of mount Ephron, and the border hath been marked out [to] Baalah, (it [is] Kirjath-Jearim);

10 and the border hath gone round from Baalah westward, unto mount Seir, and passed over unto the side of mount Jearim (it [is] Chesalon), on the north, and gone down [to] Beth- Shemesh, and passed over to Timnah;

11 and the border hath gone out unto the side of Ekron northward, and the border hath been marked out [to] Shicron, and hath passed over to mount Baalah, and gone out [to] Jabneel; and the outgoings of the border have been at the sea.

12 And the west border [is] to the great sea, and [its] border; this [is] the border of the sons of Judah round about for their families.

13 And to Caleb son of Jephunneh hath he given a portion in the midst of the sons of Judah, according to the command of Jehovah to Joshua, [even] the city of Arba, father of Anak--it [is] Hebron.

14 And Caleb is dispossessing thence the three sons of Anak, Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai, children of Anak,

15 and he goeth up thence unto the inhabitants of Debir; and the name of Debir formerly is Kirjath-Sepher.

16 And Caleb saith, `He who smiteth Kirjath-Sephar, and hath captured it--I have given to him Achsah my daughter for a wife.'

17 And Othniel son of Kenaz, brother of Caleb, doth capture it, and he giveth to him Achsah his daughter for a wife.

18 And it cometh to pass, in her coming in, that she persuadeth him to ask from her father a field, and she lighteth from off the ass, and Caleb saith to her, `What--to thee?'

19 And she saith, `Give to me a blessing; when the land of the south thou hast given me, then thou hast given to me springs of waters;' and he giveth to her the upper springs and the lower springs.

20 This [is] the inheritance of the tribe of the sons of Judah, for their families.

21 And the cities at the extremity of the tribe of the sons of Judah are unto the border of Edom in the south, Kabzeel, and Eder, and Jagur,

22 and Kinah, and Dimonah, and Adadah,

23 and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Ithnan,

24 Ziph, and Telem, and Bealoth,

25 and Hazor, Hadattah, and Kerioth, Hezron, (it [is] Hazor,)

26 Amam, and Shema, and Moladah,

27 and Hazar-Gaddah, and Heshmon, and Beth-Palet,

28 and Hazar-Shual, and Beer-Sheba, and Bizjothjah,

29 Baalah, and Iim, and Azem,

30 And Eltolad, and Chesil, and Hormah,

31 and Ziklag, and Madmannah, and Sansannah,

32 and Lebaoth, and Shilhim, and Ain, and Rimmon; all the cities [are] twenty and nine, and their villages.

33 In the low country: Eshtaol, and Zoreah, and Ashnah,

34 and Zanoah, and En-Gannim, Tappuah, and Enam,

35 Jarmuth, and Adullam, Socoh, and Azekah,

36 and Sharaim, and Adithaim, and Gederah, and Gederothaim; fourteen cities and their villages.

37 Zenan, and Hadashah, and Migdal-Gad,

38 and Dilean, and Mizpeh, and Joktheel,

39 Lachish, and Bozkath, and Eglon,

40 and Cabbon, and Lahmam, and Kithlish,

41 and Gederoth, Beth-Dagon, and Naamah, and Makkedah; sixteen cities and their villages.

42 Libnah, and Ether, and Ashan,

43 and Jiphtah, and Ashnah, and Nezib,

44 and Keilah, and Achzib, and Mareshah; nine cities and their villages.

45 Ekron and its towns and its villages,

46 from Ekron and westward, all that [are] by the side of Ashdod, and their villages.

47 Ashdod, its towns and its villages, Gaza, its towns and its villages, unto the brook of Egypt, and the great sea, and [its] border.

48 And in the hill-country: Shamir, and Jattir, and Socoh,

49 and Dannah, and Kirjath-Sannah (it [is] Debir)

50 and Anab, and Eshtemoh, and Anim,

51 and Goshen, and Holon, and Giloh; eleven cities and their villages.

52 Arab, and Dumah, and Eshean,

53 and Janum, and Beth-Tappuah, and Aphekah,

54 and Humtah, and Kirjath-Arba (it [is] Hebron), and Zior; nine cities and their villages.

55 Maon, Carmel, and Ziph, and Juttah,

56 and Jezreel, and Jokdeam, and Zanoah,

57 Cain, Gibeah, and Timnah; ten cities and their villages.

58 Halhul, Beth-Zur, and Gedor,

59 and Maarath, and Beth-Anoth, and Eltekon; six cities and their villages.

60 Kirjath-Baal (it [is] Kirjath-Jearim), and Rabbah; two cities and their villages.

61 In the wilderness: Beth-Arabah, Middin, and Secacah,

62 and Nibshan, and the city of Salt, and En-Gedi; six cities and their villages.

63 As to the Jebusites, inhabitants of Jerusalem, the sons of Judah have not been able to dispossess them, and the Jebusite dwelleth with the sons of Judah in Jerusalem unto this day.

Joshua 21

1 And the heads of the fathers of the Levites draw nigh unto Eleazar the priest, and unto Joshua son of Nun, and unto the heads of the fathers of the tribes of the sons of Israel,

2 and they speak unto them in Shiloh, in the land of Canaan, saying, `Jehovah commanded by the hand of Moses to give to us cities to dwell in, and their suburbs for our cattle.'

3 And the sons of Israel give to the Levites, out of their inheritance, at the command of Jehovah, these cities and their suburbs:

4 And the lot goeth out for the families of the Kohathite, and there are for the sons of Aaron the priest (of the Levites), out of the tribe of Judah, and out of the tribe of Simeon, and out of the tribe of Benjamin, by lot thirteen cities,

5 and for the sons of Kohath who are left, out of the families of the tribe of Ephraim, and out of the tribe of Dan, and out of the half of the tribe of Manasseh, by lot ten cities:

6 And for the sons of Gershon [are], out of the families of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the half tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, by lot, thirteen cities.

7 For the sons of Merari, for their families, [are], out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities.

8 And the sons of Israel give to the Levites these cities and their suburbs, as Jehovah commanded by the hand of Moses, by lot.

9 And they give out of the tribe of the sons of Judah, and out of the tribe of the sons of Simeon, these cities which are called by name;

10 and they are for the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathite, of the sons of Levi, for theirs hath been the first lot;

11 and they give to them the city of Arba father of Anak (it [is] Hebron), in the hillcountry of Judah, and its suburbs round about it;

12 and the field of the city and its villages they have given to Caleb son of Jephunneh for his possession.

13 And to the sons of Aaron the priest they have given the city of refuge [for] the manslayer, Hebron and its suburbs, and Libnah and its suburbs,

14 and Jattir and its suburbs, and Eshtemoa and its suburbs,

15 and Holon and its suburbs, and Debir and its suburbs,

16 and Ain and its suburbs, and Juttah and its suburbs, Beth-Shemesh and its suburbs; nine cities out of these two tribes.

17 And out of the tribe of Benjamin, Gibeon and its suburbs, Geba and its suburbs,

18 Anathoth and its suburbs, and Almon and its suburbs--four cities;

19 all the cities of the sons of Aaron the priests, [are] thirteen cities and their suburbs.

20 And for the families of the sons of Kohath, the Levites, who are left of the sons of Kohath, even the cities of their lot are of the tribe of Ephraim;

21 and they give to them the city of refuge [for] the man-slayer, Shechem and its suburbs, in the hill-country of Ephraim, and Gezer and its suburbs,

22 and Kibzaim and its suburbs, and Beth-Horon and its suburbs--four cities.

23 And out of the tribe of Dan, Eltekeh and its suburbs, Gibbethon and its suburbs,

24 Aijalon and its suburbs, Gath-Rimmon and its suburbs--four cities.

25 And out of the half of the tribe of Manasseh, Taanach and its suburbs, and Gath- Rimmon and its suburbs--two cities;

26 all the cities [are] ten and their suburbs, for the families of the sons of Kohath who are left.

27 And for the sons of Gershon, of the families of the Levites, out of the half of the tribe of Manasseh, the city of refuge [for] the man-slayer, Golan in Bashan and its suburbs, and Beeshterah and its suburbs--two cities.

28 And out of the tribe of Issachar, Kishon and its suburbs, Dabarath and its suburbs,

29 Jarmuth and its suburbs, En-Gannim and its suburbs--four cities.

30 And out of the tribe of Asher, Mishal and its suburbs, Abdon and its suburbs,

31 Helkath and its suburbs, and Rehob and its suburbs--four cities.

32 And out of the tribe of Naphtali, the city of refuge [for] the man-slayer, Kedesh in Galilee and its suburbs, and Hammoth-Dor and its suburbs, and Kartan and its suburbs--three cities;

33 all the cities of the Gershonite, for their families, [are] thirteen cities and their suburbs.

34 And for the families of the sons of Merari, the Levites, who are left, [are,] out of the tribe of Zebulun, Jokneam and its suburbs, Kartah and its suburbs,

35 Dimnah and its suburbs, Nahalal and its suburbs--four cities.

36 And out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer and its suburbs, and Jahazah and its suburbs,

37 Kedemoth and its suburbs, and Mephaath and its suburbs--four cities.

38 And out of the tribe of Gad, the city of refuge [for] the man-slayer, Ramoth in Gilead and its suburbs, and Mahanaim and its suburbs,

39 Heshbon and its suburbs, Jazer and its suburbs--[in] all four cities.

40 All the cities for the sons of Merari, for their families, who are left of the families of the Levites--their lot is twelve cities.

41 All the cities of the Levites in the midst of the possession of the sons of Israel [are] forty and eight cities, and their suburbs.

42 These cities are each city and its suburbs round about it; so to all these cities.

43 And Jehovah giveth to Israel the whole of the land which He hath sworn to give to their fathers, and they possess it, and dwell in it;

44 and Jehovah giveth rest to them round about, according to all that which He hath sworn to their fathers, and there hath not stood a man in their presence of all their enemies, the whole of their enemies hath Jehovah given into their hand;

45 there hath not fallen a thing of all the good thing which Jehovah spake unto the house of Israel--the whole hath come.

Joshua 24

1 And Joshua gathereth all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and calleth for the elders of Israel, and for its heads, and for its judges, and for its authorities, and they station themselves before God.

2 And Joshua saith unto all the people, `Thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, Beyond the River have your fathers dwelt of old--Terah father of Abraham and father of Nachor--and they serve other gods;

3 and I take your father Abraham from beyond the River, and cause him to go through all the land of Canaan, and multiply his seed, and give to him Isaac.

4 And I give to Isaac, Jacob and Esau; and I give to Esau mount Seir, to possess it; and Jacob and his sons have gone down to Egypt.

5 And I send Moses and Aaron, and plague Egypt, as I have done in its midst, and afterwards I have brought you out.

6 And I bring out your fathers from Egypt, and ye go into the sea, and the Egyptians pursue after your fathers, with chariot and with horsemen, to the Red Sea;

7 and they cry unto Jehovah, and He setteth thick darkness between you and the Egyptians, and bringeth on them the sea, and covereth them, and your eyes see that which I have done in Egypt; and ye dwell in a wilderness many days.

8 `And I bring you in unto the land of the Amorite who is dwelling beyond the Jordan, and they fight with you, and I give them into your hand, and ye possess their land, and I destroy them out of your presence.

9 `And Balak son of Zippor, king of Moab, riseth and fighteth against Israel, and sendeth and calleth for Balaam son of Beor, to revile you,

10 and I have not been willing to hearken to Balaam, and he doth greatly bless you, and I deliver you out of his hand.

11 `And ye pass over the Jordan, and come in unto Jericho, and fight against you do the possessors of Jericho--the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Canaanite, and the Hittite, and the Girgashite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite--and I give theminto your hand.

12 And I send before you the hornet, and it casteth them out from your presence--two kings of the Amorite--not by thy sword, nor by thy bow.

13 `And I give to you a land for which thou hast not laboured, and cities which ye have not built, and ye dwell in them; of vineyards and olive-yards which ye have not planted ye are eating.

14 `And now, fear ye Jehovah, and serve Him, in perfection and in truth, and turn aside the gods which your fathers served beyond the River, and in Egypt, and serve ye Jehovah;

15 and if wrong in your eyes to serve Jehovah--choose for you to-day whom ye do serve; --whether the gods whom your fathers served, which [are] beyond the River, or the gods of the Amorite in whose land ye are dwelling; and I and my house--we serve Jehovah.'

16 And the people answer and say, `Far be it from us to forsake Jehovah, to serve other gods;

17 for Jehovah our God [is] He who is bringing us and our fathers up out of the land of Egypt, out of a house of servants, and who hath done before our eyes these great signs, and doth keep us in all the way in which we have gone, and among allthe peoples through whose midst we passed;

18 and Jehovah casteth out the whole of the peoples, even the Amorite inhabiting the land, from our presence; we also do serve Jehovah, for He [is] our God.'

19 And Joshua saith unto the people, `Ye are not able to serve Jehovah, for a God most holy He [is]; a zealous God He [is]; He doth not bear with your transgression and with your sins.

20 When ye forsake Jehovah, and have served gods of a stranger, then He hath turned back and done evil to you, and consumed you, after that He hath done good to you.'

21 And the people saith unto Joshua, `No, but Jehovah we do serve.'

22 And Joshua saith unto the people, `Witnesses ye are against yourselves, that ye have chosen for you Jehovah to serve Him (and they say, `Witnesses!')

23 and, now, turn aside the gods of the stranger which [are] in your midst, and incline your heart unto Jehovah, God of Israel.'

24 And the people say unto Joshua, `Jehovah our God we serve, and to His voice we hearken.'

25 And Joshua maketh a covenant with the people on that day, and layeth on it a statute and an ordinance, in Shechem.

26 And Joshua writeth these words in the Book of the Law of God, and taketh a great stone, and raiseth it up there under the oak which [is] in the sanctuary of Jehovah.

27 And Joshua saith unto all the people, `Lo, this stone is against us for a witness, for it hath heard all the sayings of Jehovah which He hath spoken with us, and it hath been against you for a witness, lest ye lie against your God.'

28 And Joshua sendeth the people away, each to his inheritance.

29 And it cometh to pass, after these things, that Joshua son of Nun, servant of Jehovah, dieth, a son of a hundred and ten years,

30 and they bury him in the border of his inheritance, in Timnath-Serah, which [is] in the hill-country of Ephraim, on the north of the hill of Gaash.

31 And Israel serveth Jehovah all the days of Joshua, and all the days of the elders who prolonged days after Joshua, and who knew all the work of Jehovah which He did to Israel.

32 And the bones of Joseph, which the sons of Israel brought up out of Egypt, they buried in Shechem, in the portion of the field which Jacob bought from the sons of Hamor father of Shechem, with a hundred kesitah; and they are to the sons of Joseph for an inheritance.

33 And Eleazar son of Aaron died, and they bury him in the hill of Phinehas his son, which was given to him in the hill-country of Ephraim.

Judges 1

1 And it cometh to pass, after the death of Joshua, that the sons of Israel ask at Jehovah, saying, `Who doth go up for us unto the Canaanite, at the commencement, to fight against it?'

2 And Jehovah saith, `Judah doth go up; lo, I have given the land into his hand.'

3 And Judah saith to Simeon his brother, `Go up with me into my lot, and we fight against the Canaanite--and I have gone, even I, with thee into thy lot;' and Simeon goeth with him.

4 And Judah goeth up, and Jehovah giveth the Canaanite and the Perizzite into their hand, and they smite them in Bezek--ten thousand men;

5 and they find Adoni-Bezek in Bezek, and fight against him, and smite the Canaanite and the Perizzite.

6 And Adoni-Bezek fleeth, and they pursue after him, and seize him, and cut off his thumbs and his great toes,

7 and Adoni-Bezek saith, `Seventy kings--their thumbs and their great toes cut off--have been gathering under my table; as I have done so hath God repaid to me;' and they bring him in to Jerusalem, and he dieth there.

8 And the sons of Judah fight against Jerusalem, and capture it, and smite it by the mouth of the sword, and the city they have sent into fire;

9 and afterwards have the sons of Judah gone down to fight against the Canaanite, inhabiting the hill-country, and the south, and the low country;

10 and Judah goeth unto the Canaanite who is dwelling in Hebron (and the name of Hebron formerly [is] Kirjath-Arba), and they smite Sheshai, and Ahiman, and Talmai.

11 And he goeth thence unto the inhabitants of Debir (and the name of Debir formerly [is] Kirjath-Sepher),

12 and Caleb saith, `He who smiteth Kirjath-Sepher--and hath captured it--then I have given to him Achsah my daughter for a wife.'

13 And Othniel son of Kenaz, younger brother of Caleb, doth capture it, and he giveth to him Achsah his daughter for a wife.

14 And it cometh to pass in her coming in, that she persuadeth him to ask from her father the field, and she lighteth from off the ass, and Caleb saith to her, `What--to thee?'

15 And she saith to him, `Give to me a blessing; when the south land thou hast given me- -then thou hast given to me springs of water; and Caleb giveth to her the upper springs and the lower springs.

16 And the sons of the Kenite, father-in-law of Moses, have gone up out of the city of palms with the sons of Judah [to] the wilderness of Judah, which [is] in the south of Arad, and they go and dwell with the people.

17 And Judah goeth with Simeon his brother, and they smite the Canaanite inhabiting Zephath, and devote it; and [one] calleth the name of the city Hormah.

18 And Judah captureth Gaza and its border, and Askelon and its border, and Ekron and its border;

19 and Jehovah is with Judah, and he occupieth the hill-country, but not to dispossess the inhabitants of the valley, for they have chariots of iron.

20 And they give to Caleb Hebron, as Moses hath spoken, and he dispossesseth thence the three sons of Anak.

21 And the Jebusite, inhabiting Jerusalem, the sons of Benjamin have not dispossessed; and the Jebusite dwelleth with the sons of Benjamin, in Jerusalem, till this day.

22 And the house of Joseph go up--even they--to Beth-El, and Jehovah [is] with them;

23 and the house of Joseph cause [men] to spy about Beth-El (and the name of the city formerly is Luz),

24 and the watchers see a man coming out from the city, and say to him, `Shew us, we pray thee, the entrance of the city, and we have done with thee kindness.'

25 And he sheweth them the entrance of the city, and they smite the city by the mouth of the sword, and the man and all his family they have sent away;

26 and the man goeth to the land of the Hittites, and buildeth a city, and calleth its name Luz--it [is] its name unto this day.

27 And Manasseh hath not occupied Beth-Shean and its towns, and Taanach and its towns, and the inhabitants of Dor and its towns, and the inhabitants of Iblaim and its towns, and the inhabitants of Megiddo and its towns, and the Canaanite is desirous to dwell in that land;

28 and it cometh to pass, when Israel hath been strong, that he setteth the Canaanite to tribute, and hath not utterly dispossessed it.

29 And Ephraim hath not dispossessed the Canaanite who is dwelling in Gezer, and the Canaanite dwelleth in its midst, in Gezer.

30 Zebulun hath not dispossessed the inhabitants of Kitron, and the inhabitants of Nahalol, and the Canaanite dwelleth in its midst, and they become tributary.

31 Asher hath not dispossessed the inhabitants of Accho, and the inhabitants of Zidon, and Ahlab, and Achzib, and Helbah, and Aphik, and Rehob;

32 and the Asherite dwelleth in the midst of the Canaanite, the inhabitants of the land, for it hath not dispossessed them.

33 Naphtali hath not dispossessed the inhabitants of Beth-Shemesh, and the inhabitants of Beth-Anath, and he dwelleth in the midst of the Canaanite, the inhabitants of the land; and the inhabitants of Beth-Shemesh and of Beth-Anath have become tributary to them.

34 And the Amorites press the sons of Dan to the mountain, for they have not suffered them to go down to the valley;

35 and the Amorite is desirous to dwell in mount Heres, in Aijalon, and in Shaalbim, and the hand of the house of Joseph is heavy, and they become tributary;

36 and the border of the Amorite [is] from the ascent of Akrabbim, from the rock and upward.

Judges 4

1 And the sons of Israel add to do the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah when Ehud is dead,

2 and Jehovah selleth them into the hand of Jabin king of Canaan, who hath reigned in Hazor, and the head of his host [is] Sisera, and he is dwelling in Harosheth of the Goyim;

3 and the sons of Israel cry unto Jehovah, for he hath nine hundred chariots of iron, and he hath oppressed the sons of Israel mightily twenty years.

4 And Deborah, a woman inspired, wife of Lapidoth, she is judging Israel at that time,

5 and she is dwelling under the palm-tree of Deborah, between Ramah and Beth-El, in the hill-country of Ephraim, and the sons of Israel go up unto her for judgment.

6 And she sendeth and calleth for Barak son of Abinoam, out of Kedesh-Naphtali, and saith unto him, `Hath not Jehovah, God of Israel, commanded? go, and thou hast drawn towards mount Tabor, and hast taken with thee ten thousand men, out of the sons of Naphtali, and out of the sons of Zebulun,

7 and I have drawn unto thee, unto the brook Kishon, Sisera, head of the host of Jabin, and his chariot, and his multitude, and have given him into thy hand.'

8 And Barak saith unto her, `If thou dost go with me, then I have gone; and if thou dost not go with me, I do not go;'

9 and she saith, `I do certainly go with thee; only, surely thy glory is not on the way which thou art going, for into the hand of a woman doth Jehovah sell Sisera;' and Deborah riseth and goeth with Barak to Kedesh.

10 And Barak calleth Zebulun and Naphtali to Kedesh, and he goeth up--at his feet [are] ten thousand men--and Deborah goeth up with him.

11 And Heber the Kenite hath been separated from the Kenite, from the sons of Hobab father-in-law of Moses, and he stretcheth out his tent unto the oak in Zaanaim, which [is] by Kedesh.

12 And they declare to Sisera that Barak son of Abinoam hath gone up to mount Tabor,

13 and Sisera calleth all his chariots, nine hundred chariots of iron, and all the people who [are] with him, from Harosheth of the Goyim, unto the brook Kishon.

14 And Deborah saith unto Barak, `Rise, for this [is] the day in which Jehovah hath given Sisera into thy hand; hath not Jehovah gone out before thee?' And Barak goeth down from mount Tabor, and ten thousand men after him.

15 And Jehovah destroyeth Sisera, and all the chariots, and all the camp, by the mouth of the sword, before Barak, and Sisera cometh down from off the chariot, and fleeth on his feet.

16 And Barak hath pursued after the chariots and after the camp, unto Harosheth of the Goyim, and all the camp of Sisera falleth by the mouth of the sword--there hath not been left even one.

17 And Sisera hath fled on his feet unto the tent of Jael wife of Heber the Kenite, for peace [is] between Jabin king of Hazor and the house of Heber the Kenite;

18 and Jael goeth out to meet Sisera, and saith unto him, `Turn aside, my lord, turn aside unto me, fear not;' and he turneth aside unto her, into the tent, and she covereth him with a coverlet.

19 And he saith unto her, `Give me to drink, I pray thee, a little water, for I am thirsty;' and she openeth the bottle of milk, and giveth him to drink, and covereth him.

20 And he saith unto her, `Stand at the opening of the tent, and it hath been, if any doth come in, and hath asked thee, and said, Is there a man here? that thou hast said, There is not.'

21 And Jael wife of Heber taketh the pin of the tent, and taketh the hammer in her hand, and goeth unto him gently, and striketh the pin into his temples, and it fasteneth in the earth--and he hath been fast asleep, and is weary--and he dieth.

22 And lo, Barak is pursuing Sisera, and Jael cometh out to meet him, and saith to him, `Come, and I shew thee the man whom thou art seeking;' and he cometh in unto her, and lo, Sisera is fallen--dead, and the pin in his temples.

23 And God humbleth on that day Jabin king of Canaan before the sons of Israel,

24 and the hand of the sons of Israel goeth, going on and becoming hard on Jabin king of Canaan, till that they have cut off Jabin king of Canaan.

Judges 5

1 And Deborah singeth--also Barak son of Abinoam--on that day, saying: --

2 `For freeing freemen in Israel, For a people willingly offering themselves Bless ye Jehovah.

3 Hear, ye kings; give ear, ye princes, I, to Jehovah, I--I do sing, I sing praise to Jehovah, God of Israel.

4 Jehovah, in Thy going forth out of Seir, In Thy stepping out of the field of Edom, Earth trembled, also the heavens dropped, Also thick clouds dropped water.

5 Hills flowed from the face of Jehovah, This one--Sinai--From the face of Jehovah, God of Israel.

6 In the days of Shamgar son of Anath--In the days of Jael--The ways have ceased, And those going in the paths go [in] crooked ways.

7 Villages ceased in Israel--they ceased, Till that I arose--Deborah, That I arose, a mother in Israel.

8 He chooseth new gods, Then war [is] at the gates! A shield is not seen--and a spear Among forty thousand in Israel.

9 My heart [is] to the lawgivers of Israel, Who are offering themselves willingly among the people, Bless ye Jehovah!

10 Riders on white asses--Sitters on a long robe--And walkers by the way--meditate!

11 By the voice of shouters Between the places of drawing water, There they give out righteous acts of Jehovah, Righteous acts of His villages in Israel, Then ruled in the gates have the people of Jehovah.

12 Awake, awake, Deborah; Awake, awake, utter a song; Rise, Barak, and take captive thy captivity, Son of Abinoam.

13 Then him who is left of the honourable ones He caused to rule the people of Jehovah, He caused me to rule among the mighty.

14 Out of Ephraim their root [is] against Amalek. After thee, Benjamin, among thy peoples. Out of Machir came down lawgivers, And out of Zebulun those drawing with the reed of a writer.

15 And princes in Issachar [are] with Deborah, Yea, Issachar [is] right with Barak, Into the valley he was sent on his feet. In the divisions of Reuben, Great [are] the decrees of heart!

16 Why hast thou abode between the boundaries, To hear lowings of herds? For the divisions of Reuben, Great [are] the searchings of heart!

17 Gilead beyond the Jordan did tabernacle, And Dan--why doth he sojourn [in] ships? Asher hath abode at the haven of the seas, And by his creeks doth tabernacle.

18 Zebulun [is] a people who exposed its soul to death, Naphtali also--on high places of the field.

19 Kings came--they fought; Then fought kings of Canaan, In Taanach, by the waters of Megiddo; Gain of money they took not!

20 From the heavens they fought: The stars from their highways fought with Sisera.

21 The brook Kishon swept them away, The brook most ancient--the brook Kishon. Thou dost tread down strength, O my soul!

22 Then broken were the horse-heels, By pransings--pransings of its mighty ones.

23 Curse Meroz--said a messenger of Jehovah, Cursing, curse ye its inhabitants, For they came not to the help of Jehovah, To the help of Jehovah among the mighty!

24 Blessed above women is Jael, Wife of Heber the Kenite, Above women in the tent she is blessed.

25 Water he asked--milk she gave; In a lordly dish she brought near butter.

26 Her hand to the pin she sendeth forth, And her right hand to the labourers' hammer, And she hammered Sisera--she smote his head, Yea, she smote, and it passed through his temple.

27 Between her feet he bowed--He fell, he lay down; Between her feet he bowed, he fell; Where he bowed, there he fell--destroyed.

28 Through the window she hath looked out--Yea, she crieth out--the mother of Sisera, Through the lattice: Wherefore is his chariot delaying to come? Wherefore tarried have the steps of his chariot?

29 The wise ones, her princesses, answer her, Yea, she returneth her sayings to herself:

30 Do they not find? --they apportion spoil, A female--two females--for every head, Spoil of finger-work for Sisera, Spoil of embroidered finger-work, Finger-work--a pair of embroidered things, For the necks of the spoil!

31 So do all Thine enemies perish, O Jehovah, And those loving Him [are] As the going out of the sun in its might!' and the land resteth forty years.

Judges 9

1 and Abimelech son of Jerubbaal goeth to Shechem, unto his mother's brethren, and speaketh unto them, and unto all the family of the house of his mother's father, saying,

2 `Speak, I pray you, in the ears of all the masters of Shechem, Which [is] good for you-- the ruling over you of seventy men (all the sons of Jerubbaal), or the ruling over you of one man? -- and ye have remembered that I [am] your bone and your flesh.'

3 And his mother's brethren speak concerning him, in the ears of all the masters of Shechem, all these words, and their heart inclineth after Abimelech, for they said, `He [is] our brother;'

4 and they give to him seventy silverings out of the house of Baal-Berith, and Abimelech hireth with them men, vain and unstable, and they go after him;

5 and he goeth into the house of his father at Ophrah, and slayeth his brethren, sons of Jerubbaal, seventy men, on one stone; and Jotham, youngest son of Jerubbaal, is left, for he was hidden.

6 And all the masters of Shechem are gathered together, and all the house of Millo, and come and cause Abimelech to reign for king at the oak of the camp which [is] in Shechem;

7 and they declare [it] to Jotham, and he goeth and standeth on the top of mount Gerizim, and lifteth up his voice, and calleth, and saith to them, `Hearken unto me, O masters of Shechem, and God doth hearken unto you:

8 `The trees have diligently gone to anoint over them a king, and they say to the olive, Reign thou over us.

9 And the olive saith to them, Have I ceased from my fatness, by which they honour gods and men, that I have gone to stagger over the trees?

10 And the trees say to the fig, Come thou, reign over us.

11 And the fig saith to them, Have I ceased from my sweetness, and my good increase, that I have gone to stagger over the trees?

12 `And the trees say to the vine, Come thou, reign over us.

13 And the vine saith to them, Have I ceased from my new wine, which is rejoicing gods and men, that I have gone to stagger over the trees?

14 And all the trees say unto the bramble, Come thou, reign over us.

15 And the bramble saith unto the trees, If in truth ye are anointing me for king over you, come, take refuge in my shadow; and if not--fire cometh out from the bramble, and devoureth the cedars of Lebanon.

16 `And, now, if in truth and in sincerity ye have acted, when ye make Abimelech king; and if ye have done good with Jerubbaal, and with his house; and if according to the deed of his hands ye have done to him--

17 because my father hath fought for you, and doth cast away his life from [him], and deliver you from the hand of Midian;

18 and ye have risen against the house of my father to-day, and slay his sons, seventy men, on one stone, and cause Abimelech son of his handmaid to reign over the masters of Shechem, because he [is] your brother--

19 yea, if in truth and in sincerity ye have acted with Jerubbaal and with his house this day, rejoice ye in Abimelech, and he doth rejoice--even he--in you;

20 and if not--fire cometh out from Abimelech and devoureth the masters of Shechem and the house of Millo, and fire cometh out from the masters of Shechem and from the house of Millo, and devoureth Abimelech.'

21 And Jotham hasteth, and fleeth, and goeth to Beer, and dwelleth there, from the face of Abimelech his brother.

22 And Abimelech is prince over Israel three years,

23 and God sendeth an evil spirit between Abimelech and the masters of Shechem, and the masters of Shechem deal treacherously with Abimelech,

24 for the coming in of the violence [to] the seventy sons of Jerubbaal, and of their blood to place [it] on Abimelech their brother, who slew them, and on the masters of Shechem, who strengthened his hands to slay his brethren.

25 And the masters of Shechem set for him ambushes on the top of the hills, and rob every one who passeth over by them in the way, and it is declared to Abimelech.

26 And Gaal son of Ebed cometh--also his brethren--and they pass over into Shechem, and the masters of Shechem trust in him,

27 and go out into the field, and gather their vineyards, and tread, and make praises, and go into the house of their god, and eat and drink, and revile Abimelech.

28 And Gaal son of Ebed saith, `Who [is] Abimelech, and who [is] Shechem, that we serve him? is [he] not son of Jerubbaal? and Zebul his commander? Serve ye the men of Hamor father of Shechem, and wherefore do we serve him--we?

29 and oh that this people were in my hand--then I turn Abimelech aside;' and he saith to Abimelech, `Increase thy host, and come out.'

30 And Zebul, prince of the city, heareth the words of Gaal son of Ebed, and his anger burneth,

31 and he sendeth messengers unto Abimelech deceitfully, saying, `Lo, Gaal son of Ebed and his brethren are coming into Shechem, and lo, they are fortifying the city against thee;

32 and, now, rise by night, thou and the people who [are] with thee, and lay wait in the field,

33 and it hath been, in the morning, about the rising of the sun, thou dost rise early, and hast pushed against the city; and lo, he and the people who [are] with him are going out unto thee-- and thou hast done to him as thy hand doth find.'

34 And Abimelech riseth, and all the people who [are] with him, by night, and they lay wait against Shechem--four detachments;

35 and Gaal son of Ebed goeth out, and standeth at the opening of the gate of the city, and Abimelech riseth--also the people who [are] with him--from the ambush,

36 and Gaal seeth the people, and saith unto Zebul, `Lo, people are coming down from the top of the hills;' and Zebul saith unto him, `The shadow of the hills thou art seeing like men.'

37 And Gaal addeth yet to speak, and saith, `Lo, people are coming down from the high part of the land, and another detachment is coming by the way of the oak of Meonenim.'

38 And Zebul saith unto him, `Where [is] now thy mouth, in that thou sayest, Who [is] Abimelech that we serve him? is not this the people against which thou hast kicked? go out, I pray thee now, and fight against it.'

39 And Gaal goeth out before the masters of Shechem, and fighteth against Abimelech,

40 and Abimelech pursueth him, and he fleeth from his presence, and many fall wounded--unto the opening of the gate.

41 And Abimelech abideth in Arumah, and Zebul casteth out Gaal and his brethren from dwelling in Shechem.

42 And it cometh to pass, on the morrow, that the people go out to the field, and they declare [it] to Abimelech,

43 and he taketh the people, and divideth them into three detachments, and layeth wait in a field, and looketh, and lo, the people are coming out from the city, and he riseth against them, and smiteth them.

44 And Abimelech and the detachments who [are] with him have pushed on, and stand at the opening of the gate of the city, and the two detachments have pushed against all who are in the field, and smite them,

45 and Abimelech hath fought against the city all that day, and captureth the city, and the people who [are] in it he hath slain, and he breaketh down the city, and soweth it [with] salt.

46 And all the masters of the tower of Shechem hear, and go in unto the high place of the house of the god Berith,

47 and it is declared to Abimelech that all the masters of the tower of Shechem have gathered themselves together,

48 and Abimelech goeth up to mount Zalmon, he and all the people who [are] with him, and Abimelech taketh the great axe in his hand, and cutteth off a bough of the trees, and lifteth it up, and setteth [it] on his shoulder, and saith unto the people who [are] with him, `What ye have seen I have done--haste, do ye like it.'

49 And all the people also cut down each one his bough, and go after Abimelech, and set [them] at the high place, and burn by these the high place with fire, and also all the men of the tower of Shechem die, about a thousand men and women.

50 And Abimelech goeth unto Thebez, and encampeth against Thebez, and captureth it,

51 and a strong tower hath been in the midst of the city, and thither flee do all the men and the women, and all the masters of the city, and they shut [it] behind them, and go up on the roof of the tower.

52 And Abimelech cometh unto the tower, and fighteth against it, and draweth nigh unto the opening of the tower to burn it with fire,

53 and a certain woman doth cast a piece of a rider on the head of Abimelech, and breaketh his skull,

54 and he calleth hastily unto the young man bearing his weapons, and saith to him, `Draw thy sword, and thou hast put me to death, lest they say of me--A woman slew him;' and his young man pierced him through, and he dieth.

55 And the men of Israel see that Abimelech [is] dead, and go each one to his place;

56 and God turneth back the evil of Abimelech which he did to his father to slay his seventy brethren;

57 and all the evil of the men of Shechem hath God turned back on their head, and come unto them doth the cursing of Jotham son of Jerubbaal.

Judges 10

1 And there riseth after Abimelech, to save Israel, Tola son of Puah, son of Dodo, a man of Issachar, and he is dwelling in Shamir, in the hill-country of Ephraim,

2 and he judgeth Israel twenty and three years, and he dieth, and is buried in Shamir.

3 And there riseth after him Jair the Gileadite, and he judgeth Israel twenty and two years,

4 and he hath thirty sons riding on thirty ass-colts, and they have thirty cities, (they call them Havoth-Jair unto this day), which [are] in the land of Gilead;

5 and Jair dieth, and is buried in Kamon.

6 And the sons of Israel add to do the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, and serve the Baalim, and Ashtaroth, and the gods of Aram, and the gods of Zidon, and the gods of Moab, and the gods of the Bene-Ammon, and the gods of the Philistines, and forsake Jehovah, and have not served Him;

7 and the anger of Jehovah burneth against Israel, and He selleth them into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the Bene-Ammon,

8 and they crush and oppress the sons of Israel in that year--eighteen years all the sons of Israel [who] are beyond the Jordan, in the land of the Amorite, which [is] in Gilead.

9 And the Bene-Ammon pass over the Jordan to fight also against Judah, and against Benjamin, and against the house of Ephraim, and Israel hath great distress.

10 And the sons of Israel cry unto Jehovah, saying, `We have sinned against Thee, even because we have forsaken our God, and serve the Baalim.'

11 And Jehovah saith unto the sons of Israel, `[Have I] not [saved you] from the Egyptians, and from the Amorite, from the Bene-Ammon, and from the Philistines?

12 And the Zidonians, and Amalek, and Maon have oppressed you, and ye cry unto Me, and I save you out of their hand;

13 and ye--ye have forsaken Me, and serve other gods, therefore I add not to save you.

14 Go and cry unto the gods on which ye have fixed; they--they save you in the time of your adversity.'

15 And the sons of Israel say unto Jehovah, `We have sinned, do Thou to us according to all that is good in Thine eyes; only deliver us, we pray Thee, this day.'

16 And they turn aside the gods of the stranger out of their midst, and serve Jehovah, and His soul is grieved with the misery of Israel.

17 And the Bene-Ammon are called together, and encamp in Gilead, and the sons of Israel are gathered together, and encamp in Mizpah.

18 And the people--heads of Gilead--say one unto another, `Who [is] the man that doth begin to fight against the Bene-Ammon? he is for head to all inhabitants of Gilead.'

Judges 12

1 And the men of Ephraim are called together, and pass over northward, and say to Jephthah, `Wherefore has thou passed over to fight against the Bene-Ammon, and on us hast not called to go with thee? thy house we burn over thee with fire.'

2 And Jephthah saith unto them, `A man of great strife I have been (I and my people) with the Bene-Ammon, and I call you, and ye have not saved me out of their hand,

3 and I see that thou art not a saviour, and I put my life in my hand, and pass over unto the Bene-Ammon, and Jehovah giveth them into my hand--and why have ye come up unto me this day to fight against me?'

4 And Jephthah gathered all the men of Gilead, and fighteth with Ephraim, and the men of Gilead smite Ephraim, because they said, `Fugitives of Ephraim [are] ye Gileadites, in the midst of Ephraim--in the midst of Manasseh.'

5 And Gilead captureth the passages of the Jordan to Ephraim, and it hath been, when [any of] the fugitives of Ephraim say, `Let me pass over,' and the men of Gilead say to him, `An Ephramite thou?' and he saith, `No;'

6 that they say to him, `Say, I pray thee, Shibboleth;' and he saith, `Sibboleth,' and is not prepared to speak right--and they seize him, and slaughter him at the passages of the Jordan, and there fall at that time, of Ephraim, forty and two chiefs.

7 And Jephthah judged Israel six years, and Jephthah the Gileadite dieth, and is buried in [one of] the cities of Gilead.

8 And after him Ibzan of Beth-Lehem judgeth Israel,

9 and he hath thirty sons and thirty daughters, he hath sent without and thirty daughters hath brought in to his sons from without; and he judgeth Israel seven years.

10 And Ibzan dieth, and is buried in Beth-Lehem.

11 And after him Elon the Zebulunite judgeth Israel, and he judgeth Israel ten years,

12 and Elon the Zebulunite dieth, and is buried in Aijalon, in the land of Zebulun.

13 And after him, Abdon son of Hillel, the Pirathonite, judgeth Israel,

14 and he hath forty sons, and thirty grandsons, riding on seventy ass-colts, and he judgeth Israel eight years.

15 And Abdon son of Hillel, the Pirathonite, dieth, and is buried in Pirathon, in the land of Ephraim, in the hill-country of the Amalekite.

Judges 20

1 And all the sons of Israel go out, and the company is assembled as one man, from Dan even unto Beer-Sheba, and the land of Gilead, unto Jehovah, at Mizpeh.

2 And the chiefs of all the people, of all the tribes of Israel, station themselves in the assembly of the people of God, four hundred thousand footmen drawing sword.

3 And the sons of Benjamin hear that the sons of Israel have gone up to Mizpeh. And the sons of Israel say, `Speak ye, how hath this evil been?'

4 And the man, the Levite, husband of the woman who hath been murdered, answereth and saith, `Into Gibeah (which [is] to Benjamin) I have come, I and my concubine, to lodge;

5 and rise against me do the masters of Gibeah--and they go round the house against me by night--me they thought to slay, and my concubine they have humbled, and she dieth;

6 and I lay hold on my concubine, and cut her in pieces, and send her into all the country of the inheritance of Israel; for they have done wickedness and folly in Israel;

7 lo, ye [are] all sons of Israel; give for you a word and counsel here.'

8 And all the people rise as one man, saying, `None of us doth go to his tent, and none of us doth turn aside to his house;

9 and now, this [is] the thing which we do to Gibeah--against it by lot!

10 and we have taken ten men of a hundred, of all the tribes of Israel, and a hundred of a thousand, and a thousand of a myriad, to receive provision for the people, to do, at their coming to Gibeah of Benjamin, according to all the folly whichit hath done in Israel.'

11 And every man of Israel is gathered unto the city, as one man--companions.

12 And the tribes of Israel send men among all the tribes of Benjamin, saying, `What [is] this evil which hath been among you?

13 And now, give up the men--sons of worthlessness--which [are] in Gibeah, and we put them to death, and we put away evil from Israel.' And [the sons of] Benjamin have not been willing to hearken to the voice of their brethren, the sons of Israel;

14 and the sons of Benjamin are gathered out of the cities to Gibeah, to go out to battle with the sons of Israel.

15 And the sons of Benjamin number themselves on that day; out of the cities [are] twenty and six thousand men drawing sword, apart from the inhabitants of Gibeah, [who] numbered themselves, seven hundred chosen men;

16 among all this people [are] seven hundred chosen men, bound of their right hand, each of these slinging with a stone at the hair, and he doth not err.

17 And the men of Israel numbered themselves, apart from Benjamin, four hundred thousand men, drawing sword, each of these a man of war.

18 And they rise and go up to Beth-El, and ask of God, and the sons of Israel say, `Who doth go up for us at the commencement to battle with the sons of Benjamin?' and Jehovah saith, `Judah--at the commencement.'

19 And the sons of Israel rise in the morning, and encamp against Gibeah,

20 and the men of Israel go out to battle with Benjamin, and the men of Israel set themselves in array with them, [for] battle against Gibeah,

21 and the sons of Benjamin come out from Gibeah, and destroy in Israel on that day two and twenty thousand men--to the earth.

22 And the people, the men of Israel, strengthen themselves, and add to set the battle in array in the place where they arranged themselves on the first day.

23 And the sons of Israel go up and weep before Jehovah till the evening, and ask of Jehovah, saying, `Do I add to draw nigh to battle with the sons of Benjamin, my brother?' And Jehovah saith, `Go up against him.'

24 And the sons of Israel draw near unto the sons of Benjamin on the second day,

25 and Benjamin cometh out to meet them from Gibeah on the second day, and destroy among the sons of Israel again eighteen thousand men--to the earth; all these are drawing sword.

26 And all the sons of Israel go up, even all the people, and come in to Beth-El, and weep, and sit there before Jehovah, and fast on that day till the evening, and cause to ascend burntofferings and peace-offerings before Jehovah.

27 And the sons of Israel ask of Jehovah, --and there [is] the ark of the covenant of God in those days,

28 and Phinehas son of Eleazar, son of Aaron, is standing before it in those days-- saying, `Do I add again to go out to battle with the sons of Benjamin, my brother, or do I cease?' And Jehovah saith, `Go up, for to-morrow I give him into thy hand.'

29 And Israel setteth liers in wait against Gibeah, round about,

30 and the sons of Israel go up against the sons of Benjamin, on the third day, and arrange themselves against Gibeah, as time by time.

31 And the sons of Benjamin come out to meet the people; they have been drawn away out of the city, and begin to smite [some] of the people--wounded as time by time, in the highways (of which one is going up to Beth-El, and the other to Gibeah in the field), [are] about thirty men of Israel.

32 And the sons of Benjamin say, `They are smitten before us as at the beginning;' but the sons of Israel said, `Let us flee, and draw them away out of the city, unto the highways.'

33 And all the men of Israel have risen from their place, and arrange themselves at Baal- Tamar, and the ambush of Israel is coming forth out of its place, out of the meadow of Gibeah.

34 And they come in over against Gibeah--ten thousand chosen men out of all Israel-- and the battle [is] grievous, and they have not known that the evil is striking against them.

35 And Jehovah smiteth Benjamin before Israel, and the sons of Israel destroy in Benjamin, on that day, twenty and five thousand, and a hundred men; all these [are] drawing sword.

36 And the sons of Benjamin see that they have been smitten--and the men of Israel give place to Benjamin, for they have trusted unto the ambush which they had set against Gibeah,

37 and the ambush have hasted, and push against Gibeah, and the ambush draweth itself out, and smiteth the whole of the city by the mouth of the sword.

38 And there was the appointed sign to the men of Israel with the ambush--their causing to go up a great volume of smoke from the city.

39 And the men of Israel turn in battle, and Benjamin hath begun to smite the wounded among the men of Israel, about thirty men, for they said, `Surely they are utterly smitten before us, as [at] the first battle;

40 and the volume hath begun to go up from the city--a pillar of smoke--and Benjamin turneth behind, and lo, gone up hath the perfection of the city toward the heavens.

41 And the men of Israel have turned, and the men of Benjamin are troubled, for they have seen that the evil hath stricken against them--

42 and they turn before the men of Israel unto the way of the wilderness, and the battle hath followed them; and those who [are] from the city are destroying them in their midst;

43 they have compassed the Benjamites--they have pursued them--with ease they have trodden them down till over-against Gibeah, at the sun-rising.

44 And there fall of Benjamin eighteen thousand men--the whole of these [are] men of valour;

45 and they turn and flee toward the wilderness, unto the rock of Rimmon; and they glean of them in the highways five thousand men, and follow after them unto Gidom, and smite of them two thousand men.

46 And all those falling of Benjamin are twenty and five thousand men drawing sword, on that day--the whole of these [are] men of valour;

47 and there turn and flee into the wilderness, unto the rock of Rimmon six hundred men, and they dwell in the rock Rimmon four months.

48 And the men of Israel have turned back unto the sons of Benjamin, and smite them by the mouth of the sword out of the city, --men unto cattle, unto all that is found; also all the cities which are found they have sent into fire.

Ruth 1

1 And it cometh to pass, in the days of the judging of the judges, that there is a famine in the land, and there goeth a man from Beth-Lehem-Judah to sojourn in the fields of Moab, he, and his wife, and his two sons.

2 And the name of the man [is] Elimelech, and the name of his wife Naomi, and the name of his two sons Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites from Beth-Lehem-Judah; and they come into the fields of Moab, and are there.

3 And Elimelech husband of Naomi dieth, and she is left, she and her two sons;

4 and they take to them wives, Moabitesses: the name of the one [is] Orpah, and the name of the second Ruth; and they dwell there about ten years.

5 And they die also, both of them--Mahlon and Chilion--and the woman is left of her two children and of her husband.

6 And she riseth, she and her daughters-in-law, and turneth back from the fields of Moab, for she hath heard in the fields of Moab that God hath looked after His people, --to give to them bread.

7 And she goeth out from the place where she hath been, and her two daughters-in-law with her, and they go in the way to turn back unto the land of Judah.

8 And Naomi saith to her two daughters-in-law, `Go, turn back, each to the house of her mother; Jehovah doth with you kindness as ye have done with the dead, and with me;

9 Jehovah doth grant to you, and find ye rest each in the house of her husband;' and she kisseth them, and they lift up their voice and weep.

10 And they say to her, `Surely with thee we go back to thy people.'

11 And Naomi saith, `Turn back, my daughters; why do ye go with me? are there yet to me sons in my bowels that they have been to you for husbands?

12 Turn back, my daughters, go, for I am too aged to be to a husband; though I had said, There is for me hope, also, I have been to-night to a husband, and also I have borne sons:

13 for them do ye wait till that they grow up? for them do ye shut yourselves up, not to be to a husband? nay, my daughters, for more bitter to me than to you, for the hand of Jehovah hath gone out against me.'

14 And they lift up their voice, and weep again, and Orpah kisseth her mother-in-law, and

15 And she saith, `Lo, thy sister-in-law hath turned back unto her people, and unto her god, turn thou back after thy sister-in-law.'

16 And Ruth saith, `Urge me not to leave thee--to turn back from after thee; for whither thou goest I go, and where thou lodgest I lodge; thy people [is] my people, and thy God my God.

17 Where thou diest I die, and there I am buried; thus doth Jehovah to me, and thus doth He add--for death itself doth part between me and thee.'

18 And she seeth that she is strengthening herself to go with her, and she ceaseth to speak unto her;

19 and they go both of them till their coming in to Beth-Lehem; and it cometh to pass at their coming in to Beth-Lehem, that all the city is moved at them, and they say, `Is this Naomi?'

20 And she saith unto them, `Call me not Naomi; call me Mara, for the Almighty hath dealt very bitterly to me,

21 I went out full, and empty hath Jehovah brought me back, why do ye call me Naomi, and Jehovah hath testified against me, and the Almighty hath done evil to me?'

22 And Naomi turneth back, and Ruth the Moabitess her daughter-in-law with her, who hath turned back from the fields of Moab, and they have come in to Beth-Lehem at the commencement of barley-harvest.

Ruth 3

1 And Naomi her mother-in-law saith to her, `My daughter, do not I seek for thee rest, that it may be well with thee?

2 and now, is not Boaz of our acquaintance, with whose young women thou hast been? lo, he is winnowing the threshing-floor of barley to-night,

3 and thou hast bathed, and anointed thyself, and put thy garments upon thee, and gone down to the threshing-floor; let not thyself be known to the man till he complete to eat and to drink;

4 and it cometh to pass when he lieth down, that thou hast known the place where he lieth down, and hast gone in, and uncovered his feet, and lain down, --and he doth declare to thee that which thou dost do.'

5 And she saith unto her, `All that thou sayest--I do.'

6 And she goeth down [to] the threshing-floor, and doth according to all that her motherin- law commanded her

7 And Boaz eateth and drinketh, and his heart is glad; and he goeth in to lie down at the end of the heap; and she cometh in gently, and uncovereth his feet, and lieth down.

8 And it cometh to pass, at the middle of the night, that the man trembleth, and turneth himself, and lo, a woman is lying at his feet.

9 And he saith, `Who [art] thou?' and she saith, `I [am] Ruth thy handmaid, and thou hast spread thy skirt over thy handmaid, for thou [art] a redeemer.'

10 And he saith, `Blessed [art] thou of Jehovah, my daughter; thou hast dealt more kindly at the latter end than at the beginning--not to go after the young men, either poor or rich.

11 And now, my daughter, fear not, all that thou sayest I do to thee, for all the gate of my people doth know that thou [art] a virtuous woman.

12 And now, surely, true, that I [am] a redeemer, but also there is a redeemer nearer than I.

13 Lodge to night, and it hath been in the morning, if he doth redeem thee, well: he redeemeth; and if he delight not to redeem thee, then I have redeemed thee--I; Jehovah liveth! lie down till the morning.'

14 And she lieth down at his feet till the morning, and riseth before one doth discern another; and he saith, `Let it not be known that the woman hath come into the floor.'

15 And he saith, `Give the covering which [is] on thee, and keep hold on it;' and she keepeth hold on it, and he measureth six [measures] of barley, and layeth [it] on her; and he goeth into the city.

16 And she cometh in unto her mother-in-law, and she saith, `Who [art] thou, my daughter?' and she declareth to her all that the man hath done to her.

17 And she saith, `These six [measures] of barley he hath given to me, for he said, Thou dost not go in empty unto thy mother-in-law.'

18 And she saith, `Sit still, my daughter, till thou dost know how the matter falleth, for the man doth not rest except he hath completed the matter to-day.'

1 Samuel 1

1 And there is a certain man of Ramathaim-Zophim, of the hill-country of Ephraim, and his name [is] Elkanah, son of Jeroham, son of Elihu, son of Tohu, son of Zuph, and Ephrathite,

2 and he hath two wives, the name of the one [is] Hannah, and the name of the second Peninnah, and Peninnah hath children, and Hannah hath no children.

3 And that man hath gone up out of his city from time to time, to bow himself, and to sacrifice, before Jehovah of Hosts, in Shiloh, and there [are] two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, priests to Jehovah.

4 And the day cometh, and Elkanah sacrificeth, and he hath given to Peninnah his wife, and to all her sons and her daughters, portions,

5 and to Hannah he giveth a certain portion--double, for he hath loved Hannah, and Jehovah hath shut her womb;

6 and her adversity hath also provoked her greatly, so as to make her tremble, for Jehovah hath shut up her womb.

7 And so he doth year by year, from the time of her going up into the house of Jehovah, so it provoketh her, and she weepeth, and doth not eat.

8 And Elkanah her husband saith to her, `Hannah, why weepest thou? and why dost thou not eat? and why is thy heart afflicted? am I not better to thee than ten sons?'

9 And Hannah riseth after eating in Shiloh, and after drinking, and Eli the priest is sitting on the throne by the side-post of the temple of Jehovah.

10 And she is bitter in soul, and prayeth unto Jehovah, and weepeth greatly,

11 and voweth a vow, and saith, `Jehovah of Hosts, if Thou dost certainly look on the affliction of Thy handmaid, and hast remembered me, and dost not forget Thy handmaid, and hast given to Thy handmaid seed of men--then I have given him to Jehovah all days of his life, and a razor doth not go up upon his head.'

12 And it hath been, when she multiplied praying before Jehovah, that Eli is watching her mouth,

13 and Hannah, she is speaking to her heart, only her lips are moving, and her voice is not heard, and Eli reckoneth her to be drunken.

14 And Eli saith unto her, `Until when are thou drunken? turn aside thy wine from thee.'

15 And Hannah answereth and saith, `No, my lord, A woman sharply pained in spirit I [am], and wine and strong drink I have not drunk, and I pour out my soul before Jehovah;

16 put not thy handmaid before a daughter of worthlessness, for from the abundance of my meditation, and of my provocation, I have spoken hitherto.'

17 And Eli answereth and saith, `Go in peace, and the God of Israel doth give thy petition which thou hast asked of Him.'

18 And she saith, `Let thy handmaid find grace in thine eyes;' and the woman goeth on her way, and eateth, and her countenance hath not been [sad] for it any more.

19 And they rise early in the morning, and bow themselves before Jehovah, and turn back, and come in unto their house in Ramah, and Elkanah knoweth Hannah his wife, and Jehovah remembereth her;

20 and it cometh to pass, at the revolution of the days, that Hannah conceiveth, and beareth a son, and calleth his name Samuel, `for, from Jehovah I have asked him.'

21 And the man Elkanah goeth up, and all his house, to sacrifice to Jehovah the sacrifice of the days, and his vow.

22 And Hannah hath not gone up, for she said to her husband, `Till the youth is weaned--then I have brought him in, and he hath appeared before the face of Jehovah, and dwelt there--unto the age.'

23 And Elkanah her husband saith to her, `Do that which is good in thine eyes; abide till thy weaning him; only, Jehovah establish His word;' and the woman abideth and suckleth her son till she hath weaned him,

24 and she causeth him to go up with her when she hath weaned him, with three bullocks, and one ephah of flour, and a bottle of wine, and she bringeth him into the house of Jehovah at Shiloh, and the youth [is but] a youth.

25 And they slaughter the bullock, and bring in the youth unto Eli,

26 and she saith, `O, my lord, thy soul liveth! my lord, I [am] the woman who stood with thee in this [place], to pray unto Jehovah;

27 for this youth I prayed, and Jehovah doth give to me my petition which I asked of Him;

28 and also I have caused him to be asked for Jehovah, all the days that he hath lived-- he is asked for Jehovah;' and he boweth himself there before Jehovah.

1 Samuel 2

1 And Hannah prayeth, and saith: `My heart hath exulted in Jehovah, My horn hath been high in Jehovah, My mouth hath been large over mine enemies, For I have rejoiced in Thy salvation.

2 There is none holy like Jehovah, For there is none save Thee, And there is no rock like our God.

3 Ye multiply not--ye speak haughtily--The old saying goeth out from your mouth, For a God of knowledge [is] Jehovah, And by Him actions are weighed.

4 Bows of the mighty are broken, And the stumbling have girded on strength.

5 The satiated for bread hired themselves, And the hungry have ceased. While the barren hath borne seven, And she abounding with sons hath languished.

6 Jehovah putteth to death, and keepeth alive, He bringeth down to Sheol, and bringeth up.

7 Jehovah dispossesseth, and He maketh rich, He maketh low, yea, He maketh high.

8 He raiseth from the dust the poor, From a dunghill He lifteth up the needy, To cause [them] to sit with nobles, Yea, a throne of honour He doth cause them to inherit, For to Jehovah [are] the fixtures of earth, And He setteth on them the habitable world.

9 The feet of His saints He keepeth, And the wicked in darkness are silent, For not by power doth man become mighty.

10 Jehovah--broken down are His adversaries, Against them in the heavens He thundereth: Jehovah judgeth the ends of earth, And giveth strength to His king, And exalteth the horn of His anointed.'

11 And Elkanah goeth to Ramath, unto his house, and the youth hath been serving Jehovah, [in] the presence of Eli the priest;

12 and the sons of Eli [are] sons of worthlessness, they have not known Jehovah.

13 And the custom of the priests with the people [is]: any man sacrificing a sacrifice-- then hath the servant of the priest come in when the flesh is boiling, and the hook of three teeth in his hand,

14 and hath struck [it] into the pan, or kettle, or caldron, or pot; all that the hook bringeth up doth the priest take for himself; thus they do to all Israel who are coming in, there, in Shiloh.

15 Also before they make perfume with the fat--then hath the priest's servant come in, and said to the man who is sacrificing, `Give flesh to roast for the priest, and he doth not take of thee flesh boiled, but raw;'

16 and the man saith unto him, `Let them surely make a perfume (as to-day) with the fat, then take to thee as thy soul desireth;' and he hath said to him, `Surely now thou dost give; and if not--I have taken by strength.'

17 And the sin of the young men is very great [in] the presence of Jehovah, for the men have despised the offering of Jehovah.

18 And Samuel is ministering [in] the presence of Jehovah, a youth girt [with] an ephod of linen;

19 and a small upper coat doth his mother make to him, and she hath brought it up to him from time to time, in her coming up with her husband to sacrifice the sacrifice of the time.

20 And Eli blessed Elkanah, and his wife, and said, `Jehovah doth appoint for thee seed of this woman, for the petition which she asked for Jehovah;' and they have gone to their place.

21 When Jehovah hath looked after Hannah, then she conceiveth and beareth three sons and two daughters; and the youth Samuel groweth up with Jehovah.

22 And Eli [is] very old, and hath heard all that his sons do to all Israel, and how that they lie with the women who are assembling [at] the opening of the tent of meeting,

23 and he saith to them, `Why do ye things like these? for I am hearing of your evil words from all the people--these!

24 Nay, my sons; for the report which I am hearing is not good causing the people of Jehovah to transgress. --

25 If a man sin against a man, then hath God judged him; but if against Jehovah a man sin, who doth pray for him?' and they hearken not to the voice of their father, though Jehovah hath delighted to put them to death.

26 And the youth Samuel is going on and growing up, and [is] good both with Jehovah, and also with men.

27 And there cometh a man of God unto Eli, and saith unto him, `Thus said Jehovah, Was I really revealed unto the house of thy father in their being in Egypt, before Pharaoh's house,

28 even to choose him out of all the tribes of Israel to Me for a priest, to go up on Mine altar, to make a perfume, to bear an ephod before Me, and I give to the house of thy father all the fire-offerings of the sons of Israel?

29 Why do ye kick at My sacrifice, and at Mine offering which I commanded [in] My habitation, and dost honour thy sons above Me, to make yourselves fat from the first part of every offering of Israel, of My people?

30 `Therefore--the affirmation of Jehovah, God of Israel--I certainly said, Thy house and the house of thy father, do walk up and down before Me to the age; and now--the affirmation of Jehovah--Far be it from Me! for he who is honouring Me, I honour, and those despising Me, are lightly esteemed.

31 `Lo, days [are] coming, and I have cut off thine arm, and the arm of the house of thy father, that an old man is not in thy house;

32 and thou hast beheld an adversary [in My] habitation, in all that He doth good with Israel, and there is not an old man in thy house all the days.

33 `And the man I cut not off of thine from Mine altar, [is] to consume thine eyes, and to grieve thy soul; and all the increase of thy house do die men;

34 and this [is] to thee the sign that cometh unto thy two sons, unto Hophni and Phinehas--in one day they die both of them;

35 and I have raised up for Me a stedfast priest; as in My heart and in My soul he doth do; and I have built for him a stedfast house, and he hath walked up and down before Mine anointed all the days;

36 and it hath been, every one who is left in thy house doth come in to bow himself to him, for a wage of silver, and a cake of bread, and hath said, Admit me, I pray thee, unto one of the priest's offices, to eat a morsel of bread.'

1 Samuel 3

1 And the youth Samuel is serving Jehovah before Eli, and the word of Jehovah hath been precious in those days--there is no vision broken forth.

2 And it cometh to pass, at that time, that Eli is lying down in his place, and his eyes have begun to be dim--he is not able to see.

3 And the lamp of God is not yet extinguished, and Samuel is lying down in the temple of Jehovah, where the ark of God [is],

4 and Jehovah calleth unto Samuel, and he saith, `Here [am] I.'

5 And he runneth unto Eli, and saith, `Here [am] I, for thou hast called for me;' and he saith, `I called not; turn back, lie down;' and he goeth and lieth down.

6 And Jehovah addeth to call again Samuel, and Samuel riseth and goeth unto Eli, and saith, `Here [am] I, for thou hast called for me;' and he saith, `I have not called, my son, turn back, lie down.'

7 And Samuel hath not yet known Jehovah, and the word of Jehovah is not yet revealed unto him.

8 And Jehovah addeth to call Samuel the third time, and he riseth and goeth unto Eli, and saith, `Here [am] I, for thou hast called for me;' and Eli understandeth that Jehovah is calling to the youth.

9 And Eli saith to Samuel, `Go, lie down, and it hath been, if He doth call unto thee, that thou hast said, Speak, Jehovah, for Thy servant is hearing;' and Samuel goeth and lieth down in his place.

10 And Jehovah cometh, and stationeth Himself, and calleth as time by time, `Samuel, Samuel;' and Samuel saith, `Speak, for Thy servant if hearing.'

11 And Jehovah saith unto Samuel, `Lo, I am doing a thing in Israel, at which the two ears of every one hearing it do tingle.

12 In that day I establish unto Eli all that I have spoken unto his house, beginning and completing;

13 and I have declared to him that I am judging his house--to the age, for the iniquity which he hath known, for his sons are making themselves vile, and he hath not restrained them,

14 and therefore I have sworn to the house of Eli: the iniquity of the house of Eli is not atoned for, by sacrifice, and by offering--unto the age.'

15 And Samuel lieth till the morning, and openeth the doors of the house of Jehovah, and Samuel is afraid of declaring the vision unto Eli.

16 And Eli calleth Samuel, and saith, `Samuel, my son;' and he saith, `Here [am] I.'

17 And he saith, `What [is] the word which He hath spoken unto thee? I pray thee, hide it not from me; so doth God do to thee, and so doth He add, if thou hidest from me a word of all the words that He hath spoken unto thee.'

18 And Samuel declareth to him the whole of the words, and hath not hid from him; and he saith, `It [is] Jehovah; that which is good in His eyes He doth.'

19 And Samuel groweth up, and Jehovah hath been with him, and hath not let fall any of his words to the earth;

20 and all Israel know, from Dan even unto Beer-Sheba, that Samuel is established for a prophet to Jehovah.

21 And Jehovah addeth to appear in Shiloh, for Jehovah hath been revealed unto Samuel, in Shiloh, by the word of Jehovah.

1 Samuel 4

1 And the word of Samuel is to all Israel, and Israel goeth out to meet the Philistines for battle, and they encamp by Eben-Ezer, and the Philistines have encamped in Aphek,

2 and the Philistines set themselves in array to meet Israel, and the battle spreadeth itself, and Israel is smitten before the Philistines, and they smite among the ranks in the field about four thousand men.

3 And the people cometh in unto the camp, and the elders of Israel say, `Why hath Jehovah smitten us to-day before the Philistines? we take unto us from Shiloh the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and it cometh into our midst, and He doth save us out of the hand of our enemies.'

4 And the people sendeth to Shiloh, and they take up thence the ark of the covenant of Jehovah of Hosts, inhabiting the cherubs, and there [are] two sons of Eli, with the ark of the covenant of God, Hophni and Phinehas.

5 And it cometh to pass, at the coming in of the ark of the covenant of Jehovah unto the camp, that all Israel shout--a great shout--and the earth is moved.

6 And the Philistines hear the noise of the shouting, and say, `What [is] the noise of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews?' and they perceive that the ark of Jehovah hath come in unto the camp.

7 And the Philistines are afraid, for they said, `God hath come in unto the camp;' and they say, `Woe to us, for there hath not been like this heretofore.

8 Woe to us, who doth deliver us out of the hand of these honourable gods? these [are] the gods who are smiting the Egyptians with every plague in the wilderness.

9 Strengthen yourselves, and become men, O Philistines, lest ye do service to

10 And the Philistines fight, and Israel is smitten, and they flee each to his tents, and the blow is very great, and there fall of Israel thirty thousand footmen;

11 and the ark of God hath been taken, and the two sons of Eli have died, Hophni and Phinehas.

12 And a man of Benjamin runneth out of the ranks, and cometh into Shiloh, on that day, and his long robes [are] rent, and earth on his head;

13 and he cometh in, and lo, Eli is sitting on the throne by the side of the way, watching, for his heart hath been trembling for the ark of God, and the man hath come in to declare [it] in the city, and all the city crieth out.

14 And Eli heareth the noise of the cry, and saith, `What--the noise of this tumult!' And the man hasted, and cometh in, and declareth to Eli.

15 And Eli is a son of ninety and eight years, and his eyes have stood, and he hath not been able to see.

16 And the man saith unto Eli, `I [am] he who hath come out of the ranks, and I out of the ranks have fled to-day;' and he saith, `What hath been the matter, my son?'

17 And he who is bearing tidings answereth and saith, `Israel hath fled before the Philistines, and also a great slaughter hath been among the people, and also thy two sons have died- -Hophni and Phinehas--and the ark of God hath been captured.'

18 And it cometh to pass, at his mentioning the ark of God, that he falleth from off the throne backward, by the side of the gate, and his neck is broken, and he dieth, for the man [is] old and heavy, and he hath judged Israel forty years.

19 And his daughter-in-law, wife of Phinehas, [is] pregnant, about to bear, and she heareth the report of the taking of the ark of God, that her father-in-law and her husband have died, and she boweth, and beareth, for her pains have turned upon her.

20 And at the time of her death, when the women who are standing by her say, `Fear not, for a son thou hast borne,' she hath not answered, nor set her heart [to it];

21 and she calleth the youth I-Chabod, saying, `Honour hath removed from Israel,' because of the taking of the ark of God, and because of her father-in-law and her husband.

22 And she saith, `Honour hath removed from Israel, for the ark of God hath been taken.'

1 Samuel 8

1 And it cometh to pass, when Samuel [is] aged, that he maketh his sons judges over Israel.

2 And the name of his first-born son is Joel, and the name of his second Abiah, judges in Beer-Sheba:

3 and his sons have not walked in his ways, and turn aside after the dishonest gain, and take a bribe, and turn aside judgment.

4 And all the elders of Israel gather themselves together, and come in unto Samuel to Ramath,

5 and say unto him, `Lo, thou hast become aged, and thy sons have not walked in thy ways; now, appoint to us a king, to judge us, like all the nations.'

6 And the thing is evil in the eyes of Samuel, when they have said, `Give to us a king to judge us;' and Samuel prayeth unto Jehovah.

7 And Jehovah saith unto Samuel, `Hearken to the voice of the people, to all that they say unto thee, for thee they have not rejected, but Me they have rejected, from reigning over them.

8 According to all the works that they have done from the day of My bringing them up out of Egypt, even unto this day, when they forsake Me, and serve other gods--so they are doing also to thee.

9 And now, hearken to their voice; only, surely thou dost certainly protest to them, and hast declared to them the custom of the king who doth reign over them.'

10 And Samuel speaketh all the words of Jehovah unto the people who are asking from him a king,

11 and saith, `This is the custom of the king who doth reign over you: Your sons he doth take, and hath appointed for himself among his chariots, and among his horsemen, and they have run before his chariots;

12 also to appoint for himself heads of thousands, and heads of fifties; also to plow his plowing, and to reap his reaping; and to make instruments of his war, and instruments of his charioteer.

13 `And your daughters he doth take for perfumers, and for cooks, and for bakers;

14 and your fields, and your vineyards, and your olive-yards--the best--he doth take, and hath given to his servants.

15 And your seed and your vineyards he doth tithe, and hath given to his eunuchs, and to his servants.

16 And your men-servants, and your maid-servants, and your young men--the best, and your asses, he doth take, and hath prepared for his own work;

17 your flock he doth tithe, and ye are to him for servants.

18 And ye have cried out in that day because of the king whom ye have chosen for yourselves, and Jehovah doth not answer you in that day.'

19 And the people refuse to hearken to the voice of Samuel, and say, `Nay, but a king is over us,

20 and we have been, even we, like all the nations; and our king hath judged us, and gone out before us, and fought our battles.'

21 And Samuel heareth all the words of the people, and speaketh them in the ears of Jehovah;

22 and Jehovah saith unto Samuel, `Hearken to their voice, and thou hast caused to reign over them a king.' And Samuel saith unto the men of Israel, `Go ye each to his city.'

1 Samuel 12

1 And Samuel saith unto all Israel, `Lo, I have hearkened to your voice, to all that ye said to me, and I cause to reign over you a king,

2 and now, lo, the king is walking habitually before you, and I have become aged and gray-headed, and my sons, lo, they [are] with you, and I have walked habitually before you from my youth till this day.

3 `Lo, here [am] I; testify against me, over-against Jehovah, and over-against His anointed; whose ox have I taken, and whose ass have I taken, and whom have I oppressed; whom have I bruised, and of whose hand have I taken a ransom, and hide mine eyes with it? --and I restore to you.'

4 And they say, `Thou hast not oppressed us, nor hast thou crushed us, nor hast thou taken from the hand of any one anything.'

5 And he saith unto them, `A witness [is] Jehovah against you: and a witness [is] His anointed this day, that ye have not found anything in my hand;' and they say, `A witness.'

6 And Samuel saith unto the people, `Jehovah--He who made Moses and Aaron, and who brought up your fathers out of the land of Egypt!

7 and, now, station yourselves, and I judge you before Jehovah, with all the righteous acts of Jehovah, which He did with you, and with your fathers.

8 `When Jacob hath come in to Egypt, and your fathers cry unto Jehovah, then Jehovah sendeth Moses and Aaron, and they bring out your fathers from Egypt, and cause them to dwell in this place,

9 and they forget Jehovah their God, and He selleth them into the hand of Sisera, head of the host of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab, and they fight against them,

10 and they cry unto Jehovah, and say, We have sinned, because we have forsaken Jehovah, and serve the Baalim, and Ashtaroth, and now, deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, and we serve Thee.

11 `And Jehovah sendeth Jerubbaal, and Bedan, and Jephthah, and Samuel, and delivereth you out of the hand of your enemies round about, and ye dwell confidently.

12 `And ye see that Nahash king of the Bene-Ammon hath come against you, and ye say to me, Nay, but a king doth reign over us; and Jehovah your God [is] your king!

13 And, now, lo, the king whom ye have chosen--whom ye have asked! and lo, Jehovah hath placed over you a king.

14 `If ye fear Jehovah, and have served Him, and hearkened to His voice, then ye do not provoke the mouth of Jehovah, and ye have been--both ye and the king who hath reigned over you--after Jehovah your God.

15 `And if ye do not hearken to the voice of Jehovah--then ye have provoked the mouth of Jehovah, and the hand of Jehovah hath been against you, and against your fathers.

16 `Also now, station yourselves and see this great thing which Jehovah is doing before your eyes;

17 is it not wheat-harvest to-day? I call unto Jehovah, and He doth give voices and rain; and know ye and see that your evil is great which ye have done in the eyes of Jehovah, to ask for you a king.'

18 And Samuel calleth unto Jehovah, and Jehovah giveth voices and rain, on that day, and all the people greatly fear Jehovah and Samuel;

19 and all the people say unto Samuel, `Pray for thy servants unto Jehovah thy God, and we do not die, for we have added to all our sins evil to ask for us a king.'

20 And Samuel saith unto the people, `Fear not; ye have done all this evil; only, turn not aside from after Jehovah--and ye have served Jehovah with all your heart,

21 and ye do not turn aside after the vain things which do not profit nor deliver, for they [are] vain,

22 for Jehovah doth not leave His people, on account of His great name; for Jehovah hath been pleased to make you to Him for a people.

23 `I, also, far be it from me to sin against Jehovah, by ceasing to pray for you, and I have directed you in the good and upright way;

24 only, fear ye Jehovah, and ye have served Him in truth with all your heart, for see that which He hath made great with you;

25 and if ye really do evil, both ye and your king are consumed.'

1 Samuel 14

1 And the day cometh that Jonathan son of Saul saith unto the young man bearing his weapons, `Come, and we pass over unto the station of the Philistines, which [is] on the other side of this;' and to his father he hath not declared [it].

2 And Saul is abiding at the extremity of Gibeah, under the pomegranate which [is] in Migron, and the people who [are] with him, about six hundred men,

3 and Ahiah, son of Ahitub, brother of I-Chabod, son of Phinehas son of Eli priest of Jehovah in Shiloh, bearing an ephod; and the people knew not that Jonathan hath gone.

4 And between the passages where Jonathan sought to pass over unto the station of the Philistines [is] the edge of a rock on the one side, and the edge of a rock on the other side, and the name of the one is Bozez, and the name of the other Seneh.

5 The one edge [is] fixed on the north over-against Michmash, and the one on the south over-against Gibeah.

6 And Jonathan saith unto the young man bearing his weapons, `Come, and we pass over unto the station of these uncircumcised; it may be Jehovah doth work for us, for there is no restraint to Jehovah to save by many or by few.'

7 And the bearer of his weapons saith to him, `Do all that [is] in thy heart; turn for thee; lo, I [am] with thee, as thine own heart.'

8 And Jonathan saith, `Lo, we are passing over unto the men, and are revealed unto them;

9 if thus they say unto us, `Stand still till we have come unto you,' then we have stood in our place, and do not go up unto them;

10 and if thus they say, `Come up against us,' then we have gone up, for Jehovah hath given them into our hand, and this to us [is] the sign.

11 And revealed are both of them unto the station of the Philistines, and the Philistines say, `Lo, Hebrews are coming out of the holes where they have hid themselves.'

12 And the men of the station answer Jonathan, and the bearer of his weapons, and say, `Come up unto us, and we cause you to know something.' And Jonathan saith unto the bearer of his weapons, `Come up after me, for Jehovah hath given them into the hand of Israel.'

13 And Jonathan goeth up on his hands, and on his feet, and the bearer of his weapons after him; and they fall before Jonathan, and the bearer of his weapons is putting to death after him.

14 And the first smiting which Jonathan and the bearer of his weapons have smitten is of about twenty men, in about half a furrow of a yoke of a field,

15 and there is a trembling in the camp, in the field, and among all the people, the station and the destroyers have trembled--even they, and the earth shaketh, and it becometh a trembling of God.

16 And the watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin see, and lo, the multitude hath melted away, and it goeth on, and is beaten down.

17 And Saul saith to the people who [are] with him, `Inspect, I pray you, and see; who hath gone from us?' and they inspect, and lo, Jonathan and the bearer of his weapons are not.

18 And Saul saith to Ahiah, `Bring nigh the ark of God;' for the ark of God hath been on that day with the sons of Israel.

19 And it cometh to pass, while Saul spake unto the priest, that the noise which [is] in the camp of the Philistines goeth on, going on and becoming great, and Saul saith unto the priest, `Remove thy hand.'

20 And Saul is called, and all the people who [are] with him, and they come in unto the battle, and, lo, the sword of each hath been against his neighbour--a very great destruction.

21 And the Hebrews [who] have been for the Philistines as heretofore, who had gone up with them into the camp, have turned round, even they, to be with Israel who [are] with Saul and Jonathan,

22 and all the men of Israel, who are hiding themselves in the hill-country of Ephraim, have heard that the Philistines have fled, and they pursue--even they--after them in battle.

23 And Jehovah saveth Israel on that day, and the battle hath passed over to Beth- Aven.

24 And the men of Israel have been distressed on that day, and Saul adjureth the people, saying, `Cursed [is] the man who eateth food till the evening, and I have been avenged of mine enemies;' and none of the people hath tasted food.

25 And all [they of] the land have come into a forest, and there is honey on the face of the field;

26 and the people come in unto the forest, and lo, the honey dropped, and none is moving his hand unto his mouth, for the people feared the oath.

27 And Jonathan hath not heard of his father's adjuring the people, and putteth forth the end of the rod, which [is] in his hand, and dippeth it in the honeycomb, and bringeth back his hand unto his mouth--and his eyes see!

28 And a man of the people answereth and saith, `Thy father certainly adjured the people, saying, Cursed [is] the man who eateth food to-day; and the people are weary.'

29 And Jonathan saith, `My father hath troubled the land; see, I pray you, that mine eyes have become bright because I tasted a little of this honey.

30 How much more if the people had well eaten to-day of the spoil of its enemies which it hath found, for now, the smiting hath not been great among the Philistines.'

31 And they smite on that day among the Philistines from Michmash to Aijalon, and the people are very weary,

32 and the people make unto the spoil, and take sheep, and oxen, and sons of the herd, and slaughter on the earth, and the people eat with the blood.

33 And they declare to Saul, saying, `Lo, the people are sinning against Jehovah, to eat with the blood.' And he saith, `Ye have dealt treacherously, roll unto me to-day a great stone.'

34 And Saul saith, `Be ye scattered among the people, and ye have said to them, Bring ye nigh unto me each his ox, and each his sheep; and ye have slain [them] in this place, and eaten, and ye do not sin against Jehovah to eat with the blood.' And all the people bring nigh each his ox, in his hand, that night, and slaughter [them] there.

35 And Saul buildeth an alter to Jehovah; with it he hath begun to build altars to Jehovah.

36 And Saul saith, `Let us go down after the Philistines by night, and we prey upon them till the light of the morning, and leave not a man of them.' And they say, `All that is good in thine eyes do.' And the priest saith, `Let us draw near hither unto God.'

37 And Saul asketh of God, `Do I go down after the Philistines? dost Thou give them into the hand of Israel?' and He hath not answered him on that day.

38 And Saul saith, `Draw ye nigh hither all, the chiefs of the people, and know and see in what this sin hath been to-day;

39 for, Jehovah liveth, who is saving Israel: surely if it be in Jonathan my son, surely he doth certainly die;' and none is answering him out of all the people.

40 And he saith unto all Israel, `Ye--ye are on one side, and I and Jonathan my son are on another side;' and the people say unto Saul, `That which is good in thine eyes do.'

41 And Saul saith unto Jehovah, God of Israel, `Give perfection;' and Jonathan and Saul are captured, and the people went out.

42 And Saul saith, `Cast between me and Jonathan my son;' and Jonathan is captured.

43 And Saul saith unto Jonathan, `Declare to me, what hast thou done?' and Jonathan declareth to him, and saith, `I certainly tasted with the end of the rod that [is] in my hand a little honey; lo, I die!'

44 And Saul saith, `Thus doth God do, and thus doth He add, for thou dost certainly die, Jonathan.'

45 And the people say unto Saul, `Doth Jonathan die who wrought this great salvation in Israel? --a profanation! Jehovah liveth, if there falleth from the hair of his head to the earth, for with God he hath wrought this day;' and the people rescue Jonathan, and he hath not died.

46 And Saul goeth up from after the Philistines, and the Philistines have gone to their place;

47 and Saul captured the kingdom over Israel, and he fighteth round about against all his enemies, against Moab, and against the Bene-Ammon, and against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines, and whithersoever he turneth he doth vex [them].

48 And he maketh a force, and smiteth Amalek, and delivereth Israel out of the hand of its spoiler.

49 And the sons of Saul are Jonathan, and Ishui, and Melchi-Shua; as to the name of his two daughters, the name of the first-born [is] Merab, and the name of the younger Michal;

50 and the name of the wife of Saul [is] Ahinoam, daughter of Ahimaaz; and the name of the head of his host [is] Abner son of Ner, uncle of Saul;

51 and Kish [is] father of Saul, and Ner father of Abner [is] son of Ahiel.

52 And the war is severe against the Philistines all the days of Saul; when Saul hath seen any mighty man, and any son of valour, then he doth gather him unto himself.

1 Samuel 17

1 And the Philistines gather their camps to battle, and are gathered to Shochoh, which [is] to Judah, and encamp between Shochoh and Azekah, in Ephes-Dammim;

2 and Saul and the men of Israel have been gathered, and encamp by the valley of Elah, and set the battle in array to meet the Philistines.

3 And the Philistines are standing on the mountain on this side, and the Israelites are standing on the mountain on that side, and the valley [is] between them.

4 And there goeth out a man of the duellists from the camps of the Philistines, Goliath [is] his name, from Gath; his height [is] six cubits and a span,

5 and a helmet of brass [is] on his head, and [with] a scaled coat of mail he [is] clothed, and the weight of the coat of mail [is] five thousand shekels of brass,

6 and a frontlet of brass [is] on his feet, and a javelin of brass between his shoulders,

7 and the wood of his spear [is] like a beam of weavers', and the flame of his spear [is] six hundred shekels of iron, and the bearer of the buckler is going before him.

8 And he standeth and calleth unto the ranks of Israel, and saith to them, `Why are ye come out to set in array the battle? [am] not I the Philistine, and ye servants to Saul? choose for you a man, and let him come down unto me;

9 if he be able to fight with me, and have smitten me, then we have been to you for servants; and if I am able for him, and have smitten him, then ye have been to us for servants, and have served us.'

10 And the Philistine saith, `I have reproached the ranks of Israel this day; give to me a man, and we fight together.'

11 And Saul heareth--and all Israel--these words of the Philistine, and they are broken down and greatly afraid.

12 And David [is] son of this Ephrathite of Beth-Lehem-Judah, whose name [is] Jesse, and he hath eight sons, and the man in the days of Saul hath become aged among men;

13 and the three eldest sons of Jesse go, they have gone after Saul to battle; and the name of his three sons who have gone into battle [are] Eliab the first-born, and his second Abinadab, and the third Shammah.

14 And David is the youngest, and the three eldest have gone after Saul,

15 and David is going and returning from Saul, to feed the flock of his father at Beth- Lehem.

16 And the Philistine draweth nigh, morning and evening, and stationeth himself forty days.

17 And Jesse saith to David his son, `Take, I pray thee, to thy brethren, an ephah of this roasted [corn], and these ten loaves, and run to the camp to thy brethren;

18 and these ten cuttings of the cheese thou dost take in to the head of the thousand, and thy brethren thou dost inspect for welfare, and their pledge dost receive.'

19 And Saul, and they, and all the men of Israel [are] in the valley of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.

20 And David riseth early in the morning, and leaveth the flock to a keeper, and lifteth up, and goeth, as Jesse commanded him, and he cometh in to the path, and to the force which is going out unto the rank, and they have shouted for battle;

21 and Israel and the Philistines set in array rank to meet rank.

22 And David letteth down the goods from off him on the hand of a keeper of the goods, and runneth into the rank, and cometh and asketh of his brethren of welfare.

23 And he is speaking with them, and lo, a man of the duellists is coming up, Goliath the Philistine [is] his name, of Gath, out of the ranks of the Philistines, and he speaketh according to those words, and David heareth;

24 and all the men of Israel when they see the man flee from his presence, and are greatly afraid.

25 And the men of Israel say, `Have ye seen this man who is coming up? for, to reproach Israel he is coming up, and it hath been--the man who smiteth him, the king doth enrich him with great riches, and his daughter he doth give to him, and his father's house doth make free in Israel.'

26 And David speaketh unto the men who are standing by him, saying, `What is done to the man who smiteth this Philistine, and hath turned aside reproach from Israel? for who [is] this uncircumcised Philistine that he hath reproached the ranksof the living God?'

27 And the people speak to him according to this word, saying, `Thus it is done to the man who smiteth him.'

28 And Eliab, his eldest brother, heareth when he speaketh unto the men, and the anger of Eliab burneth against David, and he saith, `Why [is] this--thou hast come down! and to whom hast thou left those few sheep in the wilderness? I have known thy pride, and the evil of thy heart--for, to see the battle thou hast come down.'

29 And David saith, `What have I done now? is it not a word?'

30 And he turneth round from him unto another, and saith according to this word, and the people return him word as the first word.

31 And the words which David hath spoken are heard, and they declare before Saul, and he receiveth him;

32 and David saith unto Saul, `Let no man's heart fall because of him, thy servant doth go, and hath fought with this Philistine.'

33 And Saul saith unto David, `Thou art not able to go unto this Philistine, to fight with him, for a youth thou [art], and he a man of war from his youth.'

34 And David saith unto Saul, `A shepherd hath thy servant been to his father among the sheep, and the lion hath come--and the bear--and hath taken away a sheep out of the drove,

35 and I have gone out after him, and smitten him, and delivered out of his mouth, and he riseth against me, and I have taken hold on his beard, and smitten him, and put him to death.

36 Both the lion and the bear hath thy servant smitten, and this uncircumcised Philistine hath been as one of them, for he hath reproached the ranks of the living God.'

37 And David saith, `Jehovah, who delivered me out of the paw of the lion, and out of the paw of the bear, He doth deliver me from the hand of this Philistine.' And Saul saith unto David, `Go, and Jehovah is with thee.'

38 And Saul clotheth David with his long robe, and hath put a helmet of brass on his head, and doth clothe him with a coat of mail.

39 And David girded his sword above his long robe, and beginneth to go, for he hath not tried [it]; and David saith unto Saul, `I am not able to go with these, for I had not tried;' and David turneth them aside from off him.

40 And he taketh his staff in his hand, and chooseth for him five smooth stones from the brook, and putteth them in the shepherds' habiliments that he hath, even in the scrip, and his sling [is] in his hand, and he draweth nigh unto the Philistine.

41 And the Philistine goeth on, going and drawing near unto David, and the man bearing the buckler [is] before him,

42 and the Philistine looketh attentively, and seeth David, and despiseth him, for he was a youth, and ruddy, with a fair appearance.

43 And the Philistine saith unto David, `Am I a dog that thou art coming unto me with staves?' and the Philistine revileth David by his gods,

44 and the Philistine saith unto David, `Come unto me, and I give thy flesh to the fowl of the heavens, and to the beast of the field.'

45 And David saith unto the Philistine, `Thou art coming unto me with sword, and with spear, and with buckler, and I am coming unto thee in the name of Jehovah of Hosts, God of the ranks of Israel, which thou hast reproached.

46 This day doth Jehovah shut thee up into my hand--and I have smitten thee, and turned aside thy head from off thee, and given the carcase of the camp of the Philistines this day to the fowl of the heavens, and to the beast of the earth, andall the earth do know that God is for Israel.

47 and all this assembly do know that not by sword and by spear doth Jehovah save, that the battle [is] Jehovah's, and He hath given you into our hand.'

48 And it hath come to pass, that the Philistine hath risen, and goeth, and draweth near to meet David, and David hasteth and runneth to the rank to meet the Philistine,

49 and David putteth forth his hand unto the vessel, and taketh thence a stone, and slingeth, and smiteth the Philistine on his forehead, and the stone sinketh into his forehead, and he falleth on his face to the earth.

50 And David is stronger than the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and smiteth the Philistine, and putteth him to death, and there is no sword in the hand of David,

51 and David runneth and standeth over the Philistine, and taketh his sword, and draweth it out of its sheath, and putteth him to death, and cutteth off with it his head; and the Philistines see that their hero [is] dead, and flee.

52 And the men of Israel rise--also Judah--and shout, and pursue the Philistines till thou enter the valley, and unto the gates of Ekron, and the wounded of the Philistines fall in the way of Shaaraim, even unto Gath, and unto Ekron,

53 and the sons of Israel turn back from burning after the Philistines, and spoil their camps.

54 And David taketh the head of the Philistine, and bringeth it in to Jerusalem, and his weapons he hath put in his own tent.

55 And when Saul seeth David going out to meet the Philistine, he hath said unto Abner, head of the host, `Whose son [is] this--the youth, Abner?' and Abner saith, `Thy soul liveth, O king, I have not known.'

56 And the king saith, `Ask thou whose son this [is] --the young man.'

57 And when David turneth back from smiting the Philistine, then Abner taketh him and bringeth him in before Saul, and the head of the Philistine in his hand;

58 and Saul saith unto him, `Whose son [art] thou, O youth?' and David saith, `Son of thy servant Jesse, the Beth-Lehemite.'

1 Samuel 20

1 And David fleeth from Naioth in Ramah, and cometh, and saith before Jonathan, `What have I done? what [is] mine iniquity? and what my sin before thy father, that he is seeking my life?'

2 And he saith to him, `Far be it! thou dost not die; lo, my father doth not do anything great or small and doth not uncover mine ear; and wherefore doth my father hide from me this thing? this [thing] is not.'

3 And David sweareth again, and saith, `Thy father hath certainly known that I have found grace in thine eyes, and he saith, Let not Jonathan know this, lest he be grieved; and yet, Jehovah liveth, and thy soul liveth, but--as a step between me and death.'

4 And Jonathan saith to David, `What doth thy soul say? --and I do it for thee.'

5 And David saith unto Jonathan, `Lo, the new moon [is] to-morrow; and I do certainly sit with the king to eat; and thou hast sent me away, and I have been hidden in a field till the third evening;

6 if thy father at all look after me, and thou hast said, David asked earnestly of me to run to Beth-Lehem his city, for a sacrifice of the days [is] there for all the family.

7 If thus he say: Good; peace [is] for thy servant; and if it be very displeasing to him-- know that the evil hath been determined by him;

8 and thou hast done kindness, to thy servant, for into a covenant of Jehovah thou hast brought thy servant with thee; --and if there is in me iniquity, put thou me to death; and unto thy father, why is this--thou dost bring me in?'

9 And Jonathan saith, `Far be it from thee! for I certainly do not know that the evil hath been determined by my father to come upon thee, and I do not declare it to thee.'

10 And David saith unto Jonathan, `Who doth declare to me? or what [if] thy father doth answer thee sharply?'

11 And Jonathan saith unto David, `Come, and we go out into the field;' and they go out both of them into the field.

12 And Jonathan saith unto David, `Jehovah, God of Israel--when I search my father, about [this] time to-morrow [or] the third [day], and lo, good [is] towards David, and I do not then send unto thee, and have uncovered thine ear--

13 thus doth Jehovah do to Jonathan, and thus doth He add; when the evil concerning thee is good to my father, then I have uncovered thine ear, and sent thee away, and thou hast gone in peace, and Jehovah is with thee, as he was with my father;

14 and not only while I am alive dost thou do with me the kindness of Jehovah, and I die not,

15 but thou dost not cut off thy kindness from my house unto the age, nor in Jehovah's cutting off the enemies of David, each one from off the face of the ground.'

16 And Jonathan covenanteth with the house of David, and Jehovah hath sought [it] from the hand of the enemies of David;

17 and Jonathan addeth to cause David to swear, because he loveth him, for with the love of his own soul he hath loved him.

18 And Jonathan saith to him, `To-morrow [is] new moon, and thou hast been looked after, for thy seat is looked after;

19 and on the third day thou dost certainly come down, and hast come in unto the place where thou wast hidden in the day of the work, and hast remained near the stone Ezel.

20 `And I shoot three of the arrows at the side, sending out for myself at a mark;

21 and lo, I send the youth: Go, find the arrows. If I at all say to the youth, Lo, the arrows [are] on this side of thee--take them, --then come thou, for peace [is] for thee, and there is nothing; Jehovah liveth.

22 And if thus I say to the young man, Lo, the arrows [are] beyond thee, --go, for Jehovah hath sent thee away;

23 as to the thing which we have spoken, I and thou, lo, Jehovah [is] between me and thee--unto the age.'

24 And David is hidden in the field, and it is the new moon, and the king sitteth down by the food to eat,

25 and the king sitteth on his seat, as time by time, on a seat by the wall, and Jonathan riseth, and Abner sitteth at the side of Saul, and David's place is looked after.

26 And Saul hath not spoken anything on that day, for he said, `It [is] an accident; he is not clean--surely not clean.'

27 And it cometh to pass on the second morrow of the new moon, that David's place is looked after, and Saul saith unto Jonathan his son, `Wherefore hath the son of Jesse not come in, either yesterday or to-day, unto the food?'

28 And Jonathan answereth Saul, `David hath been earnestly asked of me unto Beth- Lehem,

29 and he saith, Send me away, I pray thee, for a family sacrifice we have in the city, and my brother himself hath given command to me, and now, if I have found grace in thine eyes, let me go away, I pray thee, and see my brethren; thereforehe hath not come unto the table of the king.'

30 And the anger of Saul burneth against Jonathan, and he saith to him, `Son of a perverse rebellious woman! have I not known that thou art fixing on the son of Jesse to thy shame, and to the shame of the nakedness of thy mother?

31 for all the days that the son of Jesse liveth on the ground thou art not established, thou and thy kingdom; and now, send and bring him unto me, for he [is] a son of death.'

32 And Jonathan answereth Saul his father, and saith unto him, `Why is he put to death? what hath he done?'

33 And Saul casteth the javelin at him to smite him, and Jonathan knoweth that it hath been determined by his father to put David to death.

34 And Jonathan riseth from the table in the heat of anger, and hath not eaten food on the second day of the new moon, for he hath been grieved for David, for his father put him to shame.

35 And it cometh to pass in the morning, that Jonathan goeth out into the field for the appointment with David, and a little youth [is] with him.

36 And he saith to his youth, `Run, find, I pray thee, the arrows which I am shooting;' the youth is running, and he hath shot the arrow, causing [it] to pass over him.

37 And the youth cometh unto the place of the arrow which Jonathan hath shot, and Jonathan calleth after the youth, and saith, `Is not the arrow beyond thee?'

38 and Jonathan calleth after the youth, `Speed, haste, stand not;' and Jonathan's youth gathereth the arrows, and cometh unto his lord.

39 And the youth hath not known anything, only Jonathan and David knew the word.

40 And Jonathan giveth his weapons unto the youth whom he hath, and saith to him, `Go, carry into the city.'

41 The youth hath gone, and David hath risen from Ezel, at the south, and falleth on his face to the earth, and boweth himself three times, and they kiss one another, and they weep one with another, till David exerted himself;

42 and Jonathan saith to David, `Go in peace, in that we have sworn--we two--in the name of Jehovah, saying, Jehovah is between me and thee, and between my seed and thy seed-- unto the age;' and he riseth and goeth; and Jonathan hath gone in to the city.

1 Samuel 22

1 And David goeth thence, and is escaped unto the cave of Adullam, and his brethren hear, and all the house of his father, and go down unto him thither;

2 and gather themselves unto him do every man in distress, and every man who hath an exactor, and every man bitter in soul, and he is over them for head, and there are with him about four hundred men.

3 And David goeth thence to Mizpeh of Moab, and saith unto the king of Moab, `Let, I pray thee, my father and my mother go out with you, till that I know what God doth for me;'

4 and he leadeth them before the king of Moab, and they dwell with him all the days of David's being in the fortress.

5 And Gad the prophet saith unto David, `Thou dost not abide in a fortress, go, and thou hast entered for thee the land of Judah;' and David goeth and entereth the forest of Hareth.

6 And Saul heareth that David hath become known, and the men who [are] with him, and Saul is abiding in Gibeah, under the grove in Ramah, and his spear [is] in his hand, and all his servants standing by him.

7 And Saul saith to his servants who are standing by him, `Hear, I pray you, ye Benjamites; also to all of you doth the son of Jesse give fields and vineyards! all of you he doth appoint heads of thousands and heads of hundreds!

8 for ye have conspired all of you against me, and there is none uncovering mine ear about my son's covenanting with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you grieving for me, and uncovering mine ear, that my son hath raised up my servant against me, to lie in wait as [at] this day.'

9 And answer doth Doeg the Edomite, who is set over the servants of Saul, and saith, `I have seen the son of Jesse coming in to Nob, unto Ahimelech son of Ahitub,

10 and he asketh for him at Jehovah, and provision hath given to him, and the sword of Goliath the Philistine hath given to him.

11 And the king sendeth to call Ahimelech son of Ahitub, the priest, and all the house of his father, the priests, who [are] in Nob, and they come all of them unto the king;

12 and Saul saith, `Hear, I pray thee, son of Ahitub;' and he saith, `Here [am] I, my lord.'

13 And Saul saith unto him, `Why have ye conspired against me, thou and the son of Jesse, by thy giving to him bread and a sword, and to ask for him at God, to rise against me, to lie in wait, as [at] this day?'

14 And Ahimelech answereth the king and saith, `And who among all thy servants [is] as David--faithful, and son-in-law of the king, and hath turned aside unto thy council, and is honoured in thy house?

15 To-day have I begun to ask for him at God? far be it from me! let not the king lay anything against his servant, against any of the house of my father, for thy servant hath known nothing of all this, less or more.'

16 And the king saith, `Thou dost surely die, Ahimelech, thou, and all the house of thy father.'

17 And the king saith to runners, those standing by him, `Turn round, and put to death the priests of Jehovah, because their hand also [is] with David, and because they have known that he is fleeing, and have not uncovered mine ear;' and the servants of the king have not been willing to put forth their hand to come against the priests of Jehovah.

18 And the king saith to Doeg, `Turn round thou, and come against the priests;' and Doeg the Edomite turneth round, and cometh himself against the priests, and putteth to death in that day eighty and five men bearing a linen ephod,

19 and Nob, the city of the priests, he hath smitten by the mouth of the sword, from man even unto woman, from infant even unto suckling, and ox, and ass, and sheep, by the mouth of the sword.

20 And there escapeth one son of Ahimelech, son of Ahitub, and his name [is] Abiathar, and he fleeth after David,

21 and Abiathar declareth to David that Saul hath slain the priests of Jehovah.

22 And David saith to Abiathar, `I have known on that day when Doeg the Edomite [is] there, that he doth certainly declare [it] to Saul; I have brought [it] round to every person of the house of thy father;

23 dwell with me; fear not; for he who seeketh my life seeketh thy life; for a charge [art] thou with me.'

1 Samuel 23

1 And they declare to David, saying, `Lo, the Philistines are fighting against Keilah, and they are spoiling the threshing-floors.'

2 And David asketh at Jehovah, saying, `Do I go? --and have I smitten among these Philistines?' And Jehovah saith unto David, `Go, and thou hast smitten among the Philistines, and saved Keilah.'

3 And David's men say unto him, `Lo, we here in Judah are afraid; and how much more when we go to Keilah, unto the ranks of the Philistines?'

4 And David addeth again to ask at Jehovah, and Jehovah answereth him, and saith, `Rise, go down to Keilah, for I am giving the Philistines into thy hand.'

5 And David goeth, and his men, to Keilah, and fighteth with the Philistines, and leadeth away their cattle, and smiteth among them--a great smiting, and David saveth the inhabitants of Keilah.

6 And it cometh to pass, in the fleeing of Abiathar son of Ahimelech unto David, to Keilah, an ephod came down in his hand.

7 And it is declared to Saul that David hath come in to Keilah, and Saul saith, `God hath made him known for my hand, for he hath been shut in, to enter into a city of doors and bar.'

8 And Saul summoneth the whole of the people to battle, to go down to Keilah, to lay siege unto David and unto his men.

9 And David knoweth that against him Saul is devising the evil, and saith unto Abiathar the priest, `Bring nigh the ephod.'

10 And David saith, `Jehovah, God of Israel, Thy servant hath certainly heard that Saul is seeking to come in unto Keilah, to destroy the city on mine account.

11 Do the possessors of Keilah shut me up into his hand? doth Saul come down as Thy servant hath heard? Jehovah, God of Israel, declare, I pray Thee, to Thy servant.' And Jehovah saith, `He doth come down.'

12 And David saith, `Do the possessors of Keilah shut me up, and my men, into the hand of Saul?' And Jehovah saith, `They shut [thee] up.'

13 And David riseth--and his men--about six hundred men, and they go out from Keilah, and go up and down where they go up and down; and to Saul it hath been declared that David hath escaped from Keilah, and he ceaseth to go out.

14 And David abideth in the wilderness, in fortresses, and abideth in the hill-country, in the wilderness of Ziph; and Saul seeketh him all the days, and God hath not given him into his hand.

15 And David seeth that Saul hath come out to seek his life, and David [is] in the wilderness of Ziph, in a forest.

16 And Jonathan son of Saul riseth, and goeth unto David to the forest, and strengtheneth his hand in God,

17 and saith unto him, `Fear not, for the hand of Saul my father doth not find thee, and thou dost reign over Israel, and I am to thee for second, and also so knoweth Saul my father.'

18 And they make a covenant both of them before Jehovah; and David abideth in the forest, and Jonathan hath gone to his house.

19 And the Ziphites go up unto Saul to Gibeah, saying, `Is not David hiding himself with us in fortresses, in the forest, in the height of Hachilah, which [is] on the south of the desolate place?

20 And, now, by all the desire of thy soul, O king, to come down, come down, and ours [is] to shut him up into the hand of the king.'

21 And Saul saith, `Blessed [are] ye of Jehovah, for ye have pity on me;

22 go, I pray you, prepare yet, and know and see his place where his foot is; who hath seen him there? for [one] hath said unto me, He is very subtile.

23 And see and know of all the hiding-places where he hideth himself, and ye have turned back unto me prepared, and I have gone with you, and it hath been, if he is in the land, that I have searched him out through all the thousands of Judah.'

24 And they rise and go to Ziph before Saul, and David and his men [are] in the wilderness of Maon, in the plain, at the south of the desolate place.

25 And Saul and his men go to seek, and they declare to David, and he goeth down the rock, and abideth in the wilderness of Maon; and Saul heareth, and pursueth after David [to] the wilderness of Maon.

26 And Saul goeth on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain, and David is hastened to go from the face of Saul, and Saul and his men are compassing David and his men, to catch them.

27 And a messenger hath come in unto Saul, saying, `Haste, and come, for the Philistines have pushed against the land.'

28 And Saul turneth back from pursuing after David, and goeth to meet the Philistines, therefore they have called that place `The Rock of Divisions.'

29 And David goeth up thence, and abideth in fortresses [at] En-gedi.

1 Samuel 24

1 And it cometh to pass when Saul hath turned back from after the Philistines, that they declare to him, saying, `Lo, David [is] in the wilderness of En-gedi.'

2 And Saul taketh three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and goeth to seek David and his men, on the front of the rocks of the wild goats,

3 and he cometh in unto folds of the flock, on the way, and there [is] a cave, and Saul goeth in to cover his feet; and David and his men in the sides of the cave are abiding.

4 And the men of David say unto him, `Lo, the day of which Jehovah said unto thee, Lo, I am giving thine enemy into thy hand, and thou hast done to him as it is good in thine eyes;' and David riseth and cutteth off the skirt of the upper robewhich [is] on Saul--gently.

5 And it cometh to pass afterwards that the heart of David smiteth him, because that he hath cut off the skirt which [is] on Saul,

6 and he saith to his men, `Far be it from me, by Jehovah; I do not do this thing to my lord--to the anointed of Jehovah--to put forth my hand against him, for the anointed of Jehovah he [is].'

7 And David subdueth his men by words, and hath not permitted them to rise against Saul; and Saul hath risen from the cave, and goeth on the way;

8 and David riseth afterwards, and goeth out from the cave, and calleth after Saul, saying, `My lord, O king!' And Saul looketh attentively behind him, and David boweth--face to the earth--and doth obeisance.

9 And David saith to Saul, `Why dost thou hear the words of man, saying, Lo, David is seeking thine evil?

10 Lo, this day have thine eyes seen how that Jehovah hath given thee to-day into my hand in the cave; and [one] said to slay thee, and [mine eye] hath pity on thee, and I say, I do not put forth my hand against my lord, for the anointed of Jehovah he [is].

11 `And, my father, see, yea see the skirt of thine upper robe in my hand; for by cutting off the skirt of thy upper robe, and I have not slain thee, know and see that there is not in my hand evil and transgression, and I have not sinned against thee, and thou art hunting my soul to take it!

12 `Jehovah doth judge between me and thee, and Jehovah hath avenged me of thee, and my hand is not on thee;

13 as saith the simile of the ancients, From the wicked goeth out wickedness, and my hand is not on thee.

14 `After whom hath the king of Israel come out? after whom art thou pursuing? -- after a dead dog! after one flea!

15 And Jehovah hath been for judge, and hath judged between me and thee, yea, he seeth and pleadeth my cause, and doth deliver me out of thy hand.'

16 And it cometh to pass, when David completeth to speak these words unto Saul, that Saul saith, `Is this thy voice, my son David?' and Saul lifteth up his voice, and weepeth.

17 And he saith unto David, `More righteous thou [art] than I; for thou hast done me good, and I have done thee evil;

18 and thou hast declared to-day how that thou hast done good with me, how that Jehovah shut me up into thy hand, and thou didst not slay me,

19 and that a man doth find his enemy, and hath sent him away in a good manner; and Jehovah doth repay thee good for that which thou didst to me this day.

20 `And, now, lo, I have known that thou dost certainly reign, and the kingdom of Israel hath stood in thy hand;

21 and, now, swear to me by Jehovah--thou dost not cut off my seed after me, nor dost thou destroy my name from the house of my father.'

22 And David sweareth to Saul, and Saul goeth unto his house, and David and his men have gone up unto the fortress.

1 Samuel 25

1 And Samuel dieth, and all Israel are gathered, and mourn for him, and bury him in his house, in Ramah; and David riseth and goeth down unto the wilderness of Paran.

2 And [there is] a man in Maon, and his work [is] in Carmel; and the man [is] very great, and he hath three thousand sheep, and a thousand goats; and he is shearing his flock in Carmel.

3 And the name of the man [is] Nabal, and the name of his wife Abigail, and the woman [is] of good understanding, and of fair form, and the man [is] hard and evil [in] doings; and he [is] a Calebite.

4 And David heareth in the wilderness that Nabal is shearing his flock,

5 and David sendeth ten young men, and David saith to the young men, `Go ye up to Carmel, and ye have come in unto Nabal, and asked of him in my name of welfare,

6 and said thus: To life! and thou, peace; and thy house, peace; and all that thou hast-- peace!

7 and, now, I have heard that thou hast shearers; now, the shepherds whom thou hast have been with us, we have not put them to shame, nor hath anything been looked after by them, all the days of their being in Carmel.

8 `Ask thy young men, and they declare to thee, and the young men find grace in thine eyes, for on a good day we have come; give, I pray thee, that which thy hand findeth, to thy servants, and to thy son, to David.'

9 And the young men of David come in, and speak unto Nabal according to all these words, in the name of David--and rest.

10 And Nabal answereth the servants of David and saith, `Who [is] David, and who the son of Jesse? to-day have servants been multiplied who are breaking away each from his master;

11 and I have taken my bread, and my water, and my flesh, which I slaughtered for my shearers, and have given [it] to men whom I have not known whence they [are]!'

12 And the young men of David turn on their way, and turn back, and come in, and declare to him according to all these words.

13 And David saith to his men, `Gird ye on each his sword;' and they gird on each his sword, and David also girdeth on his sword, and there go up after David about four hundred men, and two hundred have remained by the vessels.

14 And to Abigail wife of Nabal hath one young man of the youths declared, saying, `Lo, David hath sent messengers out of the wilderness to bless our lord, and he flieth upon them;

15 and the men [are] very good to us, and have not put us to shame, and we have not looked after anything all the days we have gone up and down with them, in our being in the field;

16 a wall they have been unto us both by night and by day, all the days of our being with them, feeding the flock.

17 `And, now, know and consider what thou dost; for evil hath been determined against our lord, and against all his house, and he [is] too much a son of worthlessness to be spoken to.'

18 And Abigail hasteth, and taketh two hundred loaves, and two bottles of wine, and five sheep, prepared, and five measures of roasted corn, and a hundred bunches of raisins, and two hundred bunches of figs, and setteth [them] on the asses.

19 And she saith to her young men, `Pass over before me; lo, after you I am coming;' and to her husband Nabal she hath not declared [it];

20 and it hath come to pass, she is riding on the ass and is coming down in the secret part of the hill-country, and lo, David and his men are coming down to meet her, and she meeteth them.

21 And David said, `Only, in vain I have kept all that this [one] hath in the wilderness, and nothing hath been looked after of all that he hath, and he turneth back to me evil for good;

22 thus doth God do to the enemies of David, and thus He doth add, if I leave of all that he hath till the light of the morning--of those sitting on the wall.'

23 And Abigail seeth David, and hasteth and cometh down from off the ass, and falleth before David on her face, and boweth herself to the earth,

24 and falleth at his feet and saith, `On me, my lord, the iniquity; and let, I pray thee, thy handmaid speak in thine ear, and hear the words of thy handmaid.

25 `Let not, I pray thee, my lord set his heart to this man of worthlessness, on Nabal, for as his name [is] so [is] he; Nabal [is] his name, and folly [is] with him; and I, thine handmaid, did not see the young men of my lord whom thou didstsend;

26 and now, my lord, Jehovah liveth, and thy soul liveth, in that Jehovah hath withheld thee from coming in with blood, and to save thy hand to thee--now let thine enemies be as Nabal, even those seeking evil unto my lord.

27 `And, now, this blessing which thy maid-servant hath brought to my lord--it hath been given to the young men who are going up and down at the feet of my lord.

28 `Bear, I pray thee, with the transgression of thy handmaid, for Jehovah doth certainly make to my lord a stedfast house; for the battles of Jehovah hath my lord fought, and evil is not found in thee [all] thy days.

29 And man riseth to pursue thee and to seek thy soul, and the soul of my lord hath been bound in the bundle of life with Jehovah thy God; as to the soul of thine enemies, He doth sling them out in the midst of the hollow of the sling.

30 `And it hath been, when Jehovah doth to my lord according to all the good which He hath spoken concerning thee, and appointed thee for leader over Israel,

31 that this is not to thee for a stumbling-block, and for an offence of heart to my lord--either to shed blood for nought, or my lord's restraining himself; and Jehovah hath done good to my lord, and thou hast remembered thy handmaid.'

32 And David saith to Abigail, `Blessed [is] Jehovah, God of Israel, who hath sent thee this day to meet me,

33 and blessed [is] thy discretion, and blessed [art] thou in that thou hast restrained me this day from coming in with blood, and to restrain my hand to myself.

34 And yet, Jehovah liveth, God of Israel, who hath kept me back from doing evil with thee, for unless thou hadst hasted, and dost come to meet me, surely there had not been left to Nabal till the light of the morning, of those sitting on thewall.'

35 And David receiveth from her hand that which she hath brought to him, and to her he hath said, `Go up in peace to thy house; see, I have hearkened to thy voice, and accept thy face.'

36 And Abigail cometh in unto Nabal, and lo, he hath a banquet in his house, like a banquet of the king, and the heart of Nabal [is] glad within him, and he [is] drunk unto excess, and she hath not declared to him anything, less or more, till the light of the morning.

37 And it cometh to pass in the morning, when the wine is gone out from Nabal, that his wife declareth to him these things, and his heart dieth within him, and he hath been as a stone.

38 And it cometh to pass, [in] about ten days, that Jehovah smiteth Nabal, and he dieth,

39 and David heareth that Nabal [is] dead, and saith, `Blessed [is] Jehovah who hath pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and His servant hath kept back from evil, and the wickedness of Nabal hath Jehovah turned back on his own head;' and David sendeth and speaketh with Abigail, to take her to him for a wife.

40 And the servants of David come in unto Abigail at Carmel, and speak unto her, saying, `David hath sent us unto thee to take thee to him for a wife.'

41 And she riseth and boweth herself--face to the earth--and saith, `Lo, thy handmaid [is] for a maid-servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.'

42 And Abigail hasteth and riseth, and rideth on the ass; and five of her young women who are going at her feet; and she goeth after the messengers of David, and is to him for a wife.

43 And Ahinoam hath David taken from Jezreel, and they are--even both of them--to him for wives;

44 and Saul gave Michal his daughter, wife to David, to Phalti son of Laish, who [is] of Gallim.

2 Samuel 1

1 And it cometh to pass, after the death of Saul, that David hath returned from smiting the Amalekite, and David dwelleth in Ziklag two days,

2 and it cometh to pass, on the third day, that lo, a man hath come in out of the camp from Saul, and his garments [are] rent, and earth on his head; and it cometh to pass, in his coming in unto David, that he falleth to the earth, and doth obeisance.

3 And David saith to him, `Whence comest thou?' and he saith unto him, `Out of the camp of Israel I have escaped.'

4 And David saith unto him, `What hath been the matter? declare, I pray thee, to me.' And he saith, that `The people hath fled from the battle, and also a multitude hath fallen of the people, and they die; and also Saul and Jonathan his son have died.'

5 And David saith unto the youth who is declaring [it] to him, `How hast thou known that Saul and Jonathan his son [are] dead?'

6 And the youth who is declaring [it] to him saith, I happened to meet in mount Gilboa, and lo, Saul is leaning on his spear; and lo, the chariots and those possessing horses have followed him;

7 and he turneth behind him, and seeth me, and calleth unto me, and I say, Here [am] I.

8 And he saith to me, Who [art] thou? and I say unto him, An Amalekite I [am].'

9 `And he saith unto me, Stand, I pray thee, over me, and put me to death, for seized me hath the arrow, for all my soul [is] still in me.

10 And I stand over him, and put him to death, for I knew that he doth not live after his falling, and I take the crown which [is] on his head, and the bracelet which [is] on his arm, and bring them in unto my lord hither.'

11 And David taketh hold on his garments, and rendeth them, and also all the men who [are] with him,

12 and they mourn, and weep, and fast till the evening, for Saul, and for Jonathan his son, and for the people of Jehovah, and for the house of Israel, because they have fallen by the sword.

13 And David saith unto the youth who is declaring [it] to him, `Whence [art] thou?' and he saith, `Son of a sojourner, an Amalekite, I [am].'

14 And David saith unto him, `How wast thou not afraid to put forth thy hand to destroy the anointed of Jehovah?'

15 And David calleth to one of the youths, and saith, `Draw nigh--fall upon him;' and he smiteth him, and he dieth;

16 and David saith unto him, `Thy blood [is] on thine own head, for thy mouth hath testified against thee, saying, I--I put to death the anointed of Jehovah.'

17 And David lamenteth with this lamentation over Saul, and over Jonathan his son;

18 and he saith to teach the sons of Judah `The Bow;' lo, it is written on the book of the Upright: --

19 `The Roebuck, O Israel, On thy high places [is] wounded; How have the mighty fallen!

20 Declare [it] not in Gath, Proclaim not the tidings in the streets of Ashkelon, Lest they rejoice--The daughters of the Philistines, Lest they exult--The daughters of the Uncircumcised!

21 Mountains of Gilboa! No dew nor rain be on you, And fields of heave-offerings! For there hath become loathsome The shield of the mighty, The shield of Saul--without the anointed with oil.

22 From the blood of the wounded, From the fat of the mighty, The bow of Jonathan Hath not turned backward; And the sword of Saul doth not return empty.

23 Saul and Jonathan! They are loved and pleasant in their lives, And in their death they have not been parted. Than eagles they have been lighter, Than lions they have been mightier!

24 Daughters of Israel! for Saul weep ye, Who is clothing you [in] scarlet with delights. Who is lifting up ornaments of gold on your clothing.

25 How have the mighty fallen In the midst of the battle! Jonathan! on thy high places wounded!

26 I am in distress for thee, my brother Jonathan, Very pleasant wast thou to me; Wonderful was thy love to me, Above the love of women!

27 How have the mighty fallen, Yea, the weapons of war perish!'

2 Samuel 3

1 And the war is long between the house of Saul and the house of David, and David is going on and [is] strong, and the house of Saul are going on and [are] weak.

2 And there are born to David sons in Hebron, and his first-born is Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess,

3 and his second [is] Chileab, of Abigail wife of Nabal the Carmelite, and the third [is] Absalom son of Maacah daughter of Talmai king of Geshur,

4 and the fourth [is] Adonijah son of Haggith, and the fifth [is] Shephatiah son of Abital,

5 and the sixth [is] Ithream, of Eglah wife of David; these have been born to David in Hebron.

6 And it cometh to pass, in the war being between the house of Saul and the house of David, that Abner hath been strengthening himself in the house of Saul,

7 and Saul hath a concubine, and her name [is] Rizpah daughter of Aiah, and [Ish- Bosheth] saith unto Abner, `Wherefore hast thou gone in unto the concubine of my father?'

8 And it is displeasing to Abner exceedingly, because of the words of Ish-Bosheth, and he saith, `The head of a dog [am] I--that in reference to Judah to-day I do kindness with the house of Saul thy father, unto his brethren, and unto his friends, and have not delivered thee into the hand of David--that thou chargest against me iniquity concerning the woman to-day?

9 thus doth God to Abner, and thus He doth add to him, surely as Jehovah hath sworn to David--surely so I do to him:

10 to cause the kingdom to pass over from the house of Saul, and to raise up the throne of David over Israel, and over Judah, from Dan even unto Beer-Sheba.'

11 And he is not able any more to turn back Abner a word, because of his fearing him.

12 And Abner sendeth messengers unto David for himself, saying, `Whose [is] the land?' saying, `Make thy covenant with me, and lo, my hand [is] with thee, to bring round unto thee all Israel.'

13 And he saith, `Good--I make with thee a covenant; only, one thing I am asking of thee, that is, Thou dost not see my face, except thou dost first bring in Michal, daughter of Saul in thy coming into see my face.'

14 And David sendeth messengers unto Ish-Bosheth son of Saul, saying, `Give up my wife Michal, whom I betrothed to myself with a hundred foreskins of the Philistines.'

15 And Ish-Bosheth sendeth, and taketh her from a man, from Phaltiel son of Laish,

16 and her husband goeth with her, going on and weeping behind her, unto Bahurim, and Abner saith unto him, `Go, turn back;' and he turneth back.

17 And the word of Abner was with the elders of Israel, saying, `Heretofore ye have been seeking David for king over you,

18 and now, do [it], for Jehovah hath spoken of David saying, By the hand of David my servant--to save My people Israel out of the hand of the Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies.'

19 And Abner speaketh also in the ears of Benjamin, and Abner goeth also to speak in the ears of David in Hebron all that [is] good in the eyes of Israel, and in the eyes of all the house of Benjamin,

20 and Abner cometh in unto David, to Hebron, and with him twenty men, and David maketh for Abner, and for the men who [are] with him, a banquet.

21 And Abner saith unto David, `I arise, and go, and gather unto my lord the king the whole of Israel, and they make with thee a covenant, and thou hast reigned over all that thy soul desireth;' and David sendeth away Abner, and he goeth in peace.

22 And lo, the servants of David, and Joab, have come from the troop, and much spoil have brought with them, and Abner is not with David in Hebron, for he hath sent him away, and he goeth in peace;

23 and Joab and all the host that [is] with him have come, and they declare to Joab, saying, `Abner son of Ner hath come unto the king, and he sendeth him away, and he goeth in peace.'

24 And Joab cometh unto the king, and saith, `What hast thou done? lo, Abner hath come unto thee! why [is] this--thou hast sent him away, and he is really gone?

25 Thou hast known Abner son of Ner, that to deceive thee he came, and to know thy going out and thy coming in, and to know all that thou art doing.'

26 And Joab goeth out from David, and sendeth messengers after Abner, and they bring him back from the well of Sirah, and David knew not.

27 And Abner turneth back to Hebron, and Joab turneth him aside unto the midst of the gate to speak with him quietly, and smiteth him there in the fifth [rib] --and he dieth--for the blood of Asahel his brother.

28 And David heareth afterwards and saith, `Acquitted [am] I, and my kingdom, by Jehovah, unto the age, from the blood of Abner son of Ner;

29 it doth stay on the head of Joab, and on all the house of his father, and there is not cut off from the house of Joab one having an issue, and leprous, and laying hold on a staff, and falling by a sword, and lacking bread.'

30 And Joab and Abishai his brother slew Abner because that he put to death Asahel their brother, in Gibeon, in battle.

31 And David saith unto Joab, and unto all the people who [are] with him, `Rend your garments, and gird on sackcloth, and mourn before Abner;' and king David is going after the bier.

32 And they bury Abner in Hebron, and the king lifteth up his voice, and weepeth at the grave of Abner, and all the people weep;

33 and the king lamenteth for Abner, and saith: --`As the death of a fool doth Abner die?

34 Thy hands not bound, And thy feet to fetters not brought nigh! As one falling before sons of evil--Thou hast fallen!' and all the people add to weep over him.

35 And all the people come to cause David to eat bread while yet day, and David sweareth, saying, `Thus doth God to me, and thus He doth add, for--before the going in of the sun, I taste no bread or any other thing.'

36 And all the people have discerned [it], and it is good in their eyes, as all that the king hath done is good in the eyes of all the people;

37 and all the people know, even all Israel, in that day, that it hath not been from the king--to put to death Abner son of Ner.

38 And the king saith unto his servants, `Do ye not know that a prince and a great one hath fallen this day in Israel?

39 and I to-day [am] tender, and an anointed king: and these men, sons of Zeruiah, [are] too hard for me; Jehovah doth recompense to the doer of the evil according to his evil.'

2 Samuel 5

1 And all the tribes of Israel come unto David, to Hebron, and speak, saying, `Lo, we [are] thy bone and thy flesh;

2 also heretofore, in Saul's being king over us, thou hast been he who is bringing out and bringing in Israel, and Jehovah saith to thee, Thou dost feed My people Israel, and thou art for leader over Israel.'

3 And all the elders of Israel come unto the king, to Hebron, and king David maketh with them a covenant in Hebron before Jehovah, and they anoint David for king over Israel.

4 A son of thirty years [is] David in his being king; forty years he hath reigned;

5 in Hebron he reigned over Judah seven years and six months, and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty and three years, over all Israel and Judah.

6 And the king goeth, and his men, to Jerusalem, unto the Jebusite, the inhabitant of the land, and they speak to David, saying, `Thou dost not come in hither, except thou turn aside the blind and the lame;' saying, `David doth not come in hither.'

7 And David captureth the fortress of Zion, it [is] the city of David.

8 And David saith on that day, `Any one smiting the Jebusite, (let him go up by the watercourse), and the lame and the blind--the hated of David's soul,' --because the blind and lame say, `He doth not come into the house.'

9 And David dwelleth in the fortress, and calleth it--City of David, and David buildeth round about, from Millo and inward,

10 and David goeth, going on and becoming great, and Jehovah, God of Hosts, [is] with him.

11 And Hiram king of Tyre sendeth messengers unto David, and cedar-trees, and artificers of wood, and artificers of stone, for walls, and they build a house for David,

12 and David knoweth that Jehovah hath established him for king over Israel, and that He hath lifted up his kingdom, because of His people Israel.

13 And David taketh again concubines and wives out of Jerusalem, after his coming from Hebron, and there are born again to David sons and daughters.

14 And these [are] the names of those born to him in Jerusalem: Shammuah, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon,

15 and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Nepheg, and Japhia,

16 and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphalet.

17 And the Philistines hear that they have anointed David for king over Israel, and all the Philistines come up to seek David, and David heareth, and goeth down unto the fortress,

18 and the Philistines have come, and are spread out in the valley of Rephaim.

19 And David asketh of Jehovah, saying, `Do I go up unto the Philistines? dost Thou give them into my hand?' And Jehovah saith unto David, `Go up, for I certainly give the Philistines into thy hand.'

20 And David cometh in to Baal-Perazim, and David smiteth them there, and saith, `Jehovah hath broken forth [on] mine enemies before me, as the breaking forth of waters;' therefore he hath called the name of that place Baal-Perazim.

21 And they forsake there their idols, and David and his men lift them up.

22 And the Philistines add again to come up, and are spread out in the valley of Rephaim,

23 and David asketh of Jehovah, and He saith, `Thou dost not go up, turn round unto their rear, and thou hast come to them over-against the mulberries,

24 and it cometh to pass, in thy hearing the sound of a stepping in the tops of the mulberries, then thou dost move sharply, for then hath Jehovah gone out before thee to smite in the camp of the Philistines.'

25 And David doth so, as Jehovah commanded him, and smiteth the Philistines from Geba unto thy coming to Gazer.

2 Samuel 7

1 And it cometh to pass, when the king sat in his house, and Jehovah hath given rest to him round about, from all his enemies,

2 that the king saith unto Nathan the prophet, `See, I pray thee, I am dwelling in a house of cedars, and the ark of God is dwelling in the midst of the curtain.'

3 And Nathan saith unto the king, `All that [is] in thine heart--go, do, for Jehovah [is] with thee.'

4 And it cometh to pass in that night, that the word of Jehovah is unto Nathan, saying,

5 `Go, and thou hast said unto My servant, unto David, Thus said Jehovah, Dost thou build for Me a house for My dwelling in?

6 for I have not dwelt in a house even from the day of My bringing up the sons of Israel out of Egypt, even unto this day, and am walking up and down in a tent and in a tabernacle.

7 During all [the time] that I have walked up and down among all the sons of Israel, a word have I spoken with one of the tribes of Israel which I commanded to feed my people Israel, saying, `Why have ye not built to Me a house of cedars?

8 and now, thus dost thou say to My servant, to David: `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, I have taken thee from the comely place, from after the flock, to be leader over My people, over Israel;

9 and I am with thee whithersoever thou hast gone, and I cut off all thine enemies from thy presence, and have made for thee a great name, as the name of the great ones who [are] in the earth,

10 and I have appointed a place for My people, for Israel, and have planted it, and it hath tabernacled in its place, and it is not troubled any more, and the sons of perverseness do not add to afflict it any more, as in the beginning,

11 even from the day that I appointed judges over My people Israel; and I have given rest to thee from all thine enemies, and Jehovah hath declared to thee that Jehovah doth make for thee a house.

12 `When thy days are full, and thou hast lain with thy fathers, then I have raised up thy seed after thee which goeth out from thy bowels, and have established his kingdom;

13 He doth build a house for My Name, and I have established the throne of his kingdom unto the age.

14 I am to him for a father, and he is to Me for a son; whom in his dealings perversely I have even reproved with a rod of men, and with strokes of the sons of Adam,

15 and My kindness doth not turn aside from him, as I turned it aside from Saul, whom I turned aside from before thee,

16 and stedfast [is] thy house and thy kingdom unto the age before thee, thy throne is established unto the age.'

17 According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so spake Nathan unto David.

18 And king David cometh in and sitteth before Jehovah, and saith, `Who [am] I, Lord Jehovah? and what my house, that Thou hast brought me hitherto?

19 And yet this [is] little in Thine eyes, Lord Jehovah, and Thou dost speak also concerning the house of Thy servant afar off; and this [is] the law of the Man, Lord Jehovah.

20 And what doth David add more to speak unto Thee? and Thou, Thou hast known Thy servant, Lord Jehovah.

21 Because of Thy word, and according to Thy heart, Thou hast done all this greatness, to cause Thy servant to know [it].

22 Therefore Thou hast been great, Jehovah God, for there is none like Thee, and there is no God save Thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears.

23 `And who [is] as Thy people, as Israel--one nation in the earth, whom God hath gone to redeem to Him for a people, and to make for Him a name--and to do for you the greatness-- even fearful things for Thy land, at the presence of Thy people,whom Thou hast redeemed to Thee out of Egypt--[among the] nations and their gods?

24 Yea, Thou dost establish to Thee Thy people Israel, to Thee for a people unto the age, and Thou, Jehovah, hast been to them for God.

25 `And now, Jehovah God, the word which Thou hast spoken concerning Thy servant, and concerning his house, establish unto the age, and do as Thou hast spoken;

26 And Thy Name is great unto the age, saying, Jehovah of Hosts [is] God over Israel, and the house of Thy servant David is established before Thee,

27 For Thou, Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, Thou hast uncovered the ear of Thy servant, saying, A house I build for thee, therefore hath Thy servant found his heart to pray unto Thee this prayer;

28 And now, Lord Jehovah, Thou [art] God Himself, and Thy words are truth, and Thou speakest unto Thy servant this goodness,

29 And now, begin and bless the house of Thy servant, to be unto the age before Thee, for Thou, Lord Jehovah, hast spoken, and by Thy blessing is the house of Thy servant blessed--to the age.'

2 Samuel 11

1 And it cometh to pass, at the revolution of the year--at the time of the going out of the messengers--that David sendeth Joab, and his servants with him, and all Israel, and they destroy the Bene-Ammon, and lay siege against Rabbah. And David is dwelling in Jerusalem,

2 and it cometh to pass, at evening-time, that David riseth from off his couch, and walketh up and down on the roof of the king's house, and seeth from the roof a woman bathing, and the woman [is] of very good appearance,

3 and David sendeth and inquireth about the woman, and saith, `Is not this Bath- Sheba, daughter of Eliam, wife of Uriah the Hittite?'

4 And David sendeth messengers, and taketh her, and she cometh unto him, and he lieth with her--and she is purifying herself from her uncleanness--and she turneth back unto her house;

5 and the woman conceiveth, and sendeth, and declareth to David, and saith, `I [am] conceiving.'

6 And David sendeth unto Joab, `Send unto me Uriah the Hittite,' and Joab sendeth Uriah unto David;

7 and Uriah cometh unto him, and David asketh of the prosperity of Joab, and of the prosperity of the people, and of the prosperity of the war.

8 And David saith to Uriah, `Go down to thy house, and wash thy feet;' and Uriah goeth out of the king's house, and there goeth out after him a gift from the king,

9 and Uriah lieth down at the opening of the king's house, with all the servants of his lord, and hath not gone down unto his house.

10 And they declare to David, saying, `Uriah hath not gone down unto his house;' and David saith unto Uriah, `Hast thou not come from a journey? wherefore hast thou not gone down unto thy house?'

11 And Uriah saith unto David, `The ark, and Israel, and Judah, are abiding in booths, and my lord Joab, and the servants of my lord, on the face of the field are encamping; and I--I go in unto my house to eat and to drink, and to lie with mywife! --thy life, and the life of thy soul--if I do this thing.'

12 And David saith unto Uriah, `Abide in this [place] also to-day, and to-morrow I send thee away;' and Uriah abideth in Jerusalem, on that day, and on the morrow,

13 and David calleth for him, and he eateth before him, and drinketh, and he causeth him to drink, and he goeth out in the evening to lie on his couch with the servants of his lord, and unto his house he hath not gone down.

14 And it cometh to pass in the morning, that David writeth a letter unto Joab, and sendeth by the hand of Uriah;

15 and he writeth in the letter, saying, `Place ye Uriah over-against the front of the severest battle, and ye have turned back from after him, and he hath been smitten, and hath died.'

16 And it cometh to pass in Joab's watching of the city, that he appointeth Uriah unto the place where he knew that valiant men [are];

17 and the men of the city go out and fight with Joab, and there fall [some] of the people, of the servants of David; and there dieth also Uriah the Hittite.

18 And Joab sendeth and declareth to David all the matters of the war,

19 and commandeth the messenger, saying, `At thy finishing all the matters of the war to speak unto the king,

20 then, it hath been, if the king's fury ascend, and he hath said to thee, Wherefore did ye draw nigh unto the city to fight? did ye not know that they shoot from off the wall?

21 Who smote Abimelech son of Jerubbesheth? did not a woman cast on him a piece of a rider from the wall, and he dieth in Thebez? why drew ye nigh unto the wall? that thou hast said, Also thy servant Uriah the Hittite is dead.'

22 And the messenger goeth, and cometh in, and declareth to David all that with which Joab sent him,

23 and the messenger saith unto David, `Surely the men have been mighty against us, and come out unto us into the field, and we are upon them unto the opening of the gate,

24 and those shooting shoot at thy servants from off the wall, and [some] of the servants of the king are dead, and also, thy servant Uriah the Hittite is dead.

25 And David saith unto the messenger, `Thus dost thou say unto Joab, Let not this thing be evil in thine eyes; for thus and thus doth the sword devour; strengthen thy warfare against the city, and throw it down--and strengthen thou him.'

26 And the wife of Uriah heareth that Uriah her husband [is] dead, and lamenteth for her lord;

27 and the mourning passeth by, and David sendeth and gathereth her unto his house, and she is to him for a wife, and beareth to him a son; and the thing which David hath done is evil in the eyes of Jehovah.

2 Samuel 13

1 And it cometh to pass afterwards that Absalom son of David hath a fair sister, and her name [is] Tamar, and Amnon son of David loveth her.

2 And Amnon hath distress--even to become sick, because of Tamar his sister, for she [is] a virgin, and it is hard in the eyes of Amnon to do anything to her.

3 And Amnon hath a friend, and his name [is] Jonadab, son of Shimeah, David's brother, and Jonadab [is] a very wise man,

4 and saith to him, `Wherefore [art] thou thus lean, O king's son, morning by morning? dost thou not declare to me?' And Amnon saith to him, `Tamar--sister of Absalom my brother--I am loving.'

5 And Jonadab saith to him, `Lie down on thy couch, and feign thyself sick, and thy father hath come in to see thee, and thou hast said unto him, `Let, I pray thee, Tamar my sister come in and give me bread to eat; and she hath made the food before mine eyes so that I see [it], and have eaten from her hand.'

6 And Amnon lieth down, and feigneth himself sick, and the king cometh in to see him, and Amnon saith unto the king, `Let, I pray thee, Tamar my sister come, and she maketh before mine eyes two cakes, and I eat from her hand.'

7 And David sendeth unto Tamar, to the house, saying, `Go, I pray thee, to the house of Amnon thy brother, and make for him food.'

8 And Tamar goeth to the house of Amnon her brother, and he is lying down, and she taketh the dough, and kneadeth, and maketh cakes before his eyes, and cooketh the cakes,

9 and taketh the frying-pan, and poureth out before him, and he refuseth to eat, and Amnon saith, `Take ye out every one from me;' and they go out every one from him.

10 And Amnon saith unto Tamar, `Bring the food into the inner chamber, and I eat from thy hand;' and Tamar taketh the cakes that she hath made, and bringeth in to Amnon her brother, into the inner chamber,

11 and she bringeth nigh unto him to eat, and he layeth hold on her, and saith to her, `Come, lie with me, my sister.'

12 And she saith to him, `Nay, my brother, do not humble me, for it is not done so in Israel; do not this folly.

13 And I--whither do I cause my reproach to go? and thou--thou art as one of the fools in Israel; and now, speak, I pray thee, unto the king; for he doth not withhold me from thee.'

14 And he hath not been willing to hearken to her voice, and is stronger than she, and humbleth her, and lieth with her.

15 And Amnon hateth her--a very great hatred--that greater [is] the hatred with which he hath hated her than the love with which he loved her, and Amnon saith to her, `Rise, go.'

16 And she saith to him, `Because of the circumstances this evil is greater than the other that thou hast done with me--to send me away;' and he hath not been willing to hearken to her,

17 and calleth his young man, his servant, and saith, `Send away, I pray thee, this one from me without, and bolt the door after her;'

18 --and upon her [is] a long coat, for such upper robes do daughters of the king who [are] virgins put on, --and his servant taketh her out without, and hath bolted the door after her.

19 And Tamar taketh ashes for her head, and the long coat that [is] on her she hath rent, and putteth her hand on her head, and goeth, going on and crying;

20 and Absalom her brother saith unto her, `Hath Amnon thy brother been with thee? and now, my sister, keep silent, he [is] thy brother; set not thy heart to this thing;' and Tamar dwelleth--but desolate--in the house of Absalom her brother.

21 And king David hath heard all these things, and it is very displeasing to him;

22 and Absalom hath not spoken with Amnon either evil or good, for Absalom is hating Amnon, because that he humbled Tamar his sister.

23 And it cometh to pass, after two years of days, that Absalom hath shearers in Baal- Hazor, which [is] with Ephraim, and Absalom calleth for all the sons of the king.

24 And Absalom cometh unto the king, and saith, `Lo, I pray thee, thy servant hath shearers, let the king go, I pray thee, and his servants, with thy servant.'

25 And the king saith unto Absalom, `Nay, my son, let us not all go, I pray thee, and we are not too heavy on thee;' and he presseth on him, and he hath not been willing to go, and he blesseth him.

26 And Absalom saith, `If not--let, I pray thee, Amnon my brother go with us;' and the king saith to him, `Why doth he go with thee?'

27 and Absalom urgeth on him, and he sendeth with him Amnon, and all the sons of the king.

28 And Absalom commandeth his young men, saying, `See, I pray thee, when the heart of Amnon [is] glad with wine, and I have said unto you, Smite Amnon, that ye have put him to death; fear not; is it not because I have commanded you? be strong, yea, become sons of valour.'

29 And the young men of Absalom do to Amnon as Absalom commanded, and rise do all the sons of the king, and they ride, each on his mule, and flee.

30 And it cometh to pass--they [are] in the way--and the report hath come unto David, saying, `Absalom hath smitten all the sons of the king, and there is not left of them one;'

31 and the king riseth, and rendeth his garments, and lieth on the earth, and all his servants are standing by [with] rent garments.

32 And Jonadab son of Shimeah, David's brother, answereth and saith, `Let not my lord say, The whole of the young men, the sons of the king, they have put to death; for Amnon alone [is] dead, for by the command of Absalom it hath been appointed from the day of his humbling Tamar his sister;

33 and now, let not my lord the king lay unto his heart the word, saying, All the sons of the king have died, for Amnon alone [is] dead.'

34 And Absalom fleeth, and the young man who is watching lifteth up his eyes and looketh, and lo, much people are coming by the way behind him, on the side of the hill.

35 And Jonadab saith unto the king, `Lo, the sons of the king have come; as the word of thy servant, so it hath been.'

36 And it cometh to pass at his finishing to speak, that lo, the sons of the king have come, and they lift up their voice, and weep, and also the king and all his servants have wept--a very great weeping.

37 And Absalom hath fled, and goeth unto Talmai, son of Ammihud, king of Geshur, and [David] mourneth for his son all the days.

38 And Absalom hath fled, and goeth to Geshur, and is there three years;

39 and [the soul of] king David determineth to go out unto Absalom, for he hath been comforted for Amnon, for [he is] dead.

2 Samuel 16

1 And David hath passed on a little from the top, and lo, Ziba, servant of Mephibosheth--to meet him, and a couple of asses saddled, and upon them two hundred loaves, and a hundred bunches of raisins, and a hundred [of] summer-fruit, and a bottle of wine.

2 And the king saith unto Ziba, `What--these to thee?' and Ziba saith, `The asses for the household of the king to ride on, and the bread and the summer-fruit for the young men to eat, and the wine for the wearied to drink in the wilderness.'

3 And the king saith, `And where [is] the son of thy lord?' and Ziba saith unto the king, `Lo, he is abiding in Jerusalem, for he said, To-day do the house of Israel give back to me the kingdom of my father.'

4 And the king saith to Ziba, `Lo, thine [are] all that Mephibosheth hath;' and Ziba saith, `I have bowed myself--I find grace in thine eyes, my lord, O king.'

5 And king David hath come in unto Bahurim, and lo, thence a man is coming out, of the family of the house of Saul, and his name [is] Shimei, son of Gera, he cometh out, coming out and reviling;

6 and he stoneth David with stones, and all the servants of king David, and all the people, and all the mighty men on his right and on his left.

7 And thus said Shimei in his reviling, `Go out, go out, O man of blood, and man of worthlessness!

8 Jehovah hath turned back on thee all the blood of the house of Saul, in whose stead thou hast reigned, and Jehovah doth give the kingdom in to the hand of Absalom thy son; and lo, thou [art] in thine evil, for a man of blood thou [art].'

9 And Abishai son of Zeruiah saith unto the king, `Why doth this dead dog revile my lord the king? let me pass over, I pray thee, and I turn aside his head.'

10 And the king saith, `What--to me and to you, O sons of Zeruiah? for--let him revile; even because Jehovah hath said to him, Revile David; and who saith, Wherefore hast Thou done so?'

11 And David saith unto Abishai, and unto all his servants, `Lo, my son who came out of my bowels is seeking my life, and also surely now the Benjamite; leave him alone, and let him revile, for Jehovah hath said [so] to him;

12 it may be Jehovah doth look on mine affliction, and Jehovah hath turned back to me good for his reviling this day.'

13 And David goeth with his men in the way, and Shimei is going at the side of the hill over-against him, going on, and he revileth, and stoneth with stones over-against him, and hath dusted with dust.

14 And the king cometh in, and all the people who [are] with him, wearied, and they are refreshed there.

15 And Absalom and all the people, the men of Israel, have come in to Jerusalem, and Ahithophel with him,

16 and it cometh to pass, when Hushai the Archite, David's friend, hath come unto Absalom, that Hushai saith unto Absalom, `Let the king live! let the king live!'

17 And Absalom saith unto Hushai, `This thy kindness with thy friend! why hast thou not gone with thy friend?'

18 And Hushai saith unto Absalom, `Nay, for he whom Jehovah hath chosen, and this people, even all the men of Israel, his I am, and with him I abide;

19 and secondly, for whom do I labour? is it not before his son? as I served before thy father so am I before thee.'

20 And Absalom saith unto Ahithophel, `Give for you counsel what we do.'

21 And Ahithophel saith unto Absalom, `Go in unto the concubines of thy father, whom he left to keep the house, and all Israel hath heard that thou hast been abhorred by thy father, and the hands of all who [are] with thee have been strong.'

22 And they spread out for Absalom the tent on the roof, and Absalom goeth in unto the concubines of his father before the eyes of all Israel.

23 And the counsel of Ahithophel which he counselled in those days [is] as [when] one inquireth at the word of God; so [is] all the counsel of Ahithophel both to David and to Absalom.

2 Samuel 22

1 And David speaketh to Jehovah the words of this song in the day Jehovah hath delivered him out of the hand of all his enemies, and out of the hand of Saul,

2 and he saith: `Jehovah [is] my rock, And my bulwark, and a deliverer to me,

3 My God [is] my rock--I take refuge in Him; My shield, and the horn of my salvation, My high tower, and my refuge! My Saviour, from violence Thou savest me!

4 The Praised One, I call Jehovah: And from mine enemies I am saved.

5 When the breakers of death compassed me, The streams of the worthless terrify me,

6 The cords of Sheol have surrounded me, Before me have been the snares of death.

7 In mine adversity I call Jehovah, And unto my God I call, And He heareth from His temple my voice, And my cry [is] in His ears,

8 And shake and tremble doth the earth, Foundations of the heavens are troubled, And are shaken, for He hath wrath!

9 Gone up hath smoke by His nostrils. And fire from His mouth devoureth, Brands have been kindled by it.

10 And He inclineth heaven, and cometh down, And thick darkness [is] under His feet.

11 And He rideth on a cherub, and doth fly, And is seen on the wings of the wind.

12 And He setteth darkness Round about Him--tabernacles, Darkness of waters--thick clouds of the skies.

13 From the brightness before Him Were brands of fire kindled!

14 Thunder from the heavens doth Jehovah, And the Most High giveth forth His voice.

15 And He sendeth forth arrows, And scattereth them; Lightning, and troubleth them;

16 And seen are the streams of the sea, Revealed are foundations of the world, By the rebuke of Jehovah, From the breath of the spirit of His anger.

17 He sendeth from above--He taketh me, He draweth me out of many waters.

18 He delivereth me from my strong enemy, From those hating me, For they were stronger than I.

19 They are before me in a day of my calamity, And Jehovah is my support,

20 And He bringeth me out to a large place, He draweth me out for He delighted in me.

21 Jehovah recompenseth me, According to my righteousness, According to the cleanness of my hands, He doth return to me.

22 For I have kept the ways of Jehovah, And have not done wickedly against my God.

23 For all His judgments [are] before me, As to His statutes, I turn not from them.

24 And I am perfect before Him, And I keep myself from mine iniquity.

25 And Jehovah returneth to me, According to my righteousness, According to my cleanness before His eyes.

26 With the kind Thou shewest Thyself kind, With the perfect man Thou shewest Thyself perfect,

27 With the pure Thou shewest Thyself pure, And with the perverse Thou shewest Thyself a wrestler.

28 And the poor people Thou dost save, And Thine eyes on the high causest to fall.

29 For Thou [art] my lamp, O Jehovah, And Jehovah doth lighten my darkness.

30 For by Thee I run--a troop, By my God I leap a wall.

31 God! Perfect [is] His way, The saying of Jehovah is tried, A shield He [is] to all those trusting in Him.

32 For who is God save Jehovah? And who a Rock save our God?

33 God--my bulwark, [my] strength, And He maketh perfect my way;

34 Making my feet like hinds, And on my high places causeth me to stand,

35 Teaching my hands for battle, And brought down was a bow of brass by mine arms,

36 And Thou givest to me the shield of Thy salvation, And Thy lowliness maketh me great.

37 Thou enlargest my step under me, And mine ankles have not slidden.

38 I pursue mine enemies and destroy them, And I turn not till they are consumed.

39 And I consume them, and smite them, And they rise not, and fall under my feet.

40 And Thou girdest me [with] strength for battle, Thou causest my withstanders to bow under me.

41 And mine enemies--Thou givest to me the neck, Those hating me--and I cut them off.

42 They look, and there is no saviour; Unto Jehovah, and He hath not answered them.

43 And I beat them as dust of the earth, As mire of the streets I beat them small--I spread them out!

44 And--Thou dost deliver me From the strivings of my people, Thou placest me for a head of nations; A people I have not known do serve me.

45 Sons of a stranger feign obedience to me, At the hearing of the ear they hearken to me.

46 Sons of a stranger fade away, And gird themselves by their close places.

47 Jehovah liveth, and blessed [is] my Rock, And exalted is my God--The Rock of my salvation.

48 God--who is giving vengeance to me, And bringing down peoples under me,

49 And bringing me forth from mine enemies, Yea, above my withstanders Thou raisest me up. From a man of violence Thou deliverest me.

50 Therefore I confess Thee, O Jehovah, among nations. And to Thy name I sing praise.

51 Magnifying the salvations of His king, And doing loving-kindness to His anointed, To David, and to his seed--unto the age!'

2 Samuel 23

1 And these [are] the last words of David: --`The affirmation of David son of Jesse-- And the affirmation of the man raised up--Concerning the Anointed of the God of Jacob, And the Sweetness of the Songs of Israel:

2 The Spirit of Jehovah hath spoken by me, And His word [is] on my tongue.

3 He said--the God of Israel--to me, He spake--the Rock of Israel: He who is ruling over man [is] righteous, He is ruling in the fear of God.

4 And as the light of morning he riseth, A morning sun--no clouds! By the shining, by the rain, Tender grass of the earth!

5 For--not so [is] my house with God; For--a covenant age-during He made with me, Arranged in all things, and kept; For--all my salvation, and all desire, For--He hath not caused [it] to spring up.

6 As to the worthless--As a thorn driven away [are] all of them, For--not by hand are they taken;

7 And the man who cometh against them Is filled with iron and the staff of a spear, And with fire they are utterly burnt In the cessation.'

8 These [are] the names of the mighty ones whom David hath: sitting in the seat [is] the Tachmonite, head of the captains--he [is] Adino, who hardened himself against eight hundred-- wounded at one time.

9 And after him [is] Eleazar son of Dodo, son of Ahohi, of the three mighty men with David; in their exposing themselves among the Philistines--they have been gathered there to battle, and the men of Israel go up--

10 he hath arisen, and smiteth among the Philistines till that his hand hath been weary, and his hand cleaveth unto the sword, and Jehovah worketh a great salvation on that day, and the people turn back after him only to strip off.

11 And after him [is] Shammah son of Agee the Hararite, and the Philistines are gathered into a company, and there is there a portion of the field full of lentiles, and the people hath fled from the presence of the Philistines,

12 and he stationeth himself in the midst of the portion, and delivereth it, and smiteth the Philistines, and Jehovah worketh a great salvation.

13 And three of the thirty heads go down and come unto the harvest, unto David, unto the cave of Adullam, and the company of the Philistines are encamping in the valley of Rephaim,

14 and David [is] then in a fortress, and the station of the Philistines [is] then in Beth- Lehem,

15 and David longeth and saith, `Who doth give me a drink of the water of the well of Beth-Lehem, which [is] by the gate?'

16 And the three mighty ones cleave through the camp of the Philistines, and draw water out of the well of Beth-Lehem, which [is] by the gate, and take [it] up, and bring in unto David; and he was not willing to drink it, and poureth it out to Jehovah,

17 and saith, `Far be it from me, O Jehovah, to do this; is it the blood of the men who are going with their lives?' and he was not willing to drink it; these [things] did the three mighty ones.

18 And Abishai brother of Joab, son of Zeruiah, he [is] head of three, and he is lifting up his spear against three hundred--wounded, and he hath a name among three.

19 Of the three is he not the honoured? and he becometh their head; and unto the [first] three he hath not come.

20 And Benaiah son of Jehoiada (son of a man of valour, great in deeds from Kabzeel), he hath smitten two lion-like men of Moab, and he hath gone down and smitten the lion in the midst of the pit in a day of snow.

21 And he hath smitten the Egyptian man, a man of appearance, and in the hand of the Egyptian [is] a spear, and he goeth down unto him with a rod, and taketh violently away the spear out of the hand of the Egyptian, and slayeth him with his own spear.

22 These [things] hath Benaiah son of Jehoiada done, and hath a name among three mighty.

23 Of the thirty he is honoured, and unto the three he came not; and David setteth him over his guard.

24 Asahel brother of Joab [is] of the thirty; Elhanan son of Dodo of Beth-Lehem.

25 Shammah the Harodite, Elika the Harodite,

26 Helez the Paltite, Ira son of Ikkesh the Tekoite,

27 Abiezer the Annethothite, Mebunnai the Hushathite,

28 Zalmon the Ahohite, Maharai the Netophathite,

29 Heleb son of Baanah the Netophathite, Ittai son of Ribai from Gibeah of the sons of Benjamin,

30 Benaiah the Pirathonite, Hiddai of the brooks of Gaash,

31 Abi-Albon the Arbathite, Azmaveth the Barhumite,

32 Eliahba the Shaalbonite, [of] the sons of Jashen, Jonathan,

33 Shammah the Hararite, Ahiam son of Sharar the Hararite,

34 Eliphelet son of Ahasbai, son of the Maachathite, Eliam son of Ahithophel the Gilonite,

35 Hezrai the Carmelite, Paarai the Arbite,

36 Igal son of Nathan from Zobah, Bani the Gadite,

37 Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, bearer of the weapons of Joab son of Zeruiah,

38 Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,

39 Uriah the Hittite; in all thirty and seven.

1 Kings 4

1 And king Solomon is king over all Israel,

2 and these [are] the heads whom he hath: Azariah son of Zadok [is] the priest;

3 Elihoreph and Ahiah sons of Shisha [are] scribes; Jehoshaphat son of Ahilud [is] remembrancer;

4 and Benaiah son of Jehoiada [is] over the host; and Zadok and Abiathar [are] priests;

5 and Azariah son of Nathan [is] over the officers; and Zabud son of Nathan [is] minister, friend of the king;

6 And Ahishar [is] over the household, and Adoniram son of Abda [is] over the tribute.

7 And Solomon hath twelve officers over all Israel, and they have sustained the king and his household--a month in the year is on each one for sustenance;

8 and these [are] their names: Ben-Hur in the hill-country of Ephraim;

9 Ben-Dekar in Makaz, and Shaalbim, and Beth-Shemesh, and Elon-Beth-Hanan.

10 Ben-Hesed [is] in Aruboth, hath Sochoh and all the land of Hepher;

11 Ben-Abinadab [hath] all the elevation of Dor, Taphath daughter of Solomon became his wife.

12 Baana Ben-Ahilud [hath] Taanach and Megiddo, and all Beth-Shean, which [is] by Zartanah beneath Jezreel, from Beth-Shean unto Abel-Meholah, unto beyond Jokneam.

13 Ben-Geber, in Ramoth-Gilead, hath the small towns of Jair son of Manasseh, which [are] in Gilead; he hath a portion of Argob that [is] in Bashan, sixty great cities [with] wall and brazen bar.

14 Ahinadab son of Iddo [hath] Mahanaim.

15 Ahimaaz [is] in Naphtali; he also hath taken Basemath daughter of Solomon for a wife.

16 Baanah Ben-Hushai [is] in Asher, and in Aloth.

17 Jehoshaphat Ben-Paruah [is] in Issachar.

18 Shimei Ben-Elah [is] in Benjamin.

19 Geber Ben-Uri [is] in the land of Gilead, the land of Sihon king of the Amorite, and of Og king of Bashan: and one officer who [is] in the land.

20 Judah and Israel [are] many, as the sand that [is] by the sea for multitude, eating and drinking and rejoicing.

21 And Solomon hath been ruling over all the kingdoms, from the River [to] the land of the Philistines and unto the border of Egypt: they are bringing nigh a present, and serving Solomon, all days of his life.

22 And the provision of Solomon for one day is thirty cors of flour, and sixty cors of meal;

23 ten fat oxen, and twenty feeding oxen, and a hundred sheep, apart from hart, and roe, and fallow-deer, and fatted beasts of the stalls,

24 for he is ruling over all beyond the river, from Tiphsah and unto Gaza, over all the kings beyond the river, and he hath peace from all his servants round about.

25 And Judah dwelleth--and Israel--in confidence, each under his vine, and under his fig-tree, from Dan even unto Beer-Sheba, all the days of Solomon.

26 And Solomon hath forty thousand stalls of horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen.

27 And these officers have sustained king Solomon and every one drawing near unto the table of king Solomon, each [in] his month; they let nothing be lacking.

28 And the barley and the straw, for horses and for dromedaries, they bring in unto the place where they are, each according to his ordinance.

29 And God giveth wisdom to Solomon, and understanding, very much, and breadth of heart, as the sand that [is] on the edge of the sea;

30 and the wisdom of Solomon is greater than the wisdom of any of the sons of the east, and than all the wisdom of Egypt;

31 and he is wiser than all men, than Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Chalcol, and Darda, sons of Mahol, and his name is in all the nations round about.

32 And he speaketh three thousand similes, and his songs [are] five, and the chief one;

33 and he speaketh concerning the trees, from the cedar that [is] in Lebanon, even unto the hyssop that is coming out in the wall, and he speaketh concerning the cattle, and concerning the fowl, and concerning the creeping things, and concerning the fishes,

34 and there come out of all the peoples to hear the wisdom of Solomon, from all kings of the earth who have heard of his wisdom.

1 Kings 6

1 And it cometh to pass, in the four hundred and eightieth year of the going out of the sons of Israel from the land of Egypt, in the fourth year--in the month of Zif, it [is] the second month--of the reigning of Solomon over Israel, that he buildeth the house for Jehovah.

2 As to the house that king Solomon hath built for Jehovah, sixty cubits [is] its length, and twenty its breadth, and thirty cubits its height.

3 As to the porch on the front of the temple of the house, twenty cubits [is] its length on the front of the breadth of the house; ten by the cubit [is] its breadth on the front of the house;

4 and he maketh for the house windows of narrow lights.

5 And he buildeth against the wall of the house a couch round about, [even] the walls of the house round about, of the temple and of the oracle, and maketh sides round about.

6 The lowest couch, five by the cubit [is] its breadth; and the middle, six by the cubit [is] its breadth; and the third, seven by the cubit [is] its breadth, for withdrawings he hath put to the house round about, without--not to lay hold on the walls of the house.

7 And the house, in its being built, of perfect stone brought [thither] hath been built, and hammer, and the axe--any instrument of iron--was not heard in the house, in its being built.

8 The opening of the middle side [is] at the right shoulder of the house, and with windings they go up on the middle one, and from the middle one unto the third.

9 And he buildeth the house, and completeth it, and covereth the house [with] beams and rows of cedars.

10 And he buildeth the couch against all the house, five cubits [is] its height, and it taketh hold of the house by cedar-wood.

11 And the word of Jehovah is unto Solomon, saying,

12 `This house that thou art building--if thou dost walk in My statutes, and My judgments dost do, yea, hast done all My commands, to walk in them, then I have established My word with thee, which I spake unto David thy father,

13 and have tabernacled in the midst of the sons of Israel, and do not forsake My people Israel.'

14 And Solomon buildeth the house and completeth it;

15 and he buildeth the walls of the house within with beams of cedar, from the floor of the house unto the walls of the ceiling; he hath overlaid with wood the inside, and covereth the floor of the house with ribs of fir.

16 And he buildeth the twenty cubits on the sides of the house with ribs of cedar, from the floor unto the walls; and he buildeth for it within, for the oracle, for the holy of holies.

17 And forty by the cubit was the house, it [is] the temple before [it].

18 And the cedar for the house within [is] carvings of knobs and openings of flowers; the whole [is] cedar, there is not a stone seen.

19 And the oracle in the midst of the house within he hath prepared, to put there the ark of the covenant of Jehovah.

20 And before the oracle [is] twenty cubits in length, and twenty cubits in breadth, and twenty cubits [is] its height; and he overlayeth it with gold refined, and overlayeth the altar with cedar.

21 And Solomon overlayeth the house within with gold refined, and causeth [it] to pass over in chains of gold before the oracle, and overlayeth it with gold.

22 And the whole of the house he hath overlaid with gold, till the completion of all the house; and the whole of the altar that the oracle hath, he hath overlaid with gold.

23 And he maketh within the oracle two cherubs, of the oil-tree, ten cubits [is] their height;

24 and five cubits [is] the one wing of the cherub, and five cubits the second wing of the cherub, ten cubits from the ends of its wings even unto the ends of its wings;

25 and ten by the cubit [is] the second cherub, one measure and one form [are] to the two cherubs,

26 the height of the one cherub [is] ten by the cubit, and so [is] the second cherub;

27 and he setteth the cherubs in the midst of the inner house, and they spread out the wings of the cherubs, and a wing of the one cometh against the wall, and a wing of the second cherub is coming against the second wall, and their wings [are]unto the midst of the house, coming wing against wing;

28 and he overlayeth the cherubs with gold,

29 and all the walls of the house round about he hath carved with openings of carvings, cherubs, and palm trees, and openings of flowers, within and without.

30 And the floor of the house he hath overlaid with gold, within and without;

31 as to the opening of the oracle, he made doors of the oil-tree; the lintel, side-posts, a fifth.

32 And the two doors [are] of the oil-tree, and he hath carved upon them carvings of cherubs, and palm-trees, and openings of flowers, and overlaid with gold, and he causeth the gold to go down on the cherubs and on the palm-trees.

33 And so he hath made for the opening of the temple, side-posts of the oil-tree, from the fourth.

34 And the two doors [are] of fir-tree, the two sides of the one door are revolving, and the two hangings of the second door are revolving.

35 And he hath carved cherubs, and palms, and openings of flowers, and overlaid with straightened gold the graved work.

36 And he buildeth the inner court, three rows of hewn work, and a row of beams of cedar.

37 In the fourth year hath the house of Jehovah been founded, in the month Zif,

38 and in the eleventh year, in the month Bul--[that is] the eighth month--hath the house been finished in all its matters, and in all its ordinances, and he buildeth it seven years.

1 Kings 7

1 And his own house hath Solomon built thirteen years, and he finisheth all his house.

2 And he buildeth the house of the forest of Lebanon; a hundred cubits [is] its length, and fifty cubits its breadth, and thirty cubits its height, on four rows of cedar pillars, and cedarbeams on the pillars;

3 and [it is] covered with cedar above, on the sides that [are] on the forty and five pillars, fifteen in the row.

4 And windows [are] in three rows, and sight [is] over-against sight three times.

5 And all the openings and the side-posts [are] square--windows; and sight [is] overagainst sight three times.

6 And the porch of the pillars he hath made; fifty cubits its length, and thirty cubits its breadth, and the porch [is] before them, and pillars and a thick place [are] before them.

7 And the porch of the throne where he judgeth--the porch of judgment--he hath made, and [it is] covered with cedar from the floor unto the floor.

8 As to his house where he dwelleth, the other court [is] within the porch--as this work it hath been; and a house he maketh for the daughter of Pharaoh--whom Solomon hath taken--like this porch.

9 All these [are] of precious stone, according to the measures of hewn work, sawn with a saw, within and without, even from the foundation unto the coping, and at the outside, unto the great court.

10 And the foundation [is] of precious stone, great stones, stones of ten cubits, and stones of eight cubits;

11 and above [are] precious stone, according to the measures of hewn work, and cedar;

12 and the great court round about [is] three rows of hewn work, and a row of cedarbeams, even for the inner court of the house of Jehovah, and for the porch of the house.

13 And king Solomon sendeth and taketh Hiram out of Tyre--

14 he [is] son of a woman, a widow, of the tribe of Naphtali, and his father a man of Tyre, a worker in brass, and he is filled with the wisdom and the understanding, and the knowledge to do all work in brass--and he cometh unto king Solomon, and doth all his work.

15 And he formeth the two pillars of brass; eighteen cubits [is] the height of the one pillar, and a cord of twelve cubits doth compass the second pillar.

16 And two chapiters he hath made to put on the tops of the pillars, cast in brass; five cubits the height of the one chapiter, and five cubits the height of the second chapiter.

17 Nets of net-work, wreaths of chain-work [are] for the chapiters that [are] on the top of the pillars, seven for the one chapiter, and seven for the second chapiter.

18 And he maketh the pillars, and two rows round about on the one net-work, to cover the chapiters that [are] on the top, with the pomegranates, and so he hath made for the second chapiter.

19 And the chapiters that [are] on the top of the pillars [are] of lily-work in the porch, four cubits;

20 and the chapiters on the two pillars also above, over-against the protuberance that [is] beside the net; and the pomegranates [are] two hundred, in rows round about on the second chapiter.

21 And he raiseth up the pillars for the porch of the temple, and he raiseth up the right pillar, and calleth its name Jachin, and he raiseth up the left pillar, and calleth its name Boaz;

22 and on the top of the pillars [is] lily-work; and the work of the pillars [is] completed.

23 And he maketh the molten sea, ten by the cubit from its edge unto its edge; [it is] round all about, and five by the cubit [is] its height, and a line of thirty by the cubit doth compass it round about;

24 and knops beneath its brim round about are compassing it, ten by the cubit, going round the sea round about; in two rows [are] the knops, cast in its being cast.

25 It is standing on twelve oxen, three facing the north, and three facing the west, and three facing the south, and three facing the east, and the sea [is] upon them above, and all their hinder parts [are] inward.

26 And its thickness [is] an handbreadth, and its edge as the work of the edge of a cup, flowers of lilies; two thousand baths it containeth.

27 And he maketh the ten bases of brass; four by the cubit [is] the length of the one base, and four by the cubit its breadth, and three by the cubit its height.

28 And this [is] the work of the base: they have borders, and the borders [are] between the joinings;

29 and on the borders that [are] between the joinings [are] lions, oxen, and cherubs, and on the joinings a base above, and beneath the lions and the oxen [are] additions--sloping work.

30 And four wheels of brass [are] to the one base, and axles of brass; and its four corners have shoulders--under the laver [are] the molten shoulders, beside each addition.

31 And its mouth within the chapiter and above [is] by the cubit, and its mouth [is] round, the work of the base, a cubit and half a cubit; and also on its mouth [are] carvings and their borders, square, not round.

32 And the four wheels [are] under the borders, and the spokes of the wheels [are] in the base, and the height of the one wheel [is] a cubit and half a cubit.

33 And the work of the wheels [is] as the work of the wheel of a chariot, their spokes, and their axles, and their felloes, and their naves; the whole [is] molten.

34 And four shoulders [are] unto the four corners of the one base; out of the base [are] its shoulders.

35 And in the top of the base [is] the half of a cubit in the height all round about; and on the top of the base its spokes and its borders [are] of the same.

36 And he openeth on the tablets of its spokes, and on its borders, cherubs, lions, and palm-trees, according to the void space of each, and additions round about.

37 Thus he hath made the ten bases; one casting, one measure, one form, have they all.

38 And he maketh ten lavers of brass; forty baths doth the one laver contain, four by the cubit [is] the one laver, one laver on the one base [is] to the ten bases;

39 and he putteth the five bases on the right side of the house, and five on the left side of the house, and the sea he hath put on the right side of the house, eastward--over-against the south.

40 And Hiram maketh the lavers, and the shovels, and the bowls; and Hiram completeth to do all the work that he made for king Solomon, [for] the house of Jehovah;

41 pillars two, and bowls of the chapiters that [are] on the top of the pillars two, and the nets two, to cover the two bowls of the chapiters that [are] on the top of the pillars;

42 and the pomegranates four hundred for the two nets, two rows of pomegranates for the one net, to cover the two bowls of the chapiters that [are] on the front of the pillars;

43 and the ten bases, and the ten lavers on the bases;

44 and the one sea, the twelve oxen under the sea,

45 and the pots, and the shovels, and the bowls; and all these vessels, that Hiram hath made to king Solomon [for] the house of Jehovah, [are] of brass--polished.

46 In the circuit of the Jordan hath the king cast them, in the thick soil of the ground, between Succoth and Zarthan.

47 And Solomon placeth the whole of the vessels; because of the very great abundance, the weight of the brass hath not been searched out.

48 And Solomon maketh all the vessels that [are] in the house of Jehovah: the altar of gold, and the table--on which [is] the bread of the Presence--of gold,

49 and the candlesticks, five on the right, and five on the left, before the oracle, of refined gold, and the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, of gold,

50 and the basins, and the snuffers, and the bowls, and the spoons, and the censers, of refined gold, and the hinges for the doors of the inner-house, for the holy of holies, for the doors of the house of the temple, of gold.

51 And it is complete--all the work that king Solomon hath made [for] the house of Jehovah, and Solomon bringeth in the sanctified things of David his father; the silver, and the gold, and the vessels he hath put in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah.

1 Kings 9

1 And it cometh to pass, at Solomon's finishing to build the house of Jehovah, and the house of the king, and all the desire of Solomon that he delighted to do,

2 that Jehovah appeareth unto Solomon a second time, as He appeared unto him in Gibeon,

3 and Jehovah saith unto him, `I have heard thy prayer and thy supplication with which thou hast made supplication before Me; I have hallowed this house that thou hast built to put My name there--unto the age, and Mine eyes and My heart have been there all the days.

4 `And thou--if thou dost walk before Me as David thy father walked, in simplicity of heart, and in uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded thee--My statutes and My judgments thou dost keep--

5 then I have established the throne of thy kingdom over Israel--to the age, as I spake unto David thy father, saying, There is not cut off to thee a man from [being] on the throne of Israel.

6 `If ye at all turn back--you and your sons--from after Me, and keep not My commands- -My statutes, that I have set before you, and ye have gone and served other gods, and bowed yourselves to them,

7 then I have cut off Israel from the face of the ground that I have given to them, and the house that I have hallowed for My name I send away from My presence, and Israel hath been for a simile and for a byword among all the peoples;

8 as to this house, [that] is high, every one passing by it is astonished, and hath hissed, and they have said, Wherefore hath Jehovah done thus to this land and to this house?

9 and they have said, Because that they have forsaken Jehovah their God, who brought out their fathers from the land of Egypt, and they lay hold on other gods, and bow themselves to them, and serve them; therefore hath Jehovah brought in upon them all this evil.'

10 And it cometh to pass, at the end of twenty years, that Solomon hath built the two houses, the house of Jehovah, and the house of the king.

11 Hiram king of Tyre hath assisted Solomon with cedar-trees, and with fir-trees, and with gold, according to all his desire; then doth king Solomon give to Hiram twenty cities in the land of Galilee.

12 And Hiram cometh out from Tyre to see the cities that Solomon hath given to him, and they have not been right in his eyes,

13 and he saith, `What [are] these cities that thou hast given to me, my brother?' and one calleth them the land of Cabul unto this day.

14 And Hiram sendeth to the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold.

15 And this [is] the matter of the tribute that king Solomon hath lifted up, to build the house of Jehovah, and his own house, and Millo, and the wall of Jerusalem, and Hazor, and Megiddo, and Gezer,

16 (Pharaoh king of Egypt hath gone up and doth capture Gezer, and doth burn it with fire, and the Canaanite who is dwelling in the city he hath slain, and giveth it [with] presents to his daughter, wife of Solomon.)

17 And Solomon buildeth Gezer, and Beth-Horon the lower,

18 and Baalath, and Tadmor in the wilderness, in the land;

19 and all the cities of stores that king Solomon hath, and the cities of the chariots, and the cities of the horsemen, and the desire of Solomon that he desired to build in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion.

20 The whole of the people that is left of the Amorite, the Hittite, the Perizzite, the Hivite, and the Jebusite, who [are] not of the sons of Israel--

21 their sons who are left behind them in the land, whom the sons of Israel have not been able to devote--he hath even lifted up [on] them a tribute of service unto this day.

22 And out of the sons of Israel Solomon hath not appointed a servant, for they [are] the men of war, and his servants, and his heads, and his captains, and the heads of his chariots, and his horsemen.

23 These [are] the heads of the officers who [are] over the work of Solomon, fifty and five hundred, those ruling among the people who are labouring in the work.

24 Only, the daughter of Pharaoh went up out of the city of David unto her house that [Solomon] built for her; then he built Millo.

25 And Solomon caused to ascend, three times in a year, burnt-offerings and peaceofferings on the altar that he built to Jehovah, and he perfumed it with that which [is] before Jehovah, and finished the house.

26 And a navy hath king Solomon made in Ezion-Geber, that is beside Eloth, on the edge of the Sea of Suph, in the land of Edom.

27 And Hiram sendeth in the navy his servants, shipmen knowing the sea, with servants of Solomon,

28 and they come in to Ophir and take thence gold, four hundred and twenty talents, and bring [it] in unto king Solomon.

1 Kings 10

1 And the queen of Sheba is hearing of the fame of Solomon concerning the name of Jehovah, and cometh to try him with enigmas,

2 and she cometh to Jerusalem, with a very great company, camels bearing spices, and very much gold, and precious stone, and she cometh unto Solomon, and speaketh unto him all that hath been with her heart.

3 And Solomon declareth to her all her matters--there hath not been a thing hid from the king that he hath not declared to her.

4 And the queen of Sheba seeth all the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he built,

5 and the food of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the standing of his ministers, and their clothing, and his butlers, and his burnt-offering that he causeth to ascend in the house of Jehovah, and there hath not been in her any more spirit.

6 And she saith unto the king, `True hath been the word that I heard in my land, concerning thy matters and thy wisdom;

7 and I gave no credence to the words till that I have come, and my eyes see, and lo, it was not declared to me--the half; thou hast added wisdom and goodness unto the report that I heard.

8 O the happiness of thy men, O the happiness of thy servants--these--who are standing before thee continually, who are hearing thy wisdom!

9 Jehovah thy God is blessed who delighted in thee, to put thee on the throne of Israel; in Jehovah's loving Israel to the age He doth set thee for king, to do judgment and righteousness.

10 And she giveth to the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold, and spices very many, and precious stone; there came not like that spice any more for abundance that the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon.

11 And also, the navy of Hiram that bore gold from Ophir, brought in from Ophir almug-trees very many, and precious stone;

12 and the king maketh the almug-trees a support for the house of Jehovah, and for the house of the king, and harps and psalteries for singers; there have not come such almug-trees, nor have there been seen [such] unto this day.

13 And king Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire that she asked, apart from that which he gave to her as a memorial of king Solomon, and she turneth and goeth to her land, she and her servants.

14 And the weight of the gold that hath come to Solomon in one year is six hundred sixty and six talents of gold,

15 apart from [that of] the tourists, and of the traffic of the merchants, and of all the kings of Arabia, and of the governors of the land.

16 And king Solomon maketh two hundred targets of alloyed gold--six hundred of gold go up on the one target;

17 and three hundred shields of alloyed gold--three pounds of gold go up on the one shield; and the king putteth them [in] the house of the forest of Lebanon.

18 And the king maketh a great throne of ivory, and overlayeth it with refined gold;

19 six steps hath the throne, and a round top [is] to the throne behind it, and hands [are] on this [side] and on that, unto the place of the sitting, and two lions are standing near the hands,

20 and twelve lions are standing there on the six steps, on this [side] and on that; it hath not been made so for any kingdom.

21 And all the drinking vessels of king Solomon [are] of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon [are] of refined gold--there are none of silver; it was not reckoned in the days of Solomon for anything,

22 for a navy of Tarshish hath the king at sea with a navy of Hiram; once in three years cometh the navy of Tarshish, bearing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks.

23 And king Solomon is greater than any of the kings of the earth for riches and for wisdom,

24 and all the earth is seeking the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom that God hath put into his heart,

25 and they are bringing each his present, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and garments, and armour, and spices, horses, and mules, the matter of a year in a year.

26 And Solomon gathereth chariots, and horsemen, and he hath a thousand and four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, and he placeth them in the cities of the chariot, and with the king in Jerusalem.

27 And the king maketh the silver in Jerusalem as stones, and the cedars he hath made as the sycamores that [are] in the low country, for abundance.

28 And the outgoing of the horses that king Solomon hath [is] from Egypt, and from Keveh; merchants of the king take from Keveh at a price;

29 and a chariot cometh up and cometh out of Egypt for six hundred silverlings, and a horse for fifty and a hundred, and so for all the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Aram; by their hand they bring out.

1 Kings 15

1 And in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam son of Nebat, reigned hath Abijam over Judah;

2 three years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Maachah daughter of Abishalom;

3 and he walketh in all the sins of his father, that he did before him, and his heart hath not been perfect with Jehovah his God, as the heart of David his father;

4 but for David's sake hath Jehovah his God given to him a lamp in Jerusalem, to raise up his son after him, and to establish Jerusalem,

5 in that David did that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah, and turned not aside from all that He commanded him all days of his life--only in the matter of Uriah the Hittite;

6 and war hath been between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all the days of his life.

7 And the rest of the matters of Abijam, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah? And war hath been between Abijam and Jeroboam;

8 and Abijam lieth with his fathers, and they bury him in the city of David, and reign doth Asa his son in his stead.

9 And in the twentieth year of Jeroboam king of Israel reigned hath Asa over Judah,

10 and forty and one years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Maachah daughter of Abishalom.

11 And Asa doth that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his father,

12 and removeth the whoremongers out of the land, and turneth aside all the idols that his fathers made;

13 and also Maachah his mother--he turneth her aside from being mistress, in that she made a horrible thing for a shrine, and Asa cutteth down her horrible thing, and burneth [it] by the brook Kidron;

14 and the high places have not turned aside; only, the heart of Asa hath been perfect with Jehovah all his days,

15 and he bringeth in the sanctified things of his father, and his own sanctified things, to the house of Jehovah, silver, and gold, and vessels.

16 And war hath been between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days,

17 and Baasha king of Israel goeth up against Judah, and buildeth Ramah, not to permit any one going out and coming in to Asa king of Judah.

18 And Asa taketh all the silver and the gold that are left in the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the house of the king, and giveth them into the hand of his servants, and king Asa sendeth them unto Ben-Hadad, son of Tabrimmon, son of Hezion king of Aram, who is dwelling in Damascus, saying,

19 `A covenant [is] between me and thee, between my father and thy father; lo, I have sent to thee a reward of silver and gold; go, break thy covenant with Baasha king of Israel, and he goeth up from off me.'

20 And Ben-Hadad hearkeneth unto king Asa, and sendeth the heads of the forces that he hath against cities of Israel, and smiteth Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-Beth-Maachah, and all Chinneroth, besides all the land of Naphtali;

21 and it cometh to pass at Baasha's hearing, that he ceaseth from building Ramah, and dwelleth in Tirzah.

22 And king Asa hath summoned all Judah--there is none exempt--and they lift up the stones of Ramah, and its wood, that Baasha hath built, and king Asa buildeth with them Geba of Benjamin, and Mizpah.

23 And the rest of all the matters of Asa, and all his might, and all that he did, and the cities that he built, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah? Only, at the time of his old age he was diseased in his feet;

24 and Asa lieth with his fathers, and is buried with his fathers in the city of David his father, and Jehoshaphat his son reigneth in his stead.

25 And Nadab son of Jeroboam hath reigned over Israel, in the second year of Asa king of Judah, and he reigneth over Israel two years,

26 and doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, and goeth in the way of his father, and in his sin that he made Israel to sin.

27 And conspire against him doth Baasha son of Ahijah, of the house of Issachar, and Baasha smiteth him in Gibbethon, which [is] to the Philistines--and Nadab and all Israel are laying siege against Gibbethon--

28 yea, Baasha putteth him to death in the third year of Asa king of Judah, and reigneth in his stead.

29 And it cometh to pass, at his reigning, he hath smitten the whole house of Jeroboam, he hath not left any breathing to Jeroboam till his destroying him, according to the word of Jehovah, that He spake by the hand of His servant Ahijah the Shilonite,

30 because of the sins of Jeroboam that he sinned, and that he caused Israel to sin, by his provocation with which he provoked to anger Jehovah, God of Israel.

31 And the rest of the matters of Nadab, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

32 And war hath been between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days.

33 In the third year of Asa king of Judah reigned hath Baasha son of Ahijah over all Israel in Tirzah, twenty and four years,

34 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, and walketh in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin that he caused Israel to sin.

1 Kings 16

1 And a word of Jehovah is unto Jehu son of Hanani, against Baasha, saying,

2 `Because that I have raised thee up out of the dust, and appoint thee leader over My people Israel, and thou walkest in the way of Jeroboam, and causest My people Israel to sin--to provoke Me to anger with their sins;

3 lo, I am putting away the posterity of Baasha, even the posterity of his house, and have given up thy house as the house of Jeroboam son of Nebat;

4 him who dieth of Baasha in a city do the dogs eat, and him who dieth of his in a field do fowl of the heavens eat.'

5 And the rest of the matters of Baasha, and that which he did, and his might, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

6 And Baasha lieth with his fathers, and is buried in Tirzah, and Elah his son reigneth in his stead.

7 And also by the hand of Jehu son of Hanani the prophet a word of Jehovah hath been concerning Baasha, and concerning his house, and concerning all the evil that he did in the eyes of Jehovah to provoke Him to anger with the work of his hands, to be like the house of Jeroboam, and concerning that for which he smote him.

8 In the twenty and sixth year of Asa king of Judah reigned hath Elah son of Baasha over Israel in Tirzah, two years;

9 and conspire against him doth his servant Zimri (head of the half of the chariots) and he [is] in Tirzah drinking--a drunkard in the house of Arza, who [is] over the house in Tirzah.

10 And Zimri cometh in and smiteth him, and putteth him to death, in the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah, and reigneth in his stead;

11 and it cometh to pass in his reigning, at his sitting on his throne, he hath smitten the whole house of Baasha; he hath not left to him any sitting on the wall, and of his redeemers, and of his friends.

12 And Zimri destroyeth the whole house of Baasha, according to the word of Jehovah, that He spake concerning Baasha, by the hand of Jehu the prophet:

13 concerning all the sins of Baasha, and the sins of Elah his son, that they sinned, and that they caused Israel to sin to provoke Jehovah, God of Israel, with their vanities.

14 And the rest of the matters of Elah, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

15 In the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah, reigned hath Zimri seven days in Tirzah; and the people are encamping against Gibbethon, which [is] to the Philistines;

16 and the people who are encamping hear, saying, `Zimri hath conspired, and also hath smitten the king;' and all Israel cause Omri head of the host to reign over Israel on that day in the camp.

17 And Omri goeth up, and all Israel with him, from Gibbethon, and they lay siege to Tirzah.

18 And it cometh to pass, at Zimri's seeing that the city hath been captured, that he cometh in unto a high place of the house of the king, and burneth over him the house of the king with fire, and dieth,

19 for his sins that he sinned, to do the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, to walk in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin that he did, to cause Israel to sin;

20 and the rest of the matters of Zimri, and his conspiracy that he made, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

21 Then are the sons of Israel parted into halves; half of the people hath been after Tibni son of Ginath to cause him to reign, and the half after Omri;

22 and stronger are the people that are after Omri than the people that are after Tibni son of Ginath, and Tibni dieth, and Omri reigneth.

23 In the thirty and first year of Asa king of Judah reigned hath Omri over Israel twelve years; in Tirzah he hath reigned six years,

24 and he buyeth the mount Samaria from Shemer, with two talents of silver, and buildeth [on] the mount, and calleth the name of the city that he hath built by the name of Shemer, lord of the hill--Samaria.

25 And Omri doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, and doth evil above all who [are] before him,

26 and walketh in all the way of Jeroboam son of Nebat, and in his sin that he caused Israel to sin, to provoke Jehovah, God of Israel, with their vanities.

27 And the rest of the matters of Omri that he did, and his might that he got, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

28 And Omri lieth with his fathers, and is buried in Samaria, and Ahab his son reigneth in his stead.

29 And Ahab son of Omri hath reigned over Israel in the thirty and eighth year of Asa king of Judah, and Ahab son of Omri reigneth over Israel in Samaria twenty and two years,

30 and Ahab son of Omri doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah above all who [are] before him.

31 And it cometh to pass--hath it been light his walking in the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat? --then he taketh a wife, Jezebel daughter of Ethbaal, king of the Zidonians, and goeth and serveth Baal, and boweth himself to it,

32 and raiseth up an altar for Baal, in the house of the Baal, that he built in Samaria;

33 and Ahab maketh the shrine, and Ahab addeth to do so as to provoke Jehovah, God of Israel, above all the kings of Israel who have been before him.

34 In his days hath Hiel the Beth-Elite built Jericho; in Abiram his first-born he laid its foundation, and in Segub his youngest he set up its doors, according to the word of Jehovah that He spake by the hand of Joshua son of Nun.

2 Kings 15

1 In the twenty and seventh year of Jeroboam king of Israel reigned hath Azariah son of Amaziah king of Judah,

2 a son of sixteen years was he in his reigning, and fifty and two years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Jecholiah of Jerusalem,

3 and he doth that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that Amaziah his father did,

4 only, the high places have not turned aside--yet are the people sacrificing and making perfume in high places.

5 And Jehovah smiteth the king, and he is a leper unto the day of his death, and he dwelleth in a separate house, and Jotham son of the king [is] over the house, judging the people of the land.

6 And the rest of the matters of Azariah, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah?

7 And Azariah lieth with his fathers, and they bury him with his fathers, in the city of David, and reign doth Jotham his son in his stead.

8 In the thirty and eighth year of Azariah king of Judah reigned hath Zechariah son of Jeroboam over Israel, in Samaria, six months,

9 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, as did his fathers, he hath not turned aside from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat that he caused Israel to sin.

10 And Shallum son of Jabesh conspireth against him, and smiteth him before the people, and putteth him to death, and reigneth in his stead.

11 And the rest of the matters of Zechariah, lo, they are written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel.

12 It [is] the word of Jehovah that He spake unto Jehu, saying, `Sons of the fourth [generation] do sit for thee on the throne of Israel;' and it is so.

13 Shallum son of Jabesh hath reigned in the thirty and ninth year of Uzziah king of Judah, and he reigneth a month of days in Samaria;

14 and go up doth Menahem son of Gadi from Tirzah and cometh in to Samaria, and smiteth Shallum son of Jabesh in Samaria, and putteth him to death, and reigneth in his stead.

15 And the rest of the matters of Shallum, and his conspiracy that he made, lo, they are written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel.

16 Then doth Menahem smite Tiphsah, and all who [are] in it, and its borders from Tirzah, for it opened not [to him], and he smiteth [it], all its pregnant women he hath ripped up.

17 In the thirty and ninth year of Azariah king of Judah reigned hath Menahem son of Gadi over Israel--ten years in Samaria.

18 And he doth the evil in the eyes of Jehovah, he hath turned not aside from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat that he caused Israel to sin, all his days.

19 Pul king of Asshur hath come against the land, and Menahem giveth to Pul a thousand talents of silver, for his hand being with him to strengthen the kingdom in his hand.

20 And Menahem bringeth out the silver [from] Israel, [from] all the mighty men of wealth, to give to the king of Asshur, fifty shekels of silver for each one, and the king of Asshur turneth back and hath not stayed there in the land.

21 And the rest of the matters of Menahem, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel?

22 And Menahem lieth with his fathers, and reign doth Pekahiah his son in his stead.

23 In the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah hath Pekahiah son of Menahem reigned over Israel, in Samaria--two years,

24 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, he hath not turned aside from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat that he caused Israel to sin.

25 And Pekah son of Remaliah, his captain, doth conspire against him, and smiteth him in Samaria, in the high place of the house of the king with Argob and Arieh, and with him fifty men of the sons of the Gileadites, and he putteth him to death, and reigneth in his stead.

26 And the rest of the matters of Pekahiah, and all that he did, lo, they are written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel.

27 In the fifty and second year of Azariah king of Judah, reigned hath Pekah son of Remaliah over Israel, in Samaria--twenty years,

28 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, he hath not turned aside from the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat, that he caused Israel to sin.

29 In the days of Pekah king of Israel hath Tiglath-Pileser king of Asshur come, and taketh Ijon, and Abel-Beth-Maachah, and Janoah, and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Gilead, and Galilee, all the land of Naphtali, and removeth them to Asshur.

30 And make a conspiracy doth Hoshea son of Elah against Pekah son of Remaliah, and smiteth him, and putteth him to death, and reigneth in his stead, in the twentieth year of Jotham son of Uzziah.

31 And the rest of the matters of Pekah, and all that he did, lo, they are written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Israel.

32 In the second year of Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel reigned hath Jotham son of Uzziah king of Judah.

33 A son of twenty and five years was he in his reigning, and sixteen years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Jerusha daughter of Zadok,

34 and he doth that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that Uzziah his father did he hath done.

35 Only, the high places have not turned aside--yet are the people sacrificing and making perfume in high places; he hath built the high gate of the house of Jehovah.

36 And the rest of the matters of Jotham, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah?

37 In those days hath Jehovah begun to send against Judah Rezin king of Amram and Pekah son of Remaliah.

38 And Jotham lieth with his fathers, and is buried with his fathers, in the city of David his father, and reign doth Ahaz his son in his stead.

2 Kings 16

1 In the seventeenth year of Pekah son of Remaliah reigned hath Ahaz son of Jotham king of Judah.

2 A son of twenty years [is] Ahaz in his reigning, and sixteen years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and he hath not done that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah his God, like David his father,

3 and he walketh in the way of the kings of Israel, and also his son he hath caused to pass over into fire, according to the abominations of the nations that Jehovah dispossessed from the presence of the sons of Israel,

4 and he sacrificeth and maketh perfume in high places, and on the heights, and under every green tree.

5 Then doth Rezin king of Aram go up, and Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel, to Jerusalem, to battle, and they lay siege to Ahaz, and they have not been able to fight.

6 At that time hath Rezin king of Aram brought back Elath to Aram, and casteth out the Jews from Elath, and the Aramaeans have come in to Elath, and dwell there unto this day.

7 And Ahaz sendeth messengers unto Tiglath-Pileser king of Asshur, saying, `Thy servant and thy son [am] I; come up and save me out of the hand of the king of Aram, and out of the hand of the king of Israel, who are rising up against me.'

8 And Ahaz taketh the silver and the gold that is found in the house of Jehovah, and in the treasures of the house of the king, and sendeth to the king of Asshur--a bribe.

9 And hearken unto him doth the king of Asshur, and the king of Asshur goeth up unto Damascus, and seizeth it, and removeth [the people of] it to Kir, and Rezin he hath put to death.

10 And king Ahaz goeth to meet Tiglath-Pileser king of Asshur [at] Damascus, and seeth the altar that [is] in Damascus, and king Ahaz sendeth unto Urijah the priest the likeness of the altar, and its pattern, according to all its work,

11 and Urijah the priest buildeth the altar according to all that king Ahaz hath sent from Damascus; so did Urijah the priest till the coming in of king Ahaz from Damascus.

12 And the king cometh in from Damascus, and the king seeth the altar, and the king draweth near on the altar, and offereth on it,

13 and perfumeth his burnt-offering, and his present, and poureth out his libation, and sprinkleth the blood of the peace-offerings that he hath, on the altar.

14 As to the altar of brass that [is] before Jehovah--he bringeth [it] near from the front of the house, from between the altar and the house of Jehovah, and putteth it on the side of the altar, northward.

15 And king Ahaz commandeth him--Urijah the priest--saying, `On the great altar perfume the burnt-offering of the morning, and the present of the evening, and the burnt-offering of the king, and his present, and the burnt-offering of all the people of the land, and their present, and their libations; and all the blood of the burnt-offering, and all the blood of the sacrifice, on it thou dost sprinkle, and the altar of brass is to me to inquire [by].'

16 And Urijah the priest doth according to all that king Ahaz commanded.

17 And king Ahaz cutteth off the borders of the bases, and turneth aside from off them the laver, and the sea he hath taken down from off the brazen oxen that [are] under it, and putteth it on a pavement of stones.

18 And the covered place for the sabbath that they built in the house, and the entrance of the king without, he turned [from] the house of Jehovah, because of the king of Asshur.

19 And the rest of the matters of Ahaz that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah?

20 And Ahaz lieth with his fathers, and is buried with his fathers, in the city of David, and reign doth Hezekiah his son in his stead.

2 Kings 18

1 And it cometh to pass, in the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, reigned hath Hezekiah son of Ahaz king of Judah;

2 a son of twenty and five years was he in his reigning, and twenty and nine years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Abi daughter of Zechariah.

3 And he doth that which [is] right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that David his father did,

4 he hath turned aside the high places, and broken in pieces the standing-pillars, and cut down the shrine, and beaten down the brazen serpent that Moses made, for unto these days were the sons of Israel making perfume to it, and he calleth it`a piece of brass.'

5 In Jehovah, God of Israel, he hath trusted, and after him there hath not been like him among all the kings of Judah, nor [among any] who were before him;

6 and he cleaveth to Jehovah, he hath not turned aside from after Him, and keepeth His commands that Jehovah commanded Moses.

7 And Jehovah hath been with him, in every place where he goeth out he acteth wisely, and he rebelleth against the king of Asshur, and hath not served him;

8 he hath smitten the Philistines unto Gaza, and its borders, from a tower of watchers unto the fenced city.

9 And it cometh to pass, in the fourth year of king Hezekiah--it [is] the seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel--come up hath Shalmaneser king of Asshur against Samaria, and layeth siege to it,

10 and they capture it at the end of three years; in the sixth year of Hezekiah--it [is] the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel--hath Samaria been captureth,

11 and the king of Asshur removeth Israel to Asshur, and placed them in Halah, and in Habor [by] the river Gozan, and [in] cities of the Medes,

12 because that they have not hearkened to the voice of Jehovah their God, and transgress His covenant--all that He commanded Moses, servant of Jehovah--yea, they have not hearkened nor done [it].

13 And in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah hath Sennacherib king of Asshur come up against all the fenced cities of Judah, and seizeth them,

14 and Hezekiah king of Judah sendeth unto the king of Asshur to Lachish, saying, `I have sinned, turn back from off me; that which thou puttest on me I bear;' and the king of Asshur layeth on Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of silver, and thirty talents of gold,

15 and Hezekiah giveth all the silver that is found in the house of Jehovah, and in the treasures of the house of the king;

16 at that time hath Hezekiah cut off the doors of the temple of Jehovah, and the pillars that Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and giveth them to the king of Asshur.

17 And the king of Asshur sendeth Tartan, and the chief of the eunuchs, and the chief of the butlers, from Lachish, unto king Hezekiah, with a heavy force, to Jerusalem, and they go up and come in to Jerusalem, and they go up, and come in andstand by the conduit of the upper pool that [is] in the highway of the fuller's field.

18 And they call unto the king, and go out unto them doth Eliakim son of Hilkiah, who [is] over the house, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah son of Asaph the remembrancer.

19 And the chief of the butlers saith unto them, `Say, I pray you, unto Hezekiah, Thus said the great king, the king of Asshur, What [is] this confidence in which thou hast confided?

20 Thou hast said: Only a word of the lips! counsel and might [are] for battle; now, on whom hast thou trusted that thou hast rebelled against me?

21 `Now, lo, thou hast trusted for thee on the staff of this broken reed, on Egypt; which a man leaneth on, and it hath gone into his hand, and pierced it! --so [is] Pharaoh king of Egypt to all those trusting on him.

22 `And when ye say unto me, Unto Jehovah our God we have trusted, is it not He whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath turned aside, and saith to Judah and to Jerusalem, Before this altar do ye bow yourselves in Jerusalem?

23 `And, now, give a pledge for thee, I pray thee, to my lord the king of Asshur, and I give to thee two thousand horses, if thou art able to give for thee riders on them.

24 And how dost thou turn back the face of one captain of the least of the servants of my lord, that thou dost trust for thee on Egypt for chariot, and for horsemen?

25 Now, without Jehovah have I come up against this place to destroy it? Jehovah said unto me, Go up against this land, and thou hast destroyed it.'

26 And Eliakim son of Hilkiah saith--and Shebna, and Joah--to the chief of the butlers, `Speak, we pray thee, unto thy servants [in] Aramaean, for we are understanding, and do not speak with us [in] Jewish, in the ears of the people who [are] on the wall.'

27 And the chief of the butlers saith unto them, `For thy lord, and unto thee, hath my lord sent me to speak these words? is it not for the men, those sitting on the wall to eat their own dung and to drink their own water, with you?'

28 And the chief of the butlers standeth and calleth with a great voice [in] Jewish, and speaketh and saith, `Hear ye a word of the great king, the king of Asshur:

29 thus said the king, Let not Hezekiah lift you up, for he is not able to deliver you out of his hand;

30 and let not Hezekiah make you trust unto Jehovah, saying, Jehovah doth certainly deliver us, and this city is not given into the hand of the king of Asshur.

31 `Do not hearken unto Hezekiah, for thus said the king of Asshur, Make with me a blessing, and come out unto me, and eat ye each of his vine, and each of his fig-tree, and drink ye each the waters of his own well,

32 till my coming in, and I have taken you unto a land like your own land, a land of corn and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of oil olive, and honey, and live, and die not; and do not hearken unto Hezekiah, when he persuadeth you, saying, Jehovah doth deliver us.

33 `Have the gods of the nations delivered at all each his land out of the hand of the king of Asshur?

34 Where [are] the gods of Hamath and Arpad? where the gods of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivvah, that they have delivered Samaria out of my hand?

35 Who [are they] among all the gods of the lands that have delivered their land out of my hand, that Jehovah doth deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?'

36 And the people have kept silent, and have not answered him a word, for the command of the king is, saying, `Do not answer him.'

37 And Eliakim son of Hilkiah, who [is] over the house, cometh in, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah son of Asaph the remembrancer, unto Hezekiah, with rent garments, and they declare to him the words of the chief of the butlers.

2 Kings 19

1 And it cometh to pass, at king Hezekiah's hearing, that he rendeth his garments, and covereth himself with sackcloth, and entereth the house of Jehovah,

2 and sendeth Eliakim, who [is] over the house, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covering themselves with sackcloth, unto Isaiah the prophet, son of Amoz,

3 and they say unto him, `Thus said Hezekiah--A day of distress, and rebuke, and despising [is] this day; for come have sons unto the birth, and power there is not to bring forth.

4 `It may be Jehovah thy God doth hear all the words of the chief of the butlers with which the king of Asshur his lord hath sent him to reproach the living God, and hath decided concerning the words that Jehovah thy God hath heard, and thou hast lifted up prayer for the remnant that is found.'

5 And the servants of king Hezekiah come in unto Isaiah,

6 and Isaiah saith to them, `Thus do ye say unto your lord: Thus said Jehovah, Be not afraid because of the words that thou hast heard, with which the servants of the king of Asshur have reviled Me.

7 Lo, I am giving in him a spirit, and he hath heard a report, and hath turned back to his land, and I have caused him to fall by the sword in his land.'

8 And the chief of the butlers turneth back and findeth the king of Asshur fighting against Libnah, for he hath heard that he hath journeyed from Lachish.

9 And he heareth concerning Tirhakah king of Cush, saying, `Lo, he hath come out to fight with thee;' and he turneth and sendeth messengers unto Hezekiah, saying,

10 `Thus do ye speak unto Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Let not thy God lift thee up in whom thou art trusting, saying, Jerusalem is not given into the hand of the king of Asshur.

11 Lo, thou hast heard that which the kings of Asshur have done to all the lands--to devote them; and thou art delivered!

12 did the gods of the nations deliver them whom my fathers destroyed--Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the sons of Eden, who [are] in Thelassar?

13 Where [is] the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivvah?'

14 And Hezekiah taketh the letters out of the hand of the messengers, and readeth them, and goeth up to the house of Jehovah, and Hezekiah spreadeth it before Jehovah.

15 And Hezekiah prayeth before Jehovah, and saith, `O Jehovah, God of Israel, inhabiting the cherubs, Thou [art] God Himself--Thyself alone--to all the kingdoms of the earth: Thou hast made the heavens and the earth.

16 Incline, O Jehovah, Thine ear, and hear; open, O Jehovah, Thine eyes, and see; and hear Thou the words of Sennacherib with which he hath sent him to reproach the living God.

17 `Truly, O Jehovah, kings of Asshur have laid waste the nations, and their land,

18 and have put their gods into fire, for they [are] no gods, but work of the hands of man, wood and stone, and destroy them.

19 And now, O Jehovah our God, save us, we pray Thee, out of his hand, and know do all kingdoms of the earth that Thou [art] Jehovah God--Thyself alone.'

20 And Isaiah son of Amoz sendeth unto Hezekiah, saying, `Thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, That which thou hast prayed unto Me concerning Sennacherib king of Asshur I have heard:

21 this [is] the word that Jehovah spake concerning him: `Trampled on thee--laughed at thee, Hath the virgin daughter of Zion Behind thee shaken the head--Hath the daughter of Jerusalem?

22 Whom hast thou reproached and reviled? And against whom lifted up a voice? Yea, thou dost lift up on high thine eyes--Against the Holy One of Israel!

23 By the hand of thy messengers Thou hast reproached the Lord, and sayest: In the multitude of my chariots I have come up to a high place of mountains--The sides of Lebanon, And I cut down the height of its cedars, The choice of its firs, AndI enter the lodging of its extremity, The forest of its Carmel.

24 I have digged, and drunk strange waters, And I dry up with the sole of my steps All floods of a bulwark.

25 Hast thou not heard from afar, it I made, From days of old that I formed it? Now I have brought it in, And it becometh a desolation, Ruinous heaps [are] fenced cities,

26 And their inhabitants [are] feeble-handed, They were broken down, and are dried up, They have been the herb of the field, And the greenness of the tender grass, Grass of the roofs, And blasted corn--before it hath risen up!

27 And thy sitting down, and thy going out, And thy coming in, I have known, And thine anger towards Me;

28 Because of thine anger towards Me, And thy noise--it came up into Mine ears, I have put My hook in thy nose, And My bridle in thy lips, And have caused thee to turn back, In the way in which thou camest.

29 And this to thee [is] the sign, Food of the year [is] the spontaneous growth, And in the second year the self-produced, And in the third year sow ye, and reap, And plant vineyards, and eat their fruits.

30 And it hath continued--The escaped of the house of Judah That hath been left--to take root beneath, And hath made fruit upward.

31 For from Jerusalem goeth out a remnant, And an escape from mount Zion; The zeal of Jehovah [of Hosts] doth this.

32 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, Concerning the king of Asshur: He doth not come in unto this city, Nor doth he shoot there an arrow, Nor doth he come before it with shield. Nor doth he pour out against it a mount.

33 In the way that he cometh in--In it he turneth back, And unto this city he doth not come in, The affirmation of Jehovah--

34 And I have covered over this city, To save it, for Mine own sake, And for the sake of David My servant.'

35 And it cometh to pass, in that night, that a messenger of Jehovah goeth out, and smiteth in the camp of Asshur a hundred eighty and five thousand, and they rise early in the morning, and lo, all of them [are] dead corpses.

36 And Sennacherib king of Asshur journeyeth, and goeth, and turneth back, and dwelleth in Nineveh;

37 and it cometh to pass, he is bowing himself in the house of Nisroch his god, and Adramelech and Sharezar [his sons] have smitten him with the sword, and they have escaped to the land of Ararat, and Esar-Haddon his son reigneth in his stead.

2 Kings 23

1 And the king sendeth, and they gather unto him all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem,

2 and the king goeth up to the house of Jehovah, and every man of Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, with him, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the people, from small unto great, and he readeth in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that is found in the house of Jehovah.

3 And the king standeth by the pillar, and maketh the covenant before Jehovah, to walk after Jehovah, and to keep His commands, and His testimonies, and His statutes, with all the heart, and with all the soul, to establish the words of this covenant that are written on this book, and all the people stand in the covenant.

4 And the king commandeth Hilkiah the high priest, and the priests of the second order, and the keepers of the threshold, to bring out from the temple of Jehovah all the vessels that are made for Baal, and for the shrine, and for all the hostof the heavens, and he burneth them at the outside of Jerusalem, in the fields of Kidron, and hath borne their ashes to Beth-El.

5 And he hath caused to cease the idolatrous priests whom the kings of Judah have appointed, (and they make perfume in high places, in cities of Judah and suburbs of Jerusalem,) and those making perfume to Baal, to the sun, and to the moon, and to the planets, and to all the host of the heavens.

6 And he bringeth out the shrine from the house of Jehovah to the outside of Jerusalem, unto the brook Kidron, and burneth it at the brook Kidron, and beateth it small to dust, and casteth its dust on the grave of the sons of the people.

7 And he breaketh down the houses of the whoremongers that [are] in the house of Jehovah, where the women are weaving houses for the shrine.

8 And he bringeth in all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and defileth the high places where the priests have made perfume, from Geba unto Beer-Sheba, and hath broken down the high places of the gates that [are] at the opening of the gate of Joshua, head of the city, that [is] on a man's left hand at the gate of the city;

9 only, the priests of the high places come not up unto the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem, but they have eaten unleavened things in the midst of their brethren.

10 And he hath defiled Topheth, that [is] in the valley of the son of Hinnom, so that no man doth cause his son and his daughter to pass over through fire to Molech.

11 And he causeth to cease the horses that the kings of Judah have given to the sun from the entering in of the house of Jehovah, by the chamber of Nathan-Melech the eunuch, that [is] in the suburbs, and the chariots of the sun he hath burnt with fire.

12 And the altars that [are] on the top of the upper chamber of Ahaz, that the kings of Judah made, and the altars that Manasseh made in the two courts of the house of Jehovah, hath the king broken down, and removeth thence, and hath cast their dust unto the brook Kidron.

13 And the high places that [are] on the front of Jerusalem, that [are] on the right of the mount of corruption, that Solomon king of Israel had built to Ashtoreth abomination of the Zidonians, and Chemosh abomination of Moab, and to Milcom abomination of the sons of Ammon, hath the king defiled.

14 And he hath broken in pieces the standing-pillars, and cutteth down the shrines, and filleth their place with bones of men;

15 and also the altar that [is] in Beth-El, the high place that Jeroboam son of Nebat made, by which he made Israel sin, both that altar and the high place he hath broken down, and doth burn the high place--he hath beat it small to dust, and hath burnt the shrine.

16 And Josiah turneth, and seeth the graves that [are] there in the mount, and sendeth and taketh the bones out of the graves, and burneth [them] on the altar, and defileth it, according to the word of Jehovah that the man of God proclaimed, who proclaimed these things.

17 And he saith, `What [is] this sign that I see?' and the men of the city say unto him, `The grave of the man of God who hath come from Judah, and proclaimeth these things that thou hast done concerning the altar of Beth-El.'

18 And he saith, `Let him alone, let no man touch his bones;' and they let his bones escape, with the bones of the prophet who came out of Samaria.

19 And also all the houses of the high places that [are] in the cities of Samaria, that the kings of Israel made to provoke to anger, hath Josiah turned aside, and doth to them according to all the deeds that he did in Beth-El.

20 And he slayeth all the priests of the high places who [are] there by the altars, and burneth the bones of man upon them, and turneth back to Jerusalem.

21 And the king commandeth the whole of the people, saying, `Make ye a passover to Jehovah your God, as it is written on this book of the covenant.'

22 Surely there hath not been made like this passover from the days of the judges who judged Israel, even all the days of the kings of Israel, and of the kings of Judah;

23 but in the eighteenth year of king Josiah, hath this passover been made to Jehovah in Jerusalem.

24 And also, those having familiar spirits, and the wizards, and the teraphim, and the idols, and all the abominations that were seen in the land of Judah, and in Jerusalem, hath Josiah put away, in order to establish the words of the law thatare written on the book that Hilkiah the priest hath found in the house of Jehovah.

25 And like him there hath not been before him a king who turned back unto Jehovah with all his heart, and with all his soul, and with all his might, according to all the law of Moses, and after him there hath none risen like him.

26 Only, Jehovah hath not turned back from the fierceness of His great anger with which His anger burned against Judah, because of all the provocations with which Manasseh provoked him,

27 and Jehovah saith, `Also Judah I turn aside from my presence, as I turned Israel aside, and I have rejected this city that I have chosen--Jerusalem, and the house of which I said, My name is there.'

28 And the rest of the matters of Josiah, and all that he did, are they not written on the book of the Chronicles of the kings of Judah?

29 In his days hath Pharaoh-Nechoh king of Egypt come up against the king of Asshur, by the river Phrat, and king Josiah goeth out to meet him, and he putteth him to death in Megiddo, when he seeth him.

30 And his servants cause him to ride dying from Megiddo, and bring him in to Jerusalem, and bury him in his own grave, and the people of the land take Jehoahaz son of Josiah, and anoint him, and cause him to reign instead of his father.

31 A son of twenty and three years [is] Jehoahaz in his reigning, and three months he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Hamutal daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah,

32 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that his fathers did,

33 and Pharaoh-Nechoh bindeth him in Riblah, in the land of Hamath, from reigning in Jerusalem, and he putteth a fine on the land--a hundred talents of silver, and a talent of gold.

34 And Pharaoh-Nechoh causeth Eliakim son of Josiah to reign instead of Josiah his father, and turneth his name to Jehoiakim, and Jehoahaz he hath taken away, and he cometh in to Egypt, and dieth there.

35 And the silver and the gold hath Jehoiakim given to Pharaoh; only he valued the land to give the silver by the command of Pharaoh; from each, according to his valuation, he exacted the silver and the gold, from the people of the land, to give to Pharaoh-Nechoh.

36 A son of twenty and five years [is] Jehoiakim in his reigning, and eleven years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Zebudah daughter of Pedaiah of Rumah,

37 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that his fathers did.

1 Chronicles 1

1 Adam, Sheth, Enosh,

2 Kenan, Mahalaleel, Jered,

3 Henoch, Methuselah, Lamech,

4 Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.

5 Sons of Japheth: Gomer and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshech, and Tiras.

6 And sons of Gomer: Ashchenaz, and Riphath, and Togarmah.

7 And sons of Javan: Elisha, and Tarshishah, Kittim, and Dodanim.

8 Sons of Ham: Cush, and Mizraim, Put, and Canaan.

9 And sons of Cush: Seba and Havilah, and Sabta, and Raamah, and Sabtecka. And sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.

10 And Cush begat Nimrod: he began to be a mighty one in the land.

11 And Mizraim begat the Ludim, and the Anamim, and the Lehabim, and the Naphtuhim,

12 and the Pathrusim, and the Casluhim (from whom came out the Philistim), and the Caphtorim.

13 And Canaan begat Zidon his first born, and Heth,

14 and the Jebusite, and the Amorite, and the Girgashite,

15 and the Hivite, and the Arkite, and the Sinite,

16 and the Arvadite, and the Zemarite, and the Hamathite.

17 Sons of Shem: Elam and Asshur, and Arphaxad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Meshech.

18 And Arphaxad begat Shelah, and Shelah begat Eber.

19 And to Eber have been born two sons, the name of the one [is] Peleg, for in his days hath the land been divided, and the name of his brother is Joktan.

20 And Joktan begat Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah,

21 and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah,

22 and Ebal, and Abimael, and Sheba,

23 and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab; all these [are] sons of Joktan.

24 Shem, Arphaxad, Shelah,

25 Eber, Peleg, Reu,

26 Serug, Nahor, Terah,

27 Abram--he [is] Abraham.

28 Sons of Abraham: Isaac and Ishmael.

29 These [are] their generations: first-born of Ishmael, Nebaioth, and Kedar, and Adheel, and Mibsam,

30 Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema,

31 Jetur, Naphish, and Kedema. These are sons of Ishmael.

32 And sons of Keturah, Abraham's concubine: she bare Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And sons of Jokshan: Sheba and Dedan.

33 And sons of Midian: Ephah and Epher, and Henoch, and Abida, and Eldaah; all these [are] sons of Keturah.

34 And Abraham begetteth Isaac. Sons of Isaac: Esau and Israel.

35 Sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jaalam, and Korah.

36 Sons of Eliphaz: Teman, and Omar, Zephi, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek.

37 Sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.

38 And sons of Seir: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezar, and Dishan.

39 And sons of Lotan: Hori and Homam, and sister of Lotan [is] Timna.

40 Sons of Shobal: Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And sons of Zideon: Aiah and Anah.

41 The sons of Anah: Dishon. and sons of Dishon: Amram, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Cheran.

42 Sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zavan, Jakan. Sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran.

43 And these [are] the kings who reigned in the land of Edom before the reigning of a king of the sons of Israel: Bela son of Beor, and the name of his city [is] Dinhabah.

44 And Bela dieth, and reign in his stead doth Jobab son of Zerah from Bozrali;

45 and Jobab dieth, and reign in his stead doth Husham from the land of the Temanite;

46 and Husham dieth, and reign in his stead doth Hadad, son of Bedad (who smiteth Midian in the field of Moab) and the name of his city [is] Avith;

47 and Hadad dieth, and reign in his stead doth Samlah from Masrekah;

48 and Samlah dieth, and reign in his stead doth Shaul from Rehoboth of the River;

49 and Shaul dieth, and reign in his stead doth Baal-Hanan son of Achbor;

50 and Baal-Hanan dieth, and reign in his stead doth Hadad, and the name of his city [is] Pai, and the name of his wife [is] Mehetabel daughter of Matred, daughter of Me-Zahab; Hadad also dieth.

51 And chiefs of Edom are: chief Timnah, chief Aliah, chief Jetheth,

52 chief Aholibamah, chief Elah, chief Pinon,

53 chief Kenaz, chief Teman, chief Mibzar,

54 chief Magdiel, chief Iram. These [are] chiefs of Edom.

1 Chronicles 2

1 These [are] sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun,

2 Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.

3 Sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah, three have been born to him of a daughter of Shua the Canaanitess. And Er, first-born of Judah, is evil in the eyes of Jehovah, and He putteth him to death.

4 And Tamar his daughter-in-law hath borne to him Pharez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah [are] five.

5 Sons of Pharez: Hezron, and Hamul.

6 And sons of Zerah: Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara; all of them five.

7 And sons of Carmi: Achar, troubler of Israel, who trespassed in the devoted thing.

8 And sons of Ethan: Azariah.

9 And sons of Hezron who were born to him; Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai.

10 And Ram begat Amminadab, and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the sons of Judah;

11 and Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz,

12 and Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse;

13 and Jesse begat his first-born Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third,

14 Nethaneel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,

15 Ozem the sixth, David the seventh,

16 and their sisters Zeruiah and Abigail. And sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, and Joab, and Asah-El--three.

17 And Abigail hath borne Amasa, and the father of Amasa [is] Jether the Ishmeelite.

18 And Caleb son of Hezron hath begotten Azubah, Isshah, and Jerioth; and these [are] her sons: Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon.

19 And Azubah dieth, and Caleb taketh to him Ephrath, and she beareth to him Hur.

20 And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezaleel.

21 And afterwards hath Hezron gone in unto a daughter of Machir father of Gilead, and he hath taken her, and he [is] a son of sixty years, and she beareth to him Segub.

22 And Segub begat Jair, and he hath twenty and three cities in the land of Gilead,

23 and he taketh Geshur and Aram, the small villages of Jair, from them, with Kenath and its small towns, sixty cities--all these [belonged to] the sons of Machir father of Gilead.

24 And after the death of Hezron in Caleb-Ephratah, then the wife of Hezron, Abijah, even beareth to him Asshur, father of Tekoa.

25 And sons of Jerahmeel, first-born of Hezron, are: the first-born Ram, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, Ahijah.

26 And Jerahmeel hath another wife, and her name [is] Atarah, she [is] mother of Onam.

27 And sons of Ram, first-born of Jerahmeel, are Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker.

28 And sons of Onam are Shammai and Jada. And sons of Shammai: Nadab and Abishur.

29 And the name of the wife of Abishur [is] Abihail, and she beareth to him Ahban and Molid.

30 And sons of Nadab: Seled, and Appaim; and Seled dieth without sons.

31 And sons of Appaim: Ishi. And sons of Ishi: Sheshan. And sons of Sheshan: Ahlai.

32 And sons of Jada, brother of Shammai: Jether, and Jonathan: and Jether dieth without sons.

33 And sons of Jonathan: Peleth, and Zaza. These were sons of Jerahmeel.

34 And Sheshan had no sons, but daughters, and Sheshan hath a servant, an Egyptian, and his name [is] Jarha,

35 and Sheshan giveth his daughter to Jarha his servant for a wife, and she beareth to him Attai;

36 and Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad,

37 and Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed,

38 and Obed begat Jehu,

39 and Jehu begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah,

40 and Eleasah begat Sismai, and Sismai begat Shallum,

41 and Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.

42 And sons of Caleb brother of Jerahmeel: Mesha his first-born, he [is] father of Ziph; and sons of Mareshah: Abi-Hebron.

43 And sons of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.

44 And Shema begat Raham father of Jorkoam, and Rekem begat Shammai.

45 And a son of Shammai [is] Maon, and Maon [is] father of Beth-Zur.

46 And Ephah concubine of Caleb bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez; and Haran begat Gazez.

47 And sons of Jahdai: Regem, and Jotham, and Geshem, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph.

48 The concubine of Caleb, Maachah, bare Sheber and Tirhanah;

49 and she beareth Shaaph father of Madmannah, Sheva father of Machbenah, and father of Gibea; and a daughter of Caleb [is] Achsa.

50 These were sons of Caleb son of Hur, first-born of Ephrathah: Shobal father of Kirjath-Jearim,

51 Salma father of Beth-Lehem, Hareph father of Beth-Gader.

52 And there are sons to Shobal father of Kirjath-Jearim: Haroeh, half of the Menuhothite;

53 and the families of Kirjath-Jearim: the Ithrite, and the Puhite, and the Shumathite, and the Mishraite: from these went out the Zareathite, and the Eshtaulite.

54 Sons of Salma: Beth-Lehem, and the Netophathite, Atroth, Beth-Joab, and half of the Menuhothite, the Zorite;

55 and the families of the scribes the inhabitants of Jabez: Tirathites, Shimeathites, Suchathites. They [are] the Kenites, those coming of Hammath father of the house of Rechab.

1 Chronicles 3

1 And these were sons of David, who were born to him in Hebron: the first-born Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; second Daniel, of Abigail the Carmelitess;

2 the third Absalom, son of Maachah daughter of Talmai king of Geshur; the fourth Adonijah, son of Haggith;

3 the fifth Shephatiah, of Abital; the sixth Ithream, of Eglah his wife.

4 Six have been borne to him in Hebron, and he reigneth there seven years and six months, and thirty and three years he hath reigned in Jerusalem.

5 And these were born to him in Jerusalem: Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon--four, of Bath-Sheba daughter of Ammiel:

6 also Ibhar, and Elishama, and Eliphelet,

7 and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,

8 and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet, nine.

9 All [are] sons of David, apart from sons of the concubines, and Tamar their sister.

10 And the son of Solomon [is] Rehoboam, Abijah his son, Asa his son, Jehoshaphat his son,

11 Joram his son, Ahaziah his son, Joash his son,

12 Amaziah his son, Azariah his son, Jotham his son,

13 Ahaz his son, Hezekiah his son, Manasseh his son,

14 Amon his son, Josiah his son.

15 And sons of Josiah: the first-born Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.

16 And sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.

17 And sons of Jeconiah: Assir; Salathiel his son;

18 also Malchiram and Pedaiah, and Shenazzar, Jecamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.

19 And sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel, and Shimei. And sons of Zerubbabel: Meshullam, and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister,

20 and Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berechiah, and Hasadiah, Jushab-Hesed, five.

21 And sons of Hananiah: Pelatiah, and Jesaiah, sons of Rephaiah, sons of Arnan, sons of Obadiah, sons of Shechaniah.

22 And sons of Shechaniah: Shemaiah; and sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, and Igeal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six.

23 And sons of Neariah: Elioenai, and Hezekiah, and Azrikam, three.

24 And sons of Elioenai: Hodaiah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Delaiah, and Anani, seven.

1 Chronicles 4

1 Sons of Judah: Pharez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal.

2 And Reaiah son of Shobal begat Jahath, and Jahath begat Ahumai and Lahad; these [are] families of the Zorathite.

3 And these [are] of the father of Etam: Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash; and the name of their sister [is] Hazzelelponi,

4 and Penuel [is] father of Gedor, and Ezer father of Hushah. These [are] sons of Hur, first-born of Ephratah, father of Beth-Lehem.

5 And to Ashhur father of Tekoa were two wives, Helah and Naarah;

6 and Naarah beareth to him Ahuzzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari: these [are] sons of Naarah.

7 And sons of Helah: Zereth, and Zohar, and Ethnan.

8 And Coz begat Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel son of Harum.

9 And Jabez is honoured above his brethren, and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, `Because I have brought forth with grief.'

10 And Jabez calleth to the God of Israel, saying, `If blessing Thou dost bless me, then Thou hast made great my border, and Thy hand hath been with me, and Thou hast kept [me] from evil--not to grieve me;' and God bringeth in that which he asked.

11 And Chelub brother of Shuah begat Mehir; he [is] father of Eshton.

12 And Eshton begat Beth-Rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah father of Ir-Nahash; these [are] men of Rechah.

13 And sons of Kenaz: Othniel, and Seraiah; and sons of Othniel: Hathath.

14 And Meonothai begat Ophrah, and Seraiah begat Joab father of the valley of artificers, for they were artificers.

15 And sons of Caleb son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam; and sons of Elah, even Kenaz.

16 And sons of Jehaleleel: Ziph and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asareel.

17 And sons of Ezra [are] Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon: and she beareth Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah father of Eshtemoa.

18 And his wife Jehudijah bare Jered father of Gedor, and Heber father of Socho, and Jekuthiel father of Zanoah. And these [are] sons of Bithiah daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took,

19 and sons of the wife of Hodiah sister of Nahom: Abi-Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maachathite.

20 And sons of Shimon [are] Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben-Hanon, and Tilon; and sons of Ishi: Zoheth, and Ben-Zoheth.

21 Sons of Shelah son of Judah: Er father of Lecah, and Laadah father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of the service of fine linen, of the house of Ashbea;

22 and Jokim, and the men of Chozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who ruled over Moab and Jashubi-Lehem; and these things [are] ancient.

23 They [are] the potters and inhabitants of Netaim and Gedera; with the king in his work they dwelt there.

24 Sons of Simeon: Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul;

25 Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.

26 And sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zacchur his son, Shimei his son.

27 And to Shimei [are] sixteen sons and six daughters, and to his brethren there are not many sons, and none of their families have multiplied as much as the sons of Judah.

28 And they dwell in Beer-Sheba, and Moladah, and Hazar-Shaul,

29 and in Bilhah, and in Ezem, and in Tolad,

30 and in Bethuel, and in Hormah, and in Ziklag,

31 and in Beth-Marcaboth, and in Hazar-Susim, and in Beth-Birei, and in Shaarim; these [are] their cities till the reigning of David.

32 And their villages [are] Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities,

33 and all their villages that [are] round about these cities unto Baal; these [are] their dwellings, and they have their genealogy:

34 even Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah son of Amaziah,

35 and Joel, and Jehu son of Josibiah, son of Seraiah, son of Asiel,

36 and Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah,

37 and Ziza son of Shiphi, son of Allon, son of Jedaiah, son of Shimri, son of Shemaiah.

38 These who are coming in by name [are] princes in their families, and the house of their fathers have broken forth into a multitude;

39 and they go to the entrance of Gedor, unto the east of the valley, to seek pasture for their flock,

40 and they find pasture, fat and good, and the land broad of sides, and quiet, and safe, for of Ham are those dwelling there before.

41 And these who are written by name come in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and smite their tents, and the habitations that have been found there, and devote them to destruction unto this day, and dwell in their stead, because pasturefor their flock [is] there.

42 And of them, of the sons of Simeon, there have gone to mount Seir, five hundred men, and Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, sons of Ishi, at their head,

43 and they smite the remnant of those escaped of Amalek, and dwell there unto this day.

1 Chronicles 5

1 As to sons of Reuben, first-born of Israel--for he [is] the first-born, and on account of his profaning the couch of his father hath his birthright been given to the sons of Joseph son of Israel, and [he is] not to be reckoned by genealogy for the birthright,

2 for Judah hath been mighty over his brother, and for leader above him, and the birthright [is] to Joseph.

3 Sons of Reuben, first-born of Israel: Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi.

4 Sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son,

5 Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son,

6 Beerah his son, whom Tilgath-Pilneser king of Asshur removed; he [is] prince of the Reubenite.

7 And his brethren, by their families, in the genealogy of their generations, [are] heads: Jeiel, and Zechariah,

8 and Bela son of Azaz, son of Shema, son of Joel--he is dwelling in Aroer, even unto Nebo and Baal-Meon;

9 and at the east he dwelt even unto the entering in of the wilderness, even from the river Phrat, for their cattle were multiplied in the land of Gilead.

10 And in the days of Saul they have made war with the Hagarites, who fall by their hand, and they dwell in their tents over all the face of the east of Gilead.

11 And the sons of Gad, over-against them have dwelt in the land of Bashan unto Salcah,

12 Joel the head, and Shapham the second, and Jaanai and Shaphat in Bashan;

13 and their brethren of the house of their fathers [are] Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jachan, and Zia, and Heber, seven.

14 These [are] sons of Abihail son of Huri, son of Jaroah, son of Gilead, son of Michael, son of Jeshishai, son of Jahdo, son of Buz;

15 Ahi son of Abdiel, son of Guni, [is] head of the house of their fathers;

16 and they dwell in Gilead in Bashan, and in her small towns, and in all suburbs of Sharon, upon their outskirts;

17 all of them reckoned themselves by genealogy in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.

18 Sons of Reuben, and the Gadite, and the half of the tribe of Manasseh, of sons of valour, men bearing shield and sword, and treading bow, and taught in battle, [are] forty and four thousand and seven hundred and sixty, going out to thehost.

19 And they make war with the Hagarites, and Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab,

20 and they are helped against them, and the Hagarites are given into their hand, and all who [are] with them, for they cried to God in battle, and He was entreated of them, because they trusted in Him.

21 And they take captive their cattle, of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and of asses two thousand, and of human beings a hundred thousand;

22 for many have fallen pierced, for of God [is] the battle; and they dwell in their stead till the removal.

23 And the sons of the half of the tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land, from Bashan unto Baal-Hermon, and Senir, and mount Hermon, they have multiplied.

24 And these [are] heads of the house of their fathers, even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, men mighty in valour, men of name, heads to the house of their fathers.

25 And they trespass against the God of their fathers, and go a-whoring after the gods of the peoples of the land whom God destroyed from their presence;

26 and stir up doth the God of Israel the spirit of Pul king of Asshur, and the spirit of Tilgath-Pilneser king of Asshur, and he removeth them--even the Reubenite, and the Gadite, and the half of the tribe of Manasseh--and bringeth them in to Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and the river of Gozan unto this day.

1 Chronicles 6

1 Sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

2 And the sons of Kohath; Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.

3 And sons of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. And sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.

4 Eleazar begat Phinehas, Phinehas begat Abishua,

5 and Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi,

6 and Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth,

7 Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,

8 and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz,

9 and Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan,

10 and Johanan begat Azariah, him who acted as priest in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem.

11 And Azariah begetteth Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub,

12 and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Shallum,

13 and Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah,

14 and Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak;

15 and Jehozadak hath gone in Jehovah's removing Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.

16 Sons of Levi: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari.

17 And these [are] names of sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei.

18 And sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.

19 Sons of Merari; Mahli and Mushi. And these [are] families of the Levite according to their fathers;

20 of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,

21 Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeaterai his son.

22 Sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son,

23 Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son,

24 Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.

25 And sons of Elkanah; Amasai and Ahimoth.

26 Elkanah; sons of Elkanah: Zophai his son, and Nahath his son,

27 Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.

28 And sons of Samuel: the first-born Vashni, and the second Abijah.

29 Sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son,

30 Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.

31 And these [are] they whom David stationed over the parts of the song of the house of Jehovah, from the resting of the ark,

32 and they are ministering before the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, in song, till the building by Solomon of the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem; and they stand according to their ordinance over their service.

33 And these [are] those standing, and their sons: of the sons of the Kohathite: Heman the singer, son of Joel, son of Shemuel,

34 son of Elkanah, son of Jeroham, son of Eliel, son of Toah,

35 son of Zuph, son of Elkanah, son of Mahath, son of Amasai,

36 son of Elkanah, son of Joel, son of Azariah, son of Zephaniah,

37 son of Tahath, son of Assir, son of Ebiasaph, son of Korah,

38 son of Izhar, son of Kohath, son of Levi, son of Israel.

39 And his brother Asaph, who is standing on his right--Asaph, son of Berachiah, son of Shimea,

40 son of Michael, son of Baaseiah, son of Malchiah,

41 son of Ethni, son of Zerah, son of Adaiah,

42 son of Ethan, son of Zimmah, son of Shimei,

43 son of Jahath, son of Gershom, son of Levi.

44 And sons of Merari, their brethren, [are] on the left. Ethan son of Kishi, son of Abdi, son of Malluch,

45 son of Hashabiah, son of Amaziah, son of Hilkiah,

46 son of Amzi, son of Bani, son of Shamer,

47 son of Mahli, son of Mushi, son of Merari, son of Levi.

48 And their brethren the Levites are put to all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.

49 And Aaron and his sons are making perfume on the altar of the burnt-offering, and on the altar of the perfume, for all the work of the holy of holies, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses servant of God commanded.

50 And these [are] sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son,

51 Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son,

52 Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son,

53 Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.

54 And these [are] their dwellings, throughout their towers, in their borders, of the sons of Aaron, of the family of the Kohathite, for theirs was the lot;

55 and they give to them Hebron in the land of Judah and its suburbs round about it;

56 and the field of the city and its villages they gave to Caleb son of Jephunneh.

57 And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge: Hebron, and Libnah and its suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa and its suburbs,

58 and Hilen and its suburbs, Debir and its suburbs,

59 and Ashan and its suburbs, and Beth-Shemesh and its suburbs.

60 And from the tribe of Benjamin, Geba and its suburbs, and Allemeth and its suburbs, and Anathoth and its suburbs. All their cities [are] thirteen cities, for their families.

61 And to the sons of Kohath, those left of the family of the tribe, from the half of the tribe, the half of Manasseh, by lot, [are] ten cities.

62 And to the sons of Gershom, for their families, from the tribe of Issachar, and from the tribe of Asher, and from the tribe of Naphtali, and from the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities.

63 To the sons of Merari, for their families, from the tribe of Reuben, and from the tribe of Gad, and from the tribe of Zebulun, by lot, twelve cities.

64 And the sons of Israel give to the Levites the cities and their suburbs.

65 And they give by lot from the tribe of the sons of Judah, and from the tribe of the sons of Simeon, and from the tribe of the sons of Benjamin, these cities which they call by name;

66 and some of the families of the sons of Kohath have cities of their border from the tribe of Ephraim;

67 and they give to them the cities of refuge, Shechem and its suburbs in the hillcountry of Ephraim, and Gezer and its suburbs,

68 and Jokmeam and its suburbs, and Beth-Horan and its suburbs,

69 and Aijalon and its suburbs, and Gath-Rimmon and its suburbs;

70 and from the half tribe of Manasseh, Aner and its suburbs, and Bileam and its suburbs, for the family of the sons of Kohath who are left.

71 To the sons of Gershom from the family of the half of the tribe of Manasseh [are] Golan in Bashan and its suburbs, and Ashtaroth and its suburbs;

72 and from the tribe of Issachar; Kedesh and its suburbs, Daberath and its suburbs,

73 and Ramoth and its suburbs, and Anem and its suburbs;

74 and from the tribe of Asher; Mashal and its suburbs, and Abdon and its suburbs,

75 and Hukok and its suburbs, and Rehob and its suburbs;

76 and from the tribe of Naphtali: Kedesh in Galilee and its suburbs, and Hammon and its suburbs, and Kirjathaim and its suburbs.

77 To the sons of Merari who are left, from the tribe of Zebulun, [are] Rimmon and its suburbs, Tabor and its suburbs;

78 and from beyond the Jordan by Jericho, at the east of the Jordan, from the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness and its suburbs, and Jahzah and its suburbs,

79 and Kedemoth and its suburbs, and Mephaath and its suburbs;

80 and from the tribe of Gad: Ramoth in Gilead and its suburbs, and Mahanaim and its suburbs,

81 and Heshbon and its suburbs, and Jazer and its suburbs.

1 Chronicles 7

1 And sons of Issachar; Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.

2 And sons of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Jibsam, and Shemuel, heads of the house of their fathers, [even] of Tola, mighty of valour in their generations: their number in the days of David [is] twenty and two thousand and six hundred.

3 And sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah; and sons of Izrahiah: Michael, and Obadiah, and

4 And beside them, by their generations, of the house of their fathers, [are] troops of the host of battle, thirty and six thousand, for they multiplied wives and sons;

5 and their brethren of all the families of Issachar [are] mighty of valour, eighty and seven thousand, all have their genealogy.

6 Of Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three.

7 And sons of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of a house of fathers, mighty of valour, with their genealogy, twenty and two thousand, and thirty and four.

8 And sons of Becher: Zemirah, and Joash, and Eliezar, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jerimoth, and Abijah, and Anathoth, and Alameth. All these [are] sons of Becher,

9 with their genealogy, after their generations, heads of a house of their fathers, mighty of valour, twenty thousand and two hundred.

10 And sons of Jediael: Bilhan; and sons of Bilhan: Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tarshish, and Ahishahar.

11 All these [are] sons of Jediael, even heads of the fathers, mighty in valour, seventeen thousand and two hundred going out to the host for battle.

12 And Shuppim and Huppim [are] sons of Ir; Hushim son of Aher.

13 Sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shallum, sons of Bilhah.

14 Sons of Manasseh: Ashriel, whom Jaladah his Aramaean concubine bare, with Machir father of Gilead.

15 And Machir took wives for Huppim and for Shuppim, and the name of the one [is] Maachah, and the name of the second Zelophehad, and Zelophehad hath daughters.

16 And Maachah wife of Machir beareth a son and calleth his name Peresh, and the name of his brother [is] Sheresh, and his sons [are] Ulam and Rakem.

17 And son of Ulam: Bedan. These [are] sons of Gilead son of Machir, son of Manasseh.

18 And his sister Hammolecheth bare Ishhod, and Abiezer, and Mahalah.

19 And the sons of Shemida are Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.

20 And sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eladah his son, and Tahath his son,

21 and Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead; and slain them have men of Gath who are born in the land, because they came down to take their cattle.

22 And Ephraim their father mourneth many days, and his brethren come in to comfort him,

23 and he goeth in unto his wife, and she conceiveth and beareth a son, and he calleth his name Beriah, because in evil had been his house, --

24 and his daughter [is] Sherah, and she buildeth Beth-Horon, the lower and the upper, and Uzzen-Sherah--

25 and Rephah [is] his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son,

26 Laadan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son,

27 Non his son, Jehoshua his son.

28 And their possession and their dwellings [are] Beth-El and its small towns, and to the east Naaran, and to the west Gezer and its small towns, and Shechem and its small towns, unto Gaza and its small towns;

29 and by the parts of the sons of Manasseh, Beth-Shean and its small towns, Taanach and its small towns, Megiddo and its small towns, Dor and its small towns; in these dwelt the sons of Joseph son of Israel.

30 Son of Asher: Imnah, and Ishve, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister.

31 And sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel--he [is] father of Birzavith.

32 And Heber begat Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister.

33 And sons of Japhlet: Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath; these [are] sons of Japhlet.

34 and sons of Shamer: Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram.

35 And son of Helem his brother: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal.

36 Sons of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah,

37 Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.

38 And sons of Jether: Jephunneh, and Pispah, and Ara.

39 And sons of Ulla: Arah, and Hanniel, and Rezia.

40 All these [are] sons of Asher, heads of the house of the fathers, chosen ones, mighty in valour, heads of the princes, with their genealogy, for the host, for battle, their number [is] twenty and six thousand men.

1 Chronicles 8

1 And Benjamin begat Bela his first-born, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third,

2 Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.

3 And there are sons to Bela: Addar, and Gera,

4 and Abihud, and Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah,

5 and Gera, and Shephuphan, and Huram.

6 And these [are] sons of Ehud: they are heads of fathers to the inhabitants of Geba, and they remove them unto Manahath;

7 and Naaman, and Ahiah, and Gera, he removed them, and begat Uzza and Ahihud.

8 And Shaharaim begat in the field of Moab, after his sending them away; Hushim and Baara [are] his wives.

9 And he begetteth of Hodesh his wife, Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malcham,

10 and Jeuz, and Shachiah, and Mirmah. These [are] his sons, heads of fathers.

11 And of Hushim he begat Ahitub and Elpaal.

12 And sons of Elpaal: Eber, and Misheam, and Shamer, (he built Ono and Lod and its small towns),

13 and Beriah and Shema, (they [are] the heads of fathers to the inhabitants of Aijalon--they caused to flee the inhabitants of Gath),

14 and Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth,

15 and Zebadiah, and Arad, and Ader,

16 and Michael, and Ispah, and Joha, sons of Beriah,

17 and Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hezeki, and Heber,

18 and Ishmerai, and Jezliah, and Jobab, sons of Elpaal;

19 And Jakim, and Zichri, and Zabdi,

20 and Elienai, and Zillethai, and Eliel,

21 and Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, sons of Shimei;

22 And Ishpan, and Heber, and Eliel,

23 and Abdon, and Zichri, and Hanan,

24 and Hananiah, and Elam, and Antothijah,

25 and Iphedeiah, and Penuel, sons of Shashak;

26 And Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah,

27 and Jaareshiah, and Eliah, and Zichri, sons of Jeroham.

28 These [are] heads of fathers, by their generations, heads; these dwelt in Jerusalem.

29 And in Gibeon hath the father of Gibeon dwelt, and the name of his wife [is] Maachah;

30 and his son, the first-born, [is] Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab,

31 and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zacher;

32 and Mikloth begat Shimeah. And they also over-against their brethren dwelt in Jerusalem with their brethren.

33 And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchi-Shua, and Abinadab, and Esh-Baal.

34 And a son of Jonathan [is] Merib-Baal, and Merib-Baal begat Micah;

35 and sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tarea, and Ahaz:

36 and Ahaz begat Jehoadah, and Jehoadah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza,

37 and Moza begat Binea, Raphah [is] his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.

38 And to Azel [are] six sons, and these [are] their names: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these [are] sons of Azel.

39 And sons of Eshek his brother: Ulam his first-born, Jehush the second, and Eliphelet the third.

40 And the sons of Ulam are men mighty in valour, treading bow, and multiplying sons and son's sons, a hundred and fifty. All these [are] of the sons of Benjamin.

1 Chronicles 9

1 And all Israel have reckoned themselves by genealogy, and lo, they are written on the book of the kings of Israel and Judah--they were removed to Babylon for their trespass.

2 And the first inhabitants, who [are] in their possession, in their cities, of Israel, [are] the priests, the Levites, and the Nethinim.

3 And in Jerusalem dwelt of the sons of Judah, and of the sons of Benjamin, and of the sons of Ephraim and Manasseh:

4 Uthai son of Ammihud, son of Omri, son of Imri, son of Bani, of the sons of Pharez, son of Judah.

5 And of the Shilonite: Asaiah the first-born, and his sons.

6 And of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel, and their brethren, six hundred and ninety.

7 And of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu son of Meshullam, son of Hodaviah, son of Hassenuah,

8 and Ibneiah son of Jeroham, and Elah son of Uzzi, son of Michri, and Meshullam son of Shephatiah, son of Reuel, son of Ibnijah.

9 And their brethren, according to their generations, [are] nine hundred and fifty and six. All these [are] men, heads of fathers, according to the house of their fathers.

10 And of the priests: Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, and Jachin,

11 and Azariah son of Hilkiah, son of Meshullam, son of Zadok, son of Meraioth, son of Ahitub, leader in the house of God;

12 and Adaiah son of Jeroham, son of Pashhur, son of Malchijah, and Maasai son of Adiel, son of Jahzerah, son of Meshullam, son of Meshillemith, son of Immer.

13 And their brethren, heads to the house of their fathers, a thousand and seven hundred and sixty, mighty in valour, [are] for the work of the service of the house of God.

14 And of the Levites: Shemaiah son of Hashshub, son of Azrikam, son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari;

15 and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah son of Micah, son of Zichri, son of Asaph;

16 and Obadiah son of Shemariah, son of Galal, son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah, son of Asa, son of Elkanah, who is dwelling in the villages of the Netophathite.

17 And the gatekeepers [are] Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brethren--Shallum [is] the head;

18 and hitherto they [are] at the gate of the king eastward; they [are] the gatekeepers for the companies of the sons of Levi.

19 And Shallum son of Kore, son of Ebiasaph, son of Korah, and his brethren, of the house of his father, the Korahites, [are] over the work of the service, keepers of the thresholds of the tent, and their fathers [are] over the camp of Jehovah, keepers of the entrance;

20 and Phinehas son of Eleazar hath been leader over them formerly; Jehovah [is] with him.

21 Zechariah son of Meshelemiah [is] gatekeeper at the opening of the tent of meeting.

22 All of those who are chosen for gatekeepers at the thresholds [are] two hundred and twelve; they [are] in their villages, by their genealogy; they whom David and Samuel the seer appointed in their office.

23 And they and their sons [are] over the gates of the house of Jehovah, even of the house of the tent, by watches.

24 At four sides are the gatekeepers, east, west, north, and south.

25 And their brethren in their villages [are] to come in for seven days from time to time with these.

26 For in office [are] the four chiefs of the gatekeepers, they are Levites, and they have been over the chambers, and over the treasuries of the house of God,

27 and round about the house of God they lodge, for on them [is] the watch, and they [are] over the opening, even morning by morning.

28 And [some] of them [are] over the vessels of service, for by number they bring them in, and by number they take them out.

29 And [some] of them are appointed over the vessels, even over all the vessels of the sanctuary, and over the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices.

30 And [some] of the sons of the priests are mixing the mixture for spices.

31 And Mattithiah, of the Levites (he [is] the first-born to Shallum the Korahite), [is] in office over the work of the pans.

32 And of the sons of the Kohathite, [some] of their brethren [are] over the bread of the arrangement, to prepare [it] sabbath by sabbath.

33 And these who sing, heads of fathers of the Levites, in the chambers, [are] free, for by day and by night [they are] over them in the work.

34 These heads of the fathers of the Levites throughout their generations [are] heads. These have dwelt in Jerusalem.

35 And in Gibeon dwelt hath the father of Gibeon, Jehiel, and the name of his wife [is] Maachah;

36 and his son, the first-born, [is] Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab,

37 and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth.

38 And Mikloth begat Shimeam, and they also, over-against their brethren, have dwelt in Jerusalem with their brethren.

39 And Ner begat Kish, and Kish begat Saul, and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchi- Shua, and Abinadab, and Esh-Baal.

40 And a son of Jonathan [is] Merib-Baal, and Merib-Baal begat Micah.

41 And sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea,

42 and Ahaz--he begat Jaarah, and Jaarah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri, and Zimri begat Moza,

43 and Moza begat Binea, and Rephaiah [is] his son. Eleasah his son, Azel his son.

44 And to Azel [are] six sons, and these their names: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these [are] sons of Azel.

1 Chronicles 11

1 And gathered are all Israel unto David to Hebron, saying, `Lo, thy bone and thy flesh [are] we;

2 even in time past, even in Saul's being king, it is thou who art taking out and bringing in Israel, and Jehovah thy God saith to thee: Thou dost feed My people Israel, and thou art leader over My people Israel.'

3 And all the elders of Israel come in unto the king to Hebron, and David maketh with them a covenant in Hebron before Jehovah, and they anoint David for king over Israel, according to the word of Jehovah by the hand of Samuel.

4 And David goeth, and all Israel, to Jerusalem--it [is] Jebus--and there the Jebusite, the inhabitants of the land.

5 And the inhabitants of Jebus say to David, `Thou dost not come in hither;' and David captureth the fortress of Zion--it [is] the city of David.

6 And David saith, `Whoever smiteth the Jebusite first doth become head and prince;' and go up first doth Joab son of Zeruiah and becometh head.

7 And David dwelleth in the fortress, therefore they have called it, `City of David;'

8 and he buildeth the city round about, from Millo, and unto the circumference, and Joab restoreth the rest of the city.

9 And David goeth, going on and becoming great, and Jehovah of Hosts [is] with him.

10 And these [are] heads of the mighty ones whom David hath, who are strengthening themselves with him in his kingdom, with all Israel, to cause him to reign, according to the word of Jehovah, over Israel.

11 And this [is] an account of the mighty ones whom David hath: Jashobeam son of a Hachmonite [is] head of the thirty; he is lifting up his spear against three hundred--wounded, at one time.

12 And after him [is] Eleazar son of Dodo the Ahohite, he [is] among the three mighty;

13 he hath been with David in Pas-Dammim, and the Philistines have been gathered there to battle, and a portion of the field is full of barley, and the people have fled from the face of the Philistines,

14 and they station themselves in the midst of the portion, and deliver it, and smite the Philistines, and Jehovah saveth--a great salvation.

15 And three of the thirty heads go down on the rock unto David, unto the cave of Adullam, and the host of the Philistines is encamping in the valley of Rephaim,

16 and David [is] then in the fortress, and the station of the Philistines [is] then in Beth-Lehem,

17 and David longeth, and saith, `Who doth give me to drink water from the well of Beth-Lehem, that [is] at the gate!'

18 And the three break through the camp of the Philistines, and draw water from the well of Beth-Lehem, that [is] at the gate, and bear and bring in unto David, and David hath not been willing to drink it, and poureth it out to Jehovah,

19 and saith, `Far be it from me, by my God, to do this; the blood of these men do I drink with their lives? for with their lives they have brought it;' and he was not willing to drink it; these [things] did the three mighty ones.

20 And Abishai brother of Joab, he hath been head of the three: and he is lifting up his spear against three hundred--wounded, and hath a name among three.

21 Of the three by the two he is honoured, and becometh their head; and unto the [first] three he hath not come.

22 Benaiah son of Jehoiada, son of a man of valour, of great deeds, from Kabzeel: he hath smitten the two lion-like Moabites, and he hath gone down and smitten the lion in the midst of the pit, in the day of snow.

23 And he hath smitten the man, the Egyptian--a man of measure, five by the cubit--and in the hand of the Egyptian [is] a spear like a beam of weavers, and he goeth down unto him with a rod, and taketh violently away the spear out of the hand of the Egyptian, and slayeth him with his own spear.

24 These [things] hath Benaiah son of Jehoiada done, and hath a name among the three mighty ones.

25 Of the thirty, lo, he [is] honoured, and unto the [first] three he hath not come, and David setteth him over his guard.

26 And the mighty ones of the forces [are] Asahel brother of Joab, Elhanan son of Dodo of Beth-Lehem,

27 Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite,

28 Ira son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abi-Ezer the Annethothite,

29 Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite,

30 Maharai the Netophathite, Heled son of Baanah the Netophathite,

31 Ithai son of Ribai of Gibeah, of the sons of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite,

32 Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite,

33 Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite,

34 the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan son of Shage the Hararite,

35 Ahiam son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal son of Ur,

36 Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite,

37 Hezor the Carmelite, Naarai son of Ezbai,

38 Joel brother of Nathan, Mibhar son of Haggeri,

39 Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, bearer of the weapons of Joab son of Zeruiah,

40 Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,

41 Uriah the Hittite, Zabad son of Ahlai,

42 Adina son of Shiza the Reubenite, head of the Reubenites, and by him thirty,

43 Hanan son of Maachah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite,

44 Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jehiel sons of Hothan the Aroerite,

45 Jediael son of Shimri, and Joha his brother the Tizite,

46 Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite,

47 Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mesobaite.

1 Chronicles 12

1 And these [are] those coming in unto David to Ziklag, while shut up because of Saul son of Kish, and they [are] among the mighty ones, helping the battle,

2 armed with bow, right and left handed, with stones, and with arrows, with bows, of the brethren of Saul, of Benjamin.

3 The head [is] Ahiezer, and Joash, sons of Shemaab the Gibeathite, and Jeziel, and Pelet, sons of Azmaveth, and Berachah, and Jehu the Antothite,

4 and Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty one among the thirty, and over the thirty, and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Josabad the Gederathite.

5 Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite;

6 Elkanah, and Jesiah, and Azareel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam the Korhites,

7 and Joelah, and Zebadiah, sons of Jeroham of Gedor.

8 And of the Gadite there have been separated unto David, to the fortress, to the wilderness, mighty of valour, men of the host for battle, setting in array target and buckler, and their faces the face of the lion, and as roes on the mountains for speed:

9 Ezer the head, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third,

10 Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth,

11 Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh,

12 Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth,

13 Jeremiah the tenth, Machbannai the eleventh.

14 These [are] of the sons of Gad, heads of the host, one of a hundred [is] the least, and the greatest, of a thousand;

15 these [are] they who have passed over the Jordan in the first month, --and it is full over all its banks--and cause all [they of] the valley to flee to the east and to the west.

16 And there come of the sons of Benjamin and Judah unto the stronghold to David,

17 and David goeth out before them, and answereth and saith to them, `If for peace ye have come in unto me, to help me, I have a heart to unite with you; and if to betray me to mine adversaries--without violence in my hands--the God of our fathers doth see and reprove.'

18 And the Spirit hath clothed Amasai, head of the captains: `To thee, O David, and with thee, O son of Jesse--peace! peace to thee, and peace to thy helper, for thy God hath helped thee;' and David receiveth them, and putteth them among the heads of the troop.

19 And of Manasseh there have fallen unto David in his coming with the Philistines against Israel to battle--and they helped them not, for by counsel the princes of the Philistines sent him away, saying, `With our heads he doth fall unto his master Saul.' --

20 In his going unto Ziglag there have fallen unto him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zillthai, heads of the thousands that [are] of Manasseh;

21 and they have helped with David over the troop, for mighty of valour [are] all of them, and they are captains in the host,

22 for at that time, day by day, they come in unto David to help him, till it is a great camp, like a camp of God.

23 And these [are] the numbers of the head, of the armed men of the host; they have come in unto David to Hebron to turn round the kingdom of Saul unto him, according to the mouth of Jehovah.

24 The sons of Judah, bearing target and spear, [are] six thousand and eight hundred, armed ones of the host.

25 Of the sons of Simeon, mighty ones of valour for the host, [are] seven thousand and a hundred.

26 Of the sons of Levi [are] four thousand and six hundred;

27 and Jehoiada [is] the leader of the Aaronite, and with him [are] three thousand and seven hundred,

28 and Zadok, a young man, mighty of valour, and of the house of his father [are] twenty and two heads.

29 And of the sons of Benjamin, brethren of Saul, [are] three thousand, and hitherto their greater part are keeping the charge of the house of Saul.

30 And of the sons of Ephraim [are] twenty thousand and eight hundred, mighty of valour, men of name, according to the house of their fathers.

31 And of the half of the tribe of Manasseh [are] eighteen thousand, who have been defined by name, to come in to cause David to reign.

32 And of the sons of Issachar, having understanding for the times, to know what Israel should do; their heads [are] two hundred, and all their brethren [are] at their command.

33 Of Zebulun, going forth to the host, arranging battle with all instruments of battle, [are] fifty thousand, and keeping rank without a double heart.

34 And of Naphtali, a thousand heads, and with them, with target and spear, [are] thirty and seven thousand.

35 And of the Danite, arranging battle, [are] twenty and eight thousand and six hundred.

36 And of Asher, going forth to the host, to arrange battle, [are] forty thousand.

37 And from beyond the Jordan, of the Reubenite, and of the Gadite, and of the half of the tribe of Manasseh, with all instruments of the host for battle, [are] a hundred and twenty thousand.

38 All these [are] men of war, keeping rank--with a perfect heart they have come to Hebron, to cause David to reign over all Israel, and also all the rest of Israel [are] of one heart, to cause David to reign,

39 and they are there, with David, three days, eating and drinking, for their brethren have prepared for them.

40 And also those near unto them, unto Issachar, and Zebulun, and Naphtali, are bringing in bread on asses, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen--food of fine flour, fig-cakes and grape-cakes, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep, in abundance, for joy [is] in Israel.

1 Chronicles 15

1 And he maketh for himself houses in the city of David, and prepareth a place for the ark of God, and stretcheth out for it a tent.

2 Then said David, `None [are] to carry the ark of God, except the Levites, for on them hath Jehovah fixed to carry the ark of God, and to serve Him--unto the age.'

3 And David assembleth all Israel unto Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of Jehovah unto its place that he had prepared for it.

4 And David gathereth the sons of Aaron, and the Levites.

5 Of sons of Kohath: Uriel the chief, and his brethren, a hundred and twenty.

6 Of sons of Merari: Asaiah the chief, and his brethren, two hundred and twenty.

7 Of sons of Gershom: Joel the chief, and his brethren, a hundred and thirty.

8 Of sons of Elizaphan: Shemaiah the chief, and his brethren, two hundred.

9 Of sons of Hebron: Eliel the chief, and his brethren, eighty.

10 Of sons of Uzziel: Amminadab the chief, and his brethren, a hundred and twelve.

11 And David calleth to Zadok and to Abiathar the priests, and to the Levites, to Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab,

12 and saith to them, `Ye [are] heads of the fathers of the Levites; sanctify yourselves, ye and your brethren, and ye have brought up the ark of Jehovah, God of Israel, unto [the place] I have prepared for it;

13 because at the first [it was] not ye, Jehovah our God made a breach upon us, because we sought Him not according to the ordinance.'

14 And the priests and the Levites sanctify themselves, to bring up the ark of Jehovah, God of Israel;

15 and sons of the Levites bear the ark of God, as Moses commanded, according to the word of Jehovah, on their shoulder, with staves, above them.

16 And David saith to the heads of the Levites to appoint their brethren the singers, with instruments of song, psalteries, and harps, and cymbals, sounding, to lift up with the voice for joy.

17 And the Levites appoint Heman son of Joel, and of his brethren, Asaph son of Berechiah, and of the sons of Merari their brethren, Ethan son of Kushaiah;

18 and with them their brethren, the seconds [in rank], Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah; and Obed-Edom and Jeiel the gatekeepers;

19 and the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, with cymbals of brass to sound,

20 and Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jeheil, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries besides virgins,

21 and Mattithiah, and Elipheleh, and Mikneiah, and Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps, on the octave, to oversee.

22 And Chenaniah, head of the Levites, [is] over the burden; he instructeth about the burden, for he [is] intelligent.

23 And Berechiah and Elkanah [are] gatekeepers for the ark.

24 And Shebaniah, and Joshaphat, and Nethaneel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer the priests, are blowing with trumpets before the ark of God; and Obed- Edom and Jehiah [are] gatekeepers for the ark.

25 And it is David, and the elders of Israel, and the heads of the thousands, who are going to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah from the house of Obed-Edom with joy;

26 and it cometh to pass, in God's helping the Levites bearing the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, that they sacrifice seven bullocks and seven rams.

27 And David is wrapped in an upper robe of fine linen, and all the Levites who are bearing the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah head of the burden of the singers; and on David [is] an Ephod of linen.

28 And all Israel are bringing up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah with shouting, and with the sound of a cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, sounding with psalteries and harps,

29 and it cometh to pass, the ark of the covenant of Jehovah is entering in unto the city of David, and Michal daughter of Saul is looking through the window, and seeth king David dancing and playing, and despiseth him in her heart.

1 Chronicles 16

1 And they bring in the ark of God, and set it up in the midst of the tent that David hath stretched out for it, and they bring near burnt-offerings and peace-offerings before God;

2 and David ceaseth from offering the burnt-offering and the peace-offerings, and blesseth the people in the name of Jehovah,

3 and giveth a portion to every man of Israel, both man and woman: to each a cake of bread, and a measure of wine, and a grape-cake.

4 And he putteth before the ark of Jehovah, of the Levites, ministers, even to make mention of, and to thank, and to give praise to Jehovah, God of Israel,

5 Asaph the head, and his second Zechariah; Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, with instruments of psalteries, and with harps; and Asaph with cymbals is sounding;

6 and Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests [are] with trumpets continually before the ark of the covenant of God.

7 On that day then hath David given at the beginning to give thanks to Jehovah by the hand of Asaph and his brethren: --

8 Give thanks to Jehovah, call in His name, Make known among the peoples His doings.

9 Sing ye to Him, sing psalms to Him, Meditate on all His wonders.

10 Boast yourselves in His holy name, Rejoice doth the heart of those seeking Jehovah.

11 Seek ye Jehovah and His strength, Seek His face continually.

12 Remember His wonders that He did, His signs, and the judgments of His mouth,

13 O seed of Israel, His servant, O sons of Jacob, His chosen ones!

14 He [is] Jehovah our God, In all the earth [are] His judgments.

15 Remember ye to the age His covenant, The word He commanded--To a thousand generations,

16 Which He hath made with Abraham, And His oath--to Isaac,

17 And He establisheth it to Jacob for a statute, To Israel--a covenant age-during.

18 Saying: To thee I give the land of Canaan, The portion of your inheritance,

19 When ye are few of number, As a little thing, and sojourners in it.

20 And they go up and down, From nation unto nation, And from a kingdom unto another people.

21 He hath not suffered any to oppress them, And reproveth on their account kings:

22 Come not against Mine anointed ones, And against My prophets do not evil.

23 Sing to Jehovah, all the earth, Proclaim from day unto day His salvation.

24 Rehearse among nations His glory, Among all the peoples His wonders.

25 For great [is] Jehovah, and praised greatly, And fearful He [is] above all gods.

26 For all gods of the peoples [are] nought, And Jehovah the heavens hath made.

27 Honour and majesty [are] before Him, Strength and joy [are] in His place.

28 Ascribe to Jehovah, ye families of peoples, Ascribe to Jehovah honour and strength.

29 Ascribe to Jehovah the honour of His name, Lift up a present, and come before Him. Bow yourselves to Jehovah, In the beauty of holiness.

30 Be pained before Him, all the earth:

31 Also, established is the world, It is not moved! The heavens rejoice, and the earth is glad, And they say among nations: Jehovah hath reigned.

32 Roar doth the sea, and its fulness, Exult doth the field, and all that [is] in it,

33 Then sing do trees of the forest, From the presence of Jehovah, For He hath come to judge the earth!

34 Give thanks to Jehovah, for good, For to the age, [is] His kindness,

35 And say, Save us, O God of our salvation, And gather us, and deliver us from the nations, To give thanks to Thy holy name, To triumph in Thy praise.

36 Blessed [is] Jehovah, God of Israel, From the age and unto the age;' And all the people say, `Amen,' and have given praise to Jehovah.

37 And he leaveth there before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, for Asaph and for his brethren, to minister before the ark continually, according to the matter of a day in its day,

38 both Obed-Edom and their brethren, sixty and eight, and Obed-Edom son of Jeduthun, and Hosah for gatekeepers,

39 and Zadok the priest, and his brethren the priests, before the tabernacle of Jehovah, in a high place that [is] in Gibeon,

40 to cause to ascend burnt-offerings to Jehovah, on the altar of burnt-offering continually, morning and evening, and for all that is written in the law of Jehovah, that He charged on Israel.

41 And with them [are] Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest of those chosen, who were defined by name, to give thanks to Jehovah, for to the age [is] His kindness,

42 and with them--Heman and Jeduthun--[are] trumpets and cymbals for those sounding, and instruments of the song of God, and the sons of Jeduthun [are] at the gate.

43 And all the people go, each to his house, and David turneth round to bless his house.

1 Chronicles 19

1 And it cometh to pass after this, that Nahash king of the sons of Ammon dieth, and his son reigneth in his stead,

2 and David saith, `I do kindness with Hanun son of Nahash, for his father did with me kindness;' and David sendeth messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And the servants of David come in unto the land of the sons of Ammon, unto Hanun, to comfort him,

3 and the heads of the sons of Ammon say to Hanun, `Is David honouring thy father, in thine eyes, because he hath sent to thee comforters? in order to search, and to overthrow, and to spy out, the land, have not his servants come in unto thee?'

4 And Hanun taketh the servants of David, and shaveth them, and cutteth their long robes in the midst, unto the buttocks, and sendeth them away.

5 And [some] go, and declare to David concerning the men, and he sendeth to meet them--for the men have been greatly ashamed--and the king saith, `Dwell in Jericho till that your beard is grown, then ye have returned.'

6 And the sons of Ammon see that they have made themselves abhorred by David, and Hanun and the sons of Ammon send a thousand talents of silver, to hire to them, from Aram-Naharaim, and from Aram-Maachah, and from Zobah, chariots and horsemen;

7 and they hire to them two and thirty thousand chariots, and the king of Maachah and his people, and they come in and encamp before Medeba, and the sons of Ammon have been gathered out of their cities, and come in to the battle.

8 And David heareth, and sendeth Joab, and all the host of the mighty men,

9 and the sons of Ammon come out and set battle in array at the opening of the city, and the kings who have come [are] by themselves in the field.

10 And Joab seeth that the front of the battle hath been unto him, before and behind, and he chooseth out of all the choice in Israel, and setteth in array to meet Aram,

11 and the remnant of the people he hath given into the hand of Abishai his brother, and they set in array to meet the sons of Ammon.

12 And he saith, `If Aram be stronger than I, then thou hast been to me for salvation; and if the sons of Ammon be stronger than thou, then I have saved thee;

13 be strong, and we strengthen ourselves, for our people, and for the cities of our God, and Jehovah doth that which is good in His eyes.'

14 And Joab draweth nigh, and the people who [are] with him, before Aram to battle, and they flee from his face;

15 and the sons of Ammon have seen that Aram hath fled, and they flee--they also--from the face of Abishai his brother, and go in to the city. And Joab cometh in to Jerusalem.

16 And Aram seeth that they have been smitten before Israel, and send messengers, and bring out Aram that [is] beyond the River, and Shophach head of the host of Hadarezer [is] before them.

17 And it is declared to David, and he gathereth all Israel, and passeth over the Jordan, and cometh in unto them, and setteth in array against them; yea, David setteth in array the battle to meet Aram, and they fight with him;

18 and Aram fleeth from the face of Israel, and David slayeth of Aram seven thousand charioteers, and forty thousand footmen, and Shophach head of the host he hath put to death.

19 And the servants of Hadarezer see that they have been smitten before Israel, and they make peace with David and serve him, and Aram hath not been willing to help the sons of Ammon any more.

1 Chronicles 22

1 And David saith, `This is the house of Jehovah God, and this the altar for burntoffering for Israel.'

2 And David saith to gather the sojourners who [are] in the land of Israel, and appointeth hewers to hew hewn-stones to build a house of God.

3 And iron in abundance for nails for leaves of the gates, and for couplings, hath David prepared, and brass in abundance--there is no weighing.

4 And cedar-trees even without number, for the Zidonians and the Tyrians brought in cedar-trees in abundance to David.

5 And David saith, `Solomon my son [is] a youth and tender, and the house to be built to Jehovah [is] to be made exceedingly great, for name and for beauty to all the lands; let me prepare, I pray Thee, for it;' and David prepareth in abundance before his death.

6 And he calleth for Solomon his son, and chargeth him to build a house to Jehovah, God of Israel,

7 and David saith to Solomon his son, `As for me, it hath been with my heart to build a house to the name of Jehovah my God,

8 and the word of Jehovah [is] against me, saying, Blood in abundance thou hast shed, and great wars thou hast made: thou dost not build a house to My name, for much blood thou hast shed to the earth before Me.

9 `Lo, a son is born to thee; he is a man of rest, and I have given rest to him from all his enemies round about, for Solomon is his name, and peace and quietness I give unto Israel in his days;

10 he doth build a house to My name, and he is to Me for a son, and I [am] to him for a father, and I have established the throne of his kingdom over Israel unto the age.

11 `Now, my son, Jehovah is with thee, and thou hast prospered, and hast built the house of Jehovah thy God, as He spake concerning thee.

12 Only, Jehovah give to thee wisdom and understanding, and charge thee concerning Israel, even to keep the law of Jehovah thy God;

13 then thou dost prosper, if thou dost observe to do the statutes and the judgments that Jehovah charged Moses with concerning Israel; be strong and courageous; do not fear, nor be cast down.

14 `And lo, in mine affliction, I have prepared for the house of Jehovah of gold talents a hundred thousand, and of silver a thousand thousand talents; and of brass and of iron there is no weighing, for in abundance it hath been, and woodand stones I have prepared, and to them thou dost add.

15 `And with thee in abundance [are] workmen, hewers and artificers of stone and of wood, and every skilful man for every work.

16 To the gold, to the silver, and to the brass, and to the iron, there is no number; arise and do, and Jehovah is with thee.'

17 And David giveth charge to all heads of Israel to give help to Solomon his son,

18 `Is not Jehovah your God with you? yea, He hath given rest to you round about, for He hath given into my hand the inhabitants of the land, and subdued hath been the land before His people.

19 `Now, give your heart and your soul to seek to Jehovah your God, and rise and build the sanctuary of Jehovah God, to bring in the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and the holy vessels of God, to the house that is built to the name of Jehovah.'

1 Chronicles 23

1 And David is old, and satisfied with days, and causeth his son Solomon to reign over Israel,

2 and gathereth all the heads of Israel, and the priests, and the Levites;

3 and the Levites are numbered from a son of thirty years and upward, and their number, by their polls, is of mighty men thirty and eight thousand.

4 Of these to preside over the work of the house of Jehovah [are] twenty and four thousand, and officers and judges six thousand,

5 and four thousand gatekeepers, and four thousand giving praise to Jehovah, `with instruments that I made for praising,' [saith David.]

6 And David distributeth them into courses: Of the sons of Levi: of Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

7 Of the Gershonite: Laadan and Shimei.

8 Sons of Laadan: the head [is] Jehiel, and Zetham, and Joel, three.

9 Sons of Shimei [are] Shelomith, and Haziel, and Haran, three; these [are] heads of the fathers of Laadan.

10 And sons of Shimei [are] Jahath, Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah; these [are] sons of Shimei, four.

11 And Jahath is the head, and Zizah the second, and Jeush and Beriah have not multiplied sons, and they become the house of a father by one numbering.

12 Sons of Kohath [are] Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.

13 Sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses; and Aaron is separated for his sanctifying the holy of holies, he and his sons--unto the age, to make perfume before Jehovah, to serve Him, and to bless in His name--unto the age.

14 As to Moses, the man of God, his sons are called after the tribe of Levi.

15 Sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer.

16 Sons of Gershom: Shebuel the head.

17 And sons of Eliezer are Rehabiah the head, and Eliezer had no other sons, and the sons of Rehabiah have multiplied exceedingly.

18 Sons of Izhar: Shelomith the head.

19 Sons of Hebron: Jeriah the head, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.

20 Sons of Uzziel: Micah the head, and Ishshiah, the second.

21 Sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish.

22 And Eleazar dieth, and he had no sons, but daughters, and sons of Kish their brethren take them.

23 Sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth, three.

24 These [are] sons of Levi, by the house of their fathers, heads of the fathers, by their appointments, in the number of names, by their polls, doing the work for the service of the house of Jehovah, from a son of twenty years and upward,

25 for David said, `Jehovah, God of Israel, hath given rest to His people, and He doth tabernacle in Jerusalem unto the age;'

26 and also of the Levites, `None [are] to bear the tabernacle and all its vessels for its service;'

27 for by the last words of David they [took] the number of the sons of Levi from a son of twenty years and upward,

28 for their station [is] at the side of the sons of Aaron, for the service of the house of Jehovah, over the courts, and over the chambers, and over the cleansing of every holy thing, and the work of the service of the house of God,

29 and for the bread of the arrangement, and for fine flour for present, and for the thin unleavened cakes, and for [the work of] the pan, and for that which is fried, and for all [liquid] measure and [solid] measure;

30 and to stand, morning by morning, to give thanks, and to give praise to Jehovah, and so at evening;

31 and for all the burnt-offerings--burnt-offerings to Jehovah for sabbaths, for new moons, and for appointed seasons, by number, according to the ordinance upon them continually, before Jehovah.

32 And they have kept the charge of the tent of meeting, and the charge of the sanctuary, and the charge of the sons of Aaron, their brethren, for the service of the house of Jehovah.

1 Chronicles 24

1 And to the sons of Aaron [are] their courses: sons of Aaron [are] Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar,

2 and Nadab dieth, and Abihu, in the presence of their father, and they had no sons, and Eleazar and Ithamar act as priests.

3 And David distributeth them, and Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, according to their office in their service;

4 and there are found of the sons of Eleazar more for heads of the mighty men than of the sons of Ithamar; and they distribute them: Of the sons of Eleazar, heads for a house of fathers, sixteen; and of the sons of Ithamar, for a house oftheir fathers, eight.

5 And they distribute them, by lots, one with another, for princes of the sanctuary, and princes of God, have been of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar.

6 And Shemaiah son of Nethaneel the scribe, of the Levites, writeth them before the king and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech son of Abiathar, and heads of the fathers, for priests and for Levites: one house of a father being taken possession of for Eleazar, and one being taken possession of for Ithamar.

7 And the first lot goeth out for Jehoiarib, for Jedaiah the second,

8 for Harim the third, for Seorim the fourth,

9 for Malchijah the fifth, for Mijamin the sixth,

10 for Hakkoz the seventh, for Abijah the eighth,

11 for Jeshuah the ninth, for Shecaniah the tenth,

12 for Eliashib the eleventh, for Jakim the twelfth,

13 for Huppah the thirteenth, for Jeshebeab the fourteenth,

14 for Bilgah the fifteenth, for Immer the sixteenth,

15 for Hezir the seventeenth, for Aphses the eighteenth,

16 for Pethahiah the nineteenth, for Jehezekel the twentieth,

17 for Jachin the one and twentieth, for Gamul the two and twentieth,

18 for Delaiah the three and twentieth, for Maaziah the four and twentieth.

19 These [are] their appointments for their service, to come in to the house of Jehovah, according to their ordinance by the hand of Aaron their father, as Jehovah God of Israel, commanded them.

20 And for the sons of Levi who are left: for sons of Amram, Shubael; for sons of Shubael: Jehdeiah.

21 For Rehabiah: for sons of Rehabiah, the head Ishshiah.

22 For the Izharite: Shelomoth; for sons of Shelomoth: Jahath.

23 And sons of Jeriah: Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth.

24 Sons of Uzziel: Michah; for sons of Michah: Shamir.

25 A brother of Michah [is] Ishshiah; for sons of Ishshiah: Zechariah;

26 sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; sons of Jaaziah: Beno;

27 sons of Merari: of Jaaziah: Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri.

28 For Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons;

29 for Kish: sons of Kish: Jerahmeel.

30 And sons of Mushi [are] Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth; these [are] sons of the Levites, for the house of their fathers,

31 and they cast, they also, lots over-against their brethren the sons of Aaron, before David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and heads of the fathers, for priests and for Levites; the chief father over-against his younger brother.

1 Chronicles 26

1 For the courses of the gatekeepers: of the Korhites [is] Meshelemiah son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph;

2 and to Meshelemiah [are] sons, Zechariah the first-born, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth,

3 Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Elioenai the seventh.

4 And to Obed-Edom [are] sons, Shemaiah the first-born, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethaneel the fifth,

5 Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth, for God hath blessed him.

6 And to Shemaiah his son have sons been born, who are ruling throughout the house of their father, for they [are] mighty of valour.

7 Sons of Shemaiah [are] Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad; his brethren [are] sons of valour, Elihu and Semachiah,

8 all these [are] of the sons of Obed-Edom; they, and their sons, and their brethren, men of valour with might for service, [are] sixty and two of Obed-Edom.

9 And to Meshelemiah [are] sons and brethren, sons of valour, eighteen;

10 and to Hosah, of the sons of Merari, [are] sons: Shimri the head (though he was not first-born, yet his father setteth him for head),

11 Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth; all the sons and brethren of Hosah [are] thirteen.

12 According to these [are] the courses of the gatekeepers; to the heads of the mighty ones [are] charges over-against their brethren, to minister in the house of Jehovah,

13 and they cause to fall lots, as well the small as the great, according to the house of their fathers, for gate and gate.

14 And the lot falleth eastward to Shelemiah; and [for] Zechariah his son--a counsellor with understanding--they cause to fall lots, and his lot goeth out northward:

15 to Obed-Edom southward, and to his sons, the house of the gatherings;

16 to Shuppim and to Hosah to the west, with the gate Shallecheth, in the highway, the ascent, charge over-against charge;

17 to the east the Levites [are] six; to the north daily four, to the south daily four, and to the gatherings two by two,

18 at Parbar, to the west, [are] four at the highway, two at Parbar.

19 These are the courses of the gatekeepers, of the sons of the Korhite, and of the sons of Merari.

20 And of the Levites, Ahijah [is] over the treasures of the house of God, even for the treasures of the holy things.

21 Sons of Laadan: sons of the Gershonite, of Laadan, heads of the fathers of Laadan the Gershonite: Jehieli.

22 Sons of Jehieli: Zetham, and Joel his brother, over the treasures of the house of Jehovah,

23 for the Amramite, for the Izharite, for the Hebronite, for the Uzzielite.

24 And Shebuel son of Gershom, son of Moses, [is] president over the treasures.

25 And his brethren, of Eliezer, [are] Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomith his son.

26 This Shelomith and his brethren [are] over all the treasures of the holy things, that David the king, and heads of the fathers, even heads of thousands, and of hundreds, and heads of the host, sanctified;

27 from the battles, even from the spoil they sanctified to strengthen the house of Jehovah;

28 and all that Samuel the seer, and Saul son of Kish, and Abner son of Ner, and Joab son of Zeruiah sanctified, every one sanctifying [any thing--it is] by the side of Shelomith and his brethren.

29 Of the Izharite, Chenaniah and his sons [are] for the outward work over Israel, for officers and for judges.

30 Of the Hebronite, Hashabiah and his brethren, sons of valour, a thousand and seven hundred, [are] over the inspection of Israel, beyond the Jordan westward, for all the work of Jehovah, and for the service of the king.

31 Of the Hebronite, Jerijah [is] the head, of the Hebronite, according to his generations, for the fathers--in the fortieth year of the reign of David they have been sought out, and there are found among them mighty ones of valour, in Jazer of Gilead--

32 and his brethren, sons of valour, two thousand and seven hundred, [are] heads of the fathers, and king David appointeth them over the Reubenite, and the Gadite, and the half of the tribe of Manasseh, for every matter of God and matter of the king.

1 Chronicles 27

1 And the sons of Israel, after their number, heads of the fathers, and princes of the thousands and of the hundreds, and their officers, those serving the king in any matter of the courses, that are coming in and going out month by month, throughout all months of the year--[are] in each course twenty and four thousand.

2 Over the first course, for the first month, [is] Jashobeam son of Zabdiel, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand;

3 of the sons of Perez [is] the head of all princes of the hosts for the first month.

4 And over the course of the second month [is] Dodai the Ahohite, and his course, and Mikloth [is] the president, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

5 Head of the third host, for the third month, [is] Benaiah son of Jehoiada, the head priest, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

6 This Benaiah [is] a mighty one of the thirty, and over the thirty, and [in] his course [is] Ammizabad his son.

7 The fourth, for the fourth month, [is] Asahel brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

8 The fifth, for the fifth month, [is] the prince Shamhuth the Izrahite, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

9 The sixth, for the sixth month, [is] Ira son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

10 The seventh, for the seventh month, [is] Helez the Pelonite, of the sons of Ephraim, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

11 The eighth, for the eighth month, [is] Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zarhite, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

12 The ninth, for the ninth month, [is] Abiezer the Antothite, of the Benjamite, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

13 The tenth, for the tenth month, [is] Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zarhite, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

14 Eleventh, for the eleventh month, [is] Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the sons of Ephraim, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

15 The twelfth, for the twelfth month, [is] Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel, and on his course [are] twenty and four thousand.

16 And over the tribes of Israel: Of the Reubenite, a leader [is] Eliezer son of Zichri; of the Simeonite, Shephatiah son of Maachah;

17 of the Levite, Hashabiah son of Kemuel; of the Aaronite, Zadok;

18 of Judah, Elihu, of the brethren of David; of Issachar, Omri son of Michael;

19 of Zebulun, Ishmaiah son of Obadiah; of Naphtali, Jerimoth son of Azriel;

20 of the sons of Ephraim, Hoshea son of Azaziah; of the half of the tribe of Manasseh, Joel son of Pedaiah;

21 of the half of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo son of Zechariah; of Benjamin, Jaasiel son of Abner; of Dan, Azareel son of Jeroham:

22 these [are] heads of the tribes of Israel.

23 And David hath not taken up their number from a son of twenty years and under, for Jehovah said to multiply Israel as the stars of the heavens.

24 Joab son of Zeruiah hath begun to number--and hath not finished--and there is for this wrath against Israel, and the number hath not gone up in the account of the Chronicles of king David.

25 And over the treasures of the king [is] Azmaveth son of Adiel; and over the treasures in the field, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the towers, [is] Jehonathan son of Uzziah;

26 and over workmen of the field for the service of the ground [is] Ezri son of Chelub;

27 and over the vineyards [is] Shimei the Ramathite; and over what [is] in the vineyards for the treasures of wine [is] Zabdi the Shiphmite;

28 and over the olives, and the sycamores, that [are] in the low country, [is] Baal- Hanan the Gederite; and over the treasures of oil [is] Joash;

29 and over the herds that are feeding in Sharon [is] Shitrai the Sharonite; and over the herds in the valleys [is] Shaphat son of Adlai;

30 and over the camels [is] Obil the Ishmeelite; and over the asses [is] Jehdeiah the Meronothite;

31 and over the flock [is] Jaziz the Hagerite; all these [are] heads of the substance that king David hath.

32 And Jonathan, uncle of David, [is] counsellor, a man of understanding, he is also a scribe; and Jehiel son of Hachmoni [is] with the sons of the king;

33 and Ahithophel [is] counsellor to the king; and Hushai the Archite [is] the friend of the king;

34 and after Ahithophel [is] Jehoiada son of Benaiah, and Abiathar; and the head of the host of the king [is] Joab.

2 Chronicles 3

1 And Solomon beginneth to build the house of Jehovah, in Jerusalem, in the mount of Moriah, where He appeared to David his father, in the place that David had prepared, in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite,

2 and he beginneth to build in the second [day], in the second month, in the fourth year of his reign.

3 And [in] these hath Solomon been instructed to build the house of God: The length [in] cubits by the former measure [is] sixty cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits.

4 As to the porch that [is] on the front, the length [is] by the front of the breadth of the house, twenty cubits, and the height a hundred and twenty, and he overlayeth it within with pure gold.

5 And the large house he hath covered with fir-trees, and he doth cover it with good gold, and causeth to ascend on it palms and chains,

6 and he overlayeth the house with precious stone for beauty, and the gold [is] gold of Parvaim,

7 and he covereth the house, the beams, the thresholds, and its walls, and its doors, with gold, and hath graved cherubs on the walls.

8 And he maketh the most holy house: its length [is] by the front of the breadth of the house twenty cubits, and its breadth twenty cubits, and he covereth it with good gold, to six hundred talents;

9 and the weight of the nails [is] fifty shekels of gold, and the upper chambers he hath covered with gold.

10 And he maketh in the most holy house two cherubs, image work, and he overlayeth them with gold;

11 as to the wings of the cherubs, their length [is] twenty cubits, the wing of the one [is] five cubits, touching the wall of the house, and the other wing [is] five cubits, touching the wing of the other cherub.

12 And the wing of the other cherub [is] five cubits touching the wall of the house, and the other wing [is] five cubits, adhering to the wing of the other cherub.

13 The wings of these cherubs are spreading forth twenty cubits, and they are standing on their feet and their faces [are] inward.

14 And he maketh the vail of blue, and purple, and crimson, and fine linen, and causeth cherubs to go up on it.

15 And he maketh at the front of the house two pillars, thirty and five cubits in length, and the ornament that [is] on their heads five cubits.

16 And he maketh chains in the oracle, and putteth on the heads of the pillars, and maketh a hundred pomegranates, and putteth on the chains.

17 And he raiseth up the pillars on the front of the temple, one on the right, and one on the left, and calleth the name of that on the right Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz.

2 Chronicles 4

1 And he maketh an altar of brass, twenty cubits its length, and twenty cubits its breadth, and ten cubits its height.

2 And he maketh the molten sea; ten by the cubit, from its edge unto its edge, round in compass, and five by the cubit its height, and a line of thirty by the cubit doth compass it, round about.

3 And the likeness of oxen [is] under it, all round about encompassing it, ten in the cubit, compassing the sea round about; two rows of oxen are cast in its being cast.

4 It is standing on twelve oxen, three facing the north, and three facing the west, and three facing the south, and three facing the east, and the sea [is] upon them above, and all their hinder parts [are] within.

5 And its thickness [is] a handbreadth, and its lip as the work of the lip of a cup flowered with lilies; taking hold--baths three thousand it containeth.

6 And he maketh ten lavers, and putteth five on the right, and five on the left, to wash with them; the work of the burnt-offering they purge with them; and the sea [is] for priests to wash with.

7 And he maketh the ten candlesticks of gold, according to their ordinance, and placeth in the temple, five on the right, and five on the left.

8 And he maketh ten tables, and placeth in the temple, five on the right, and five on the left; and he maketh bowls of gold a hundred.

9 And he maketh the court of the priests, and the great court, and doors for the court, and their doors he hath overlaid with brass.

10 And the sea he hath placed on the right shoulder eastward, over-against the south.

11 And Huram maketh the pots, and the shovels, and the bowls, and Huram finisheth to make the work that he made for king Solomon in the house of God;

12 two pillars, and the bowls, and the crowns on the heads of the two pillars, and the two wreaths to cover the two bowls of the crowns that [are] on the heads of the pillars;

13 and the pomegranates four hundred to the two wreaths, two rows of pomegranates to the one wreath, to cover the two bowls of the crowns that [are] on the front of the pillars.

14 And the bases he hath made; and the lavers he hath made on the bases;

15 the one sea, and the twelve oxen under it,

16 and the pots, and the shovels, and the forks, and all their vessels, hath Huram his father made for king Solomon, for the house of Jehovah, of brass purified.

17 In the circuit of the Jordan hath the king cast them, in the thick soil of the ground, between Succoth and Zeredathah.

18 And Solomon maketh all these vessels in great abundance, that the weight of the brass hath not been searched out.

19 And Solomon maketh all the vessels that [are for] the house of God, and the altar of gold, and the tables, and on them [is] bread of the presence;

20 and the candlesticks, and their lamps, for their burning according to the ordinance, before the oracle, of gold refined;

21 and the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs of gold--it [is] the perfection of gold;

22 and the snuffers, and the bowls, and the spoons, and the censers, of gold refined, and the opening of the house, its innermost doors to the holy of holies, and the doors of the house to the temple, of gold.

2 Chronicles 8

1 And it cometh to pass, at the end of twenty years, that Solomon hath built the house of Jehovah, and his own house.

2 As to the cities that Huram hath given to Solomon, Solomon hath built them, and there he causeth the sons of Israel to dwell.

3 And Solomon goeth to Hamath-Zobah, and layeth hold upon it;

4 and he buildeth Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the cities of store that he hath built in Hamath.

5 And he buildeth Beth-Horon the upper, and Beth-Horon the lower--cities of defence, with walls, two-leaved doors, and bar--

6 and Baalath, and all the cities of store that Solomon had, and all the cities of the chariot, and the cities of the horsemen, and all the desire of Solomon that he desired to build in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of hisdominion.

7 All the people who are left of the Hittite, and the Amorite, and the Perizzite, and the Hivite, and the Jebusite, who are not of Israel--

8 of their sons who have been left after them in the land, whom the sons of Israel consumed not--doth Solomon lift up a tribute unto this day.

9 And none of the sons of Israel hath Solomon made servants for his work, but they [are] men of war, and heads of his captains, and heads of his charioteers, and of his horsemen;

10 and these [are] heads of the officers whom king Solomon hath, two hundred and fifty who are rulers among the people.

11 And the daughter of Pharaoh hath Solomon brought up from the city of David to the house that he built for her, for he said, `My wife doth not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, for they are holy unto whom hath come the ark of Jehovah.'

12 Then hath Solomon caused to ascend burnt-offerings to Jehovah on the altar of Jehovah that he built before the porch,

13 even by the matter of a day in its day, to cause to ascend according to the command of Moses, on sabbaths, and on new moons, and on appointed seasons, three times in a year--in the feast of unleavened things, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of booths.

14 And he establisheth, according to the ordinance of David his father, the courses of the priests over their service, and of the Levites over their charges, to praise and to minister overagainst the priests, according to the matter of a day in its day, and the gatekeepers in their courses at gate and gate, for so [is] the command of David the man of God.

15 And they have not turned aside [from] the command of the king concerning the priests and the Levites, in reference to any matter, and to the treasures.

16 And all the work of Solomon is prepared till the day of the foundation of the house of Jehovah, and till its completion; perfect is the house of Jehovah.

17 Then hath Solomon gone to Ezion-Geber, and unto Elath, on the border of the sea, in the land of Edom;

18 and Huram sendeth to him, by the hand of his servants, ships and servants knowing the sea, and they go with servants of Solomon to Ophir, and take thence four hundred and fifty talents of gold, and bring in unto king Solomon.

2 Chronicles 9

1 And the queen of Sheba hath heard of the fame of Solomon, and cometh in to try Solomon with acute sayings, to Jerusalem, with a very great company, and camels bearing spices and gold in abundance, and precious stone; and she cometh in unto Solomon, and speaketh with him all that hath been with her heart,

2 and Solomon declareth to her all her matters, and there hath not been hid a thing from Solomon that he hath not declared to her.

3 And the queen of Sheba seeth the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he hath built,

4 and the food of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the standing of his ministers, and their clothing, and his stewards, and their clothing, an his burnt-offering that he offered up in the house of Jehovah, and there hath notbeen any more spirit in her.

5 And she saith unto the king, `True [is] the word that I heard in my land concerning thy matters and concerning thy wisdom,

6 and I have given no credence to their words, till that I have come, and mine eyes see, and lo, there hath not been declared to me the half of the abundance of thy wisdom--thou hast added unto the report that I heard.

7 `O the happiness of thy men, and the happiness of thy servants--these--who are standing before thee continually, and hearing thy wisdom.

8 Let Jehovah thy God be blessed who hath delighted in thee, to put thee on His throne for king for Jehovah thy God; in the love of thy God to Israel, to establish it to the age, He hath put thee over them for king, to do judgment and righteousness.'

9 And she giveth to the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold, and spices in great abundance, and precious stone; and there hath not been any such spice as the queen of Sheba hath given to king Solomon.

10 And also, servants of Huram, and servants of Solomon, who brought in gold from Ophir, have brought in algum-trees and precious stone.

11 And the king maketh the algum-trees staircases for the house of Jehovah, and for the house of the king, and harps and psalteries for singers; and there have been none seen like these before in the land of Judah.

12 And king Solomon hath given to the queen of Sheba all her desire that she asked, apart from that which she had brought unto the king, and she turneth and goeth to her land, she and her servants.

13 And the weight of the gold that is coming to Solomon in one year is six hundred and sixty and six talents of gold,

14 apart from [what] the tourists, and the merchants, are bringing in; and all the kings of Arabia, and the governors of the land, are bringing in gold and silver to Solomon.

15 And king Solomon maketh two hundred targets of alloyed gold, six hundred [shekels] of alloyed gold he causeth to go up on the one target;

16 and three hundred shields of alloyed gold, three hundred [shekels] of gold he causeth to go up on the one shield, and the king putteth them in the house of the forest of Lebanon.

17 And the king maketh a great throne of ivory, and overlayeth it with pure gold;

18 and six steps [are] to the throne, and a footstool of gold, to the throne they are fastened, and hands [are] on this [side] and on that on the place of the sitting, and two lions are standing near the hands,

19 and twelve lions are standing there on the six steps on this [side], and on that: it hath not been made so for any kingdom.

20 And all the drinking vessels of king Solomon [are] of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon [are] of refined gold--silver is not reckoned in the days of Solomon for anything;

21 for ships of the king are going to Tarshish, with servants of Huram: once in three years come do the ships of Tarshish bearing gold, and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.

22 And king Solomon becometh greater than any of the kings of the earth for riches and wisdom;

23 and all the kings of the earth are seeking the presence of Solomon to hear his wisdom that God hath put in his heart,

24 and they are bringing in each his present, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and garments, harness, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year.

25 And there are to Solomon four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, and he placed them in cities of the chariot, and with the king in Jerusalem.

26 And he is ruling over all the kings from the River even unto the land of the Philistines, and unto the border of Egypt.

27 And the king maketh the silver in Jerusalem as stones, and the cedars he hath made as sycamores, that [are] in the low country, for abundance,

28 and they are bringing out horses from Egypt to Solomon, and from all the lands.

29 And the rest of the matters of Solomon, the first and the last, are they not written beside the matters of Nathan the prophet, and beside the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and with the visions of Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam son of Nebat?

30 And Solomon reigneth in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years,

31 and Solomon lieth with his fathers, and they bury him in the city of David his father, and reign doth Rehoboam his son in his stead.

2 Chronicles 11

1 And Rehoboam cometh in to Jerusalem, and assembleth the house of Judah and Benjamin, a hundred and eighty thousand chosen warriors, to fight with Israel, to bring back the kingdom to Rehoboam.

2 And a word of Jehovah is unto Shemaiah, a man of God, saying,

3 `Speak unto Rehoboam son of Solomon king of Judah, and unto all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying,

4 Thus said Jehovah, Ye do not go up nor fight with your brethren, turn back each to his house, for from Me hath this thing been;' and they hear the words of Jehovah, and turn back from going against Jeroboam.

5 And Rehoboam dwelleth in Jerusalem, and buildeth cities for a bulwark in Judah,

6 yea, he buildeth Beth-Lehem and Etam, and Tekoa,

7 and Beth-Zur, and Shocho, and Adullam,

8 and Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph,

9 and Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah,

10 and Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, that [are] in Judah and in Benjamin, cities of bulwarks.

11 And he strengtheneth the bulwarks, and putteth in them leaders, and treasures of food, and oil, and wine,

12 and in every city and city targets and spears, and strengtheneth them very greatly; and he hath Judah and Benjamin.

13 And the priests, and the Levites, that [are] in all Israel, have stationed themselves by him, out of all their border,

14 for the Levites have left their suburbs and their possession, and they come to Judah and to Jerusalem, for Jeroboam and his sons have cast them off from acting as priests to Jehovah,

15 and he establisheth to him priests for high places, and for goats, and for calves, that he made--

16 and after them, out of all the tribes of Israel, those giving their heart to seek Jehovah, God of Israel, have come in to Jerusalem to sacrifice to Jehovah, God of their father.

17 And they strengthen the kingdom of Judah, and strengthen Rehoboam son of Solomon, for three years, because they walked in the way of David and Solomon for three years.

18 And Rehoboam taketh to him a wife, Mahalath, child of Jerimoth son of David, [and] Abigail daughter of Eliab, son of Jesse.

19 And she beareth to him sons, Jeush, and Shamaria, and Zaham.

20 And after her he hath taken Maachah daughter of Absalom, and she beareth to him Abijah, and Attai, and Ziza, and Shelomith.

21 And Rehoboam loveth Maachah daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines--for eighteen wives he hath taken, and sixty concubines--and he begetteth twenty and eight sons, and sixty daughters.

22 And Rehoboam appointeth for head Abijah son of Maachah, for leader among his brethren, for to cause him to reign.

23 And he hath understanding, and spreadeth out of all his sons to all lands of Judah and Benjamin, to all cities of the bulwarks, and giveth to them provision in abundance; and he asketh a multitude of wives.

2 Chronicles 13

1 In the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam--Abijah reigneth over Judah;

2 three years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, (and the name of his mother [is] Michaiah daughter of Uriel, from Gibeah,) and war hath been between Abijah and Jeroboam.

3 And Abijah directeth the war with a force of mighty men of war, four hundred thousand chosen men, and Jeroboam hath set in array with him battle, with eight hundred thousand chosen men, mighty of valour.

4 And Abijah riseth up on the hill of Zemaraim that [is] in the hill-country of Ephraim, and saith, `Hear me, Jeroboam and all Israel!

5 Is it not for you to know that Jehovah, God of Israel, hath given the kingdom to David over Israel to the age, to him and to his sons--a covenant of salt?

6 and rise up doth Jeroboam, son of Nebat, servant of Solomon son of David, and rebelleth against his lord!

7 `And there are gathered unto him vain men, sons of worthlessness, and they strengthen themselves against Rehoboam son of Solomon, and Rehoboam was a youth, and tender of heart, and hath not strengthened himself against them.

8 `And now, ye are saying to strengthen yourselves before the kingdom of Jehovah in the hand of the sons of David, and ye [are] a numerous multitude, and with you calves of gold that Jeroboam hath made to you for gods.

9 `Have ye not cast out the priests of Jehovah, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and make to you priests like the peoples of the lands? every one who hath come to fill his hand with a bullock, a son of the herd, and seven rams, even hehath been a priest to No-gods!

10 `As for us, Jehovah [is] our God, and we have not forsaken Him, and priests are ministering to Jehovah, sons of Aaron and the Levites, in the work,

11 and are making perfume to Jehovah, burnt-offerings morning by morning, and evening by evening, and perfume of spices, and the arrangement of bread [is] on the pure table, and the candlestick of gold, and its lamps, to burn evening by evening, for we are keeping the charge of Jehovah our God, and ye--ye have forsaken Him.

12 `And lo, with us--at [our] head--[is] God, and His priests and trumpets of shouting to shout against you; O sons of Israel, do not fight with Jehovah, God of your fathers, for ye do not prosper.'

13 And Jeroboam hath brought round the ambush to come in from behind them, and they are before Judah, and the ambush [is] behind them.

14 And Judah turneth, and lo, against them [is] the battle, before and behind, and they cry to Jehovah, and the priests are blowing with trumpets,

15 and the men of Judah shout--and it cometh to pass, at the shouting of the men of Judah, that God hath smitten Jeroboam, and all Israel, before Abijah and Judah.

16 And the sons of Israel flee from the face of Judah, and God giveth them into their hand,

17 and Abijah and his people smite among them a great smiting, and there fall wounded of Israel five hundred thousand chosen men.

18 And the sons of Israel are humbled at that time, and the sons of Judah are strong, for they have leant on Jehovah, God of their fathers.

19 And Abijah pursueth after Jeroboam, and captureth from him cities, Beth-El and its small towns, and Jeshanah and its small towns, and Ephraim and its small towns.

20 And Jeroboam hath not retained power any more in the days of Abijah, and Jehovah smiteth him, and he dieth.

21 And Abijah strengtheneth himself, and taketh to him fourteen wives, and begetteth twenty and two sons, and sixteen daughters,

22 and the rest of the matters of Abijah, and his ways, and his words, are written in the `Inquiry' of the prophet Iddo.

2 Chronicles 14

1 And Abijah lieth with his fathers, and they bury him in the city of David, and reign doth Asa his son in his stead: in his days was the land quiet ten years.

2 And Asa doth that which is good, and that which is right, in the eyes of Jehovah his God,

3 and turneth aside the altars of the stranger, and the high places, and breaketh the standing-pillars, and cutteth down the shrines,

4 and saith to Judah to seek Jehovah, God of their fathers, and to do the law and the command;

5 and he turneth aside out of all cities of Judah the high places and the images, and the kingdom is quiet before him.

6 And he buildeth cities of bulwarks in Judah, for the land hath quiet, and there is no war with him in these years, because Jehovah hath given rest to him.

7 And he saith to Judah, `Let us build these cities, and compass [them] with wall, and towers, two-leaved doors, and bars, while the land [is] before us, because we have sought Jehovah our God, we have sought, and He giveth rest to us round about;' and they build and prosper.

8 And there is to Asa a force bearing target and spear, out of Judah three hundred thousand, and out of Benjamin, bearing shield and treading bow, two hundred and eighty thousand: all these [are] mighty of valour.

9 And come out unto them doth Zerah the Cushite with a force of a thousand thousand, and chariots three hundred, and he cometh in unto Mareshah,

10 and Asa goeth out before him, and they set battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah.

11 And Asa calleth unto Jehovah his God, and saith, `Jehovah! it is nothing with Thee to help, between the mighty and those who have no power; help us, O Jehovah, our God, for on Thee we have leant, and in Thy name we have come against this multitude; O Jehovah, our God thou [art]; let him not prevail with Thee--mortal man!

12 And Jehovah smiteth the Cushim before Asa, and before Judah, and the Cushim flee,

13 and Asa and the people who [are] with him pursue them even to Gerar, and there fall of the Cushim, for they have no preserving, because they have been broken before Jehovah, and before His camp; and they bear away very much spoil,

14 and smite all the cities round about Gerar, for a fear of Jehovah hath been upon them, and they spoil all the cities, for abundant spoil hath been in them;

15 and also tents of cattle they have smitten, and they capture sheep in abundance, and camels, and turn back to Jerusalem.

2 Chronicles 16

1 In the thirty and sixth year of the reign of Asa, come up hath Baasha king of Israel, against Judah, and buildeth Ramah, so as not to permit any going out and coming in to Asa king of Judah.

2 And Asa bringeth out silver and gold from the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and of the house of the king, and sendeth unto Ben-Hadad king of Aram, who is dwelling in Damascus, saying,

3 `A covenant [is] between me and thee, and between my father and thy father, lo, I have sent to thee silver and gold; go, break thy covenant with Baasha king of Israel, and he doth go up from off me.'

4 And Ben-Hadad hearkeneth unto king Asa, and sendeth the heads of the forces that he hath unto cities of Israel, and they smite Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-Maim, and all the stores, cities of Naphtali.

5 And it cometh to pass, at Baasha's hearing, that he ceaseth from building Ramah, and letteth his work rest;

6 and Asa the king hath taken all Judah, and they bear away the stones of Ramah, and its wood, that Baasha hath built, and he buildeth with them Geba and Mizpah.

7 And at that time hath Hanani the seer come in unto Asa king of Judah, and saith unto him, `Because of thy leaning on the king of Aram, and thou hast not leaned on Jehovah thy God, therefore hath the force of the king of Aram escaped from thy hand.

8 Did not the Cushim and the Lubim become a very great force for multitude, for chariot, and for horsemen? and in thy leaning on Jehovah He gave them into thy hand,

9 for Jehovah--His eyes go to and fro in all the earth, to show Himself strong [for] a people whose heart [is] perfect towards Him; thou hast been foolish concerning this, because-- henceforth there are with thee wars.'

10 And Asa is angry at the seer, and giveth him to the house of torture, for [he is] in a rage with him for this; and Asa oppresseth [some] of the people at that time.

11 And lo, the matters of Asa, the first and the last, lo, they are written on the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.

12 And Asa is diseased--in the thirty and ninth year of his reign--in his feet, till his disease is excessive, and also in his disease he hath not sought Jehovah, but among physicians.

13 And Asa lieth with his fathers, and dieth in the forty and first year of his reign,

14 and they bury him in [one of] his graves, that he had prepared for himself in the city of David, and they cause him to lie on a bed that [one] hath filled [with] spices, and divers kinds of mixtures, with perfumed work; and they burn for him a burning--very great.

2 Chronicles 17

1 And Jehoshaphat his son reigneth in his stead, and he strengtheneth himself against Israel,

2 and putteth a force in all the fenced cities of Judah, and putteth garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim that Asa his father had captured.

3 And Jehovah is with Jehoshaphat, for he hath walked in the first ways of David his father, and hath not sought to Baalim,

4 for to the God of his father he hath sought, and in His commands he hath walked, and not according to the work of Israel.

5 And Jehovah doth establish the kingdom in his hand, and all Judah give a present to Jehoshaphat, and he hath riches and honour in abundance,

6 and his heart is high in the ways of Jehovah, and again he hath turned aside the high places and the shrines out of Judah.

7 And in the third year of his reign he hath sent for his heads, for Ben-Hail, and for Obadiah, and for Zechariah, and for Nethaneel, and for Michaiah, to teach in cities of Judah,

8 and with them the Levites, Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah, and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehonathan, and Adonijah, and Tobijath, and Tob-Adonijah, the Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, the priests.

9 And they teach in Judah, and with them [is] the Book of the Law of Jehovah, and they go round about into all cities of Judah, and teach among the people.

10 And here is a fear of Jehovah on all kingdoms of the lands that [are] round about Judah, and they have not fought with Jehoshaphat;

11 and of the Philistines they are bringing in to Jehoshaphat a present, and tribute silver; also, the Arabians are bringing to him a flock, rams seven thousand an seven hundred, and he-goats seven thousand and seven hundred.

12 And Jehoshaphat is going on and becoming very great, and he buildeth in Judah palaces and cities of store,

13 and he hath much work in cities of Judah; and men of war, mighty of valour, [are] in Jerusalem.

14 And these [are] their numbers, for the house of their fathers: Of Judah, heads of thousands, Adnah the head, and with him mighty ones of valour, three hundred chiefs.

15 And at his hand [is] Jehohanan the head, and with him two hundred and eighty chiefs.

16 And at his hand [is] Amasiah son of Zichri, who is willingly offering himself to Jehovah, and with him two hundred chiefs, mighty of valour.

17 And of Benjamin: mighty of valour, Eliada, and with him, armed with bow and shield, two hundred chiefs.

18 And at his hand [is] Jehozabad, and with him a hundred and eighty chiefs, armed ones of the host.

19 These [are] those serving the king, apart from those whom the king put in the cities of fortress, in all Judah.

2 Chronicles 22

1 And the inhabitants of Jerusalem cause Ahaziah his youngest son to reign in his stead, (for all the elder had the troop slain that came in with the Arabians to the camp,) and Ahaziah son of Jehoram king of Judah reigneth.

2 A son of twenty and two years [is] Ahaziah in his reigning, and one year he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Athaliah daughter of Omri;

3 he also hath walked in the ways of the house of Ahab, for his mother hath been his counsellor to do wickedly.

4 And he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah, like the house of Ahab, for they have been his counsellors, after the death of his father, for destruction to him.

5 Also, in their counsel he hath walked, and goeth with Jehoram son of Ahab king of Israel to battle against Hazael king of Aram, in Ramoth-Gilead, and they of Ramah smite Joram;

6 and he turneth back to be healed in Jezreel because of the wounds with which they had smitten him in Ramah, in his fighting with Hazael king of Aram. And Azariah son of Jehoram king of Judah hath gone down to see Jehoram son of Ahab, inJezreel, for he [is] sick;

7 and from God hath been the destruction of Ahaziah, to come unto Joram: and in his coming he hath gone out with Jehoram unto Jehu son of Nimshi, whom Jehovah anointed to cut off the house of Ahab.

8 And it cometh to pass, in Jehu's executing judgment with the house of Ahab, that he findeth the heads of Judah and sons of the brethren of Ahaziah, ministers of Ahaziah, and slayeth them.

9 And he seeketh Ahaziah, and they capture him, (and he is hiding himself in Samaria), and bring him in unto Jehu, and put him to death, and bury him, for they said, `He [is] son of Jehoshaphat, who sought Jehovah with all his heart;' andthere is none to the house of Ahaziah to retain power for the kingdom.

10 And Athaliah mother of Ahaziah hath seen that her son is dead, and she riseth and destroyeth the whole seed of the kingdom of the house of Judah.

11 And Jehoshabeath daughter of the king taketh Joash son of Ahaziah, and stealeth him from the midst of the sons of the king who are put to death, and putteth him and his nurse into the inner part of the bed-chambers, and Jehoshabeath daughter of king Jehoram, wife of Jehoiada the priest, because she hath been sister of Ahaziah, hideth him from the face of Athaliah, and she hath not put him to death.

12 And he is with them in the house of God hiding himself six years, and Athaliah is reigning over the land.

2 Chronicles 24

1 A son of seven years [is] Joash in his reigning, and forty years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Zibiah of Beer-Sheba.

2 And Joash doth that which is right in the eyes of Jehovah all the days of Jehoiada the priest.

3 And Jehoiada taketh for him two wives, and he begetteth sons and daughters.

4 And it cometh to pass after this, it hath been with the heart of Joash to renew the house of Jehovah,

5 and he gathereth the priests and the Levites, and saith to them, `Go out to the cities of Judah, and gather from all Israel money to strengthen the house of your God sufficiently year by year, and ye, ye do haste to the matter;' and theLevites have not hasted.

6 And the king calleth for Jehoiada the head, and saith to him, `Wherefore hast thou not required of the Levites to bring in out of Judah and out of Jerusalem the tribute of Moses, servant of Jehovah, and of the assembly of Israel, for the tent of the testimony?

7 for sons of Athaliah, the wicked one, have broken up the house of God, and also, all the holy things of the house of Jehovah they have prepared for Baalim.'

8 And the king speaketh, and they make one chest, and put it at the gate of the house of Jehovah without,

9 and give an intimation in Judah and in Jerusalem to bring in to Jehovah the tribute of Moses, servant of God, [laid] on Israel in the wilderness.

10 And all the heads, and all the people rejoice, and they bring in, and cast into the chest, unto completion.

11 And it cometh to pass, at the time one bringeth in the chest for the inspection of the king by the hand of the Levites, and at their seeing that the money [is] abundant, that a scribe of the king hath come in, and an officer of the head-priest, and they empty the chest, and take it up and turn it back unto its place; thus they have done day by day, and gather money in abundance.

12 And the king and Jehoiada give it unto the doers of the work of the service of the house of Jehovah, and they are hiring hewers and artificers to renew the house of Jehovah, and also--to artificers in iron and brass to strengthen the house of Jehovah.

13 And those doing the business work, and there goeth up lengthening to the work by their hand, and they establish the house of God, by its proper measure, and strengthen it.

14 And at their completing [it], they have brought in before the king and Jehoiada the rest of the money, and they make it vessels for the house of Jehovah, vessels of serving, and of offering up, and spoons, even vessels of gold and silver; and they are causing burnt-offerings to ascend in the house of Jehovah continually, all the days of Jehoiada.

15 And Jehoiada is aged and satisfied with days, and dieth--a son of a hundred and thirty years in his death,

16 and they bury him in the city of David, with the kings, for he hath done good in Israel, and with God, and his house.

17 And after the death of Jehoiada come in have heads of Judah, and bow themselves to the king; then hath the king hearkened unto them,

18 and they forsake the house of Jehovah, God of their fathers, and serve the shrines and the idols, and there is wrath upon Judah and Jerusalem for this their guilt.

19 And He sendeth among them prophets, to bring them back unto Jehovah, and they testify against them, and they have not given ear;

20 and the Spirit of God hath clothed Zechariah son of Jehoiada the priest, and he standeth over-against the people, and saith to them, `Thus said God, Why are ye transgressing the commands of Jehovah, and prosper not? because ye have forsaken Jehovah--He doth forsake you.'

21 And they conspire against him, and stone him with stones by the command of the king, in the court of the house of Jehovah,

22 and Joash the king hath not remembered the kindness that Jehoiada his father did with him, and slayeth his son, and in his death he said, `Jehovah doth see, and require.'

23 And it cometh to pass, at the turn of the year, come up hath the force of Aram against him, and they come in unto Judah and Jerusalem, and destroy all the heads of the people from the people, and all their spoil they have sent to the king of Damascus,

24 for with few men have the force of Aram come in, and Jehovah hath given into their hand a mighty force for multitude, because they have forsaken Jehovah, God of their fathers; and with Joash they have executed judgments.

25 And in their going from him--for they left him with many diseases--his servants themselves have conspired against him, for the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and slay him on his bed, and he dieth; and they bury him in the city of David, and have not buried him in the graves of the kings.

26 And these [are] those conspiring against him, Zabad son of Shimeath the Ammonitess, and Jehozabad son of Shimrith the Moabitess.

27 As to his sons, and the greatness of the burden upon him, and the foundation of the house of God, lo, they are written on the `Inquiry' of the book of the Kings; and reign doth Amaziah his son in his stead.

2 Chronicles 26

1 And all the people of Judah take Uzziah (and he [is] a son of sixteen years), and cause him to reign instead of his father Amaziah.

2 He hath built Eloth, and restoreth it to Judah after the king's lying with his fathers.

3 A son of sixteen years [is] Uzziah in his reigning, and fifty and two years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and the name of his mother [is] Jecholiah of Jerusalem.

4 And he doth that which is right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that Amaziah his father did,

5 and he is as one seeking God in the days of Zechariah who hath understanding in visions of God: and in the days of his seeking Jehovah, God hath caused him to prosper.

6 And he goeth forth, and fighteth with the Philistines, and breaketh down the wall of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod, and buildeth cities about Ashdod, and among the Philistines.

7 And God helpeth him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians who are dwelling in Gur-Baal and the Mehunim.

8 And the Ammonites give a present to Uzziah, and his name goeth unto the entering in of Egypt, for he strengthened himself greatly.

9 And Uzziah buildeth towers in Jerusalem, by the gate of the corner, and by the gate of the valley, and by the angle, and strengtheneth them;

10 and he buildeth towers in the wilderness, and diggeth many wells, for he had much cattle, both in the low country and in the plain, husbandmen and vine-dressers in the mountains, and in Carmel; for he was a lover of the ground.

11 And Uzziah hath a force, making war, going forth to the host, by troops, in the number of their reckoning by the hand of Jeiel the scribe and Masseiah the officer, by the hand of Hananiah [one] of the heads of the king.

12 The whole number of heads of the fathers of the mighty ones of valour [is] two thousand and six hundred;

13 and by their hand [is] the force of the host, three hundred thousand, and seven thousand, and five hundred warriors, with mighty power to give help to the king against the enemy.

14 And Uzziah prepareth for them, for all the host, shields, and spears, and helmets, and coats of mail, and bows, even to stones of the slings.

15 And he maketh in Jerusalem inventions--a device of an inventor--to be on the towers, and on the corners, to shoot with arrows and with great stones, and his name goeth out unto a distance, for he hath been wonderfully helped till that he hath been strong.

16 And at his being strong his heart hath been high unto destruction, and he trespasseth against Jehovah his God, and goeth in unto the temple of Jehovah to make perfume upon the altar of perfume.

17 And Azariah the priest goeth in after him, and with him priests of Jehovah eighty, sons of valour,

18 and they stand up against Uzziah the king, and say to him, `Not for thee, O Uzziah, to make perfume to Jehovah, but for priests, sons of Aaron, who are sanctified to make perfume; go forth from the sanctuary, for thou hast trespassed, and [it is] not to thee for honour from Jehovah God.'

19 And Uzziah is wroth, and in his hand [is] a censer to make perfume, and in his being wroth with the priests--the leprosy hath risen in his forehead, before the priests, in the house of Jehovah, from beside the altar of perfume.

20 And Azariah the head priest looketh unto him, and all the priests, and lo, he [is] leprous in his forehead, and they hasten him thence, and also he himself hath hastened to go out, for Jehovah hath plagued him.

21 And Uzziah the king is a leper unto the day of his death, and inhabiteth a separate house--a leper, for he hath been cut off from the house of Jehovah, and Jotham his son [is] over the house of the king, judging the people of the land.

22 And the rest of the matters of Uzziah, the first and the last, hath Isaiah son of Amoz the prophet written;

23 and Uzziah lieth with his fathers, and they bury him with his fathers, in the field of the burying-place that the kings have, for they said, `He [is] a leper;' and reign doth Jotham his son in his stead.

2 Chronicles 28

1 A son of twenty years [is] Ahaz in his reigning, and sixteen years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and he hath not done that which is right in the eyes of Jehovah, as David his father,

2 and walketh in the ways of the kings of Israel, and also, molten images hath made for Baalim,

3 and himself hath made perfume in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burneth his sons with fire according to the abominations of the nations that Jehovah dispossessed from the presence of the sons of Israel,

4 and sacrificeth and maketh perfume in high places, and on the heights, and under every green tree.

5 And Jehovah his God giveth him into the hand of the king of Aram, and they smite him, and take captive from him a great captivity, and bring [them] in to Damascus, and also into the hand of the king of Israel he hath been given, and he smiteth him--a great smiting.

6 And Pekah son of Remaliah slayeth in Judah a hundred and twenty thousand in one day (the whole [are] sons of valour), because of their forsaking Jehovah, God of their fathers.

7 And Zichri, a mighty one of Ephraim, slayeth Maaseiah son of the king, and Azrikam leader of the house, and Elkanah second to the king.

8 And the sons of Israel take captive of their brethren, two hundred thousand, wives, sons and daughters, and also much spoil they have seized from them, and they bring in the spoil to Samaria.

9 And there hath been there a prophet of Jehovah (Oded [is] his name), and he goeth out before the host that hath come in to Samaria, and saith to them, `Lo, in the fury of Jehovah God of your fathers against Judah, He hath given them into your hand, and ye slay among them in rage--unto the heavens it hath come;

10 and now, sons of Judah and Jerusalem ye are saying to subdue for menservants and for maid-servants to you; but are there not with you causes of guilt before Jehovah your God?

11 and now, hear me, and send back the captives whom ye have taken captive of your brethren, for the heat of the anger of Jehovah [is] upon you.'

12 And certain of the heads of the sons of Ephraim (Azariah son of Johanan, Berechiah son of Meshillemoth, and Jehizkiah son of Shallum, and Amasa son of Hadlai), rise up against those coming in from the host,

13 and say to them, `Ye do not bring in the captives hither, for, to guilt against Jehovah on us, ye are saying to add unto our sin and unto our guilt? for abundant [is] the guilt we have, and the fierceness of anger on Israel.'

14 And the armed men leave the captives and the prey before the heads and all the assembly;

15 and the men who have been expressed by name rise and take hold on the captives, and all their naked ones they have clothed from the spoil, yea, they clothe them, and shoe them, and cause them to eat and drink, and anoint them, and leadthem on asses, even every feeble one, and bring them in to Jericho, the city of palms, near their brethren, and turn back to Samaria.

16 At that time hath king Ahaz sent unto the king of Asshur to give help to him;

17 and again the Edomites have come, and smite in Judah, and take captive a captivity.

18 And the Philistines have rushed against the cities of the low country, and of the south of Judah, and capture Beth-Shemesh, and Aijalon, and Gederoth, and Shocho and its villages, and Timnah and its villages, and Gimzo and its villages, and dwell there,

19 for Jehovah hath humbled Judah because of Ahaz king of Israel, for he made free with Judah, even to commit a trespass against Jehovah.

20 And Tilgath-Pilneser king of Asshur cometh in unto him, and doth distress him, and hath not strengthened him,

21 though Ahaz hath taken a portion [out] of the house of Jehovah, and [out] of the house of the king, and of the princes, and giveth to the king of Asshur, yet it is no help to him.

22 And in the time of his distress--he addeth to trespass against Jehovah, (this king Ahaz),

23 and he sacrificeth to the gods of Damascus--those smiting him, and saith, `Because the gods of the kings of Aram are helping them, to them I sacrifice, and they help me,' and they have been to him to cause him to stumble, and to all Israel.

24 And Ahaz gathereth the vessels of the house of God, and cutteth in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shutteth the doors of the house of Jehovah, and maketh to himself altars in every corner in Jerusalem.

25 And in every city and city of Judah he hath made high places to make perfume to other gods, and provoketh Jehovah, God of his fathers.

26 And the rest of his matters, and all his ways, the first and the last, lo, they are written on the book of the kings of Judah and Israel.

27 And Ahaz lieth with his fathers, and they bury him in the city, in Jerusalem, but have not brought him in to the graves of the kings of Israel, and reign doth Hezekiah his son in his stead.

2 Chronicles 36

1 And the people of the land take Jehoahaz son of Josiah, and cause him to reign instead of his father in Jerusalem.

2 A son of three and twenty years [is] Jehoahaz in his reigning, and three months he hath reigned in Jerusalem,

3 and turn him aside doth the king of Egypt in Jerusalem, and fineth the land a hundred talents of silver, and a talent of gold;

4 and the king of Egypt causeth Eliakim his brother to reign over Judah and Jerusalem, and turneth his name to Jehoiakim; and Jehoahaz his brother hath Necho taken, and bringeth him in to Egypt.

5 A son of twenty and five years [is] Jehoiakim in his reigning, and eleven years he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah his God;

6 against him hath Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon come up, and bindeth him in brazen fetters to take him away to Babylon.

7 And of the vessels of the house of Jehovah hath Nebuchadnezzar brought in to Babylon, and putteth them in his temple in Babylon.

8 And the rest of the matters of Jehoiakim, and his abominations that he hath done, and that which is found against him, lo, they are written on the book of the kings of Israel and Judah, and reign doth Jehoiachin his son in his stead.

9 A son of eight years is Jehoiachin in his reigning, and three months and ten days he hath reigned in Jerusalem, and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah;

10 and at the turn of the year hath king Nebuchadnezzar sent and bringeth him in to Babylon, with the desirable vessels of the house of Jehovah, and causeth Zedekiah his brother to reign over Judah and Jerusalem.

11 A son of twenty and one years [is] Zedekiah in his reigning, and eleven years he hath reigned in Jerusalem;

12 and he doth the evil thing in the eyes of Jehovah his God, he hath not been humbled before Jeremiah the prophet [speaking] from the mouth of Jehovah;

13 and also, against king Nebuchadnezzar he hath rebelled, who had caused him to swear by God, and he hardeneth his neck, and strengtheneth his heart, against turning back unto Jehovah, God of Israel.

14 Also, all the heads of the priests, and the people, having multiplied to commit a trespass according to all the abominations of the nations, and they defile the house of Jehovah that He hath sanctified in Jerusalem.

15 And Jehovah, God of their fathers, sendeth unto them by the hand of His messengers--rising early and sending--for He hath had pity on His people, and on His habitation,

16 and they are mocking at the messengers of God, and despising His words, and acting deceitfully with His prophets, till the going up of the fury of Jehovah against His people--till there is no healing.

17 And He causeth to go up against them the king of the Chaldeans, and he slayeth their chosen ones by the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and hath had no pity on young man and virgin, old man and very aged--the whole He hath giveninto his hand.

18 And all the vessels of the house of God, the great and the small, and the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king and of his princes--the whole he hath brought in to Babylon.

19 And they burn the house of God, and break down the wall of Jerusalem, and all its palaces they have burnt with fire, and all its desirable vessels--to destruction.

20 And he removeth those left of the sword unto Babylon, and they are to him and to his sons for servants, till the reigning of the kingdom of Persia,

21 to fulfil the word of Jehovah in the mouth of Jeremiah, till the land hath enjoyed its sabbaths; all the days of the desolation it kept sabbath--to the fulness of seventy years.

22 And in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, at the completion of the word of Jehovah in the mouth of Jeremiah, hath Jehovah waked up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, and he causeth an intimation to pass over into all his kingdom, and also in writing, saying,

23 `Thus said Cyrus king of Persia, All kingdoms of the earth hath Jehovah, God of the heavens, given to me, and He hath laid a charge on me to build to Him a house in Jerusalem, that [is] in Judah; who is among you of all His people? Jehovah his God [is] with him, and he doth go up.'

Ezra 2

1 And these [are] sons of the province who are going up--of the captives of the removal that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon removed to Babylon, and they turn back to Jerusalem and Judah, each to his city--

2 who have come in with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Seraiah, Reelaiah, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispar, Bigvai, Rehum, Baanah: The number of the men of the people of Israel:

3 Sons of Parosh, two thousand a hundred seventy and two.

4 Sons of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy and two.

5 Sons of Arah, seven hundred five and seventy.

6 Sons of Pahath-Moab, of the sons of Jeshua, Joab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve.

7 Sons of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

8 Sons of Zattu, nine hundred and forty and five.

9 Sons of Zaccai, seven hundred and sixty.

10 Sons of Bani, six hundred forty and two.

11 Sons of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three.

12 Sons of Azgad, a thousand two hundred twenty and two.

13 Sons of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and six.

14 Sons of Bigvai, two thousand fifty and six.

15 Sons of Adin, four hundred fifty and four.

16 Sons of Ater of Hezekiah, ninety and eight.

17 Sons of Bezai, three hundred twenty and three.

18 Sons of Jorah, a hundred and twelve.

19 Sons of Hashum, two hundred twenty and three.

20 Sons of Gibbar, ninety and five.

21 Sons of Beth-Lehem, a hundred twenty and three.

22 Men of Netophah, fifty and six.

23 Men of Anathoth, a hundred twenty and eight.

24 Sons of Azmaveth, forty and two.

25 Sons of Kirjath-Arim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred and forty and three.

26 Sons of Ramah and Gaba, six hundred twenty and one.

27 Men of Michmas, a hundred twenty and two.

28 Men of Beth-El and Ai, two hundred twenty and three.

29 Sons of Nebo, fifty and two.

30 Sons of Magbish, a hundred fifty and six.

31 Sons of another Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

32 Sons of Harim, three hundred and twenty.

33 Sons of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty and five.

34 Sons of Jericho, three hundred forty and five.

35 Sons of Senaah, three thousand and six hundred and thirty.

36 The Priests: sons of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy and three.

37 Sons of Imner, a thousand fifty and two.

38 Sons of Pashhur, a thousand two hundred forty and seven.

39 Sons of Harim, a thousand and seventeen.

40 The Levites; sons of Jeshua and Kadmiel, of the sons of Hodaviah, seventy and four.

41 The singers: sons of Asaph, a hundred twenty and eight.

42 Sons of the gatekeepers; sons of Shallum, sons of Ater, sons of Talmon, sons of Akkub, sons of Hatita, sons of Shobai, the whole [are] a hundred thirty and nine.

43 The Nethinim: sons of Ziha, sons of Hasupha, sons of Tabbaoth,

44 Sons of Keros, sons of Siaha, sons of Padon,

45 Sons of Lebanah, sons of Hagabah, sons of Akkub,

46 Sons of Hagab, sons of Shalmai, sons of Hanan,

47 Sons of Giddel, sons of Gahar, sons of Reaiah,

48 Sons of Rezin, sons of Nekoda, sons of Gazzam,

49 Sons of Uzza, sons of Paseah, sons of Besai,

50 Sons of Asnah, sons of Mehunim, sons of Nephusim,

51 Sons of Bakbuk, sons of Hakupha, sons of Harhur,

52 Sons of Bazluth, sons of Mehida, sons of Harsha,

53 Sons of Barkos, sons of Sisera, sons of Thamah,

54 Sons of Neziah, sons of Hatipha.

55 Sons of the servants of Solomon: sons of Sotai, sons of Sophereth, sons of Peruda,

56 Sons of Jaalah, sons of Darkon, sons of Giddel,

57 Sons of Shephatiah, sons of Hattil, sons of Pochereth of Zebaim, sons of Ami.

58 All the Nethinim, and the sons of the servants of Solomon [are] three hundred ninety and two.

59 And these [are] those going up from Tel-Melah, Tel-Harsa, Cherub, Addan, Immer, and they have not been able to declare the house of their fathers, and their seed, whether they [are] of Israel:

60 sons of Delaiah, sons of Tobiah, sons of Nekoda, six hundred fifty and two.

61 And of the sons of the priests: sons of Habaiah, sons of Koz, sons of Barzillai (who took from the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite a wife, and is called by their name;)

62 these have sought their register among those reckoning themselves by genealogy, and they have not been found, and they are redeemed from the priesthood,

63 and the Tirshatha saith to them, that they eat not of the most holy things till the standing up of a priest with Urim and with Thummim.

64 All the assembly together [is] four myriad two thousand three hundred sixty,

65 apart from their servants and their handmaids; these [are] seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven: and of them [are] singers and songstresses two hundred.

66 Their horses [are] seven hundred thirty and six, their mules, two hundred forty and five,

67 their camels, four hundred thirty and five, asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

68 And some of the heads of the fathers in their coming in to the house of Jehovah that [is] in Jerusalem, have offered willingly for the house of God, to establish it on its base;

69 according to their power they have given to the treasure of the work; of gold, drams six myriads and a thousand, and of silver, pounds five thousand, and of priests' coats, a hundred.

70 And the priests dwell, and the Levites, and of the people, and the singers, and the gatekeepers, and the Nethinim, in their cities; even all Israel in their cities.

Ezra 3

1 And the seventh month cometh, and the sons of Israel [are] in the cities, and the people are gathered, as one men, unto Jerusalem.

2 And rise doth Jeshua son of Jozadak, and his brethren the priests, and Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, and his brethren, and they build the altar of the God of Israel, to cause to ascend upon it burnt-offerings, as it is written in the law of Moses, the man of God.

3 And they establish the altar on its bases, because of the fear upon them of the peoples of the lands, and he causeth burnt-offerings to ascend upon it to Jehovah, burnt-offerings for the morning and for the evening.

4 And they make the feast of the booths as it is written, and the burnt-offering of the day daily in number according to the ordinance, the matter of a day in its day;

5 and after this a continual burnt-offering, and for new moons, and for all appointed seasons of Jehovah that are sanctified; and for every one who is willingly offering a willing-offering to Jehovah.

6 From the first day of the seventh month they have begun to cause burnt-offerings to ascend to Jehovah, and the temple of Jehovah hath not been founded,

7 and they give money to hewers and to artificers, and food, and drink, and oil to Zidonians and to Tyrians, to bring in cedar-trees from Lebanon unto the sea of Joppa, according to the permission of Cyrus king of Persia concerning them.

8 And in the second year of their coming in unto the house of God, to Jerusalem, in the second month, began Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua son of Jozadak, and the remnant of their brethren the priests and the Levites, and all those coming from the captivity to Jerusalem, and they appoint the Levites from a son of twenty years and upward, to overlook the work of the house of Jehovah.

9 And Jeshua standeth, [and] his sons, and his brethren, Kadmiel and his sons, sons of Judah together, to overlook those doing the work in the house of God; the sons of Henadad, [and] their sons and their brethren the Levites.

10 And those building have founded the temple of Jehovah, and they appoint the priests, clothed, with trumpets, and the Levites, sons of Asaph, with cymbals, to praise Jehovah, by means of [the instruments of] David king of Israel.

11 And they respond in praising and in giving thanks to Jehovah, for good, for to the age His kindness [is] over Israel, and all the people have shouted--a great shout--in giving praise to Jehovah, because the house of Jehovah hath been founded.

12 And many of the priests, and the Levites, and the heads of the fathers, the aged men who had seen the first house--in this house being founded before their eyes--are weeping with a loud voice, and many with a shout, in joy, lifting up the voice;

13 and the people are not discerning the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people, for the people are shouting--a great shout--and the noise hath been heard unto a distance.

Ezra 5

1 And prophesied have the prophets, (Haggai the prophet, and Zechariah son of Iddo) unto the Jews who [are] in Judah and in Jerusalem, in the name of the God of Israel--unto them.

2 Then have Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua son of Jozadak, risen, and begun to build the house of God, that [is] in Jerusalem, and with them are the prophets of God supporting them.

3 At that time come to them hath Tatnai, governor beyond the river, and Shethar-Boznai, and their companions, and thus they are saying to them, `Who hath made for you a decree this house to build, and this wall to finish?'

4 Then thus we have said to them, `What [are] the names of the men who are building this building?'

5 And the eye of their God hath been upon the elders of the Jews, and they have not caused them to cease till the matter goeth to Darius, and then they send back a letter concerning this thing.

6 The copy of a letter that Tatnai, governor beyond the river, hath sent, and Shethar-Boznai and his companions, the Apharsachites who [are] beyond the river, unto Darius the king.

7 A letter they have sent unto him, and thus is it written in it:

8 `To Darius the king, all peace! be it known to the king that we have gone to the province of Judah, to the great house of God, and it is built [with] rolled stones, and wood is placed in the walls, and this work is done speedily, and prospering in their hand.

9 Then we have asked of these elders, thus we have said to them, Who hath made for you a decree this house to build, and this wall to finish?

10 And also their names we have asked of them, to let thee know, that we might write the names of the men who [are] at their head.

11 `And thus they have returned us word, saying, We [are] servants of the God of heaven and earth, and are building the house that was built many years before this, that a great king of Israel built and finished:

12 but after that our fathers made the God of heaven angry, he gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon the Chaldean, and this house he destroyed, and the people he removed to Babylon;

13 but in the first year of Cyrus king of Babylon, Cyrus the king made a decree to build this house of God,

14 and also, the vessels of the house of God, of gold and silver, that Nebuchadnezzar had taken forth out of the temple that [is] in Jerusalem, and brought them to the temple of Babylon, them hath Cyrus the king brought forth out of the temple of Babylon, and they have been given to [one], Sheshbazzar [is] his name, whom he made governor,

15 and said to him, These vessels lift up, go, put them down in the temple that [is] in Jerusalem, and the house of God is builded on its place.

16 Then hath this Sheshbazzar come--he hath laid the foundations of the house of God that [is] in Jerusalem, and from thence even till now it hath been building, and is not finished.

17 `And now, if to the king it be good, let search be made in the treasure-house of the king, that [is] there in Babylon, whether it be that of Cyrus the king there was made a decree to build this house of God in Jerusalem, and the will of the king concerning this thing he doth send unto us.'

Ezra 8

1 And these [are] heads of their fathers, and the genealogy of those going up with me, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king, from Babylon.

2 From the sons of Phinehas: Gershom; from the sons of Ithamar: Daniel; from the sons of David: Hattush;

3 from the sons of Shechaniah, from the sons of Pharosh: Zechariah, and with him, reckoning themselves by genealogy, of males a hundred and fifty.

4 From the sons of Pahath-Moab: Elihoenai son of Zerahiah, and with him two hundred who are males.

5 From the sons of Shechaniah: the son of Jahaziel, and with him three hundred who are males.

6 And from the sons of Adin: Ebed son of Jonathan, and with him fifty who are males.

7 And from the sons of Elam: Jeshaiah son of Athaliah, and with him seventy who are males.

8 And from the sons of Shephatiah: Zebadiah son of Michael, and with him eighty who are males.

9 From the sons of Joab: Obadiah son of Jehiel, and with him two hundred and eighteen who are males.

10 And from the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah, and with him a hundred and sixty who are males.

11 And from the sons of Bebai: Zechariah son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight who are males.

12 And from the sons of Azgad: Johanan son of Hakkatan, and with him a hundred and ten who are males.

13 And from the younger sons of Adonikam--and these [are] their names--Eliphelet, Jeiel, and Shemaiah, and with them sixty who are males.

14 And from the sons of Bigvai, Uthai and Zabbud, and with them seventy who are males.

15 And I gather them unto the river that is going unto Ahava, and we encamp there three days; and I consider about the people, and about the priests, and of the sons of Levi I have found none there;

16 and I send for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, and for Elnathan, and for Jarib, and for Elnathan, and for Nathan, and for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, heads, and for Joiarib, and for Elnathan, men of understanding;

17 and I charge them for Iddo the head, in the place Casiphia, and put in their mouth words to speak unto Iddo, [and] his brethren the Nethinim, in the place Casiphia, to bring to us ministrants for the house of our God.

18 And they bring to us, according to the good hand of our God upon us, a man of understanding, of the sons of Mahli, son of Levi, son of Israel, and Sherebiah, and his sons, and his brethren, eighteen;

19 and Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah, of the sons of Merari, his brethren, and their sons, twenty;

20 and from the Nethinim, whom David and the heads gave for the service of the Levites, two hundred and twenty Nethinim, all of them defined by name.

21 And I proclaim there a fast, by the river Ahava, to afflict ourselves before our God, to seek from Him a right way for us, and for our infants, and for all our substance,

22 for I was ashamed to ask from the king a force and horsemen to help us because of the enemy in the way, for we spake to the king, saying, `The hand of our God [is] upon all seeking Him for good, and His strength and His wrath [is] upon all forsaking Him.'

23 And we fast, and seek from our God for this, and He is entreated of us.

24 And I separate from the heads of the priests, twelve, even Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and with them of their brethren ten,

25 and I weigh to them the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, a heave-offering of the house of our God, that the king, and his counsellors, and his heads, and all Israel--those present-- lifted up;

26 and I weigh to their hand, of silver, talents six hundred and fifty, and of vessels of silver a hundred talents, of gold a hundred talents,

27 and basins of gold twenty, of a thousand drams, and two vessels of good shining brass, desirable as gold.

28 And I say unto them, `Ye [are] holy to Jehovah, and the vessels [are] holy, and the silver and the gold [are] a willing-offering to Jehovah, God of your fathers;

29 watch, and keep, till ye weigh before the heads of the priests, and of the Levites, and the heads of the fathers of Israel, in Jerusalem, in the chambers of the house of Jehovah.'

30 And the priests and the Levites took the weight of the silver, and of the gold, and of the vessels, to bring to Jerusalem to the house of our God.

31 And we journey from the river Ahava, on the twelfth of the first month, to go to Jerusalem, and the hand of our God hath been upon us, and He delivereth us from the hand of the enemy and the lier in wait by the way;

32 and we come in to Jerusalem, and dwell there three days.

33 And on the fourth day hath been weighed the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, in the house of our God, unto the hand of Meremoth son of Uriah the priest, and with him Eleazar son of Phinehas, and with them Jozabad son of Jeshua, and Noadiah son of Binnui, the Levites:

34 by number, by weight of every one, and all the weight is written at that time.

35 Those coming in of the captives--sons of the removal--have brought near burnt-offerings to the God of Israel, bullocks twelve, for all Israel, rams ninety and six, lambs seventy and seven, young he-goats for a sin-offering twelve--the whole a burnt-offering to Jehovah;

36 and they give the laws of the king to the lieutenants of the king and the governors beyond the river, and they have lifted up the people and the house of God.

Ezra 10

1 And at Ezra's praying, and at his making confession, weeping and casting himself down before the house of God, there have been gathered unto him out of Israel an assembly very great-- men and women and children--for the people have wept, multiplying weeping.

2 And Shechaniah son of Jehiel, of the sons of Elam, answereth and saith to Ezra, `We-- we have trespassed against our God, and we settle strange women of the peoples of the land; and now there is hope for Israel concerning this,

3 and now, let us make a covenant with our God, to cause all the women to go out, and that which is born of them, by the counsel of the Lord, and of those trembling at the command of our God, and according to law it is done;

4 rise, for on thee [is] the matter, and we [are] with thee; be strong, and do.'

5 And Ezra riseth, and causeth the heads of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear to do according to this word--and they swear.

6 And Ezra riseth from before the house of God, and goeth unto the chamber of Jehohanan son of Eliashib; yea, he goeth there, bread he hath not eaten, and water he hath not drunk, for he is mourning because of the trespass of the removal.

7 And they cause a voice to pass over into Judah and Jerusalem, to all sons of the removal, to be gathered to Jerusalem,

8 and every one who cometh not in by the third day, according to the counsel of the heads and of the elders, all his substance is devoted, and himself separated from the assembly of the removal.

9 And gathered are all the men of Judah and Benjamin to Jerusalem by the third day, it [is] the ninth month, on the twentieth of the month, and all the people sit in the broad place of the house of God, trembling on account of the matter and of the showers.

10 And Ezra the priest riseth, and saith unto them, `Ye--ye have trespassed, and ye settle strange women, to add to the guilt of Israel;

11 and, now, make confession to Jehovah, God of your fathers, and do His good pleasure, and be separated from the peoples of the land, and from the strange women.'

12 And all the assembly answer and say [with] a great voice, `Right; according to thy word--on us to do;

13 but the people [are] many, and [it is] the time of showers, and there is no power to stand without, and the work [is] not for one day, nor for two, for we have multiplied to transgress in this thing.

14 `Let, we pray thee, our heads of all the assembly stand, and all who [are] in our cities, who have settled strange wives, do come in at the times appointed, and with them the elders of city and city, and its judges, till the turning back of the fury of the wrath of our God from us, for this thing.'

15 Only Jonathan son of Asahel, and Jahaziah son of Tikvah, stood against this, and Meshullam, and Shabbethai the Levite, helped them.

16 And the sons of the removal do so, and Ezra the priest, [and] men, heads of the fathers, for the house of their fathers, are separated, even all of them by name, and they sit on the first day of the tenth month, to examine the matter;

17 and they finish with all the men who have settled strange women unto the first day of the first month.

18 And there are found of the sons of the priests that have settled strange women: of the sons of Jeshua son of Jozadak, and his brethren, Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah;

19 and they give their hand to send out their wives, and, being guilty, a ram of the flock, for their guilt.

20 And of the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah;

21 and of the sons of Harim: Masseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah;

22 and of the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethaneel, Jozabad, and Elasah.

23 And of the Levites: Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah--he [is] Kelita, --Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.

24 And of the singers: Eliashib. And of the gatekeepers: Shallum, and Telem, and Uri.

25 And of Israel: of the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, and Jeziah, and Malchijah, and Miamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah.

26 And of the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Elijah.

27 And of the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza.

28 And of the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, Athlai.

29 And of the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, and Ramoth.

30 And of the sons of Pahath-Moab: Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezaleel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.

31 And of the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Ishijah, Malchiah, Shemaiah, Shimeon,

32 Benjamin, Malluch, Shemariah.

33 Of the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattathah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, Shimei.

34 Of the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, and Uel,

35 Benaiah, Bedeiah, Cheluhu,

36 Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib,

37 Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasau,

38 and Bani, and Binnui, Shimei,

39 and Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah,

40 Machnadbai, Shashai, Sharai,

41 Azareel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah,

42 Shallum, Amariah, Joseph.

43 Of the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Jadau, and Joel, Benaiah;

44 all these have taken strange women, and there are of them women--who adopt sons.

Nehemiah 3

1 And Eliashib the high priest riseth, and his brethren the priests, and they build the sheep-gate; they have sanctified it, and set up its doors, even unto the tower of Meah they have sanctified it, unto the tower of Hananeel;

2 and by his hand have men of Jericho built; and by their hand hath Zaccur son of Imri built;

3 and the fish-gate have sons of Hassenaah built, they have walled it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars.

4 And by their hand hath Merimoth son of Urijah, son of Koz, strengthened; and by his hand hath Meshullam son of Berechiah, son of Meshezabeel, strengthened; and by his hand hath Zadok son of Baana strengthened;

5 and by his hand have the Tekoites strengthened, and their honourable ones have not brought in their neck to the service of their Lord.

6 And the old gate have Jehoiada son of Paseah, and Meshullam son of Besodeiah, strengthened; they have walled it, and set up its doors, and its locks, and its bars.

7 And by their hand hath Melatiah the Gibeonite strengthened, and Jadon the Meronothite, men of Gibeon and of Mizpah, to the throne of the governor beyond the River.

8 By his hand hath Uzziel son of Harhaiah of the refiners strengthened; and by his hand hath Hananiah son of [one of] the compounders strengthened; and they leave Jerusalem unto the broad wall.

9 And by their hand hath Rephaiah son of Hur, head of the half of the district of Jerusalem, strengthened.

10 And by their hand hath Jedaiah son of Harumaph strengthened, and over-against his own house; and by his hand hath Hattush son of Hashabniah strengthened.

11 A second measure hath Malchijah son of Harim strengthened, and Hashub son of Pahath-Moab, even the tower of the furnaces.

12 And by his hand hath Shallum son of Halohesh, head of the half of the district of Jerusalem, strengthened, he and his daughters.

13 The gate of the valley hath Hanun strengthened, and the inhabitants of Zanoah; they have built it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars, and a thousand cubits in the wall unto the dung-gate.

14 And the dung-gate hath Malchijah son of Rechab, head of the district of Beth- Haccerem, strengthened; he doth built it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars.

15 And the gate of the fountain hath Shallum son of Col-Hozeh, head of the district of Mizpah, strengthened: he doth build it, and cover it, and set up its doors, its locks, and its bars, and the wall of the pool of Siloah, to the garden of the king, and unto the steps that are going down from the city of David.

16 After him hath Nehemiah son of Azbuk, head of the half of the district of Beth- Zur, strengthened, unto over-against the graves of David, and unto the pool that is made, and unto the house of the mighty ones.

17 After him have the Levites strengthened, [and] Rehum son of Bani: by his hand hath Hashabiah, head of the half of the district of Keilah, strengthened, for his district.

18 After him have their brethren strengthened, [and] Bavvai son of Henadad, head of the half of the district of Keilah.

19 And Ezer son of Jeshua, head of Mizpah, doth strengthen, by his hand, a second measure, from over-against the ascent of the armoury at the angle.

20 After him hath Baruch son of Zabbai hastened to strengthen a second measure from the angle unto the opening of the house of Eliashib the high priest.

21 After him hath Meremoth son of Urijah, son of Koz, strengthened, a second measure, from the opening of the house of Eliashib even unto the completion of the house of Eliashib.

22 And after him have the priests, men of the circuit, strengthened.

23 After them hath Benjamin strengthened, and Hashub, over-against their house; after him hath Azariah son of Maaseiah, son of Ananiah, strengthened, near his house.

24 After him hath Binnui son of Henadad strengthened, a second measure, from the house of Azariah unto the angle, and unto the corner.

25 Palal son of Uzai, from over-against the angle, and the tower that is going out from the upper house of the king that [is] at the court of the prison; after him Pedaiah son of Parosh.

26 And the Nethinim have been dwelling in Ophel, unto over-against the water-gate at the east, and the tower that goeth out.

27 After him have the Tekoites strengthened, a second measure, from over-against the great tower that goeth out, and unto the wall of Ophel.

28 From above the horse-gate have the priests strengthened, each over-against his house.

29 After them hath Zadok son of Immer strengthened, over against his house; and after him hath Shemaiah son of Shechaniah, keeper of the east gate, strengthened.

30 After him hath Hananiah son of Shelemiah strengthened, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, a second measure; after him hath Meshullam son of Berechiah strengthened, overagainst his chamber.

31 After him hath Malchijah son of the refiner strengthened, unto the house of the Nethinim, and of the merchants, over-against the gate of the Miphkad, and unto the ascent of the corner.

32 And between the ascent of the corner and the sheep-gate, have the refiners and the merchants strengthened.

Nehemiah 6

1 And it cometh to pass, when it hath been heard by Sanballat, and Tobiah, and by Geshem the Arabian, and by the rest of our enemies, that I have builded the wall, and there hath not been left in it a breach, (also, till that time the doors Ihad not set up in the gates,)

2 that Sanballat sendeth, also Geshem, unto me, saying, `Come and we meet together in the villages, in the valley of Ono;' and they are thinking to do to me evil.

3 And I send unto them messengers, saying, `A great work I am doing, and I am not able to come down; why doth the work cease when I let it alone, and have come down unto you?'

4 and they send unto me, according to this word, four times, and I return them [word] according to this word.

5 And Sanballat sendeth unto me, according to this word, a fifth time, his servant, and an open letter in his hand;

6 it is written in it, `Among the nations it hath been heard, and Gashmu is saying: Thou and the Jews are thinking to rebel, therefore thou art building the wall, and thou hast been to them for a king--according to these words!

7 And also, prophets thou hast appointed to call for thee in Jerusalem, saying, A king [is] in Judah, and now it is heard by the king according to these words; and now come, and we take counsel together.'

8 And I send unto him, saying, `It hath not been according to these words that thou art saying, for from thine own heart thou art devising them;'

9 for all of them are making us afraid, saying, `Their hands are too feeble for the work, and it is not done;' and now, strengthen Thou my hands.

10 And I have entered the house of Shemaiah son of Delaiah, son of Mehetabeel--and he is restrained--and he saith, `Let us meet at the house of God, at the inside of the temple, and we shut the doors of the temple, for they are coming in to slay thee--yea, by night they are coming in to slay thee.'

11 And I say, `A man such as I--doth he flee? and who as I, that doth go in unto the temple, and live? --I do not go in.'

12 And I discern, and lo, God hath not sent him, for in the prophecy he hath spoken unto me both Tobiah and Sanballat hired him,

13 so that he [is] an hireling, that I may fear and do so, and I had sinned, and it had been to them for an evil name that they may reproach me.

14 Be mindful, O my God, of Tobiah, and of Sanballat, according to these his works, and also, of Noadiah the prophetess, and of the rest of the prophets who have been making me afraid.

15 And the wall is completed in the twenty and fifth of Elul, on the fifty and second day;

16 and it cometh to pass, when all our enemies have heard, and all the nations who are round about us see, that they fall greatly in their own eyes, and know that by our God hath this work been done.

17 Also, in those days the freemen of Judah are multiplying their letters going unto Tobiah, and those of Tobiah are coming in unto them;

18 for many in Judah are sworn to him, for he [is] son-in-law to Shechaniah son of Arah, and Jehohanan his son hath taken the daughter of Meshullam son of Berechiah;

19 also, his good deeds they have been saying before me, and my words they have been taking out to him; letters hath Tobiah sent to make me afraid.

Nehemiah 7

1 And it cometh to pass, when the wall hath been built, that I set up the doors, and the gatekeepers are appointed, and the singers, and the Levites,

2 and I charge Hanani my brother, and Hananiah head of the palace, concerning Jerusalem--for he [is] as a man of truth, and fearing God above many--

3 and I say to them, `Let not the gates of Jerusalem be opened till the heat of the sun, and while they are standing by let them shut the doors, and fasten, and appoint guards of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, each in his guard, and each over-against his house.'

4 And the city [is] broad on both sides, and great, and the people [are] few in its midst, and there are no houses builded;

5 and my God putteth it unto my heart, and I gather the freeman, and the prefects, and the people, for the genealogy, and I find a book of the genealogy of those coming up at the beginning, and I find written in it: --

6 These [are] sons of the province, those coming up of the captives of the removal that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon removed--and they turn back to Jerusalem and to Judah, each to his city--

7 who are coming in with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah. Number of the men of the people of Israel:

8 Sons of Parosh: two thousand a hundred and seventy and two.

9 Sons of Shephatiah: three hundred seventy and two.

10 Sons of Arah: six hundred fifty and two.

11 Sons of Pahath-Moab, of the sons of Jeshua and Joab: two thousand and eight hundred [and] eighteen.

12 Sons of Elam: a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

13 Sons of Zattu: eight hundred forty and five.

14 Sons of Zaccai: seven hundred and sixty.

15 Sons of Binnui: six hundred forty and eight.

16 Sons of Bebai: six hundred twenty and eight.

17 Sons of Azgad: two thousand three hundred twenty and two.

18 Sons of Adonikam: six hundred sixty and seven.

19 Sons of Bigvai: two thousand sixty and seven.

20 Sons of Adin: six hundred fifty and five.

21 Sons of Ater of Hezekiah: ninety and eight.

22 Sons of Hashum: three hundred twenty and eight.

23 Sons of Bezai: three hundred twenty and four.

24 Sons of Hariph: a hundred [and] twelve.

25 Sons of Gibeon: ninety and five.

26 Men of Beth-Lehem and Netophah: a hundred eighty and eight.

27 Men of Anathoth: a hundred twenty and eight.

28 Men of Beth-Azmaveth: forty and two.

29 Men of Kirjath-Jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth: seven hundred forty and three.

30 Men of Ramah and Gaba: six hundred twenty and one.

31 Men of Michmas: a hundred and twenty and two.

32 Men of Bethel and Ai: a hundred twenty and three.

33 Men of the other Nebo: fifty and two.

34 Sons of the other Elam: a thousand two hundred fifty and four.

35 Sons of Harim: three hundred and twenty.

36 Sons of Jericho: three hundred forty and five.

37 Sons of Lod, Hadid, and Ono: seven hundred and twenty and one.

38 Sons of Senaah: three thousand nine hundred and thirty.

39 The priests: sons of Jedaiah: of the house of Jeshua: nine hundred seventy and three;

40 sons of Immer: a thousand fifty and two;

41 sons of Pashur: a thousand two hundred forty and seven;

42 sons of Harim: a thousand and seventeen.

43 The Levites: sons of Jeshua, of Kadmiel: of sons of Hodevah: seventy and four.

44 The singers: sons of Asaph: a hundred forty and eight.

45 The gatekeepers: sons of Shallum, sons of Ater, sons of Talmon, sons of Akkub, sons of Hatita, sons of Shobai: a hundred thirty and eight.

46 The Nethinim: sons of Ziha, sons of Hasupha, sons of Tabbaoth,

47 sons of Keros, sons of Sia, sons of Padon,

48 sons of Lebanah, sons of Hagaba, sons of Shalmai,

49 sons of Hanan, sons of Giddel, sons of Gahar,

50 sons of Reaiah, sons of Rezin, sons of Nekoda,

51 sons of Gazzam, sons of Uzza, sons of Phaseah,

52 sons of Bezai, sons of Meunim, sons of Nephishesim,

53 sons of Bakbuk, sons of Hakupha, sons of Harhur,

54 sons of Bazlith, sons of Mehida, sons of Harsha,

55 sons of Barkos, sons of Sisera, sons of Tamah,

56 sons of Neziah, sons of Hatipha.

57 Sons of the servants of Solomon: sons of Sotai, sons of Sophereth, sons of Perida,

58 sons of Jaala, sons of Darkon, sons of Giddel,

59 sons of Shephatiah, sons of Hattil, sons of Pochereth of Zebaim, sons of Amon.

60 All the Nethinim and the sons of the servants of Solomon [are] three hundred ninety and two.

61 And these [are] those coming up from Tel-Melah, Tel-Harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer--and they have not been able to declare the house of their fathers, and their seed, whether they [are] of Israel--

62 sons of Delaiah, sons of Tobiah, sons of Nekoda, six hundred forty and two.

63 And of the priests: sons of Habaiah sons of Koz, sons of Barzillai, who hath taken from the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite a wife, and is called by their name.

64 These have sought their register among those reckoning themselves by genealogy, and it hath not been found, and they are redeemed from the priesthood,

65 and the Tirshatha saith to them that they eat not of the most holy things till the standing up of the priest with Urim and Thummim.

66 All the assembly together [is] four myriads two thousand three hundred and sixty,

67 apart from their servants and their handmaids--these [are] seven thousand three hundred thirty and seven; and of them [are] singers and songstresses, two hundred forty and five.

68 Their horses [are] seven hundred thirty and six; their mules, two hundred [and] forty and five;

69 camels, four hundred thirty and five; asses, six thousand seven hundred and twenty.

70 And from the extremity of the heads of the fathers they have given to the work; the Tirshatha hath given to the treasure, of gold, drams a thousand, bowls fifty, priests' coats thirty and five hundred.

71 And of the heads of the fathers they have given to the treasure of the work, of gold, drams two myriads, and of silver, pounds two thousand and two hundred.

72 And that which the rest of the people have given [is] of gold, drams two myriads, and of silver, pounds two thousand, and of priests coats, sixty and seven.

73 And they dwell--the priests, and the Levites, and the gatekeepers, and the singers, and [some] of the people, and the Nethinim, and all Israel--in their cities, and the seventh month cometh, and the sons of Israel [are] in their cities.

Nehemiah 11

1 And the heads of the people dwell in Jerusalem, and the rest of the people have caused to fall lots to bring in one out of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts in the cities,

2 and the people give a blessing to all the men who are offering themselves willingly to dwell in Jerusalem.

3 And these [are] heads of the province who have dwelt in Jerusalem, and in cities of Judah, they have dwelt each in his possession in their cities; Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and the Nethinim, and the sons of the servants of Solomon.

4 And in Jerusalem have dwelt of the sons of Judah, and of the sons of Benjamin. Of the sons of Judah: Athaiah son of Uzziah, son of Zechariah, son of Amariah, son of Shephatiah, son of Mahalaleel, of the sons of Perez;

5 and Masseiah son of Baruch, son of Col-Hozeh, son of Hazaiah, son of Adaiah, son of Joiarib, son of Zechariah, son of Shiloni;

6 all the sons of Perez who are dwelling in Jerusalem [are] four hundred sixty and eight, men of valour.

7 And these [are] sons of Benjamin: Sallu son of Meshullam, son of Joed, son of Pedaiah, son of Kolaiah, son of Maaseiah, son of Ithiel, son of Jesaiah;

8 and after him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty and eight.

9 And Joel son of Zichri [is] inspector over them, and Judah son of Senuah [is] over the city--second.

10 Of the priests: Jedaiah son of Joiarib, Jachin,

11 Seraiah son of Hilkiah, son of Meshullam, son of Zadok, son of Meraioth, son of Ahitub, leader of the house of God,

12 and their brethren doing the work of the house [are] eight hundred twenty and two; and Adaiah son of Jeroham, son of Pelaliah, son of Amzi, son of Zechariah, son of Pashhur, son of Malchiah,

13 and his brethren, heads of fathers, two hundred forty and two; and Amashsai son of Azareel, son of Ahazai, son of Meshillemoth, son of Immer,

14 and their brethren, mighty of valour, a hundred twenty and eight; and an inspector over them [is] Zabdiel, son of [one of] the great men.

15 And of the Levites: Shemaiah son of Hashub, son of Azrikam, son of Hashabiah, son of Bunni,

16 and Shabbethai, and Jozabad, [are] over the outward work of the house of God, of the heads of the Levites,

17 and Mattaniah son of Micha, son of Zabdi, son of Asaph, [is] head--at the commencement he giveth thanks in prayer; and Bakbukiah [is] second among his brethren, and Abda son of Shammua, son of Galal, son of Jeduthun.

18 All the Levites, in the holy city, [are] two hundred eighty and four.

19 And the gatekeepers, Akkub, Talmon, and their brethren, those watching at the gates, [are] a hundred seventy and two.

20 And the rest of Israel, of the priests, of the Levites, [are] in all cities of Judah, each in his inheritance;

21 and the Nethinim are dwelling in Ophel, and Ziha and Gishpa [are] over the Nethinim.

22 And the overseer of the Levites in Jerusalem [is] Uzzi son of Bani, son of Hashabiah, son of Mattaniah, son of Micha: of the sons of Asaph, the singers [are] over-against the work of the house of God,

23 for the command of the king [is] upon them, and support [is] for the singers, a matter of a day in its day.

24 And Pethahiah son of Meshezabeel, of the sons of Zerah, son of Judah, [is] by the hand of the king, for every matter of the people.

25 And at the villages with their fields, of the sons of Judah there have dwelt, in Kirjath-Arba and its small towns, and in Dibon and its small towns, and in Jekabzeel and its villages,

26 and in Jeshua, and in Moladah, and in Beth-Phelet,

27 and in Hazar-Shaul, and in Beer-Sheba and its small towns,

28 and in Ziklag, and in Mekonah and in its small towns,

29 and En-Rimmon, and in Zareah, and in Jarmuth,

30 Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, Lachish and its fields, Azekah and its small towns; and they encamp from Beer-Sheba unto the valley of Hinnom.

31 And sons of Benjamin [are] at Geba, Michmash, and Aija, and Beth-El, and its small towns,

32 Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah,

33 Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim,

34 Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat,

35 Lod, and Ono, the valley of the artificers.

36 And of the Levites, the courses of Judah [are] for Benjamin.

Nehemiah 13

1 On that day there was read in the book of Moses, in the ears of the people, and it hath been found written in it that an Ammonite and Moabite doth not come into the assembly of God--unto the age,

2 because they have not come before the sons of Israel with bread and with water, and hire against them Balaam to revile them, and our God turneth the reviling into a blessing.

3 And it cometh to pass, at their hearing the law, that they separate all the mixed people from Israel.

4 And before this Eliashib the priest, appointed over chambers of the house of our God, [is] a relation of Tobiah,

5 and he maketh for him a great chamber, and there they were formerly putting the present, the frankincense, and the vessels, and the tithe of the corn, the new wine, and the oil--the commanded thing of the Levites, and the singers, and the gatekeepers--and the heave-offering of the priests.

6 And during all this I was not in Jerusalem, for in the thirty and second year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon did I come unto the king, and at the end of days I have asked of the king,

7 and I come in to Jerusalem, and understand concerning the evil that Eliashib hath done for Tobiah, to make to him a chamber in the courts of the house of God,

8 and it is very displeasing to me, and I cast all the vessels of the house of Tobiah without, out of the chamber,

9 and I speak, and they cleanse the chambers, and I bring back thither the vessels of the house of God with the present and the frankincense.

10 And I know that the portions of the Levites have not been given, and they flee each to his field--the Levites and the singers, doing the work.

11 And I strive with the prefects, and say, `Wherefore hath the house of God been forsaken?' and I gather them, and set them on their station;

12 and all Judah have brought in the tithe of the corn, and of the new wine, and of the oil, to the treasuries.

13 And I appoint treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and Pedaiah of the Levites; and by their hand [is] Hanan son of Zaccur, son of Mattaniah, for stedfast they have been reckoned, and on them [it is] to give a portion to their brethren.

14 Be mindful of me, O my God, for this, and do not blot out my kind acts that I have done, for the house of my God, and for its charges.

15 In those days I have seen in Judah those treading wine-vats on sabbath, and bringing in the sheaves, and lading on the asses, and also, wine, grapes, and figs, and every burden, yea, they are bringing in to Jerusalem on the sabbath-day, and I testify in the day of their selling provision.

16 And the Tyrians have dwelt in it, bringing in fish, and every ware, and selling on sabbath to the sons of Judah and in Jerusalem.

17 And I strive with the freemen of Judah, and say to them, `What [is] this evil thing that ye are doing, and polluting the sabbath-day?

18 Thus did not your fathers do? and our God bringeth in on us all this evil, and on this city, and ye are adding fierceness on Israel, to pollute the sabbath.'

19 And it cometh to pass, when the gates of Jerusalem have been dark before the sabbath, that I speak, and the doors are shut, and I say, that they do not open them till after the sabbath; and of my servants I have stationed at the gates; there doth not come in a burden on the sabbath-day.

20 And they lodge--the merchants and sellers of all ware--at the outside of Jerusalem, once or twice,

21 and I testify against them, and say unto them, `Wherefore are ye lodging overagainst the wall? if ye repeat [it], a hand I put forth upon you;' from that time they have not come in on the sabbath.

22 And I say to the Levites, that they be cleansed, and, coming in, keeping the gates, to sanctify the sabbath-day. Also, this, remember for me, O my God, and have pity on me, according to the abundance of Thy kindness.

23 Also, in those days, I have seen the Jews [who] have settled women of Ashdod, of Ammon, of Moab.

24 And of their sons, half are speaking Ashdoditish--and are not knowing to speak Jewish--and according to the language of people and people.

25 And I strive with them, and declare them vile, and smite certain of them, and pluck off their hair, and cause them to swear by God, `Ye do not give your daughters to their sons, nor do ye take of their daughters to your sons, and to yourselves.

26 `By these did not Solomon king of Israel sin? and among the many nations there was no king like him, and beloved by his God he was, and God maketh him king over all Israel-- even him did the strange women cause to sin.

27 And to you do we hearken to do all this great evil, to trespass against our God, to settle strange women?'

28 And [one] of the sons of Joiada son of Eliashib the high priest, [is] son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite, and I cause him to flee from off me.

29 Be mindful of them, O my God, for the redeemed of the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood, and of the Levites.

30 And I have cleansed them from every stranger, and appoint charges to priests and to Levites, each in his work,

31 and for the wood-offering at appointed times, and for first-fruits. Be mindful of me, O my God, for good.

Esther 5

1 And it cometh to pass on the third day, that Esther putteth on royalty, and standeth in the inner-court of the house of the king over-against the house of the king, and the king is sitting on his royal throne, in the royal-house, over-againstthe opening of the house,

2 and it cometh to pass, at the king's seeing Esther the queen standing in the court, she hath received grace in his eyes, and the king holdeth out to Esther the golden sceptre that [is] in his hand, and Esther draweth near, and toucheth the topof the sceptre.

3 And the king saith to her, `What--to thee Esther, O queen? and what thy request? unto the half of the kingdom--and it is given to thee.'

4 And Esther saith, `If unto the king [it be] good, the king doth come in, and Haman, today, unto the banquet that I have made for him;'

5 and the king saith, `Haste ye Haman--to do the word of Esther;' and the king cometh in, and Haman, unto the banquet that Esther hath made.

6 And the king saith to Esther, during the banquet of wine, `What [is] thy petition? and it is given to thee; and what thy request? unto the half of the kingdom--and it is done.'

7 And Esther answereth and saith, `My petition and my request [is]:

8 if I have found grace in the eyes of the king, and if unto the king [it be] good, to give my petition, and to perform my request, the king doth come, and Haman, unto the banquet that I make for them, and to-morrow I do according to the word ofthe king.'

9 And Haman goeth forth on that day rejoicing and glad in heart, and at Haman's seeing Mordecai in the gate of the king, and he hath not risen nor moved for him, then is Haman full of fury against Mordecai.

10 And Haman forceth himself, and cometh in unto his house, and sendeth, and bringeth in his friends, and Zeresh his wife,

11 and Haman recounteth to them the glory of his wealth, and the abundance of his sons, and all that with which the king made him great, and with which he lifted him up above the heads and servants of the king.

12 And Haman saith, `Yea, Esther the queen brought none in with the king, unto the feast that she made, except myself, and also for to-morrow I am called to her, with the king,

13 and all this is not profitable to me, during all the time that I am seeing Mordecai the Jew sitting in the gate of the king.'

14 And Zeresh his wife saith to him, and all his friends, `Let them prepare a tree, in height fifty cubits, and in the morning speak to the king, and they hang Mordecai on it, and go thou in with the king unto the banquet rejoicing;' and the thing is good before Haman, and he prepareth the tree.

Esther 7

1 And the king cometh in, and Haman, to drink with Esther the queen,

2 and the king saith to Esther also on the second day, during the banquet of wine, `What [is] thy petition, Esther, O queen? and it is given to thee; and what thy request? unto the half of the kingdom--and it is done.'

3 And Esther the queen answereth and saith, `If I have found grace in thine eyes, O king, and if to the king [it be] good, let my life be given to me at my petition, and my people at my request;

4 for we have been sold, I and my people, to cut off, to slay, and to destroy; and if for men-servants and for maid-servants we had been sold I had kept silent--but the adversity is not equal to the loss of the king.'

5 And the king Ahasuerus saith, yea, he saith to Esther the queen, `Who [is] he--this one? and where [is] this one? --he whose heart hath filled him to do so?'

6 And Esther saith, `The man--adversary and enemy--[is] this wicked Haman;' and Haman hath been afraid at the presence of the king and of the queen.

7 And the king hath risen, in his fury, from the banquet of wine, unto the garden of the house, and Haman hath remained to seek for his life from Esther the queen, for he hath seen that evil hath been determined against him by the king.

8 And the king hath turned back out of the garden of the house unto the house of the banquet of wine, and Haman is falling on the couch on which Esther [is], and the king saith, `Also to subdue the queen with me in the house?' the word hath goneout from the mouth of the king, and the face of Haman they have covered.

9 And Harbonah, one of the eunuchs, saith before the king, `Also lo, the tree that Haman made for Mordecai, who spake good for the king, is standing in the house of Haman, in height fifty cubits;' and the king saith, `Hang him upon it.'

10 And they hang Haman upon the tree that he had prepared for Mordecai, and the fury of the king hath lain down.

Job 2

1 And the day is, that sons of God come in to station themselves by Jehovah, and there doth come also the Adversary in their midst to station himself by Jehovah.

2 And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Whence camest thou?' And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `From going to and fro in the land, and from walking up and down in it.'

3 And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Hast thou set thy heart unto My servant Job because there is none like him in the land, a man perfect and upright, fearing God and turning aside from evil? and still he is keeping hold on his integrity, and thou dost move Me against him to swallow him up for nought!'

4 And the Adversary answereth Jehovah and saith, `A skin for a skin, and all that a man hath he doth give for his life.

5 Yet, put forth, I pray Thee, Thy hand, and strike unto his bone and unto his flesh--if not: unto Thy face he doth bless Thee!'

6 And Jehovah saith unto the Adversary, `Lo, he [is] in thy hand; only his life take care of.'

7 And the Adversary goeth forth from the presence of Jehovah, and smiteth Job with a sore ulcer from the sole of his foot unto his crown.

8 And he taketh to him a potsherd to scrape himself with it, and he is sitting in the midst of the ashes.

9 And his wife saith to him, `Still thou art keeping hold on thine integrity: bless God and die.'

10 And he saith unto her, `As one of the foolish women speaketh, thou speakest; yea, the good we receive from God, and the evil we do not receive.' In all this Job hath not sinned with his lips.

11 And three of the friends of Job hear of all this evil that hath come upon him, and they come in each from his place--Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite--and they are met together to come in to bemoan him, and to comfort him;

12 and they lift up their eyes from afar and have not discerned him, and they lift up their voice and weep, and rend each his robe, and sprinkle dust on their heads--heavenward.

13 And they sit with him on the earth seven days and seven nights, and there is none speaking unto him a word when they have seen that the pain hath been very great.

Job 3

1 After this hath Job opened his mouth, and revileth his day.

2 And Job answereth and saith: --

3 Let the day perish in which I am born, And the night that hath said: `A man-child hath been conceived.'

4 That day--let it be darkness, Let not God require it from above, Nor let light shine upon it.

5 Let darkness and death-shade redeem it, Let a cloud tabernacle upon it, Let them terrify it as the most bitter of days.

6 That night--let thick darkness take it, Let it not be united to days of the year, Into the number of months let it not come.

7 Lo! that night--let it be gloomy, Let no singing come into it.

8 Let the cursers of day mark it, Who are ready to wake up Leviathan.

9 Let the stars of its twilight be dark, Let it wait for light, and there is none, And let it not look on the eyelids of the dawn.

10 Because it hath not shut the doors Of the womb that was mine! And hide misery from mine eyes.

11 Why from the womb do I not die? From the belly I have come forth and gasp!

12 Wherefore have knees been before me? And what [are] breasts, that I suck?

13 For now, I have lain down, and am quiet, I have slept--then there is rest to me,

14 With kings and counsellors of earth, These building wastes for themselves.

15 Or with princes--they have gold, They are filling their houses [with] silver.

16 (Or as a hidden abortion I am not, As infants--they have not seen light.)

17 There the wicked have ceased troubling, And there rest do the wearied in power.

18 Together prisoners have been at ease, They have not heard the voice of an exactor,

19 Small and great [are] there the same. And a servant [is] free from his lord.

20 Why giveth He to the miserable light, and life to the bitter soul?

21 Who are waiting for death, and it is not, And they seek it above hid treasures.

22 Who are glad--unto joy, They rejoice when they find a grave.

23 To a man whose way hath been hidden, And whom God doth shut up?

24 For before my food, my sighing cometh, And poured out as waters [are] my roarings.

25 For a fear I feared and it meeteth me, And what I was afraid of doth come to me.

26 I was not safe--nor was I quiet--Nor was I at rest--and trouble cometh!

Job 4

1 And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --

2 Hath one tried a word with thee? --Thou art weary! And to keep in words who is able?

3 Lo, thou hast instructed many, And feeble hands thou makest strong.

4 The stumbling one do thy words raise up, And bowing knees thou dost strengthen.

5 But now, it cometh in unto thee, And thou art weary; It striketh unto thee, and thou art troubled.

6 Is not thy reverence thy confidence? Thy hope--the perfection of thy ways?

7 Remember, I pray thee, Who, being innocent, hath perished? And where have the upright been cut off?

8 As I have seen--ploughers of iniquity, And sowers of misery, reap it!

9 From the breath of God they perish, And from the spirit of His anger consumed.

10 The roaring of a lion, And the voice of a fierce lion, And teeth of young lions have been broken.

11 An old lion is perishing without prey, And the whelps of the lioness do separate.

12 And unto me a thing is secretly brought, And receive doth mine ear a little of it.

13 In thoughts from visions of the night, In the falling of deep sleep on men,

14 Fear hath met me, and trembling, And the multitude of my bones caused to fear.

15 And a spirit before my face doth pass, Stand up doth the hair of my flesh;

16 It standeth, and I discern not its aspect, A similitude [is] over-against mine eyes, Silence! and a voice I hear:

17 `Is mortal man than God more righteous? Than his Maker is a man cleaner?

18 Lo, in His servants He putteth no credence, Nor in His messengers setteth praise.'

19 Also--the inhabitants of houses of clay, (Whose foundation [is] in the dust, They bruise them before a moth.)

20 From morning to evening are beaten down, Without any regarding, for ever they perish.

21 Hath not their excellency been removed with them? They die, and not in wisdom!

Job 5

1 Pray, call, is there any to answer thee? And unto which of the holy ones dost thou turn?

2 For provocation slayeth the perverse, And envy putteth to death the simple,

3 I--I have seen the perverse taking root, And I mark his habitation straightway,

4 Far are his sons from safety, And they are bruised in the gate, And there is no deliverer.

5 Whose harvest the hungry doth eat, And even from the thorns taketh it, And the designing swallowed their wealth.

6 For sorrow cometh not forth from the dust, Nor from the ground springeth up misery.

7 For man to misery is born, And the sparks go high to fly.

8 Yet I--I inquire for God, And for God I give my word,

9 Doing great things, and there is no searching. Wonderful, till there is no numbering.

10 Who is giving rain on the face of the land, And is sending waters on the out-places.

11 To set the low on a high place, And the mourners have been high [in] safety.

12 Making void thoughts of the subtile, And their hands do not execute wisdom.

13 Capturing the wise in their subtilty, And the counsel of wrestling ones was hastened,

14 By day they meet darkness, And as night--they grope at noon.

15 And He saveth the wasted from their mouth, And from a strong hand the needy,

16 And there is hope to the poor, And perverseness hath shut her mouth.

17 Lo, the happiness of mortal man, God doth reprove him: And the chastisement of the Mighty despise not,

18 For He doth pain, and He bindeth up, He smiteth, and His hands heal.

19 In six distresses He delivereth thee, And in seven evil striketh not on thee.

20 In famine He hath redeemed thee from death, And in battle from the hands of the sword.

21 When the tongue scourgeth thou art hid, And thou art not afraid of destruction, When it cometh.

22 At destruction and at hunger thou mockest, And of the beast of the earth, Thou art not afraid.

23 (For with sons of the field [is] thy covenant, And the beast of the field Hath been at peace with thee.)

24 And thou hast known that thy tent [is] peace, And inspected thy habitation, and errest not,

25 And hast known that numerous [is] Thy seed, And thine offspring as the herb of the earth;

26 Thou comest in full age unto the grave, As the going up of a stalk in its season.

27 Lo, this--we searched it out--it [is] right, hearken; And thou, know for thyself!

Job 6

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 O that my provocation were thoroughly weighed, And my calamity in balances They would lift up together!

3 For now, than the sands of the sea it is heavier, Therefore my words have been rash.

4 For arrows of the Mighty [are] with me, Whose poison is drinking up my spirit. Terrors of God array themselves [for] me!

5 Brayeth a wild ass over tender grass? Loweth an ox over his provender?

6 Eaten is an insipid thing without salt? Is there sense in the drivel of dreams?

7 My soul is refusing to touch! They [are] as my sickening food.

8 O that my request may come, That God may grant my hope!

9 That God would please--and bruise me, Loose His hand and cut me off!

10 And yet it is my comfort, (And I exult in pain--He doth not spare,) That I have not hidden The sayings of the Holy One.

11 What [is] my power that I should hope? And what mine end That I should prolong my life?

12 Is my strength the strength of stones? Is my flesh brazen?

13 Is not my help with me, And substance driven from me?

14 To a despiser of his friends [is] shame, And the fear of the Mighty he forsaketh.

15 My brethren have deceived as a brook, As a stream of brooks they pass away.

16 That are black because of ice, By them doth snow hide itself.

17 By the time they are warm they have been cut off, By its being hot they have been Extinguished from their place.

18 Turn aside do the paths of their way, They ascend into emptiness, and are lost.

19 Passengers of Tema looked expectingly, Travellers of Sheba hoped for them.

20 They were ashamed that one hath trusted, They have come unto it and are confounded.

21 Surely now ye have become the same! Ye see a downfall, and are afraid.

22 Is it because I said, Give to me? And, By your power bribe for me?

23 And, Deliver me from the hand of an adversary? And, From the hand of terrible ones ransom me?

24 Shew me, and I--I keep silent, And what I have erred, let me understand.

25 How powerful have been upright sayings, And what doth reproof from you reprove?

26 For reproof--do you reckon words? And for wind--sayings of the desperate.

27 Anger on the fatherless ye cause to fall, And are strange to your friend.

28 And, now, please, look upon me, Even to your face do I lie?

29 Turn back, I pray you, let it not be perverseness, Yea, turn back again--my righteousness [is] in it.

30 Is there in my tongue perverseness? Discerneth not my palate desirable things?

Job 7

1 Is there not a warfare to man on earth? And as the days of an hireling his days?

2 As a servant desireth the shadow, And as a hireling expecteth his wage,

3 So I have been caused to inherit months of vanity, And nights of misery they numbered to me.

4 If I lay down then I said, `When do I rise!' And evening hath been measured, And I have been full of tossings till dawn.

5 Clothed hath been my flesh [with] worms, And a clod of dust, My skin hath been shrivelled and is loathsome,

6 My days swifter than a weaving machine, And they are consumed without hope.

7 Remember Thou that my life [is] a breath, Mine eye turneth not back to see good.

8 The eye of my beholder beholdeth me not. Thine eyes [are] upon me--and I am not.

9 Consumed hath been a cloud, and it goeth, So he who is going down to Sheol cometh not up.

10 He turneth not again to his house, Nor doth his place discern him again.

11 Also I--I withhold not my mouth--I speak in the distress of my spirit, I talk in the bitterness of my soul.

12 A sea -[monster] am I, or a dragon, That thou settest over me a guard?

13 When I said, `My bed doth comfort me,' He taketh away in my talking my couch.

14 And thou hast affrighted me with dreams, And from visions thou terrifiest me,

15 And my soul chooseth strangling, Death rather than my bones.

16 I have wasted away--not to the age do I live. Cease from me, for my days [are] vanity.

17 What [is] man that Thou dost magnify him? And that Thou settest unto him Thy heart?

18 And inspectest him in the mornings, In the evenings dost try him?

19 How long dost Thou not look from me? Thou dost not desist till I swallow my spittle.

20 I have sinned, what do I to Thee, O watcher of man? Why hast Thou set me for a mark to Thee, And I am for a burden to myself--and what?

21 Thou dost not take away my transgression, And cause to pass away mine iniquity, Because now, for dust I lie down: And Thou hast sought me--and I am not!

Job 8

1 And Bildad the Shuhite answereth and saith: --

2 Till when dost thou speak these things? And a strong wind--sayings of thy mouth?

3 Doth God pervert judgment? And doth the Mighty One pervert justice?

4 If thy sons have sinned before Him, And He doth send them away, By the hand of their transgression,

5 If thou dost seek early unto God, And unto the Mighty makest supplication,

6 If pure and upright thou [art], Surely now He waketh for thee, And hath completed The habitation of thy righteousness.

7 And thy beginning hath been small, And thy latter end is very great.

8 For, ask I pray thee of a former generation, And prepare to a search of their fathers,

9 (For of yesterday we [are], and we know not, For a shadow [are] our days on earth.)

10 Do they not shew thee--speak to thee, And from their heart bring forth words?

11 `Doth a rush wise without mire? A reed increase without water?

12 While it [is] in its budding--uncropped, Even before any herb it withereth.

13 So [are] the paths of all forgetting God, And the hope of the profane doth perish,

14 Whose confidence is loathsome, And the house of a spider his trust.

15 He leaneth on his house--and it standeth not: He taketh hold on it--and it abideth not.

16 Green he [is] before the sun, And over his garden his branch goeth out.

17 By a heap his roots are wrapped, A house of stones he looketh for.

18 If [one] doth destroy him from his place, Then it hath feigned concerning him, I have not seen thee!

19 Lo, this [is] the joy of his way, And from the dust others spring up.'

20 Lo, God doth not reject the perfect, Nor taketh hold on the hand of evil doers.

21 While he filleth with laughter thy mouth, And thy lips with shouting,

22 Those hating thee do put on shame, And the tent of the wicked is not!

Job 9

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 Truly I have known that [it is] so, And what--is man righteous with God?

3 If he delight to strive with Him--He doth not answer him one of a thousand.

4 Wise in heart and strong in power--Who hath hardened toward Him and is at peace?

5 Who is removing mountains, And they have not known, Who hath overturned them in His anger.

6 Who is shaking earth from its place, And its pillars move themselves.

7 Who is speaking to the sun, and it riseth not, And the stars He sealeth up.

8 Stretching out the heavens by Himself, And treading on the heights of the sea,

9 Making Osh, Kesil, and Kimah, And the inner chambers of the south.

10 Doing great things till there is no searching, And wonderful, till there is no numbering.

11 Lo, He goeth over by me, and I see not, And He passeth on, and I attend not to it.

12 Lo, He snatches away, who bringeth it back? Who saith unto Him, `What dost Thou?'

13 God doth not turn back His anger, Under Him bowed have proud helpers.

14 How much less do I--I answer Him? Choose out my words with Him?

15 Whom, though I were righteous, I answer not, For my judgment I make supplication.

16 Though I had called and He answereth me, I do not believe that He giveth ear [to] my voice.

17 Because with a tempest He bruiseth me, And hath multiplied my wounds for nought.

18 He permitteth me not to refresh my spirit, But filleth me with bitter things.

19 If of power, lo, the Strong One; And if of judgment--who doth convene me?

20 If I be righteous, Mine mouth doth declare me wicked, Perfect I am! --it declareth me perverse.

21 Perfect I am! --I know not my soul, I despise my life.

22 It is the same thing, therefore I said, `The perfect and the wicked He is consuming.'

23 If a scourge doth put to death suddenly, At the trial of the innocent He laugheth.

24 Earth hath been given Into the hand of the wicked one. The face of its judges he covereth, If not--where, who [is] he?

25 My days have been swifter than a runner, They have fled, they have not seen good,

26 They have passed on with ships of reed, As an eagle darteth on food.

27 Though I say, `I forget my talking, I forsake my corner, and I brighten up!'

28 I have been afraid of all my griefs, I have known that Thou dost not acquit me.

29 I--I am become wicked; why [is] this? [In] vain I labour.

30 If I have washed myself with snow-water, And purified with soap my hands,

31 Then in corruption Thou dost dip me, And my garments have abominated me.

32 But if a man like myself--I answer him, We come together into judgment.

33 If there were between us an umpire, He doth place his hand on us both.

34 He doth turn aside from off me his rod, And His terror doth not make me afraid,

35 I speak, and do not fear Him, But I am not right with myself.

Job 10

1 My soul hath been weary of my life, I leave off my talking to myself, I speak in the bitterness of my soul.

2 I say unto God, `Do not condemn me, Let me know why Thou dost strive [with] me.

3 Is it good for Thee that Thou dost oppress? That Thou despisest the labour of Thy hands, And on the counsel of the wicked hast shone?

4 Eyes of flesh hast Thou? As man seeth--seest Thou?

5 As the days of man [are] Thy days? Thy years as the days of a man?

6 That Thou inquirest for mine iniquity, And for my sin seekest?

7 For Thou knowest that I am not wicked, And there is no deliverer from Thy hand.

8 Thy hands have taken pains about me, And they make me together round about, And Thou swallowest me up!

9 Remember, I pray Thee, That as clay Thou hast made me, And unto dust Thou dost bring me back.

10 Dost Thou not as milk pour me out? And as cheese curdle me?

11 Skin and flesh Thou dost put on me, And with bones and sinews dost fence me.

12 Life and kindness Thou hast done with me. And Thy inspection hath preserved my spirit.

13 And these Thou hast laid up in Thy heart, I have known that this [is] with Thee.

14 If I sinned, then Thou hast observed me, And from mine iniquity dost not acquit me,

15 If I have done wickedly--woe to me, And righteously--I lift not up my head, Full of shame--then see my affliction,

16 And it riseth--as a lion Thou huntest me. And Thou turnest back--Thou shewest Thyself wonderful in me.

17 Thou renewest Thy witnesses against me, And dost multiply Thine anger with me, Changes and warfare [are] with me.

18 And why from the womb Hast Thou brought me forth? I expire, and the eye doth not see me.

19 As I had not been, I am, From the belly to the grave I am brought,

20 Are not my days few? Cease then, and put from me, And I brighten up a little,

21 Before I go, and return not, Unto a land of darkness and death-shade,

22 A land of obscurity as thick darkness, Death-shade--and no order, And the shining [is] as thick darkness.'

Job 11

1 And Zophar the Naamathite answereth and saith: --

2 Is a multitude of words not answered? And is a man of lips justified?

3 Thy devices make men keep silent, Thou scornest, and none is causing blushing!

4 And thou sayest, `Pure [is] my discourse, And clean I have been in Thine eyes.'

5 And yet, O that God had spoken! And doth open His lips with thee.

6 And declare to thee secrets of wisdom, For counsel hath foldings. And know thou that God forgetteth for thee, [Some] of thine iniquity.

7 By searching dost thou find out God? Unto perfection find out the Mighty One?

8 Heights of the heavens! --what dost thou? Deeper than Sheol! --what knowest thou?

9 Longer than earth [is] its measure, And broader than the sea.

10 If He pass on, and shut up, and assemble, Who then dost reverse it?

11 For he hath known men of vanity, And He seeth iniquity, And one doth not consider [it]!

12 And empty man is bold, And the colt of a wild ass man is born.

13 If thou--thou hast prepared thy heart, And hast spread out unto Him thy hands,

14 If iniquity [is] in thy hand, put it far off, And let not perverseness dwell in thy tents.

15 For then thou liftest up thy face from blemish, And thou hast been firm, and fearest not.

16 For thou dost forget misery, As waters passed away thou rememberest.

17 And above the noon doth age rise, Thou fliest--as the morning thou art.

18 And thou hast trusted because their is hope, And searched--in confidence thou liest down,

19 And thou hast rested, And none is causing trembling, And many have entreated thy face;

20 And the eyes of the wicked are consumed, And refuge hath perished from them, And their hope [is] a breathing out of soul!

Job 12

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 Truly--ye [are] the people, And with you doth wisdom die.

3 I also have a heart like you, I am not fallen more than you, And with whom is there not like these?

4 A laughter to his friend I am: `He calleth to God, and He answereth him,' A laughter [is] the perfect righteous one.

5 A torch--despised in the thoughts of the secure Is prepared for those sliding with the feet.

6 At peace are the tents of spoilers, And those provoking God have confidence, He into whose hand God hath brought.

7 And yet, ask, I pray thee, [One of] the beasts, and it doth shew thee, And a fowl of the heavens, And it doth declare to thee.

8 Or talk to the earth, and it sheweth thee, And fishes of the sea recount to thee:

9 `Who hath not known in all these, That the hand of Jehovah hath done this?

10 In whose hand [is] the breath of every living thing, And the spirit of all flesh of man.'

11 Doth not the ear try words? And the palate taste food for itself?

12 With the very aged [is] wisdom, And [with] length of days understanding.

13 With Him [are] wisdom and might, To him [are] counsel and understanding.

14 Lo, He breaketh down, and it is not built up, He shutteth against a man, And it is not opened.

15 Lo, He keepeth in the waters, and they are dried up, And he sendeth them forth, And they overturn the land.

16 With Him [are] strength and wisdom, His the deceived and deceiver.

17 Causing counsellors to go away a spoil, And judges He maketh foolish.

18 The bands of kings He hath opened, And He bindeth a girdle on their loins.

19 Causing ministers to go away a spoil And strong ones He overthroweth.

20 Turning aside the lip of the stedfast, And the reason of the aged He taketh away.

21 Pouring contempt upon princes, And the girdle of the mighty He made feeble.

22 Removing deep things out of darkness, And He bringeth out to light death-shade.

23 Magnifying the nations, and He destroyeth them, Spreading out the nations, and He quieteth them.

24 Turning aside the heart Of the heads of the people of the land, And he causeth them to wander In vacancy--no way!

25 They feel darkness, and not light, He causeth them to wander as a drunkard.

Job 13

1 Lo, all--hath mine eye seen, Heard hath mine ear, and it attendeth to it.

2 According to your knowledge I have known--also I. I am not fallen more than you.

3 Yet I for the Mighty One do speak, And to argue for God I delight.

4 And yet, ye [are] forgers of falsehood, Physicians of nought--all of you,

5 O that ye would keep perfectly silent, And it would be to you for wisdom.

6 Hear, I pray you, my argument, And to the pleadings of my lips attend,

7 For God do ye speak perverseness? And for Him do ye speak deceit?

8 His face do ye accept, if for God ye strive?

9 Is [it] good that He doth search you, If, as one mocketh at a man, ye mock at Him?

10 He doth surely reprove you, if in secret ye accept faces.

11 Doth not His excellency terrify you? And His dread fall upon you?

12 Your remembrances [are] similes of ashes, For high places of clay your heights.

13 Keep silent from me, and I speak, And pass over me doth what?

14 Wherefore do I take my flesh in my teeth? And my soul put in my hand?

15 Lo, He doth slay me--I wait not! Only, my ways unto His face I argue.

16 Also--He [is] to me for salvation, For the profane cometh not before Him.

17 Hear ye diligently my word, And my declaration with your ears.

18 Lo, I pray you, I have set in order the cause, I have known that I am righteous.

19 Who [is] he that doth strive with me? For now I keep silent and gasp.

20 Only two things, O God, do with me: Then from Thy face I am not hidden.

21 Thy hand put far off from me, And Thy terror let not terrify me.

22 And call Thou, and I--I answer, Or--I speak, and answer Thou me.

23 How many iniquities and sins have I? My transgression and my sin let me know.

24 Why dost Thou hide Thy face? And reckonest me for an enemy to Thee?

25 A leaf driven away dost Thou terrify? And the dry stubble dost Thou pursue?

26 For Thou writest against me bitter things, And causest me to possess iniquities of my youth:

27 And puttest in the stocks my feet, And observest all my paths, On the roots of my feet Thou settest a print,

28 And he, as a rotten thing, weareth away, As a garment hath a moth consumed him.

Job 14

1 Man, born of woman! Of few days, and full of trouble!

2 As a flower he hath gone forth, and is cut off, And he fleeth as a shadow and standeth not.

3 Also--on this Thou hast opened Thine eyes, And dost bring me into judgment with Thee.

4 Who giveth a clean thing out of an unclean? not one.

5 If determined are his days, The number of his months [are] with Thee, His limit Thou hast made, And he passeth not over;

6 Look away from off him that he may cease, Till he enjoy as an hireling his day.

7 For there is of a tree hope, if it be cut down, That again it doth change, That its tender branch doth not cease.

8 If its root becometh old in the earth, And its stem doth die in the dust,

9 From the fragrance of water it doth flourish, And hath made a crop as a plant.

10 And a man dieth, and becometh weak, And man expireth, and where [is] he?

11 Waters have gone away from a sea, And a river becometh waste and dry.

12 And man hath lain down, and riseth not, Till the wearing out of the heavens they awake not, Nor are roused from their sleep.

13 O that in Sheol Thou wouldest conceal me, Hide me till the turning of Thine anger, Set for me a limit, and remember me.

14 If a man dieth--doth he revive? All days of my warfare I wait, till my change come.

15 Thou dost call, and I--I answer Thee; To the work of Thy hands Thou hast desire.

16 But now, my steps Thou numberest, Thou dost not watch over my sin.

17 Sealed up in a bag [is] my transgression, And Thou sewest up mine iniquity.

18 And yet, a falling mountain wasteth away, And a rock is removed from its place.

19 Stones have waters worn away, Their outpourings wash away the dust of earth, And the hope of man Thou hast destroyed.

20 Thou prevailest [over] him for ever, and he goeth, He is changing his countenance, And Thou sendest him away.

21 Honoured are his sons, and he knoweth not; And they are little, and he attendeth not to them.

22 Only--his flesh for him is pained, And his soul for him doth mourn.'

Job 15

1 And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --

2 Doth a wise man answer [with] vain knowledge? And fill [with] an east wind his belly?

3 To reason with a word not useful? And speeches--no profit in them?

4 Yea, thou dost make reverence void, And dost diminish meditation before God.

5 For thy mouth teacheth thine iniquity, And thou chooseth the tongue of the subtile.

6 Thy mouth declareth thee wicked, and not I, And thy lips testify against thee.

7 The first man art thou born? And before the heights wast thou formed?

8 Of the secret counsel of God dost thou hear? And withdrawest thou unto thee wisdom?

9 What hast thou known, and we know not? Understandest thou--and it is not with us?

10 Both the gray-headed And the very aged [are] among us--Greater than thy father [in] days.

11 Too few for thee are the comforts of God? And a gentle word [is] with thee,

12 What--doth thine heart take thee away? And what--are thine eyes high?

13 For thou turnest against God thy spirit? And hast brought out words from thy mouth:

14 What [is] man that he is pure, And that he is righteous, one born of woman?

15 Lo, in His holy ones He putteth no credence, And the heavens have not been pure in His eyes.

16 Also--surely abominable and filthy Is man drinking as water perverseness.

17 I shew thee--hearken to me--And this I have seen and declare:

18 Which the wise declare--And have not hid--from their fathers.

19 To them alone was the land given, And a stranger passed not over into their midst:

20 `All days of the wicked he is paining himself, And few years have been laid up for the terrible one.

21 A fearful voice [is] in his ears, In peace doth a destroyer come to him.

22 He believeth not to return from darkness, And watched [is] he for the sword.

23 He is wandering for bread--`Where [is] it?' He hath known that ready at his hand Is a day of darkness.

24 Terrify him do adversity and distress, They prevail over him As a king ready for a boaster.

25 For he stretched out against God his hand, And against the Mighty he maketh himself mighty.

26 He runneth unto Him with a neck, With thick bosses of his shields.

27 For he hath covered his face with his fat, And maketh vigour over [his] confidence.

28 And he inhabiteth cities cut off, houses not dwelt in, That have been ready to become heaps.

29 He is not rich, nor doth his wealth rise, Nor doth he stretch out on earth their continuance.

30 He turneth not aside from darkness, His tender branch doth a flame dry up, And he turneth aside at the breath of His mouth!

31 Let him not put credence in vanity, He hath been deceived, For vanity is his recompence.

32 Not in his day is it completed, And his bending branch is not green.

33 He shaketh off as a vine his unripe fruit, And casteth off as an olive his blossom.

34 For the company of the profane [is] gloomy, And fire hath consumed tents of bribery.

35 To conceive misery, and to bear iniquity, Even their heart doth prepare deceit.

Job 16

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 I have heard many such things, Miserable comforters [are] ye all.

3 Is there an end to words of wind? Or what doth embolden thee that thou answerest?

4 I also, like you, might speak, If your soul were in my soul's stead. I might join against you with words, And nod at you with my head.

5 I might harden you with my mouth, And the moving of my lips might be sparing.

6 If I speak, my pain is not restrained, And I cease--what goeth from me?

7 Only, now, it hath wearied me; Thou hast desolated all my company,

8 And Thou dost loathe me, For a witness it hath been, And rise up against me doth my failure, In my face it testifieth.

9 His anger hath torn, and he hateth me, He hath gnashed at me with his teeth, My adversary sharpeneth his eyes for me.

10 They have gaped on me with their mouth, In reproach they have smitten my cheeks, Together against me they set themselves.

11 God shutteth me up unto the perverse, And to the hands of the wicked turneth me over.

12 At ease I have been, and he breaketh me, And he hath laid hold on my neck, And he breaketh me in pieces, And he raiseth me to him for a mark.

13 Go round against me do his archers. He splitteth my reins, and spareth not, He poureth out to the earth my gall.

14 He breaketh me--breach upon breach, He runneth upon me as a mighty one.

15 Sackcloth I have sewed on my skin, And have rolled in the dust my horn.

16 My face is foul with weeping, And on mine eyelids [is] death-shade.

17 Not for violence in my hands, And my prayer [is] pure.

18 O earth, do not thou cover my blood! And let there not be a place for my cry.

19 Also, now, lo, in the heavens [is] my witness, And my testifier in the high places.

20 My interpreter [is] my friend, Unto God hath mine eye dropped:

21 And he reasoneth for a man with God, And a son of man for his friend.

22 When a few years do come, Then a path I return not do I go.

Job 17

1 My spirit hath been destroyed, My days extinguished--graves [are] for me.

2 If not--mockeries [are] with me. And in their provocations mine eye lodgeth.

3 Place, I pray Thee, my pledge with Thee; Who is he that striketh hand with me?

4 For their heart Thou hast hidden From understanding, Therefore Thou dost not exalt them.

5 For a portion he sheweth friendship, And the eyes of his sons are consumed.

6 And he set me up for a proverb of the peoples, And a wonder before them I am.

7 And dim from sorrow is mine eye, And my members as a shadow all of them.

8 Astonished are the upright at this, And the innocent against the profane Stirreth himself up.

9 And the righteous layeth hold [on] his way, And the clean of hands addeth strength, And- -dumb are they all.

10 Return, and come in, I pray you, And I find not among you a wise man.

11 My days have passed by, My devices have been broken off, The possessions of my heart!

12 Night for day they appoint, Light [is] near because of darkness.

13 If I wait--Sheol [is] my house, In darkness I have spread out my couch.

14 To corruption I have called: --`Thou [art] my father.' `My mother' and `my sister' --to the worm.

15 And where [is] now my hope? Yea, my hope, who doth behold it?

16 [To] the parts of Sheol ye go down, If together on the dust we may rest.

Job 18

1 And Bildad the Shuhite answereth and saith: --

2 When do ye set an end to words? Consider ye, and afterwards do we speak.

3 Wherefore have we been reckoned as cattle? We have been defiled in your eyes!

4 (He is tearing himself in his anger.) For thy sake is earth forsaken? And removed is a rock from its place?

5 Also, the light of the wicked is extinguished. And there doth not shine a spark of his fire.

6 The light hath been dark in his tent, And his lamp over him is extinguished.

7 Straitened are the steps of his strength, And cast him down doth his own counsel.

8 For he is sent into a net by his own feet, And on a snare he doth walk habitually.

9 Seize on the heel doth a gin, Prevail over him do the designing.

10 Hidden in the earth is his cord, And his trap on the path.

11 Round about terrified him have terrors, And they have scattered him--at his feet.

12 Hungry is his sorrow, And calamity is ready at his side.

13 It consumeth the parts of his skin, Consume his parts doth death's first-born.

14 Drawn from his tent is his confidence, And it causeth him to step to the king of terrors.

15 It dwelleth in his tent--out of his provender, Scattered over his habitation is sulphur.

16 From beneath his roots are dried up, And from above cut off is his crop.

17 His memorial hath perished from the land, And he hath no name on the street.

18 They thrust him from light unto darkness, And from the habitable earth cast him out.

19 He hath no continuator, Nor successor among his people, And none is remaining in his dwellings.

20 At this day westerns have been astonished And easterns have taken fright.

21 Only these [are] tabernacles of the perverse, And this the place God hath not known.

Job 19

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 Till when do ye afflict my soul, And bruise me with words?

3 These ten times ye put me to shame, ye blush not. Ye make yourselves strange to me--

4 And also--truly, I have erred, With me doth my error remain.

5 If, truly, over me ye magnify yourselves, And decide against me my reproach;

6 Know now, that God turned me upside down, And His net against me hath set round,

7 Lo, I cry out--violence, and am not answered, I cry aloud, and there is no judgment.

8 My way He hedged up, and I pass not over, And on my paths darkness He placeth.

9 Mine honour from off me He hath stripped, And He turneth the crown from my head.

10 He breaketh me down round about, and I go, And removeth like a tree my hope.

11 And He kindleth against me His anger, And reckoneth me to Him as His adversaries.

12 Come in do His troops together, And they raise up against me their way, And encamp round about my tent.

13 My brethren from me He hath put far off, And mine acquaintances surely Have been estranged from me.

14 Ceased have my neighbours And my familiar friends have forgotten me,

15 Sojourners of my house and my maids, For a stranger reckon me: An alien I have been in their eyes.

16 To my servant I have called, And he doth not answer, With my mouth I make supplication to him.

17 My spirit is strange to my wife, And my favours to the sons of my [mother's] womb.

18 Also sucklings have despised me, I rise, and they speak against me.

19 Abominate me do all the men of my counsel, And those I have loved, Have been turned against me.

20 To my skin and to my flesh Cleaved hath my bone, And I deliver myself with the skin of my teeth.

21 Pity me, pity me, ye my friends, For the hand of God hath stricken against me.

22 Why do you pursue me as God? And with my flesh are not satisfied?

23 Who doth grant now, That my words may be written? Who doth grant that in a book they may be graven?

24 With a pen of iron and lead--For ever in a rock they may be hewn.

25 That--I have known my Redeemer, The Living and the Last, For the dust he doth rise.

26 And after my skin hath compassed this [body], Then from my flesh I see God:

27 Whom I--I see on my side, And mine eyes have beheld, and not a stranger, Consumed have been my reins in my bosom.

28 But ye say, `Why do we pursue after him?' And the root of the matter hath been found in me.

29 Be ye afraid because of the sword, For furious [are] the punishments of the sword, That ye may know that [there is] a judgment.

Job 20

1 And Zophar the Naamathite answereth and saith: --

2 Therefore my thoughts cause me to answer, And because of my sensations in me.

3 The chastisement of my shame I hear, And the spirit of mine understanding Doth cause me to answer:

4 This hast thou known from antiquity? Since the placing of man on earth?

5 That the singing of the wicked [is] short, And the joy of the profane for a moment,

6 Though his excellency go up to the heavens, And his head against a cloud he strike--

7 As his own dung for ever he doth perish, His beholders say: `Where [is] he?'

8 As a dream he fleeth, and they find him not, And he is driven away as a vision of the night,

9 The eye hath not seen him, and addeth not. And not again doth his place behold him.

10 His sons do the poor oppress, And his hands give back his wealth.

11 His bones have been full of his youth, And with him on the dust it lieth down.

12 Though he doth sweeten evil in his mouth, Doth hide it under his tongue,

13 Hath pity on it, and doth not forsake it, And keep it back in the midst of his palate,

14 His food in his bowels is turned, The bitterness of asps [is] in his heart.

15 Wealth he hath swallowed, and doth vomit it. From his belly God driveth it out.

16 Gall of asps he sucketh, Slay him doth the tongue of a viper.

17 He looketh not on rivulets, Flowing of brooks of honey and butter.

18 He is giving back [what] he laboured for, And doth not consume [it]; As a bulwark [is] his exchange, and he exults not.

19 For he oppressed--he forsook the poor, A house he hath taken violently away, And he doth not build it.

20 For he hath not known ease in his belly. With his desirable thing he delivereth not himself.

21 There is not a remnant to his food, Therefore his good doth not stay.

22 In the fulness of his sufficiency he is straitened. Every perverse hand doth meet him.

23 It cometh to pass, at the filling of his belly, He sendeth forth against him The fierceness of His anger, Yea, He raineth on him in his eating.

24 He fleeth from an iron weapon, Pass through him doth a bow of brass.

25 One hath drawn, And it cometh out from the body, And a glittering weapon from his gall proceedeth. On him [are] terrors.

26 All darkness is hid for his treasures, Consume him doth a fire not blown, Broken is the remnant in his tent.

27 Reveal do the heavens his iniquity, And earth is raising itself against him.

28 Remove doth the increase of his house, Poured forth in a day of His anger.

29 This [is] the portion of a wicked man from God. And an inheritance appointed him by God.

Job 21

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 Hear ye diligently my word, And this is your consolation.

3 Bear with me, and I speak, And after my speaking--ye may deride.

4 I--to man [is] my complaint? and if [so], wherefore May not my temper become short?

5 Turn unto me, and be astonished, And put hand to mouth.

6 Yea, if I have remembered, then I have been troubled. And my flesh hath taken fright.

7 Wherefore do the wicked live? They have become old, Yea, they have been mighty in wealth.

8 Their seed is established, Before their face with them, And their offspring before their eyes.

9 Their houses [are] peace without fear, Nor [is] a rod of God upon them.

10 His bullock hath eaten corn, and doth not loath. His cow bringeth forth safely, And doth not miscarry.

11 They send forth as a flock their sucklings, And their children skip,

12 They lift [themselves] up at timbrel and harp, And rejoice at the sound of an organ.

13 They wear out in good their days, And in a moment [to] Sheol go down.

14 And they say to God, `Turn aside from us, And the knowledge of Thy ways We have not desired.

15 What [is] the Mighty One that we serve Him? And what do we profit when we meet with Him?'

16 Lo, not in their hand [is] their good, (The counsel of the wicked Hath been far from me.)

17 How oft is the lamp of the wicked extinguished, And come on them doth their calamity? Pangs He apportioneth in His anger.

18 They are as straw before wind, And as chaff a hurricane hath stolen away,

19 God layeth up for his sons his sorrow, He giveth recompense unto him--and he knoweth.

20 His own eyes see his destruction, And of the wrath of the Mighty he drinketh.

21 For what [is] his delight in his house after him, And the number of his months cut off?

22 To God doth [one] teach knowledge, And He the high doth judge?

23 This [one] dieth in his perfect strength, Wholly at ease and quiet.

24 His breasts have been full of milk, And marrow his bones doth moisten.

25 And this [one] dieth with a bitter soul, And have not eaten with gladness.

26 Together--on the dust they lie down, And the worm doth cover them over.

27 Lo, I have known your thoughts, And the devices against me ye do wrongfully.

28 For ye say, `Where [is] the house of the noble? And where the tent--The tabernacles of the wicked?'

29 Have ye not asked those passing by the way? And their signs do ye not know?

30 That to a day of calamity is the wicked spared. To a day of wrath they are brought.

31 Who doth declare to his face his way? And [for] that which he hath done, Who doth give recompence to him?

32 And he--to the graves he is brought. And over the heap a watch is kept.

33 Sweet to him have been the clods of the valley, And after him every man he draweth, And before him there is no numbering.

34 And how do ye comfort me [with] vanity, And in your answers hath been left trespass?

Job 22

1 And Eliphaz the Temanite answereth and saith: --

2 To God is a man profitable, Because a wise man to himself is profitable?

3 Is it a delight to the Mighty One That thou art righteous? is it gain, That thou makest perfect thy ways?

4 Because of thy reverence Doth He reason [with] thee? He entereth with thee into judgment:

5 Is not thy wickedness abundant? And there is no end to thine iniquities.

6 For thou takest a pledge of thy brother for nought, And the garments of the naked Thou dost strip off.

7 Thou causest not the weary to drink water, And from the hungry thou withholdest bread.

8 As to the man of arm--he hath the earth, And the accepted of face--he dwelleth in it.

9 Widows thou hast sent away empty, And the arms of the fatherless are bruised.

10 Therefore round about thee [are] snares, And trouble thee doth fear suddenly.

11 Or darkness--thou dost not see, And abundance of waters doth cover thee.

12 Is not God high [in] heaven? And see the summit of the stars, That they are high.

13 And thou hast said, `What--hath God known? Through thickness doth He judge?

14 Thick clouds [are] a secret place to Him, And He doth not see;' And the circle of the heavens He walketh habitually,

15 The path of the age dost thou observe, That men of iniquity have trodden?

16 Who have been cut down unexpectedly, A flood is poured out on their foundation.

17 Those saying to God, `Turn aside from us,' And what doth the Mighty One to them?

18 And he hath filled their houses [with] good: (And the counsel of the wicked Hath been far from me.)

19 See do the righteous and they rejoice, And the innocent mocketh at them,

20 `Surely our substance hath not been cut off, And their excellency hath fire consumed.'

21 Acquaint thyself, I pray thee, with Him, And be at peace, Thereby thine increase [is] good.

22 Receive, I pray thee, from His mouth a law, And set His sayings in thy heart.

23 If thou dost return unto the Mighty Thou art built up, Thou puttest iniquity far from thy tents.

24 So as to set on the dust a defence, And on a rock of the valleys a covering.

25 And the Mighty hath been thy defence, And silver [is] strength to thee.

26 For then on the Mighty thou delightest thyself, And dost lift up unto God thy face,

27 Thou dost make supplication unto Him, And He doth hear thee, And thy vows thou completest.

28 And thou decreest a saying, And it is established to thee, And on thy ways hath light shone.

29 For they have made low, And thou sayest, `Lift up.' And the bowed down of eyes he saveth.

30 He delivereth the not innocent, Yea, he hath been delivered By the cleanness of thy hands.

Job 23

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 Also--to-day [is] my complaint bitter, My hand hath been heavy because of my sighing.

3 O that I had known--and I find Him, I come in unto His seat,

4 I arrange before Him the cause, And my mouth fill [with] arguments.

5 I know the words He doth answer me, And understand what He saith to me.

6 In the abundance of power doth He strive with me? No! surely He putteth [it] in me.

7 There the upright doth reason with Him, And I escape for ever from my judge.

8 Lo, forward I go--and He is not, And backward--and I perceive him not.

9 [To] the left in His working--and I see not, He is covered [on] the right, and I behold not.

10 For He hath known the way with me, He hath tried me--as gold I go forth.

11 On His step hath my foot laid hold, His way I have kept, and turn not aside,

12 The command of His lips, and I depart not. Above my allotted portion I have laid up The sayings of His mouth.

13 And He [is] in one [mind], And who doth turn Him back? And His soul hath desired-- and He doth [it].

14 For He doth complete my portion, And many such things [are] with Him.

15 Therefore, from His presence I am troubled, I consider, and am afraid of Him.

16 And God hath made my heart soft, And the Mighty hath troubled me.

17 For I have not been cut off before darkness, And before me He covered thick darkness.

Job 24

1 Wherefore from the Mighty One Times have not been hidden, And those knowing Him have not seen His days.

2 The borders they reach, A drove they have taken violently away, Yea, they do evil.

3 The ass of the fatherless they lead away, They take in pledge the ox of the widow,

4 They turn aside the needy from the way, Together have hid the poor of the earth.

5 Lo, wild asses in a wilderness, They have gone out about their work, Seeking early for prey, A mixture for himself--food for young ones.

6 In a field his provender they reap, And the vineyard of the wicked they glean.

7 The naked they cause to lodge Without clothing. And there is no covering in the cold.

8 From the inundation of hills they are wet, And without a refuge--have embraced a rock.

9 They take violently away From the breast the orphan, And on the poor they lay a pledge.

10 Naked, they have gone without clothing, And hungry--have taken away a sheaf.

11 Between their walls they make oil, Wine-presses they have trodden, and thirst.

12 Because of enmity men do groan, And the soul of pierced ones doth cry, And God doth not give praise.

13 They have been among rebellious ones of light, They have not discerned His ways, Nor abode in His paths.

14 At the light doth the murderer rise, He doth slay the poor and needy, And in the night he is as a thief.

15 And the eye of an adulterer Hath observed the twilight, Saying, `No eye doth behold me.' And he putteth the face in secret.

16 He hath dug in the darkness--houses; By day they shut themselves up, They have not known light.

17 When together, morning [is] to them death shade, When he discerneth the terrors of death shade.

18 Light he [is] on the face of the waters, Vilified is their portion in the earth, He turneth not the way of vineyards.

19 Drought--also heat--consume snow-waters, Sheol [those who] have sinned.

20 Forget him doth the womb, Sweeten [on] him doth the worm, No more is he remembered, And broken as a tree is wickedness.

21 Treating evil the barren [who] beareth not, And [to] the widow he doth no good,

22 And hath drawn the mighty by his power, He riseth, and none believeth in life.

23 He giveth to him confidence, and he is supported, And his eyes [are] on their ways.

24 High they were [for] a little, and they are not, And they have been brought low. As all [others] they are shut up, And as the head of an ear of corn cut off.

25 And if not now, who doth prove me a liar, And doth make of nothing my word?

Job 26

1 And Job answereth and saith: --

2 What--thou hast helped the powerless, Saved an arm not strong!

3 What--thou hast given counsel to the unwise, And wise plans in abundance made known.

4 With whom hast thou declared words? And whose breath came forth from thee?

5 The Rephaim are formed, Beneath the waters, also their inhabitants.

6 Naked [is] Sheol over-against Him, And there is no covering to destruction.

7 Stretching out the north over desolation, Hanging the earth upon nothing,

8 Binding up the waters in His thick clouds, And the cloud is not rent under them.

9 Taking hold of the face of the throne, Spreading over it His cloud.

10 A limit He hath placed on the waters, Unto the boundary of light with darkness.

11 Pillars of the heavens do tremble, And they wonder because of His rebuke.

12 By His power He hath quieted the sea, And by His understanding smitten the proud.

13 By His Spirit the heavens He beautified, Formed hath His hand the fleeing serpent.

14 Lo, these [are] the borders of His way, And how little a matter is heard of Him, And the thunder of His might Who doth understand?

Job 27

1 And Job addeth to lift up his simile, and saith: --

2 God liveth! He turned aside my judgment, And the Mighty--He made my soul bitter.

3 For all the while my breath [is] in me, And the spirit of God in my nostrils.

4 My lips do not speak perverseness, And my tongue doth not utter deceit.

5 Pollution to me--if I justify you, Till I expire I turn not aside mine integrity from me.

6 On my righteousness I have laid hold, And I do not let it go, My heart doth not reproach me while I live.

7 As the wicked is my enemy, And my withstander as the perverse.

8 For what [is] the hope of the profane, When He doth cut off? When God doth cast off his soul?

9 His cry doth God hear, When distress cometh on him?

10 On the Mighty doth he delight himself? Call God at all times?

11 I shew you by the hand of God, That which [is] with the Mighty I hide not.

12 Lo, ye--all of you--have seen, And why [is] this--ye are altogether vain?

13 This [is] the portion of wicked man with God, And the inheritance of terrible ones From the Mighty they receive.

14 If his sons multiply--for them [is] a sword. And his offspring [are] not satisfied [with] bread.

15 His remnant in death are buried, And his widows do not weep.

16 If he heap up as dust silver, And as clay prepare clothing,

17 He prepareth--and the righteous putteth [it] on, And the silver the innocent doth apportion.

18 He hath built as a moth his house, And as a booth a watchman hath made.

19 Rich he lieth down, and he is not gathered, His eyes he hath opened, and he is not.

20 Overtake him as waters do terrors, By night stolen him away hath a whirlwind.

21 Take him up doth an east wind, and he goeth, And it frighteneth him from his place,

22 And it casteth at him, and doth not spare, From its hand he diligently fleeth.

23 It clappeth at him its hands, And it hisseth at him from his place.

Job 28

1 Surely there is for silver a source, And a place for the gold they refine;

2 Iron from the dust is taken, And [from] the firm stone brass.

3 An end hath he set to darkness, And to all perfection he is searching, A stone of darkness and death-shade.

4 A stream hath broken out from a sojourner, Those forgotten of the foot, They were low, from man they wandered.

5 The earth! from it cometh forth bread, And its under-part is turned like fire.

6 A place of the sapphire [are] its stones, And it hath dust of gold.

7 A path--not known it hath a ravenous fowl, Nor scorched it hath an eye of the kite,

8 Nor trodden it have the sons of pride, Not passed over it hath the fierce lion.

9 Against the flint he sent forth his hand, He overturned from the root mountains.

10 Among rocks, brooks he hath cleaved, And every precious thing hath his eye seen.

11 From overflowing floods he hath bound, And the hidden thing bringeth out [to] light.

12 And the wisdom--whence is it found? And where [is] this, the place of understanding?

13 Man hath not known its arrangement, Nor is it found in the land of the living.

14 The deep hath said, `It [is] not in me,' And the sea hath said, `It is not with me.'

15 Gold is not given for it, Nor is silver weighed--its price.

16 It is not valued with pure gold of Ophir, With precious onyx and sapphire,

17 Not equal it do gold and crystal, Nor [is] its exchange a vessel of fine gold.

18 Corals and pearl are not remembered, The acquisition of wisdom [is] above rubies.

19 Not equal it doth the topaz of Cush, With pure gold it is not valued.

20 And the wisdom--whence doth it come? And where [is] this, the place of understanding?

21 It hath been hid from the eyes of all living. And from the fowl of the heavens It hath been hidden.

22 Destruction and death have said: `With our ears we have heard its fame.'

23 God hath understood its way, And He hath known its place.

24 For He to the ends of the earth doth look, Under the whole heavens He doth see,

25 To make for the wind a weight, And the waters He meted out in measure.

26 In His making for the rain a limit, And a way for the brightness of the voices,

27 Then He hath seen and declareth it, He hath prepared it, and also searched it out,

28 And He saith to man: --`Lo, fear of the Lord, that [is] wisdom, And to turn from evil [is] understanding.'

Job 29

1 And Job addeth to lift up his simile, and saith: --

2 Who doth make me as [in] months past, As [in] the days of God's preserving me?

3 In His causing His lamp to shine on my head, By His light I walk [through] darkness.

4 As I have been in days of my maturity, And the counsel of God upon my tent.

5 When yet the Mighty One [is] with me. Round about me--my young ones,

6 When washing my goings with butter, And the firm rock [is] with me rivulets of oil.

7 When I go out to the gate by the city, In a broad place I prepare my seat.

8 Seen me have youths, and they, been hidden, And the aged have risen--they stood up.

9 Princes have kept in words, And a hand they place on their mouth.

10 The voice of leaders hath been hidden, And their tongue to the palate hath cleaved.

11 For the ear heard, and declareth me happy, And the eye hath seen, and testifieth [to] me.

12 For I deliver the afflicted who is crying, And the fatherless who hath no helper.

13 The blessing of the perishing cometh on me, And the heart of the widow I cause to sing.

14 Righteousness I have put on, and it clotheth me, As a robe and a diadem my justice.

15 Eyes I have been to the blind, And feet to the lame [am] I.

16 A father I [am] to the needy, And the cause I have not known I search out.

17 And I break the jaw-teeth of the perverse, And from his teeth I cast away prey.

18 And I say, `With my nest I expire, And as the sand I multiply days.'

19 My root is open unto the waters, And dew doth lodge on my branch.

20 My honour [is] fresh with me, And my bow in my hand is renewed.

21 To me they have hearkened, Yea, they wait, and are silent for my counsel.

22 After my word they change not, And on them doth my speech drop,

23 And they wait as [for] rain for me, And their mouth they have opened wide [As] for the latter rain.

24 I laugh unto them--they give no credence, And the light of my face cause not to fall.

25 I choose their way, and sit head, And I dwell as a king in a troop, When mourners he doth comfort.

Job 30

1 And now, laughed at me, Have the younger in days than I, Whose fathers I have loathed to set With the dogs of my flock.

2 Also--the power of their hands, why [is it] to me? On them hath old age perished.

3 With want and with famine gloomy, Those fleeing to a dry place, Formerly a desolation and waste,

4 Those cropping mallows near a shrub, And broom-roots [is] their food.

5 From the midst they are cast out, (They shout against them as a thief),

6 In a frightful place of valleys to dwell, Holes of earth and clefts.

7 Among shrubs they do groan, Under nettles they are gathered together.

8 Sons of folly--even sons without name, They have been smitten from the land.

9 And now, their song I have been, And I am to them for a byword.

10 They have abominated me, They have kept far from me, And from before me have not spared to spit.

11 Because His cord He loosed and afflicteth me, And the bridle from before me, They have cast away.

12 On the right hand doth a brood arise, My feet they have cast away, And they raise up against me, Their paths of calamity.

13 They have broken down my path, By my calamity they profit, `He hath no helper.'

14 As a wide breach they come, Under the desolation have rolled themselves.

15 He hath turned against me terrors, It pursueth as the wind mine abundance, And as a thick cloud, Hath my safety passed away.

16 And now, in me my soul poureth itself out, Seize me do days of affliction.

17 At night my bone hath been pierced in me, And mine eyelids do not lie down.

18 By the abundance of power, Is my clothing changed, As the mouth of my coat it doth gird me.

19 Casting me into mire, And I am become like dust and ashes.

20 I cry unto Thee, And Thou dost not answer me, I have stood, and Thou dost consider me.

21 Thou art turned to be fierce to me, With the strength of Thy hand, Thou oppressest me.

22 Thou dost lift me up, On the wind Thou dost cause me to ride, And Thou meltest--Thou levellest me.

23 For I have known To death Thou dost bring me back, And [to] the house appointed for all living.

24 Surely not against the heap Doth He send forth the hand, Though in its ruin they have safety.

25 Did not I weep for him whose day is hard? Grieved hath my soul for the needy.

26 When good I expected, then cometh evil, And I wait for light, and darkness cometh.

27 My bowels have boiled, and have not ceased, Gone before me have days of affliction.

28 Mourning I have gone without the sun, I have risen, in an assembly I cry.

29 A brother I have been to dragons, And a companion to daughters of the ostrich.

30 My skin hath been black upon me, And my bone hath burned from heat,

31 And my harp doth become mourning, And my organ the sound of weeping.

Job 31

1 A covenant I made for mine eyes, And what--do I attend to a virgin?

2 And what [is] the portion of God from above? And the inheritance of the Mighty from the heights?

3 Is not calamity to the perverse? And strangeness to workers of iniquity?

4 Doth not He see my ways, And all my steps number?

5 If I have walked with vanity, And my foot doth hasten to deceit,

6 He doth weigh me in righteous balances, And God doth know my integrity.

7 If my step doth turn aside from the way, And after mine eyes hath my heart gone, And to my hands cleaved hath blemish,

8 Let me sow--and another eat, And my products let be rooted out.

9 If my heart hath been enticed by woman, And by the opening of my neighbour I laid wait,

10 Grind to another let my wife, And over her let others bend.

11 For it [is] a wicked thing, and a judicial iniquity;

12 For a fire it [is], to destruction it consumeth, And among all mine increase doth take root,

13 If I despise the cause of my man-servant, And of my handmaid, In their contending with me,

14 Then what do I do when God ariseth? And when He doth inspect, What do I answer Him?

15 Did not He that made me in the womb make him? Yea, prepare us in the womb doth One.

16 If I withhold from pleasure the poor, And the eyes of the widow do consume,

17 And I do eat my morsel by myself, And the orphan hath not eat of it,

18 (But from my youth He grew up with me as [with] a father, And from the belly of my mother I am led.)

19 If I see [any] perishing without clothing, And there is no covering to the needy,

20 If his loins have not blessed me, And from the fleece of my sheep He doth not warm himself,

21 If I have waved at the fatherless my hand, When I see in [him] the gate of my court,

22 My shoulder from its blade let fall, And mine arm from the bone be broken.

23 For a dread unto me [is] calamity [from] God, And because of His excellency I am not able.

24 If I have made gold my confidence, And to the pure gold have said, `My trust,'

25 If I rejoice because great [is] my wealth, And because abundance hath my hand found,

26 If I see the light when it shineth, And the precious moon walking,

27 And my heart is enticed in secret, And my hand doth kiss my mouth,

28 It also [is] a judicial iniquity, For I had lied to God above.

29 If I rejoice at the ruin of my hater, And stirred up myself when evil found him,

30 Yea, I have not suffered my mouth to sin, To ask with an oath his life.

31 If not--say ye, O men of my tent, `O that we had of his flesh, we are not satisfied.'

32 In the street doth not lodge a stranger, My doors to the traveller I open.

33 If I have covered as Adam my transgressions, To hide in my bosom mine iniquity,

34 Because I fear a great multitude, And the contempt of families doth affright me, Then I am silent, I go not out of the opening.

35 Who giveth to me a hearing? lo, my mark. The Mighty One doth answer me, And a bill hath mine adversary written.

36 If not--on my shoulder I take it up, I bind it a crown on myself.

37 The number of my steps I tell Him, As a leader I approach Him.

38 If against me my land doth cry out, And together its furrows weep,

39 If its strength I consumed without money, And the life of its possessors, I have caused to breathe out,

40 Instead of wheat let a thorn go forth, And instead of barley a useless weed! The words of

Job 32

1 And these three men cease from answering Job, for he [is] righteous in his own eyes,

2 and burn doth the anger of Elihu son of Barachel the Buzite, of the family of Ram; against

3 and against his three friends hath his anger burned, because that they have not found an answer, and condemn Job.

4 And Elihu hath waited earnestly beside Job with words, for they are older than he in days.

5 And Elihu seeth that there is no answer in the mouth of the three men, and his anger burneth.

6 And Elihu son of Barachel the Buzite answereth and saith: --Young I [am] in days, and ye [are] age Therefore I have feared, And am afraid of shewing you my opinion.

7 I said: Days do speak, And multitude of years teach wisdom.

8 Surely a spirit is in man, And the breath of the Mighty One Doth cause them to understand.

9 The multitude are not wise, Nor do the aged understand judgment.

10 Therefore I have said: Hearken to me, I do shew my opinion--even I.

11 Lo, I have waited for your words, I give ear unto your reasons, Till ye search out sayings.

12 And unto you I attend, And lo, there is no reasoner for Job, [Or] answerer of his sayings among you.

13 Lest ye say, We have found wisdom, God doth thrust him away, not man.

14 And he hath not set in array words for me, And with your sayings I do not answer him.

15 (They have broken down, They have not answered again, They removed from themselves words.

16 And I have waited, but they do not speak, For they have stood still, They have not answered any more.)

17 I answer, even I--my share, I shew my opinion--even I.

18 For I have been full of words, Distressed me hath the spirit of my breast,

19 Lo, my breast [is] as wine not opened, Like new bottles it is broken up.

20 I speak, and there is refreshment to me, I open my lips and answer.

21 Let me not, I pray you, accept the face of any, Nor unto man give flattering titles,

22 For I have not known to give flattering titles, In a little doth my Maker take me away.

Job 33

1 And yet, I pray thee, O Job, Hear my speech and [to] all my words give ear.

2 Lo, I pray thee, I have opened my mouth, My tongue hath spoken in the palate.

3 Of the uprightness of my heart [are] my sayings, And knowledge have my lips clearly spoken.

4 The Spirit of God hath made me, And the breath of the Mighty doth quicken me.

5 If thou art able--answer me, Set in array before me--station thyself.

6 Lo, I [am], according to thy word, for God, From the clay I--I also, have been formed.

7 Lo, my terror doth not frighten thee, And my burden on thee is not heavy.

8 Surely--thou hast said in mine ears, And the sounds of words I hear:

9 `Pure [am] I, without transgression, Innocent [am] I, and I have no iniquity.

10 Lo, occasions against me He doth find, He doth reckon me for an enemy to Him,

11 He doth put in the stocks my feet, He doth watch all my paths.'

12 Lo, [in] this thou hast not been righteous, I answer thee, that greater is God than man.

13 Wherefore against Him hast thou striven, When [for] all His matters He answereth not?

14 For once doth God speak, and twice, (He doth not behold it.)

15 In a dream--a vision of night, In the falling of deep sleep on men, In slumberings on a bed.

16 Then He uncovereth the ear of men, And for their instruction sealeth:

17 To turn aside man [from] doing, And pride from man He concealeth.

18 He keepeth back his soul from corruption, And his life from passing away by a dart.

19 And he hath been reproved With pain on his bed, And the strife of his bones [is] enduring.

20 And his life hath nauseated bread, And his soul desirable food.

21 His flesh is consumed from being seen, And high are his bones, they were not seen!

22 And draw near to the pit doth his soul, And his life to those causing death.

23 If there is by him a messenger, An interpreter--one of a thousand, To declare for man his uprightness:

24 Then He doth favour him and saith, `Ransom him from going down to the pit, I have found an atonement.'

25 Fresher [is] his flesh than a child's, He returneth to the days of his youth.

26 He maketh supplication unto God, And He accepteth him. And he seeth His face with shouting, And He returneth to man His righteousness.

27 He looketh on men, and saith, `I sinned, And uprightness I have perverted, And it hath not been profitable to me.

28 He hath ransomed my soul From going over into the pit, And my life on the light looketh.'

29 Lo, all these doth God work, Twice--thrice with man,

30 To bring back his soul from the pit, To be enlightened with the light of the living.

31 Attend, O Job, hearken to me, Keep silent, and I--I do speak.

32 If there are words--answer me, Speak, for I have a desire to justify thee.

33 If there are not--hearken thou to me, Keep silent, and I teach thee wisdom.

Job 34

1 And Elihu answereth and saith:

2 Hear, O wise men, my words, And, O knowing ones, give ear to me.

3 For the ear doth try words, And the palate tasteth to eat.

4 Judgment let us choose for ourselves, Let us know among ourselves what [is] good.

5 For Job hath said, `I have been righteous, And God hath turned aside my right,

6 Against my right do I lie? Mortal [is] mine arrow--without transgression.'

7 Who [is] a man like Job? He drinketh scoffing like water,

8 And he hath travelled for company With workers of iniquity, So as to go with men of wickedness.

9 For he hath said, `It doth not profit a man, When he delighteth himself with God.'

10 Therefore, O men of heart, hearken to me; Far be it from God to do wickedness, And [from] the Mighty to do perverseness:

11 For the work of man he repayeth to him, And according to the path of each He doth cause him to find.

12 Yea, truly, God doth not do wickedly, And the Mighty doth not pervert judgment.

13 Who hath inspected for Himself the earth? And who hath placed all the habitable world?

14 If He doth set on him His heart, His spirit and his breath unto Him He gathereth.

15 Expire doth all flesh together, And man to dust returneth.

16 And if [there is] understanding, hear this, Give ear to the voice of my words.

17 Yea, doth one hating justice govern? Or the Most Just dost thou condemn?

18 Who hath said to a king--`Worthless,' Unto princes--`Wicked?'

19 That hath not accepted the person of princes, Nor hath known the rich before the poor, For a work of His hands [are] all of them.

20 [In] a moment they die, and at midnight Shake do people, and they pass away, And they remove the mighty without hand.

21 For His eyes [are] on the ways of each, And all his steps He doth see.

22 There is no darkness nor death-shade, For workers of iniquity to be hidden there;

23 For He doth not suffer man any more, To go unto God in judgment,

24 He breaketh the mighty--no searching! And He appointeth others in their stead.

25 Therefore He knoweth their works, And He hath overturned by night, And they are bruised.

26 As wicked He hath stricken them, In the place of beholders.

27 Because that against right They have turned aside from after Him, And none of His ways have considered wisely,

28 To cause to come in unto Him The cry of the poor, And the cry of the afflicted He heareth.

29 And He giveth rest, and who maketh wrong? And hideth the face, and who beholdeth it? And in reference to a nation and to a man, [It is] the same.

30 From the reigning of a profane man, From the snares of a people;

31 For unto God hath any said: `I have taken away, I do not corruptly,

32 Besides [that which] I see, shew Thou me, If iniquity I have done--I do not add?'

33 By thee doth He recompense, That thou hast refused--That thou dost choose, and not I? And what thou hast known, speak.

34 Let men of heart say to me, And a wise man is hearkening to me.

35 Job--not with knowledge doth he speak, And his words [are] not with wisdom.

36 My Father! let Job be tried--unto victory, Because of answers for men of iniquity,

37 For he doth add to his sin, Transgression among us he vomiteth, And multiplieth his sayings to God.

Job 35

1 And Elihu answereth and saith: --

2 This hast thou reckoned for judgment: Thou hast said--`My righteousness [is] more than God's?'

3 For thou sayest, `What doth it profit Thee! What do I profit from my sin?'

4 I return thee words, and thy friends with thee,

5 Behold attentively the heavens--and see, And behold the clouds, They have been higher than thou.

6 If thou hast sinned, what dost thou against Him? And thy transgressions have been multiplied, What dost thou to Him?

7 If thou hast been righteous, What dost thou give to Him? Or what from thy hand doth He receive?

8 For a man like thyself [is] thy wickedness, And for a son of man thy righteousness.

9 Because of the multitude of oppressions They cause to cry out, They cry because of the arm of the mighty.

10 And none said, `Where [is] God my maker? Giving songs in the night,

11 Teaching us more than the beasts of the earth, Yea, than the fowl of the heavens He maketh us wiser.'

12 There they cry, and He doth not answer, Because of the pride of evil doers.

13 Surely vanity God doth not hear, And the Mighty doth not behold it.

14 Yea, though thou sayest thou dost not behold Him, Judgment [is] before Him, and stay for Him.

15 And, now, because there is not, He hath appointed His anger, And He hath not known in great extremity.

16 And Job [with] vanity doth open his mouth, Without knowledge words he multiplieth.

Job 36

1 And Elihu addeth and saith: --

2 Honour me a little, and I shew thee, That yet for God [are] words.

3 I lift up my knowledge from afar, And to my Maker I ascribe righteousness.

4 For, truly, my words [are] not false, The perfect in knowledge [is] with thee.

5 Lo, God [is] mighty, and despiseth not, Mighty [in] power [and] heart.

6 He reviveth not the wicked, And the judgment of the poor appointeth;

7 He withdraweth not from the righteous His eyes, And [from] kings on the throne, And causeth them to sit for ever, and they are high,

8 And if prisoners in fetters They are captured with cords of affliction,

9 Then He declareth to them their work, And their transgressions, Because they have become mighty,

10 And He uncovereth their ear for instruction, And saith that they turn back from iniquity.

11 If they do hear and serve, They complete their days in good, And their years in pleasantness.

12 And if they do not hearken, By the dart they pass away, And expire without knowledge.

13 And the profane in heart set the face, They cry not when He hath bound them.

14 Their soul dieth in youth, And their life among the defiled.

15 He draweth out the afflicted in his affliction, And uncovereth in oppression their ear.

16 And also He moved thee from a strait place, [To] a broad place--no straitness under it, And the sitting beyond of thy table Hath been full of fatness.

17 And the judgment of the wicked thou hast fulfilled, Judgment and justice are upheld-- because of fury,

18 Lest He move thee with a stroke, And the abundance of an atonement turn thee not aside.

19 Doth He value thy riches? He hath gold, and all the forces of power.

20 Desire not the night, For the going up of peoples in their stead.

21 Take heed--do not turn unto iniquity, For on this thou hast fixed Rather than [on] affliction.

22 Lo, God doth sit on high by His power, Who [is] like Him--a teacher?

23 Who hath appointed unto Him his way? And who said, `Thou hast done iniquity?'

24 Remember that thou magnify His work That men have beheld.

25 All men have looked on it, Man looketh attentively from afar.

26 Lo, God [is] high, And we know not the number of His years, Yea, there [is] no searching.

27 When He doth diminish droppings of the waters, They refine rain according to its vapour,

28 Which clouds do drop, They distil on man abundantly.

29 Yea, doth [any] understand The spreadings out of a cloud? The noises of His tabernacle?

30 Lo, He hath spread over it His light, And the roots of the sea He hath covered,

31 For by them He doth judge peoples, He giveth food in abundance.

32 By two palms He hath covered the light, And layeth a charge over it in meeting,

33 He sheweth by it [to] his friend substance, Anger against perversity.

Job 37

1 Also, at this my heart trembleth, And it moveth from its place.

2 Hearken diligently to the trembling of His voice, Yea, the sound from His mouth goeth forth.

3 Under the whole heavens He directeth it, And its light [is] over the skirts of the earth.

4 After it roar doth a voice--He thundereth with the voice of His excellency, And He doth not hold them back, When His voice is heard.

5 God thundereth with His voice wonderfully, Doing great things and we know not.

6 For to snow He saith, `Be [on] the earth.' And the small rain and great rain of His power.

7 Into the hand of every man he sealeth, For the knowledge by all men of His work.

8 And enter doth the beast into covert, And in its habitations it doth continue.

9 From the inner chamber cometh a hurricane, And from scatterings winds--cold,

10 From the breath of God is frost given, And the breadth of waters is straitened,

11 Yea, by filling He doth press out a cloud, Scatter a cloud doth His light.

12 And it is turning itself round by His counsels, For their doing all He commandeth them, On the face of the habitable earth.

13 Whether for a rod, or for His land, Or for kindness--He doth cause it to come.

14 Hear this, O Job, Stand and consider the wonders of God.

15 Dost thou know when God doth place them, And caused to shine the light of His cloud?

16 Dost thou know the balancings of a cloud? The wonders of the Perfect in knowledge?

17 How thy garments [are] warm, In the quieting of the earth from the south?

18 Thou hast made an expanse with Him For the clouds--strong as a hard mirror!

19 Let us know what we say to Him, We set not in array because of darkness.

20 Is it declared to Him that I speak? If a man hath spoken, surely he is swallowed up.

21 And now, they have not seen the light, Bright it [is] in the clouds, And the wind hath passed by and cleanseth them.

22 From the golden north it cometh, Beside God [is] fearful honour.

23 The Mighty! we have not found Him out, High in power and judgment, He doth not answer! And abundant in righteousness,

24 Therefore do men fear Him, He seeth not any of the wise of heart.

Job 38

1 And Jehovah answereth Job out of the whirlwind, and saith: --

2 Who [is] this--darkening counsel, By words without knowledge?

3 Gird, I pray thee, as a man, thy loins, And I ask thee, and cause thou Me to know.

4 Where wast thou when I founded earth? Declare, if thou hast known understanding.

5 Who placed its measures--if thou knowest? Or who hath stretched out upon it a line?

6 On what have its sockets been sunk? Or who hath cast its corner-stone?

7 In the singing together of stars of morning, And all sons of God shout for joy,

8 And He shutteth up with doors the sea, In its coming forth, from the womb it goeth out.

9 In My making a cloud its clothing, And thick darkness its swaddling band,

10 And I measure over it My statute, And place bar and doors,

11 And say, `Hitherto come thou, and add not, And a command is placed On the pride of thy billows.'

12 Hast thou commanded morning since thy days? Causest thou the dawn to know its place?

13 To take hold on the skirts of the earth, And the wicked are shaken out of it,

14 It turneth itself as clay of a seal And they station themselves as clothed.

15 And withheld from the wicked is their light, And the arm lifted up is broken.

16 Hast thou come in to springs of the sea? And in searching the deep Hast thou walked up and down?

17 Revealed to thee were the gates of death? And the gates of death-shade dost thou see?

18 Thou hast understanding, Even unto the broad places of earth! Declare--if thou hast known it all.

19 Where [is] this--the way light dwelleth? And darkness, where [is] this--its place?

20 That thou dost take it unto its boundary, And that thou dost understand The paths of its house.

21 Thou hast known--for then thou art born And the number of thy days [are] many!

22 Hast thou come in unto the treasure of snow? Yea, the treasures of hail dost thou see?

23 That I have kept back for a time of distress, For a day of conflict and battle.

24 Where [is] this, the way light is apportioned? It scattereth an east wind over the earth.

25 Who hath divided for the flood a conduit? And a way for the lightning of the voices?

26 To cause [it] to rain on a land--no man, A wilderness--no man in it.

27 To satisfy a desolate and waste place, And to cause to shoot up The produce of the tender grass?

28 Hath the rain a father? Or who hath begotten the drops of dew?

29 From whose belly came forth the ice? And the hoar-frost of the heavens, Who hath begotten it?

30 As a stone waters are hidden, And the face of the deep is captured.

31 Dost thou bind sweet influences of Kimah? Or the attractions of Kesil dost thou open?

32 Dost thou bring out Mazzaroth in its season? And Aysh for her sons dost thou comfort?

33 Hast thou known the statutes of heaven? Or dost thou appoint Its dominion in the earth?

34 Dost thou lift up to the cloud thy voice, And abundance of water doth cover thee?

35 Dost thou send out lightnings, and they go And say unto thee, `Behold us?'

36 Who hath put in the inward parts wisdom? Or who hath given To the covered part understanding?

37 Who doth number the clouds by wisdom? And the bottles of the heavens, Who doth cause to lie down,

38 In the hardening of dust into hardness, And clods cleave together?

39 Dost thou hunt for a lion prey? And the desire of young lions fulfil?

40 When they bow down in dens--Abide in a thicket for a covert?

41 Who doth prepare for a raven his provision, When his young ones cry unto God? They wander without food.

Job 39

1 Hast thou known the time of The bearing of the wild goats of the rock? The bringing forth of hinds thou dost mark!

2 Thou dost number the months they fulfil? And thou hast known the time of their bringing forth!

3 They bow down, Their young ones they bring forth safely, Their pangs they cast forth.

4 Safe are their young ones, They grow up in the field, they have gone out, And have not returned to them.

5 Who hath sent forth the wild ass free? Yea, the bands of the wild ass who opened?

6 Whose house I have made the wilderness, And his dwellings the barren land,

7 He doth laugh at the multitude of a city, The cries of an exactor he heareth not.

8 The range of mountains [is] his pasture, And after every green thing he seeketh.

9 Is a Reem willing to serve thee? Doth he lodge by thy crib?

10 Dost thou bind a Reem in a furrow [with] his thick band? Doth he harrow valleys after thee?

11 Dost thou trust in him because great [is] his power? And dost thou leave unto him thy labour?

12 Dost thou trust in him That he doth bring back thy seed? And [to] thy threshing-floor doth gather [it]?

13 The wing of the rattling ones exulteth, Whether the pinion of the ostrich or hawk.

14 For she leaveth on the earth her eggs, And on the dust she doth warm them,

15 And she forgetteth that a foot may press it, And a beast of the field tread it down.

16 Her young ones it hath hardened without her, In vain [is] her labour without fear.

17 For God hath caused her to forget wisdom, And He hath not given a portion To her in understanding:

18 At the time on high she lifteth herself up, She laugheth at the horse and at his rider.

19 Dost thou give to the horse might? Dost thou clothe his neck [with] a mane?

20 Dost thou cause him to rush as a locust? The majesty of his snorting [is] terrible.

21 They dig in a valley, and he rejoiceth in power, He goeth forth to meet the armour.

22 He laugheth at fear, and is not affrighted, And he turneth not back from the face of the sword.

23 Against him rattle doth quiver, The flame of a spear, and a halbert.

24 With trembling and rage he swalloweth the ground, And remaineth not stedfast Because of the sound of a trumpet.

25 Among the trumpets he saith, Aha, And from afar he doth smell battle, Roaring of princes and shouting.

26 By thine understanding flieth a hawk? Spreadeth he his wings to the south?

27 At thy command goeth an eagle up high? Or lifteth he up his nest?

28 A rock he doth inhabit, Yea, he lodgeth on the tooth of a rock, and fortress.

29 From thence he hath sought food, To a far off place his eyes look attentively,

30 And his brood gulp up blood, And where the pierced [are] --there [is] he!

Job 40

1 And Jehovah doth answer Job, and saith: --

2 Is the striver with the Mighty instructed? The reprover of God, let him answer it.

3 And Job answereth Jehovah, and saith: --

4 Lo, I have been vile, What do I return to Thee? My hand I have placed on my mouth.

5 Once I have spoken, and I answer not, And twice, and I add not.

6 And Jehovah answereth Job out of the whirlwind, and saith: --

7 Gird, I pray thee, as a man, thy loins, I ask thee, and cause thou Me to know.

8 Dost thou also make void My judgment? Dost thou condemn Me, That thou mayest be righteous?

9 And an arm like God hast thou? And with a voice like Him dost thou thunder?

10 Put on, I pray thee, excellency and loftiness, Yea, honour and beauty put on.

11 Scatter abroad the wrath of thine anger, And see every proud one, and make him low.

12 See every proud one--humble him, And tread down the wicked in their place.

13 Hide them in the dust together, Their faces bind in secret.

14 And even I--I do praise thee, For thy right hand giveth salvation to thee.

15 Lo, I pray thee, Behemoth, that I made with thee: Grass as an ox he eateth.

16 Lo, I pray thee, his power [is] in his loins, And his strength in the muscles of his belly.

17 He doth bend his tail as a cedar, The sinews of his thighs are wrapped together,

18 His bones [are] tubes of brass, His bones [are] as a bar of iron.

19 He [is] a beginning of the ways of God, His Maker bringeth nigh his sword;

20 For food do mountains bear for him, And all the beasts of the field play there.

21 Under shades he lieth down, In a secret place of reed and mire.

22 Cover him do shades, [with] their shadow, Cover him do willows of the brook.

23 Lo, a flood oppresseth--he doth not haste, He is confident though Jordan Doth come forth unto his mouth.

24 Before his eyes doth [one] take him, With snares doth [one] pierce the nose?

Job 41

1 Dost thou draw leviathan with an angle? And with a rope thou lettest down--his tongue?

2 Dost thou put a reed in his nose? And with a thorn pierce his jaw?

3 Doth he multiply unto thee supplications? Doth he speak unto thee tender things?

4 Doth he make a covenant with thee? Dost thou take him for a servant age-during?

5 Dost thou play with him as a bird? And dost thou bind him for thy damsels?

6 (Feast upon him do companions, They divide him among the merchants!)

7 Dost thou fill with barbed irons his skin? And with fish-spears his head?

8 Place on him thy hand, Remember the battle--do not add!

9 Lo, the hope of him is found a liar, Also at his appearance is not one cast down?

10 None so fierce that he doth awake him, And who [is] he before Me stationeth himself?

11 Who hath brought before Me and I repay? Under the whole heavens it [is] mine.

12 I do not keep silent concerning his parts, And the matter of might, And the grace of his arrangement.

13 Who hath uncovered the face of his clothing? Within his double bridle who doth enter?

14 The doors of his face who hath opened? Round about his teeth [are] terrible.

15 A pride--strong ones of shields, Shut up--a close seal.

16 One unto another they draw nigh, And air doth not enter between them.

17 One unto another they adhere, They stick together and are not separated.

18 His sneezings cause light to shine, And his eyes [are] as the eyelids of the dawn.

19 Out of his mouth do flames go, sparks of fire escape.

20 Out of his nostrils goeth forth smoke, As a blown pot and reeds.

21 His breath setteth coals on fire, And a flame from his mouth goeth forth.

22 In his neck lodge doth strength, And before him doth grief exult.

23 The flakes of his flesh have adhered--Firm upon him--it is not moved.

24 His heart [is] firm as a stone, Yea, firm as the lower piece.

25 From his rising are the mighty afraid, From breakings they keep themselves free.

26 The sword of his overtaker standeth not, Spear--dart--and lance.

27 He reckoneth iron as straw, brass as rotten wood.

28 The son of the bow doth not cause him to flee, Turned by him into stubble are stones of the sling.

29 As stubble have darts been reckoned, And he laugheth at the shaking of a javelin.

30 Under him [are] sharp points of clay, He spreadeth gold on the mire.

31 He causeth to boil as a pot the deep, The sea he maketh as a pot of ointment.

32 After him he causeth a path to shine, One thinketh the deep to be hoary.

33 There is not on the earth his like, That is made without terror.

34 Every high thing he doth see, He [is] king over all sons of pride.

Job 42

1 And Job answereth Jehovah and saith: --

2 Thou hast known that [for] all things Thou art able, And not withheld from Thee is [any] device:

3 `Who [is] this, hiding counsel without knowledge?' Therefore, I have declared, and understand not, Too wonderful for me, and I know not.

4 `Hear, I pray thee, and I--I do speak, I ask thee, and cause thou me to know.'

5 By the hearing of the ear I heard Thee, And now mine eye hath seen Thee.

6 Therefore do I loathe [it], And I have repented on dust and ashes.

7 And it cometh to pass after Jehovah's speaking these words unto Job, that Jehovah saith unto Eliphaz the Temanite, `Burned hath Mine anger against thee, and against thy two friends, because ye have not spoken concerning Me rightly, like My servant Job.

8 And now, take to you seven bullocks and seven rams, and go ye unto My servant Job, and ye have caused a burnt-offering to ascend for you; and Job My servant doth pray for you, for surely his face I accept, so as not to do with you folly, becauseye have not spoken concerning Me rightly, like My servant Job.

9 And they go--Eliphaz the Temanite, and Bildad the Shuhite, Zophar the Naamathite--and do as Jehovah hath spoken unto them; and Jehovah doth accept the face of Job.

10 And Jehovah hath turned [to] the captivity of Job in his praying for his friends, and Jehovah doth add [to] all that Job hath--to double.

11 And come unto him do all his brethren, and all his sisters, and all his former acquaintances, and they eat bread with him in his house, and bemoan him, and comfort him concerning all the evil that Jehovah had brought upon him, and they gave to him each one kesitah, and each one ring of gold.

12 And Jehovah hath blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning, and he hath fourteen thousand of a flock, and six thousand camels, and a thousand pairs of oxen, and a thousand she-asses.

13 And he hath seven sons and three daughters;

14 and he calleth the name of the one Jemima, and the name of the second Kezia, and the name of the third Keren-Happuch.

15 And there have not been found women fair as the daughters of Job in all the land, and their father doth give to them an inheritance in the midst of their brethren.

16 And Job liveth after this a hundred and forty years, and seeth his sons, and his sons' sons, four generations;

17 and Job dieth, aged and satisfied [with] days.

Psalms 5

1 To the Overseer, `Concerning the Inheritances.' --A Psalm of David. My sayings hear, O Jehovah, Consider my meditation.

2 Be attentive to the voice of my cry, My king and my God, For unto Thee I pray habitually.

3 Jehovah, [at] morning Thou hearest my voice, [At] morning I set in array for Thee, And I look out.

4 For not a God desiring wickedness [art] Thou, Evil inhabiteth Thee not.

5 The boastful station not themselves before Thine eyes: Thou hast hated all working iniquity.

6 Thou destroyest those speaking lies, A man of blood and deceit Jehovah doth abominate.

7 And I, in the abundance of Thy kindness, I enter Thy house, I bow myself toward Thy holy temple in Thy fear.

8 O Jehovah, lead me in Thy righteousness, Because of those observing me, Make straight before me Thy way,

9 For there is no stability in their mouth. Their heart [is] mischiefs, An open grave [is] their throat, Their tongue they make smooth.

10 Declare them guilty, O God, Let them fall from their own counsels, In the abundance of their transgressions Drive them away, Because they have rebelled against Thee.

11 And rejoice do all trusting in Thee, To the age they sing, and Thou coverest them over, And those loving Thy name exult in Thee.

12 For Thou blessest the righteous, O Jehovah, As a buckler with favour dost compass him!

Psalms 7

1 `The Erring One,' by David, that he sung to Jehovah concerning the words of Cush a Benjamite. O Jehovah, my God, in Thee I have trusted, Save me from all my pursuers, and deliver me.

2 Lest he tear as a lion my soul, Rending, and there is no deliverer.

3 O Jehovah, my God, if I have done this, If there is iniquity in my hands,

4 If I have done my well-wisher evil, And draw mine adversary without cause,

5 An enemy pursueth my soul, and overtaketh, And treadeth down to the earth my life, And my honour placeth in the dust. Selah.

6 Rise, O Jehovah, in Thine anger, Be lifted up at the wrath of mine adversaries, And awake Thou for me: Judgment Thou hast commanded:

7 And a company of peoples compass Thee, And over it on high turn Thou back,

8 Jehovah doth judge the peoples; Judge me, O Jehovah, According to my righteousness, And according to mine integrity on me,

9 Let, I pray Thee be ended the evil of the wicked, And establish Thou the righteous, And a trier of hearts and reins is the righteous God.

10 My shield [is] on God, Saviour of the upright in heart!

11 God [is] a righteous judge, And He is not angry at all times.

12 If [one] turn not, His sword he sharpeneth, His bow he hath trodden--He prepareth it,

13 Yea, for him He hath prepared Instruments of death, His arrows for burning pursuers He maketh.

14 Lo, he travaileth [with] iniquity, And he hath conceived perverseness, And hath brought forth falsehood.

15 A pit he hath prepared, and he diggeth it, And he falleth into a ditch he maketh.

16 Return doth his perverseness on his head, And on his crown his violence cometh down.

17 I thank Jehovah, According to His righteousness, And praise the name of Jehovah Most High!

Psalms 9

1 To the Overseer, `On the Death of Labben.' --A Psalm of David. I confess, O Jehovah, with all my heart, I recount all Thy wonders,

2 I rejoice and exult in Thee, I praise Thy Name, O Most High.

3 In mine enemies turning backward, they stumble and perish from Thy face.

4 For Thou hast done my judgment and my right. Thou hast sat on a throne, A judge of righteousness.

5 Thou hast rebuked nations, Thou hast destroyed the wicked, Their name Thou hast blotted out to the age and for ever.

6 O thou Enemy, Finished have been destructions for ever, As to cities thou hast plucked up, Perished hath their memorial with them.

7 And Jehovah to the age abideth, He is preparing for judgment His throne.

8 And He judgeth the world in righteousness, He judgeth the peoples in uprightness.

9 And Jehovah is a tower for the bruised, A tower for times of adversity.

10 They trust in Thee who do know Thy name, For Thou hast not forsaken Those seeking Thee, O Jehovah.

11 Sing ye praise to Jehovah, inhabiting Zion, Declare ye among the peoples His acts,

12 For He who is seeking for blood Them hath remembered, He hath not forgotten the cry of the afflicted.

13 Favour me, O Jehovah, See mine affliction by those hating me, Thou who liftest me up from the gates of death,

14 So that I recount all Thy praise, In the gates of the daughter of Zion. I rejoice on Thy salvation.

15 Sunk have nations in a pit they made, In a net that they hid hath their foot been captured.

16 Jehovah hath been known, Judgment He hath done, By a work of his hands Hath the wicked been snared. Meditation. Selah.

17 The wicked do turn back to Sheol, All nations forgetting God.

18 For not for ever is the needy forgotten, The hope of the humble lost to the age.

19 Rise, O Jehovah, let not man be strong, Let nations be judged before Thy face.

20 Appoint, O Jehovah, a director to them, Let nations know they [are] men! Selah.

Psalms 10

1 Why, Jehovah, dost Thou stand at a distance? Thou dost hide in times of adversity,

2 Through the pride of the wicked, Is the poor inflamed, They are caught in devices that they devised.

3 Because the wicked hath boasted Of the desire of his soul, And a dishonest gainer he hath blessed, He hath despised Jehovah.

4 The wicked according to the height of his face, inquireth not. `God is not!' [are] all his devices.

5 Pain do his ways at all times, On high [are] Thy judgments before him, All his adversaries--he puffeth at them.

6 He hath said in his heart, `I am not moved,' To generation and generation not in evil.

7 Of oaths his mouth is full, And deceits, and fraud: Under his tongue [is] perverseness and iniquity,

8 He doth sit in an ambush of the villages, In secret places he doth slay the innocent. His eyes for the afflicted watch secretly,

9 He lieth in wait in a secret place, as a lion in a covert. He lieth in wait to catch the poor, He catcheth the poor, drawing him into his net.

10 He is bruised--he boweth down, Fallen by his mighty ones hath the afflicted.

11 He said in his heart, `God hath forgotten, He hath hid His face, He hath never seen.'

12 Arise, O Jehovah! O God, lift up Thy hand! Forget not the humble.

13 Wherefore hath the wicked despised God? He hath said in his heart, `It is not required.'

14 Thou hast seen, For Thou perverseness and anger beholdest; By giving into Thy hand, On Thee doth the afflicted leave [it], Of the fatherless Thou hast been an helper.

15 Break the arm of the wicked and the evil, Seek out his wickedness, find none;

16 Jehovah [is] king to the age, and for ever, The nations have perished out of His land!

17 The desire of the humble Thou hast heard, O Jehovah. Thou preparest their heart; Thou causest Thine ear to attend,

18 To judge the fatherless and bruised: He addeth no more to oppress--man of the earth!

Psalms 16

1 A Secret Treasure of David. Preserve me, O God, for I did trust in Thee.

2 Thou hast said to Jehovah, `My Lord Thou [art];' My good [is] not for thine own sake;

3 For the holy ones who [are] in the land, And the honourable, all my delight [is] in them.

4 Multiplied are their griefs, [Who] have hastened backward; I pour not out their libations of blood, Nor do I take up their names on my lips.

5 Jehovah [is] the portion of my share, and of my cup, Thou--Thou dost uphold my lot.

6 Lines have fallen to me in pleasant places, Yea, a beauteous inheritance [is] for me.

7 I bless Jehovah who hath counselled me; Also [in] the nights my reins instruct me.

8 I did place Jehovah before me continually, Because--at my right hand I am not moved.

9 Therefore hath my heart been glad, And my honour doth rejoice, Also my flesh dwelleth confidently:

10 For Thou dost not leave my soul to Sheol, Nor givest thy saintly one to see corruption.

11 Thou causest me to know the path of life; Fulness of joys [is] with Thy presence, Pleasant things by Thy right hand for ever!

Psalms 17

1 A Prayer of David. Hear, O Jehovah, righteousness, attend my cry, Give ear [to] my prayer, without lips of deceit.

2 From before thee my judgment doth go out; Thine eyes do see uprightly.

3 Thou hast proved my heart, Thou hast inspected by night, Thou hast tried me, Thou findest nothing; My thoughts pass not over my mouth.

4 As to doings of man, Through a word of Thy lips I have observed The paths of a destroyer;

5 To uphold my goings in Thy paths, My steps have not slidden.

6 I--I called Thee, for Thou dost answer me, O God, incline Thine ear to me, hear my speech.

7 Separate wonderfully Thy kindness, O Saviour of the confiding, By Thy right hand, from withstanders.

8 Keep me as the apple, the daughter of the eye; In shadow of Thy wings thou dost hide me.

9 From the face of the wicked who spoiled me. Mine enemies in soul go round against me.

10 Their fat they have closed up, Their mouths have spoken with pride:

11 `Our steps now have compassed [him];' Their eyes they set to turn aside in the land.

12 His likeness as a lion desirous to tear, As a young lion dwelling in secret places.

13 Arise, O Jehovah, go before his face, Cause him to bend. Deliver my soul from the wicked, Thy sword,

14 From men, Thy hand, O Jehovah, From men of the world, their portion [is] in life, And [with] Thy hidden things Thou fillest their belly, They are satisfied [with] sons; And have left their abundance to their sucklings.

15 I--in righteousness, I see Thy face; I am satisfied, in awaking, [with] Thy form!

Psalms 18

1 To the Overseer. --By a servant of Jehovah, by David, who hath spoken to Jehovah the words of this song in the day Jehovah delivered him from the hand of all his enemies, and from the hand of Saul, and he saith: --I love Thee, O Jehovah, my strength.

2 Jehovah [is] my rock, and my bulwark, And my deliverer, My God [is] my rock, I trust in Him: My shield, and a horn of my salvation, My high tower.

3 The `Praised One' I call Jehovah, And from my enemies I am saved.

4 Compassed me have cords of death, And streams of the worthless make me afraid.

5 Cords of Sheol have surrounded me, Before me have been snares of death.

6 In mine adversity I call Jehovah, And unto my God I cry. He heareth from His temple my voice, And My cry before Him cometh into His ears.

7 And shake and tremble doth the earth, And foundations of hills are troubled, And they shake--because He hath wrath.

8 Gone up hath smoke by His nostrils, And fire from His mouth consumeth, Coals have been kindled by it.

9 And He inclineth the heavens, and cometh down, And thick darkness [is] under His feet.

10 And He rideth on a cherub, and doth fly, And He flieth on wings of wind.

11 He maketh darkness His secret place, Round about Him His tabernacle, Darkness of waters, thick clouds of the skies.

12 From the brightness over-against Him His thick clouds have passed on, Hail and coals of fire.

13 And thunder in the heavens doth Jehovah, And the Most High giveth forth His voice, Hail and coals of fire.

14 And He sendeth His arrows and scattereth them, And much lightning, and crusheth them.

15 And seen are the streams of waters, And revealed are foundations of the earth. From Thy rebuke, O Jehovah, From the breath of the spirit of Thine anger.

16 He sendeth from above--He taketh me, He draweth me out of many waters.

17 He delivereth me from my strong enemy, And from those hating me, For they have been stronger than I.

18 They go before me in a day of my calamity And Jehovah is for a support to me.

19 And He bringeth me forth to a large place, He draweth me out, because He delighted in me.

20 Jehovah doth recompense me According to my righteousness, According to the cleanness of my hands, He doth return to me.

21 For I have kept the ways of Jehovah, And have not done wickedly against my God.

22 For all His judgments [are] before me, And His statutes I turn not from me.

23 And I am perfect with him, And I keep myself from mine iniquity.

24 And Jehovah doth return to me, According to my righteousness, According to the cleanness of my hands, Over-against his eyes.

25 With the kind Thou showest Thyself kind, With a perfect man showest Thyself perfect.

26 With the pure Thou showest Thyself pure, And with the perverse showest Thyself a wrestler,

27 For Thou a poor people savest, And the eyes of the high causest to fall.

28 For Thou--Thou lightest my lamp, Jehovah my God enlighteneth my darkness.

29 For by Thee I run--a troop! And by my God I leap a wall.

30 God! perfect [is] His way, The saying of Jehovah is tried, A shield [is] He to all those trusting in Him.

31 For who [is] God besides Jehovah? And who [is] a rock save our God?

32 God! who is girding me [with] strength, And He maketh perfect my way.

33 Making my feet like hinds, And on my high places causeth me to stand.

34 Teaching my hands for battle, And a bow of brass was brought down by my arms.

35 And Thou givest to me the shield of Thy salvation, And Thy right hand doth support me, And Thy lowliness maketh me great.

36 Thou enlargest my step under me, And mine ankles have not slidden.

37 I pursue mine enemies, and overtake them, And turn back not till they are consumed.

38 I smite them, and they are not able to rise, They fall under my feet,

39 And Thou girdest me [with] strength for battle, Causest my withstanders to bow under me.

40 As to mine enemies--Thou hast given to me the neck, As to those hating me--I cut them off.

41 They cry, and there is no saviour, On Jehovah, and He doth not answer them.

42 And I beat them as dust before wind, As mire of the streets I empty them out.

43 Thou dost deliver me From the strivings of the people, Thou placest me for a head of nations, A people I have not known do serve me.

44 At the hearing of the ear they hearken to me, Sons of a stranger feign obedience to me,

45 Sons of a stranger fade away, And are slain out of their close places.

46 Jehovah liveth--and blessed [is] my rock, And exalted is the God of my salvation.

47 God--who is giving vengeance to me, And He subdueth peoples under me,

48 My deliverer from mine enemies, Above my withstanders Thou raisest me, From a man of violence dost deliver me.

49 Therefore I confess Thee among nations, O Jehovah, And to Thy name I sing praise,

50 Magnifying the salvation of His king, And doing kindness to His anointed, To David, and to his seed--unto the age!

Psalms 19

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. The heavens [are] recounting the honour of God, And the work of His hands The expanse [is] declaring.

2 Day to day uttereth speech, And night to night sheweth knowledge.

3 There is no speech, and there are no words. Their voice hath not been heard.

4 Into all the earth hath their line gone forth, And to the end of the world their sayings, For the sun He placed a tent in them,

5 And he, as a bridegroom, goeth out from his covering, He rejoiceth as a mighty one To run the path.

6 From the end of the heavens [is] his going out, And his revolution [is] unto their ends, And nothing is hid from his heat.

7 The law of Jehovah [is] perfect, refreshing the soul, The testimonies of Jehovah [are] stedfast, Making wise the simple,

8 The precepts of Jehovah [are] upright, Rejoicing the heart, The command of Jehovah [is] pure, enlightening the eyes,

9 The fear of Jehovah [is] clean, standing to the age, The judgments of Jehovah [are] true, They have been righteous--together.

10 They are more desirable than gold, Yea, than much fine gold; and sweeter than honey, Even liquid honey of the comb.

11 Also--Thy servant is warned by them, `In keeping them [is] a great reward.'

12 Errors! who doth understand? From hidden ones declare me innocent,

13 Also--from presumptuous ones keep back Thy servant, Let them not rule over me, Then am I perfect, And declared innocent of much transgression,

14 Let the sayings of my mouth, And the meditation of my heart, Be for a pleasing thing before Thee, O Jehovah, my rock, and my redeemer!

Psalms 21

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. Jehovah, in Thy strength is the king joyful, In Thy salvation how greatly he rejoiceth.

2 The desire of his heart Thou gavest to him, And the request of his lips Thou hast not withheld. Selah.

3 For Thou puttest before him blessings of goodness, Thou settest on his head a crown of fine gold.

4 Life he hath asked from Thee, Thou hast given to him--length of days, Age-during-- and for ever.

5 Great [is] his honour in Thy salvation, Honour and majesty Thou placest on him.

6 For Thou makest him blessings for ever, Thou dost cause him to rejoice with joy, By Thy countenance.

7 For the king is trusting in Jehovah, And in the kindness of the Most High He is not moved.

8 Thy hand cometh to all Thine enemies, Thy right hand doth find Thy haters.

9 Thou makest them as a furnace of fire, At the time of Thy presence. Jehovah in His anger doth swallow them, And fire doth devour them.

10 Their fruit from earth Thou destroyest, And their seed from the sons of men.

11 For they stretched out against Thee evil, They devised a wicked device, they prevail not,

12 For Thou makest them a butt, When Thy strings Thou preparest against their faces.

13 Be Thou exalted, O Jehovah in, Thy strength, We sing and we praise Thy might!

Psalms 22

1 To the Overseer, on `The Hind of the Morning.' --A Psalm of David. My God, my God, why hast Thou forsaken me? Far from my salvation, The words of my roaring?

2 My God, I call by day, and Thou answerest not, And by night, and there is no silence to me.

3 And Thou [art] holy, Sitting--the Praise of Israel.

4 In Thee did our fathers trust--they trusted, And Thou dost deliver them.

5 Unto Thee they cried, and were delivered, In Thee they trusted, and were not ashamed.

6 And I [am] a worm, and no man, A reproach of man, and despised of the people.

7 All beholding me do mock at me, They make free with the lip--shake the head,

8 `Roll unto Jehovah, He doth deliver him, He doth deliver him, for he delighted in him.'

9 For thou [art] He bringing me forth from the womb, Causing me to trust, On the breasts of my mother.

10 On Thee I have been cast from the womb, From the belly of my mother Thou [art] my God.

11 Be not far from me, For adversity is near, for there is no helper.

12 Many bulls have surrounded me, Mighty ones of Bashan have compassed me,

13 They have opened against me their mouth, A lion tearing and roaring.

14 As waters I have been poured out, And separated themselves have all my bones, My heart hath been like wax, It is melted in the midst of my bowels.

15 Dried up as an earthen vessel is my power, And my tongue is cleaving to my jaws.

16 And to the dust of death thou appointest me, For surrounded me have dogs, A company of evil doers have compassed me, Piercing my hands and my feet.

17 I count all my bones--they look expectingly, They look upon me,

18 They apportion my garments to themselves, And for my clothing they cause a lot to fall.

19 And Thou, O Jehovah, be not far off, O my strength, to help me haste.

20 Deliver from the sword my soul, From the paw of a dog mine only one.

21 Save me from the mouth of a lion: --And--from the horns of the high places Thou hast answered me!

22 I declare Thy name to my brethren, In the midst of the assembly I praise Thee.

23 Ye who fear Jehovah, praise ye Him, All the seed of Jacob, honour ye Him, And be afraid of Him, all ye seed of Israel.

24 For He hath not despised, nor abominated, The affliction of the afflicted, Nor hath He hidden His face from him, And in his crying unto Him He heareth.

25 Of Thee my praise [is] in the great assembly. My vows I complete before His fearers.

26 The humble do eat and are satisfied, Praise Jehovah do those seeking Him, Your heart doth live for ever.

27 Remember and return unto Jehovah, Do all ends of the earth, And before Thee bow themselves, Do all families of the nations,

28 For to Jehovah [is] the kingdom, And He is ruling among nations.

29 And the fat ones of earth have eaten, And they bow themselves, Before Him bow do all going down to dust, And he [who] hath not revived his soul.

30 A seed doth serve Him, It is declared of the Lord to the generation.

31 They come and declare His righteousness, To a people that is borne, that He hath made!

Psalms 25

1 By David. Unto Thee, O Jehovah, my soul I lift up.

2 My God, in Thee I have trusted, Let me not be ashamed, Let not mine enemies exult over me.

3 Also let none waiting on Thee be ashamed, Let the treacherous dealers without cause be ashamed.

4 Thy ways, O Jehovah, cause me to know, Thy paths teach Thou me.

5 Cause me to tread in Thy truth, and teach me, For Thou [art] the God of my salvation, Near Thee I have waited all the day.

6 Remember Thy mercies, O Jehovah, And Thy kindnesses, for from the age [are] they.

7 Sins of my youth, and my transgressions, Do not Thou remember. According to Thy kindness be mindful of me, For Thy goodness' sake, O Jehovah.

8 Good and upright [is] Jehovah, Therefore He directeth sinners in the way.

9 He causeth the humble to tread in judgment, And teacheth the humble His way.

10 All the paths of Jehovah [are] kindness and truth, To those keeping His covenant, And His testimonies.

11 For Thy name's sake, O Jehovah, Thou hast pardoned mine iniquity, for it [is] great.

12 Who [is] this--the man fearing Jehovah? He directeth him in the way He doth choose.

13 His soul in good doth remain, And his seed doth possess the land.

14 The secret of Jehovah [is] for those fearing Him, And His covenant--to cause them to know.

15 Mine eyes [are] continually unto Jehovah, For He bringeth out from a net my feet.

16 Turn Thou unto me, and favour me, For lonely and afflicted [am] I.

17 The distresses of my heart have enlarged themselves, From my distresses bring me out.

18 See mine affliction and my misery, And bear with all my sins.

19 See my enemies, for they have been many, And with violent hatred they have hated me.

20 Keep my soul, and deliver me, Let me not be ashamed, for I trusted in Thee.

21 Integrity and uprightness do keep me, For I have waited [on] Thee.

22 Redeem Israel, O God, from all his distresses!

Psalms 27

1 By David. Jehovah [is] my light and my salvation, Whom do I fear? Jehovah [is] the strength of my life, Of whom am I afraid?

2 When evil doers come near to me to eat my flesh, My adversaries and mine enemies to me, They have stumbled and fallen.

3 Though a host doth encamp against me, My heart doth not fear, Though war riseth up against me, In this I [am] confident.

4 One [thing] I asked of Jehovah--it I seek. My dwelling in the house of Jehovah, All the days of my life, To look on the pleasantness of Jehovah, And to inquire in His temple.

5 For He hideth me in a tabernacle in the day of evil, He hideth me in a secret place of His tent, On a rock he raiseth me up.

6 And now, lifted up is my head, Above my enemies--my surrounders, And I sacrifice in His tent sacrifices of shouting, I sing, yea, I sing praise to Jehovah.

7 Hear, O Jehovah, my voice--I call, And favour me, and answer me.

8 To Thee said my heart `They sought my face, Thy face, O Jehovah, I seek.'

9 Hide not Thy face from me, Turn not aside in anger Thy servant, My help Thou hast been. Leave me not, nor forsake me, O God of my salvation.

10 When my father and my mother Have forsaken me, then doth Jehovah gather me.

11 Shew me, O Jehovah, Thy way, And lead me in a path of uprightness, For the sake of my beholders.

12 Give me not to the will of my adversaries, For risen against me have false witnesses, And they breathe out violence to me.

13 I had not believed to look on the goodness of Jehovah In the land of the living!

14 Look unto Jehovah--be strong, And He doth strengthen thy heart, Yea, look unto Jehovah!

Psalms 28

1 By David. Unto Thee, O Jehovah, I call, My rock, be not silent to me! Lest Thou be silent to me, And I have been compared With those going down to the pit.

2 Hear the voice of my supplications, In my crying unto Thee, In my lifting up my hands toward thy holy oracle.

3 Draw me not with the wicked, And with workers of iniquity, Speaking peace with their neighbours, And evil in their heart.

4 Give to them according to their acting, And according to the evil of their doings. According to the work of their hands give to them. Return their deed to them.

5 For they attend not to the doing of Jehovah, And unto the work of His hands. He throweth them down, And doth not build them up.

6 Blessed [is] Jehovah, For He hath heard the voice of my supplications.

7 Jehovah [is] my strength, and my shield, In Him my heart trusted, and I have been helped. And my heart exulteth, And with my song I thank Him.

8 Jehovah [is] strength to him, Yea, the strength of the salvation of His anointed [is] He.

9 Save Thy people, and bless Thine inheritance, And feed them, and carry them to the age!

Psalms 30

1 A Psalm. --A song of the dedication of the house of David. I exalt Thee, O Jehovah, For Thou hast drawn me up, and hast not let mine enemies rejoice over me.

2 Jehovah my God, I have cried to Thee, And Thou dost heal me.

3 Jehovah, Thou hast brought up from Sheol my soul, Thou hast kept me alive, From going down [to] the pit.

4 Sing praise to Jehovah, ye His saints, And give thanks at the remembrance of His holiness,

5 For--a moment [is] in His anger, Life [is] in His good-will, At even remaineth weeping, and at morn singing.

6 And I--I have said in mine ease, `I am not moved--to the age.

7 O Jehovah, in Thy good pleasure, Thou hast caused strength to remain for my mountain,' Thou hast hidden Thy face--I have been troubled.

8 Unto Thee, O Jehovah, I call, And unto Jehovah I make supplication.

9 `What gain [is] in my blood? In my going down unto corruption? Doth dust thank Thee? doth it declare Thy truth?

10 Hear, O Jehovah, and favour me, O Jehovah, be a helper to me.'

11 Thou hast turned my mourning to dancing for me, Thou hast loosed my sackcloth, And girdest me [with] joy.

12 So that honour doth praise Thee, and is not silent, O Jehovah, my God, to the age I thank Thee!

Psalms 31

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. In Thee, O Jehovah, I have trusted, Let me not be ashamed to the age, In Thy righteousness deliver me.

2 Incline unto me Thine ear hastily, deliver me, Be to me for a strong rock, For a house of bulwarks to save me.

3 For my rock and my bulwark [art] Thou, For Thy name's sake lead me and tend me.

4 Bring me out from the net that they hid for me, For Thou [art] my strength.

5 Into Thy hand I commit my spirit, Thou hast redeemed me, Jehovah God of truth.

6 I have hated the observers of lying vanities, And I toward Jehovah have been confident.

7 I rejoice, and am glad in Thy kindness, In that Thou hast seen mine affliction, Thou hast known in adversities my soul.

8 And Thou hast not shut me up, Into the hand of an enemy, Thou hast caused my feet to stand in a broad place.

9 Favour me, O Jehovah, for distress [is] to me, Mine eye, my soul, and my body Have become old by provocation.

10 For my life hath been consumed in sorrow And my years in sighing. Feeble because of mine iniquity hath been my strength, And my bones have become old.

11 Among all mine adversaries I have been a reproach, And to my neighbours exceedingly, And a fear to mine acquaintances, Those seeing me without--fled from me.

12 I have been forgotten as dead out of mind, I have been as a perishing vessel.

13 For I have heard an evil account of many, Fear [is] round about. In their being united against me, To take my life they have devised,

14 And I on Thee--I have trusted, O Jehovah, I have said, `Thou [art] my God.'

15 In Thy hand [are] my times, Deliver me from the hand of my enemies, And from my pursuers.

16 Cause Thy face to shine on Thy servant, Save me in Thy kindness.

17 O Jehovah, let me not be ashamed, For I have called Thee, let the wicked be ashamed, Let them become silent to Sheol.

18 Let lips of falsehood become dumb, That are speaking against the righteous, Ancient sayings, in pride and contempt.

19 How abundant is Thy goodness, That Thou hast laid up for those fearing Thee,

20 Thou hast wrought for those trusting in Thee, Before sons of men. Thou hidest them in the secret place of Thy presence, From artifices of man, Thou concealest them in a tabernacle, From the strife of tongues.

21 Blessed [is] Jehovah, For He hath made marvellous His kindness To me in a city of bulwarks.

22 And I--I have said in my haste, `I have been cut off from before Thine eyes,' But Thou hast heard the voice of my supplications, In my crying unto Thee.

23 Love Jehovah, all ye His saints, Jehovah is keeping the faithful, And recompensing abundantly a proud doer.

24 Be strong, and He strengtheneth your heart, All ye who are waiting for Jehovah!

Psalms 32

1 By David. --An Instruction. O the happiness of him whose transgression [is] forgiven, Whose sin is covered.

2 O the happiness of a man, To whom Jehovah imputeth not iniquity, And in whose spirit there is no deceit.

3 When I have kept silence, become old have my bones, Through my roaring all the day.

4 When by day and by night Thy hand is heavy upon me, My moisture hath been changed Into the droughts of summer. Selah.

5 My sin I cause Thee to know, And mine iniquity I have not covered. I have said, `I confess concerning My transgressions to Jehovah,' And Thou--Thou hast taken away, The iniquity of my sin. Selah.

6 For this doth every saintly one pray to Thee, As the time to find. Surely at an overflowing of many waters, Unto him they come not.

7 Thou [art] a hiding-place for me, From distress Thou dost keep me, [With] songs of deliverance dost compass me. Selah.

8 I cause thee to act wisely, And direct thee in the way that thou goest, I cause mine eye to take counsel concerning thee.

9 Be ye not as a horse--as a mule, Without understanding, With bridle and bit, its ornaments, to curb, Not to come near unto thee.

10 Many [are] the pains of the wicked; As to him who is trusting in Jehovah, Kindness doth compass him.

11 Be glad in Jehovah, and rejoice, ye righteous, And sing, all ye upright of heart!

Psalms 33

1 Sing, ye righteous, in Jehovah, For upright ones praise [is] comely.

2 Give ye thanks to Jehovah with a harp, With psaltery of ten strings sing praise to Him,

3 Sing ye to Him a new song, Play skilfully with shouting.

4 For upright [is] the word of Jehovah, And all His work [is] in faithfulness.

5 Loving righteousness and judgment, Of the kindness of Jehovah is the earth full.

6 By the word of Jehovah The heavens have been made, And by the breath of His mouth all their host.

7 Gathering as a heap the waters of the sea, Putting in treasuries the depths.

8 Afraid of Jehovah are all the earth, Of Him are all the inhabitants of the world afraid.

9 For He hath said, and it is, He hath commanded, and it standeth.

10 Jehovah made void the counsel of nations, He disallowed the thoughts of the peoples.

11 The counsel of Jehovah to the age standeth, The thoughts of His heart to all generations.

12 O the happiness of the nation whose God [is] Jehovah, Of the people He did choose, For an inheritance to Him.

13 From the heavens hath Jehovah looked, He hath seen all the sons of men.

14 From the fixed place of His dwelling, He looked unto all inhabitants of the earth;

15 Who is forming their hearts together, Who is attending unto all their works.

16 The king is not saved by the multitude of a force. A mighty man is not delivered, By abundance of power.

17 A false thing [is] the horse for safety, And by the abundance of his strength He doth not deliver.

18 Lo, the eye of Jehovah [is] to those fearing Him, To those waiting for His kindness,

19 To deliver from death their soul, And to keep them alive in famine.

20 Our soul hath waited for Jehovah, Our help and our shield [is] He,

21 For in Him doth our heart rejoice, For in His holy name we have trusted.

22 Let Thy kindness, O Jehovah, be upon us, As we have waited for Thee!

Psalms 34

1 By David, in his changing his behaviour before Abimelech, and he driveth him away, and he goeth. I do bless Jehovah at all times, Continually His praise [is] in my mouth.

2 In Jehovah doth my soul boast herself, Hear do the humble and rejoice.

3 Ascribe ye greatness to Jehovah with me, And we exalt His name together.

4 I sought Jehovah, and He answered me, And from all my fears did deliver me.

5 They looked expectingly unto Him, And they became bright, And their faces are not ashamed.

6 This poor [one] called, and Jehovah heard, And from all his distresses saved him.

7 A messenger of Jehovah is encamping, Round about those who fear Him, And He armeth them.

8 Taste ye and see that Jehovah [is] good, O the happiness of the man who trusteth in Him.

9 Fear Jehovah, ye His holy ones, For there is no lack to those fearing Him.

10 Young lions have lacked and been hungry, And those seeking Jehovah lack not any good,

11 Come ye, children, hearken to me, The fear of Jehovah I do teach you.

12 Who [is] the man that is desiring life? Loving days to see good?

13 Keep thy tongue from evil, And thy lips from speaking deceit.

14 Turn aside from evil and do good, Seek peace and pursue it.

15 The eyes of Jehovah [are] unto the righteous, And His ears unto their cry.

16 (The face of Jehovah [is] on doers of evil, To cut off from earth their memorial.)

17 They cried, and Jehovah heard, And from all their distresses delivered them.

18 Near [is] Jehovah to the broken of heart, And the bruised of spirit He saveth.

19 Many [are] the evils of the righteous, Out of them all doth Jehovah deliver him.

20 He is keeping all his bones, One of them hath not been broken.

21 Evil doth put to death the wicked, And those hating the righteous are desolate.

22 Jehovah redeemeth the soul of His servants, And none trusting in Him are desolate!

Psalms 35

1 By David. Strive, Jehovah, with my strivers, fight with my fighters,

2 Take hold of shield and buckler, and rise for my help,

3 And draw out spear and lance, To meet my pursuers. Say to my soul, `Thy salvation I [am].'

4 They are ashamed and blush, those seeking my soul, Turned backward and confounded, Those devising my evil.

5 They are as chaff before wind, And a messenger of Jehovah driving away.

6 Their way is darkness and slipperiness, And a messenger of Jehovah their pursuer.

7 For without cause they hid for me their netpit, Without cause they digged for my soul.

8 Meet him doth desolation--he knoweth not, And his net that he hid catcheth him, For desolation he falleth into it.

9 And my soul is joyful in Jehovah, It rejoiceth in His salvation.

10 All my bones say, `Jehovah, who is like Thee, Delivering the poor from the stronger than he, And the poor and needy from his plunderer.'

11 Violent witnesses rise up, That which I have not known they ask me.

12 They pay me evil for good, bereaving my soul,

13 And I--in their sickness my clothing [is] sackcloth, I have humbled with fastings my soul, And my prayer unto my bosom returneth.

14 As [if] a friend, as [if] my brother, I walked habitually, As a mourner for a mother, Mourning I have bowed down.

15 And--in my halting they have rejoiced, And have been gathered together, Gathered against me were the smiters, And I have not known, They have rent, and they have not ceased;

16 With profane ones, mockers in feasts, Gnashing against me their teeth.

17 Lord, how long dost thou behold? Keep back my soul from their desolations, From young lions my only one.

18 I thank Thee in a great assembly, Among a mighty people I praise Thee.

19 Mine enemies rejoice not over me [with] falsehood, Those hating me without cause wink the eye.

20 For they speak not peace, And against the quiet of the land, Deceitful words they devise,

21 And they enlarge against me their mouth, They said, `Aha, aha, our eye hath seen.'

22 Thou hast seen, O Jehovah, Be not silent, O Lord--be not far from me,

23 Stir up, and wake to my judgment, My God, and my Lord, to my plea.

24 Judge me according to Thy righteousness, O Jehovah my God, And they do not rejoice over me.

25 They do not say in their heart, `Aha, our desire.' They do not say, `We swallowed him up.'

26 They are ashamed and confounded together, Who are rejoicing at my evil. They put on shame and confusion, Who are magnifying themselves against me.

27 They sing and rejoice, who are desiring my righteousness, And they say continually, `Jehovah is magnified, Who is desiring the peace of His servant.'

28 And my tongue uttereth Thy righteousness, All the day Thy praise!

Psalms 36

1 To the Overseer. --By a servant of Jehovah, by David. The transgression of the wicked Is affirming within my heart, `Fear of God is not before his eyes,

2 For he made [it] smooth to himself in his eyes, To find his iniquity to be hated.

3 The words of his mouth [are] iniquity and deceit, He ceased to act prudently--to do good.

4 Iniquity he deviseth on his bed, He stationeth himself on a way not good, Evil he doth not refuse.'

5 O Jehovah, in the heavens [is] Thy kindness, Thy faithfulness [is] unto the clouds.

6 Thy righteousness [is] as mountains of God, Thy judgments [are] a great deep. Man and beast Thou savest, O Jehovah.

7 How precious [is] Thy kindness, O God, And the sons of men In the shadow of Thy wings do trust.

8 They are filled from the fatness of Thy house, And the stream of Thy delights Thou dost cause them to drink.

9 For with Thee [is] a fountain of life, In Thy light we see light.

10 Draw out Thy kindness to those knowing Thee, And Thy righteousness to the upright of heart.

11 Let not a foot of pride meet me, And a hand of the wicked let not move me.

12 There have workers of iniquity fallen, They have been overthrown, And have not been able to arise!

Psalms 37

1 By David. Do not fret because of evil doers, Be not envious against doers of iniquity,

2 For as grass speedily they are cut off, And as the greenness of the tender grass do fade.

3 Trust in Jehovah, and do good, Dwell [in] the land, and enjoy faithfulness,

4 And delight thyself on Jehovah, And He giveth to thee the petitions of thy heart.

5 Roll on Jehovah thy way, And trust upon Him, and He worketh,

6 And hath brought out as light thy righteousness, And thy judgment as noon-day.

7 Be silent for Jehovah, and stay thyself for Him, Do not fret because of him Who is making prosperous his way, Because of a man doing wicked devices.

8 Desist from anger, and forsake fury, Fret not thyself only to do evil.

9 For evil doers are cut off, As to those waiting on Jehovah, they possess the land.

10 And yet a little, and the wicked is not, And thou hast considered his place, and it is not.

11 And the humble do possess the land, And they have delighted themselves In the abundance of peace.

12 The wicked is devising against the righteous, And gnashing against him his teeth.

13 The Lord doth laugh at him, For He hath seen that his day cometh.

14 A sword have the wicked opened, And they have trodden their bow, To cause to fall the poor and needy, To slaughter the upright of the way.

15 Their sword doth enter into their own heart, And their bows are shivered.

16 Better [is] the little of the righteous, Than the store of many wicked.

17 For the arms of the wicked are shivered, And Jehovah is sustaining the righteous.

18 Jehovah knoweth the days of the perfect, And their inheritance is--to the age.

19 They are not ashamed in a time of evil, And in days of famine they are satisfied.

20 But the wicked perish, and the enemies of Jehovah, As the preciousness of lambs, Have been consumed, In smoke they have been consumed.

21 The wicked is borrowing and repayeth not, And the righteous is gracious and giving.

22 For His blessed ones do possess the land, And His reviled ones are cut off.

23 From Jehovah [are] the steps of a man, They have been prepared, And his way he desireth.

24 When he falleth, he is not cast down, For Jehovah is sustaining his hand.

25 Young I have been, I have also become old, And I have not seen the righteous forsaken, And his seed seeking bread.

26 All the day he is gracious and lending, And his seed [is] for a blessing.

27 Turn aside from evil, and do good, and dwell to the age.

28 For Jehovah is loving judgment, And He doth not forsake His saintly ones, To the age they have been kept, And the seed of the wicked is cut off.

29 The righteous possess the land, And they dwell for ever on it.

30 The mouth of the righteous uttereth wisdom, And his tongue speaketh judgment.

31 The law of his God [is] his heart, His steps do not slide.

32 The wicked is watching for the righteous, And is seeking to put him to death.

33 Jehovah doth not leave him in his hand, Nor condemn him in his being judged.

34 Look unto Jehovah, and keep His way, And He doth exalt thee to possess the land, In the wicked being cut off--thou seest!

35 I have seen the wicked terrible, And spreading as a green native plant,

36 And he passeth away, and lo, he is not, And I seek him, and he is not found!

37 Observe the perfect, and see the upright, For the latter end of each [is] peace.

38 And transgressors were destroyed together, The latter end of the wicked was cut off.

39 And the salvation of the righteous [is] from Jehovah, Their strong place in a time of adversity.

40 And Jehovah doth help them and deliver them, He delivereth them from the wicked, And saveth them, Because they trusted in Him!

Psalms 38

1 A Psalm of David, `To cause to remember.' Jehovah, in Thy wrath reprove me not, Nor in Thy fury chastise me.

2 For Thine arrows have come down on me, And Thou lettest down upon me Thy hand.

3 Soundness is not in my flesh, Because of Thine indignation, Peace is not in my bones because of my sin.

4 For mine iniquities have passed over my head, As a heavy burden--too heavy for me.

5 Stunk--become corrupt have my wounds, Because of my folly.

6 I have been bent down, I have been bowed down--unto excess, All the day I have gone mourning.

7 For my flanks have been full of drought, And soundness is not in my flesh.

8 I have been feeble and smitten--unto excess, I have roared from disquietude of heart.

9 Lord, before Thee [is] all my desire, And my sighing from Thee hath not been hid.

10 My heart [is] panting, my power hath forsaken me, And the light of mine eyes, Even they are not with me.

11 My lovers and my friends over-against my plague stand. And my neighbours afar off have stood.

12 And those seeking my soul lay a snare, And those seeking my evil Have spoken mischievous things, And they do deceits meditate all the day.

13 And I, as deaf, hear not. And as a dumb one who openeth not his mouth.

14 Yea, I am as a man who heareth not, And in his mouth are no reproofs.

15 Because for Thee, O Jehovah, I have waited, Thou dost answer, O Lord my God.

16 When I said, `Lest they rejoice over me, In the slipping of my foot against me they magnified themselves.

17 For I am ready to halt, And my pain [is] before me continually.

18 For mine iniquity I declare, I am sorry for my sin.

19 And mine enemies [are] lively, They have been strong, and those hating me without cause, Have been multiplied.

20 And those paying evil for good accuse me, Because of my pursuing good.

21 Do not forsake me, O Jehovah, My God, be not far from me,

22 Haste to help me, O Lord, my salvation!

Psalms 39

1 To the Overseer, to Jeduthun. --A Psalm of David. I have said, `I observe my ways, Against sinning with my tongue, I keep for my mouth a curb, while the wicked [is] before me.'

2 I was dumb [with] silence, I kept silent from good, and my pain is excited.

3 Hot [is] my heart within me, In my meditating doth the fire burn, I have spoken with my tongue.

4 `Cause me to know, O Jehovah, mine end, And the measure of my days--what it [is],' I know how frail I [am].

5 Lo, handbreadths Thou hast made my days, And mine age [is] as nothing before Thee, Only, all vanity [is] every man set up. Selah.

6 Only, in an image doth each walk habitually, Only, [in] vain, they are disquieted, He heapeth up and knoweth not who gathereth them.

7 And, now, what have I expected? O Lord, my hope--it [is] of Thee.

8 From all my transgressions deliver me, A reproach of the fool make me not.

9 I have been dumb, I open not my mouth, Because Thou--Thou hast done [it].

10 Turn aside from off me Thy stroke, From the striving of Thy hand I have been consumed.

11 With reproofs against iniquity, Thou hast corrected man, And dost waste as a moth his desirableness, Only, vanity [is] every man. Selah.

12 Hear my prayer, O Jehovah, And [to] my cry give ear, Unto my tear be not silent, For a sojourner I [am] with Thee, A settler like all my fathers.

13 Look from me, and I brighten up before I go and am not!

Psalms 40

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. I have diligently expected Jehovah, And He inclineth to me, and heareth my cry,

2 And He doth cause me to come up From a pit of desolation--from mire of mud, And He raiseth up on a rock my feet, He is establishing my steps.

3 And He putteth in my mouth a new song, `Praise to our God.' Many do see and fear, and trust in Jehovah.

4 O the happiness of the man Who hath made Jehovah his trust, And hath not turned unto the proud, And those turning aside to lies.

5 Much hast Thou done, Jehovah my God; Thy wonders and Thy thoughts toward us, There is none to arrange unto Thee, I declare and speak: They have been more than to be numbered.

6 Sacrifice and present Thou hast not desired, Ears Thou hast prepared for me, Burnt and sin-offering Thou hast not asked.

7 Then said I, `Lo, I have come,' In the roll of the book it is written of me,

8 To do Thy pleasure, my God, I have delighted, And Thy law [is] within my heart.

9 I have proclaimed tidings of righteousness In the great assembly, lo, my lips I restrain not, O Jehovah, Thou hast known.

10 Thy righteousness I have not concealed In the midst of my heart, Thy faithfulness and Thy salvation I have told, I have not hidden Thy kindness and Thy truth, To the great assembly.

11 Thou, O Jehovah, restrainest not Thy mercies from me, Thy kindness and Thy truth do continually keep me.

12 For compassed me have evils innumerable, Overtaken me have mine iniquities, And I have not been able to see; They have been more than the hairs of my head, And my heart hath forsaken me.

13 Be pleased, O Jehovah, to deliver me, O Jehovah, for my help make haste.

14 They are ashamed and confounded together, Who are seeking my soul to destroy it, They are turned backward, And are ashamed, who are desiring my evil.

15 They are desolate because of their shame, Who are saying to me, `Aha, aha.'

16 All seeking Thee rejoice and are glad in Thee, Those loving Thy salvation say continually, `Jehovah is magnified.'

17 And I [am] poor and needy, The Lord doth devise for me. My help and my deliverer [art] Thou, O my God, tarry Thou not.

Psalms 41

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. O the happiness of him Who is acting wisely unto the poor, In a day of evil doth Jehovah deliver him.

2 Jehovah doth preserve him and revive him, He is happy in the land, And Thou givest him not into the will of his enemies.

3 Jehovah supporteth on a couch of sickness, All his bed Thou hast turned in his weakness.

4 I--I said, `O Jehovah, favour me, Heal my soul, for I did sin against Thee,'

5 Mine enemies say evil of me: When he dieth--his name hath perished!

6 And if he came to see--vanity he speaketh, His heart gathereth iniquity to itself, He goeth out--at the street he speaketh.

7 All hating me whisper together against me, Against me they devise evil to me:

8 A thing of Belial is poured out on him, And because he lay down he riseth not again.

9 Even mine ally, in whom I trusted, One eating my bread, made great the heel against me,

10 And Thou, Jehovah, favour me, And cause me to rise, And I give recompence to them.

11 By this I have known, That Thou hast delighted in me, Because my enemy shouteth not over me.

12 As to me, in mine integrity, Thou hast taken hold upon me, And causest me to stand before Thee to the age.

13 Blessed [is] Jehovah, God of Israel, From the age--and unto the age. Amen and Amen.

Psalms 42

1 To the Overseer. --An Instruction. By sons of Korah. As a hart doth pant for streams of water, So my soul panteth toward Thee, O God.

2 My soul thirsted for God, for the living God, When do I enter and see the face of God?

3 My tear hath been to me bread day and night, In their saying unto me all the day, `Where [is] thy God?'

4 These I remember, and pour out my soul in me, For I pass over into the booth, I go softly with them unto the house of God, With the voice of singing and confession, The multitude keeping feast!

5 What! bowest thou thyself, O my soul? Yea, art thou troubled within me? Wait for God, for still I confess Him: The salvation of my countenance--My God!

6 In me doth my soul bow itself, Therefore I remember Thee from the land of Jordan, And of the Hermons, from the hill Mizar.

7 Deep unto deep is calling At the noise of Thy water-spouts, All Thy breakers and Thy billows passed over me.

8 By day Jehovah commandeth His kindness, And by night a song [is] with me, A prayer to the God of my life.

9 I say to God my rock, `Why hast Thou forgotten me? Why go I mourning in the oppression of an enemy?

10 With a sword in my bones Have mine adversaries reproached me, In their saying unto me all the day, `Where [is] thy God?'

11 What! bowest thou thyself, O my soul? And what! art thou troubled within me? Wait for God, for still I confess Him, The salvation of my countenance, and my God!

Psalms 44

1 To the Overseer. --By sons of Korah. An Instruction. O God, with our ears we have heard, Our fathers have recounted to us, The work Thou didst work in their days, In the days of old.

2 Thou, [with] Thy hand, nations hast dispossessed. And Thou dost plant them. Thou afflictest peoples, and sendest them away.

3 For, not by their sword Possessed they the land, And their arm gave not salvation to them, But Thy right hand, and Thine arm, And the light of Thy countenance, Because Thou hadst accepted them.

4 Thou [art] He, my king, O God, Command the deliverances of Jacob.

5 By Thee our adversaries we do push, By Thy name tread down our withstanders,

6 For, not in my bow do I trust, And my sword doth not save me.

7 For Thou hast saved us from our adversaries, And those hating us Thou hast put to shame.

8 In God we have boasted all the day, And Thy name to the age we thank. Selah.

9 In anger Thou hast cast off and causest us to blush, And goest not forth with our hosts.

10 Thou causest us to turn backward from an adversary, And those hating us, Have spoiled for themselves.

11 Thou makest us food like sheep, And among nations Thou hast scattered us.

12 Thou sellest Thy people--without wealth, And hast not become great by their price.

13 Thou makest us a reproach to our neighbours, A scorn and a reproach to our surrounders.

14 Thou makest us a simile among nations, A shaking of the head among peoples.

15 All the day my confusion [is] before me, And the shame of my face hath covered me.

16 Because of the voice of a reproacher and reviler, Because of an enemy and a selfavenger.

17 All this met us, and we did not forget Thee, Nor have we dealt falsely in Thy covenant.

18 We turn not backward our heart, Nor turn aside doth our step from Thy path.

19 But Thou hast smitten us in a place of dragons, And dost cover us over with deathshade.

20 If we have forgotten the name of our God, And spread our hands to a strange God,

21 Doth not God search out this? For He knoweth the secrets of the heart.

22 Surely, for Thy sake we have been slain all the day, Reckoned as sheep of the slaughter.

23 Stir up--why dost Thou sleep, O Lord? Awake, cast us not off for ever.

24 Why Thy face hidest Thou? Thou forgettest our afflictions and our oppression,

25 For bowed to the dust hath our soul, Cleaved to the earth hath our belly.

26 Arise, a help to us, And ransom us for thy kindness' sake.

Psalms 45

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Lilies.' --By sons of Korah. --An Instruction. --A song of loves. My heart hath indited a good thing, I am telling my works to a king, My tongue [is] the pen of a speedy writer.

2 Thou hast been beautified above the sons of men, Grace hath been poured into thy lips, Therefore hath God blessed thee to the age.

3 Gird Thy sword upon the thigh, O mighty, Thy glory and Thy majesty!

4 As to Thy majesty--prosper! --ride! Because of truth, and meekness--righteousness, And Thy right hand showeth Thee fearful things.

5 Thine arrows [are] sharp, --Peoples fall under Thee--In the heart of the enemies of the king.

6 Thy throne, O God, [is] age-during, and for ever, A sceptre of uprightness [Is] the sceptre of Thy kingdom.

7 Thou hast loved righteousness and hatest wickedness, Therefore God, thy God, hath anointed thee, Oil of joy above thy companions.

8 Myrrh and aloes, cassia! all thy garments, Out of palaces of ivory Stringed instruments have made thee glad.

9 Daughters of kings [are] among thy precious ones, A queen hath stood at thy right hand, In pure gold of Ophir.

10 Hearken, O daughter, and see, incline thine ear, And forget thy people, and thy father's house,

11 And the king doth desire thy beauty, Because he [is] thy lord--bow thyself to him,

12 And the daughter of Tyre with a present, The rich of the people do appease thy face.

13 All glory [is] the daughter of the king within, Of gold-embroidered work [is] her clothing.

14 In divers colours she is brought to the king, Virgins--after her--her companions, Are brought to thee.

15 They are brought with joy and gladness, They come into the palace of the king.

16 Instead of thy fathers are thy sons, Thou dost appoint them for princes in all the earth.

17 I make mention of Thy name in all generations, Therefore do peoples praise Thee, To the age, and for ever!

Psalms 46

1 To the Overseer. --By sons of Korah. `For the Virgins.' --A song. God [is] to us a refuge and strength, A help in adversities found most surely.

2 Therefore we fear not in the changing of earth, And in the slipping of mountains Into the heart of the seas.

3 Roar--troubled are its waters, Mountains they shake in its pride. Selah.

4 A river--its rivulets rejoice the city of God, Thy holy place of the tabernacles of the Most High.

5 God [is] in her midst--she is not moved, God doth help her at the turn of the morn!

6 Troubled have been nations, Moved have been kingdoms, He hath given forth with His voice, earth melteth.

7 Jehovah of Hosts [is] with us, A tower for us [is] the God of Jacob. Selah.

8 Come ye, see the works of Jehovah, Who hath done astonishing things in the earth,

9 Causing wars to cease, Unto the end of the earth, the bow he shivereth, And the spear He hath cut asunder, Chariots he doth burn with fire.

10 Desist, and know that I [am] God, I am exalted among nations, I am exalted in the earth.

11 Jehovah of hosts [is] with us, A tower for us [is] the God of Jacob! Selah.

Psalms 48

1 A Song, a Psalm, by sons of Korah. Great [is] Jehovah, and praised greatly, In the city of our God--His holy hill.

2 Beautiful [for] elevation, A joy of all the land, [is] Mount Zion, The sides of the north, the city of a great king.

3 God in her high places is known for a tower.

4 For, lo, the kings met, they passed by together,

5 They have seen--so they have marvelled, They have been troubled, they were hastened away.

6 Trembling hath seized them there, Pain, as of a travailing woman.

7 By an east wind Thou shiverest ships of Tarshish.

8 As we have heard, so we have seen, In the city of Jehovah of hosts, In the city of our God, God doth establish her--to the age. Selah.

9 We have thought, O God, of Thy kindness, In the midst of Thy temple,

10 As [is] Thy name, O God, so [is] Thy praise, Over the ends of the earth, Righteousness hath filled Thy right hand.

11 Rejoice doth Mount Zion, The daughters of Judah are joyful, For the sake of Thy judgments.

12 Compass Zion, and go round her, count her towers,

13 Set your heart to her bulwark, Consider her high places, So that ye recount to a later generation,

14 That this God [is] our God--To the age and for ever, He--he doth lead us over death!

Psalms 49

1 To the Overseer. --By sons of Korah. A Psalm. Hear this, all ye peoples, Give ear, all ye inhabitants of the world.

2 Both low and high, together rich and needy.

3 My mouth speaketh wise things, And the meditations of my heart [are] things of understanding.

4 I incline to a simile mine ear, I open with a harp my riddle:

5 Why do I fear in days of evil? The iniquity of my supplanters doth compass me.

6 Those trusting on their wealth, And in the multitude of their riches, Do shew themselves foolish.

7 A brother doth no one at all ransom, He doth not give to God his atonement.

8 And precious [is] the redemption of their soul, And it hath ceased--to the age.

9 And still he liveth for ever, He seeth not the pit.

10 For he seeth wise men die, Together the foolish and brutish perish, And have left to others their wealth.

11 Their heart [is]: Their houses [are] to the age, Their tabernacles to all generations. They proclaimed their names over the lands.

12 And man in honour doth not remain, He hath been like the beasts, they have been cut off.

13 This their way [is] folly for them, And their posterity with their sayings are pleased. Selah.

14 As sheep for Sheol they have set themselves, Death doth afflict them, And the upright rule over them in the morning, And their form [is] for consumption. Sheol [is] a dwelling for him.

15 Only, God doth ransom my soul from the hand of Sheol, For He doth receive me. Selah.

16 Fear not, when one maketh wealth, When the honour of his house is abundant,

17 For at his death he receiveth nothing, His honour goeth not down after him.

18 For his soul in his life he blesseth, (And they praise thee when thou dost well for thyself.)

19 It cometh to the generation of his fathers, For ever they see not the light.

20 Man in honour, who understandest not, Hath been like the beasts, they have been cut off!

Psalms 50

1 A Psalm of Asaph. The God of gods--Jehovah--hath spoken, And He calleth to the earth From the rising of the sun unto its going in.

2 From Zion, the perfection of beauty, God shone.

3 Our God cometh, and is not silent, Fire before Him doth devour, And round about him it hath been very tempestuous.

4 He doth call unto the heavens from above, And unto the earth, to judge His people.

5 Gather ye to Me My saints, Making covenant with Me over a sacrifice.

6 And the heavens declare His righteousness, For God Himself [is] judge. Selah.

7 Hear, O My people, and I speak, O Israel, and I testify against thee, God, thy God [am] I.

8 Not for thy sacrifices do I reprove thee, Yea, thy burnt-offerings [Are] before Me continually.

9 I take not from thy house a bullock, From thy folds he goats.

10 For Mine [is] every beast of the forest, The cattle on the hills of oxen.

11 I have known every fowl of the mountains, And the wild beast of the field [is] with Me.

12 If I am hungry I tell not to thee, For Mine [is] the world and its fulness.

13 Do I eat the flesh of bulls, And drink the blood of he-goats?

14 Sacrifice to God confession, And complete to the Most High thy vows.

15 And call Me in a day of adversity, I deliver thee, and thou honourest Me.

16 And to the wicked hath God said: What to thee--to recount My statutes? That thou liftest up My covenant on thy mouth?

17 Yea, thou hast hated instruction, And dost cast My words behind thee.

18 If thou hast seen a thief, Then thou art pleased with him, And with adulterers [is] thy portion.

19 Thy mouth thou hast sent forth with evil, And thy tongue joineth deceit together,

20 Thou sittest, against thy brother thou speakest, Against a son of thy mother givest slander.

21 These thou didst, and I kept silent, Thou hast thought that I am like thee, I reprove thee, and set in array before thine eyes.

22 Understand this, I pray you, Ye who are forgetting God, Lest I tear, and there is no deliverer.

23 He who is sacrificing praise honoureth Me, As to him who maketh a way, I cause him to look on the salvation of God!

Psalms 51

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David, in the coming inn unto him of Nathan the prophet, when he hath gone in unto Bath-Sheba. Favour me, O God, according to Thy kindness, According to the abundance of Thy mercies, Blot out my transgressions.

2 Thoroughly wash me from mine iniquity, And from my sin cleanse me,

3 For my transgressions I do know, And my sin [is] before me continually.

4 Against Thee, Thee only, I have sinned, And done the evil thing in Thine eyes, So that Thou art righteous in Thy words, Thou art pure in Thy judging.

5 Lo, in iniquity I have been brought forth, And in sin doth my mother conceive me.

6 Lo, truth Thou hast desired in the inward parts, And in the hidden part Wisdom Thou causest me to know.

7 Thou cleansest me with hyssop and I am clean, Washest me, and than snow I am whiter.

8 Thou causest me to hear joy and gladness, Thou makest joyful bones Thou hast bruised.

9 Hide Thy face from my sin. And all mine iniquities blot out.

10 A clean heart prepare for me, O God, And a right spirit renew within me.

11 Cast me not forth from Thy presence, And Thy Holy Spirit take not from me.

12 Restore to me the joy of Thy salvation, And a willing spirit doth sustain me.

13 I teach transgressors Thy ways, And sinners unto Thee do return.

14 Deliver me from blood, O God, God of my salvation, My tongue singeth of Thy righteousness.

15 O Lord, my lips thou dost open, And my mouth declareth Thy praise.

16 For Thou desirest not sacrifice, or I give [it], Burnt-offering Thou acceptest not.

17 The sacrifices of God [are] a broken spirit, A heart broken and bruised, O God, Thou dost not despise.

18 Do good in Thy good pleasure with Zion, Thou dost build the walls of Jerusalem.

19 Then Thou desirest sacrifices of righteousness, Burnt-offering, and whole burntoffering, Then they offer bullocks on thine altar!

Psalms 55

1 To the Overseer with stringed instruments. --An instruction, by David. Give ear, O God, [to] my prayer, And hide not from my supplication.

2 Attend to me, and answer me, I mourn in my meditation, and make a noise,

3 Because of the voice of an enemy, Because of the oppression of the wicked, For they cause sorrow to move against me, And in anger they hate me.

4 My heart is pained within me, And terrors of death have fallen on me.

5 Fear and trembling come in to me, And horror doth cover me.

6 And I say, `Who doth give to me a pinion as a dove? I fly away and rest,

7 Lo, I move far off, I lodge in a wilderness. Selah.

8 I hasten escape for myself, From a rushing wind, from a whirlwind.

9 Swallow up, O Lord, divide their tongue, For I saw violence and strife in a city.

10 By day and by night they go round it, on its walls. Both iniquity and perverseness [are] in its midst,

11 Mischiefs [are] in its midst. Fraud and deceit depart not from its street.

12 For an enemy reproacheth me not, or I bear [it], He who is hating me Hath not magnified himself against me, Or I hide from him.

13 But thou, a man--as mine equal, My familiar friend, and mine acquaintance.

14 When together we sweeten counsel, Into the house of God we walk in company.

15 Desolations [are] upon them, They go down [to] Sheol--alive, For wickedness [is] in their dwelling, in their midst.

16 I--to God I call, and Jehovah saveth me.

17 Evening, and morning, and noon, I meditate, and make a noise, and He heareth my voice,

18 He hath ransomed in peace my soul From him who is near to me, For with the multitude they were with me.

19 God doth hear and afflict them, And He sitteth of old. Selah. Because they have no changes, and fear not God,

20 He hath sent forth his hands against his well-wishers, He hath polluted his covenant.

21 Sweeter than honey hath been his mouth, And his heart [is] war! Softer have been his words than oil, And they [are] drawn [swords].

22 Cast on Jehovah that which He hath given thee, And He doth sustain thee, He doth not suffer for ever the moving of the righteous.

23 And Thou, O God, dost bring them down To a pit of destruction, Men of blood and deceit reach not to half their days, And I--I do trust in Thee!

Psalms 56

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Dumb Dove far off.' --A secret treasure of David, in the Philistines' taking hold of him in Gath. Favour me, O God, for man swallowed me up, All the day fighting he oppresseth me,

2 Mine enemies have swallowed up all the day, For many [are] fighting against me, O most High,

3 The day I am afraid I am confident toward Thee.

4 In God I praise His word, in God I have trusted, I fear not what flesh doth to me.

5 All the day they wrest my words, Concerning me all their thoughts [are] for evil,

6 They assemble, they hide, they watch my heels, When they have expected my soul.

7 By iniquity they escape, In anger the peoples put down, O God.

8 My wandering Thou hast counted, Thou--place Thou my tear in Thy bottle, Are they not in Thy book?

9 Then turn back do mine enemies in the day I call. This I have known, that God [is] for me.

10 In God I praise the word, In Jehovah I praise the word.

11 In God I trusted, I fear not what man doth to me,

12 On me, O God, [are] Thy vows, I repay thank-offerings to Thee.

13 For Thou hast delivered my soul from death, Dost Thou not my feet from falling? To walk habitually before God in the light of the living!

Psalms 57

1 To the Overseer. --`Destroy not.' --A secret treasure of David, in his fleeing from the face of Saul into a cave. Favour me, O God, favour me, For in Thee is my soul trusting, And in the shadow of Thy wings I trust, Until the calamities passover.

2 I call to God Most High, To God [who] is perfecting for me.

3 He sendeth from the heaven, and saveth me, He reproached--who is panting after me. Selah. God sendeth forth His kindness and His truth.

4 My soul [is] in the midst of lions, I lie down [among] flames--sons of men, Their teeth [are] a spear and arrows, And their tongue a sharp sword.

5 Be Thou exalted above the heavens, O God, Above all the earth Thine honour.

6 A net they have prepared for my steps, Bowed down hath my soul, They have digged before me a pit, They have fallen into its midst. Selah.

7 Prepared is my heart, O God, Prepared is my heart, I sing and praise.

8 Awake, mine honour, awake, psaltery and harp, I awake the morning dawn.

9 I thank Thee among the peoples, O Lord, I praise Thee among the nations.

10 For great unto the heavens [is] Thy kindness, And unto the clouds Thy truth.

11 Be thou exalted above the heavens, O God. Above all the earth Thine honour!

Psalms 58

1 To the Overseer. --`Destroy not.' --A secret treasure, by David. Is it true, O dumb one, righteously ye speak? Uprightly ye judge, O sons of men?

2 Even in heart ye work iniquities, In the land the violence of your hands ye ponder.

3 The wicked have been estranged from the womb, They have erred from the belly, speaking lies.

4 Their poison [is] as poison of a serpent, As a deaf asp shutting its ear,

5 Which hearkeneth not to the voice of whisperers, A charmer of charms most skilful.

6 O God, break their teeth in their mouth, The jaw-teeth of young lions break down, O Jehovah.

7 They are melted as waters, They go up and down for themselves, His arrow proceedeth as they cut themselves off.

8 As a snail that melteth he goeth on, [As] an untimely birth of a woman, They have not seen the sun.

9 Before your pots discern the bramble, As well the raw as the heated He whirleth away.

10 The righteous rejoiceth that he hath seen vengeance, His steps he washeth in the blood of the wicked.

11 And man saith: `Surely fruit [is] for the righteous: Surely there is a God judging in the earth!'

Psalms 59

1 To the Overseer. --`Destroy not,' by David. --A secret treasure, in Saul's sending, and they watch the house to put him to death. Deliver me from mine enemies, O my God, From my withstanders set me on high.

2 Deliver me from workers of iniquity, And from men of blood save me.

3 For, lo, they laid wait for my soul, Assembled against me are strong ones, Not my transgression nor my sin, O Jehovah.

4 Without punishment they run and prepare themselves, Stir up to meet me, and see.

5 And Thou, Jehovah, God of Hosts, God of Israel, Awake to inspect all the nations. Favour not any treacherous dealers of iniquity. Selah.

6 They turn back at evening, They make a noise like a dog, And go round about the city.

7 Lo, they belch out with their mouths, Swords [are] in their lips, for `Who heareth?'

8 And Thou, O Jehovah dost laugh at them, Thou dost mock at all the nations.

9 O my Strength, unto Thee I take heed, For God [is] my tower--the God of my kindness.

10 God doth go before me, He causeth me to look on mine enemies.

11 Slay them not, lest my people forget, Shake them by Thy strength, And bring them down, O Lord our shield.

12 The sin of their mouth [is] a word of their lips, And they are captured in their pride, And from the curse and lying they recount.

13 Consume in fury, consume and they are not, And they know that God is ruling in Jacob, To the ends of the earth. Selah.

14 And they turn back at evening, They make a noise like a dog, And they go round about the city.

15 They--they wander for food, If they are not satisfied--then they murmur.

16 And I--I sing [of] Thy strength, And I sing at morn [of] Thy kindness, For thou hast been a tower to me, And a refuge for me in a day of adversity.

17 O my Strength, unto Thee I sing praise, For God [is] my tower, the God of my kindness!

Psalms 60

1 To the Overseer. --`Concerning the Lily of Testimony,' a secret treasure of David, to teach, in his striving with Aram-Naharaim, and with Aram-Zobah, and Joab turneth back and smiteth Edom in the valley of Salt--twelve thousand. O God, Thou hadst cast us off, Thou hadst broken us--hadst been angry! --Thou dost turn back to us.

2 Thou hast caused the land to tremble, Thou hast broken it, Heal its breaches, for it hath moved.

3 Thou hast shewn Thy people a hard thing, Thou hast caused us to drink wine of trembling.

4 Thou hast given to those fearing thee an ensign. To be lifted up as an ensign Because of truth. Selah.

5 That Thy beloved ones may be drawn out, Save [with] Thy right hand, and answer us.

6 God hath spoken in His holiness: I exult--I apportion Shechem, And the valley of Succoth I measure,

7 Mine [is] Gilead, and mine [is] Manasseh, And Ephraim [is] the strength of my head, Judah [is] my lawgiver,

8 Moab [is] my pot for washing, over Edom I cast my shoe, Shout, concerning me, O Philistia.

9 Who doth bring me [to] a city of bulwarks? Who hath led me unto Edom?

10 Is it not Thou, O God? hast Thou cast us off? And dost Thou not go forth, O God, with our hosts!

11 Give to us help from adversity, And vain [is] the deliverance of man.

12 In God we do mightily, And He treadeth down our adversaries!

Psalms 62

1 To the Overseer, for Jeduthun. --A Psalm of David. Only--toward God [is] my soul silent, From Him [is] my salvation.

2 Only--He [is] my rock, and my salvation, My tower, I am not much moved.

3 Till when do ye devise mischief against a man? Ye are destroyed all of you, As a wall inclined, a hedge that is cast down.

4 Only--from his excellency They have consulted to drive away, They enjoy a lie, with their mouth they bless, And with their heart revile. Selah.

5 Only--for God, be silent, O my soul, For from Him [is] my hope.

6 Only--He [is] my rock and my salvation, My tower, I am not moved.

7 On God [is] my salvation, and my honour, The rock of my strength, my refuge [is] in God.

8 Trust in Him at all times, O people, Pour forth before Him your heart, God [is] a refuge for us. Selah.

9 Only--vanity [are] the low, a lie the high. In balances to go up they than vanity [are] lighter.

10 Trust not in oppression, And in robbery become not vain, Wealth--when it increaseth--set not the heart.

11 Once hath God spoken, twice I heard this, That `strength [is] with God.'

12 And with Thee, O Lord, [is] kindness, For Thou dost recompense to each, According to his work!

Psalms 65

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. A Song. To Thee, silence--praise, O God, [is] in Zion, And to Thee is a vow completed.

2 Hearer of prayer, to Thee all flesh cometh.

3 Matters of iniquities were mightier than I, Our transgressions--Thou dost cover them.

4 O the happiness of [him whom] Thou choosest, And drawest near, he inhabiteth Thy courts, We are satisfied with the goodness of Thy house, Thy holy temple.

5 By fearful things in righteousness Thou answerest us, O God of our salvation, The confidence of all far off ends of earth and sea.

6 Establishing mountains by His power, He hath been girded with might,

7 Restraining the noise of seas, the noise of their billows, And the multitude of the peoples.

8 And the inhabitants of the uttermost parts From Thy signs are afraid, The outgoings of morning and evening Thou causest to sing.

9 Thou hast inspected the earth, and waterest it, Thou makest it very rich, the rivulet of God [is] full of water, Thou preparest their corn, When thus Thou dost prepare it,

10 Its ridges have been filled, Deepened hath been its furrow, With showers Thou dost soften it, Its springing up Thou blessest.

11 Thou hast crowned the year of Thy goodness, And Thy paths drop fatness.

12 Drop do the pastures of a wilderness, And joy of the heights Thou girdest on.

13 Clothed have lambs the flock, And valleys are covered with corn, They shout--yea, they sing!

Psalms 66

1 To the Overseer. --A Song, a Psalm. Shout ye to God, all the earth.

2 Praise ye the honour of His name, Make ye honourable His praise.

3 Say to God, `How fearful [are] Thy works, By the abundance of Thy strength, Thine enemies feign obedience to Thee.

4 All the earth do bow to Thee, They sing praise to Thee, they praise Thy name.' Selah.

5 Come ye, and see the works of God, Fearful acts toward the sons of men.

6 He hath turned a sea to dry land, Through a river they pass over on foot, There do we rejoice in Him.

7 Ruling by His might to the age, His eyes among the nations do watch, The refractory exalt not themselves. Selah.

8 Bless, ye peoples, our God, And sound the voice of His praise,

9 Who hath placed our soul in life, And suffered not our feet to be moved.

10 For Thou hast tried us, O God, Thou hast refined us as the refining of silver.

11 Thou hast brought us into a net, Thou hast placed pressure on our loins.

12 Thou hast caused man to ride at our head. We have entered into fire and into water, And Thou bringest us out to a watered place.

13 I enter Thy house with burnt-offerings, I complete to Thee my vows,

14 For opened were my lips, And my mouth spake in my distress:

15 `Burnt-offerings of fatlings I offer to Thee, With perfume of rams, I prepare a bullock with he-goats.' Selah.

16 Come, hear, all ye who fear God, And I recount what he did for my soul.

17 Unto Him [with] my mouth I have called, And exaltation [is] under my tongue.

18 Iniquity, if I have seen in my heart, The Lord doth not hear.

19 But God hath heard, He hath attended to the voice of my prayer.

20 Blessed [is] God, Who hath not turned aside my prayer, And His loving-kindness, from me!

Psalms 68

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm, a song of David. Rise doth God--scattered are His enemies! And those hating Him flee from His face.

2 As the driving away of smoke Thou drivest away, As the melting of wax before fire, The wicked perish at the presence of God.

3 And the righteous rejoice, they exult before God, And they joy with gladness.

4 Sing ye to God--praise His name, Raise up a highway for Him who is riding in deserts, In Jah [is] His name, and exult before Him.

5 Father of the fatherless, and judge of the widows, [Is] God in His holy habitation.

6 God--causing the lonely to dwell at home, Bringing out bound ones into prosperity, Only--the refractory have inhabited a dry place.

7 O God, in Thy going forth before Thy people, In Thy stepping through the wilderness, Selah.

8 The earth hath shaken, Yea, the heavens have dropped before God, This Sinai--before God, the God of Israel.

9 A shower of free-will gifts thou shakest out, O God. Thine inheritance, when it hath been weary, Thou hast established it.

10 Thy company have dwelt in it, Thou preparest in Thy goodness for the poor, O God.

11 The Lord doth give the saying, The female proclaimers [are] a numerous host.

12 Kings of hosts flee utterly away, And a female inhabitant of the house apportioneth spoil.

13 Though ye do lie between two boundaries, Wings of a dove covered with silver, And her pinions with yellow gold.

14 When the Mighty spreadeth kings in it, It doth snow in Salmon.

15 A hill of God [is] the hill of Bashan, A hill of heights [is] the hill of Bashan.

16 Why do ye envy, O high hills, The hill God hath desired for His seat? Jehovah also doth tabernacle for ever.

17 The chariots of God [are] myriads, thousands of changes, The Lord [is] among them, in Sinai, in the sanctuary.

18 Thou hast ascended on high, Thou hast taken captive captivity, Thou hast taken gifts for men, That even the refractory may rest, O Jah God.

19 Blessed [is] the Lord, day by day He layeth on us. God Himself [is] our salvation. Selah.

20 God Himself [is] to us a God for deliverances, And Jehovah Lord hath the outgoings of death.

21 Only--God doth smite The head of His enemies, The hairy crown of a habitual walker in his guilt.

22 The Lord said: `From Bashan I bring back, I bring back from the depths of the sea.

23 So that thou dashest thy foot in blood, [In the blood of] enemies--the tongue of Thy dogs.'

24 They have seen Thy goings, O God, Goings of my God, my king, in the sanctuary.

25 Singers have been before, Behind [are] players on instruments, In the midst virgins playing with timbrels.

26 In assemblies bless ye God, The Lord--from the fountain of Israel.

27 There [is] little Benjamin their ruler, Heads of Judah their defence, Heads of Zebulun--heads of Naphtali.

28 Thy God hath commanded thy strength, Be strong, O God, this Thou hast wrought for us.

29 Because of Thy temple at Jerusalem, To Thee do kings bring a present.

30 Rebuke a beast of the reeds, a company of bulls, With calves of the peoples, Each humbling himself with pieces of silver, Scatter Thou peoples delighting in conflicts.

31 Come do fat ones out of Egypt, Cush causeth her hands to run to God.

32 Kingdoms of the earth, sing ye to God, Praise ye the Lord. Selah.

33 To him who is riding on the heavens of the heavens of old, Lo, He giveth with His voice a strong voice.

34 Ascribe ye strength to God, Over Israel [is] His excellency, and His strength in the clouds.

35 Fearful, O God, out of Thy sanctuaries, The God of Israel Himself, Giving strength and might to the people. Blessed [is] God!

Psalms 69

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Lilies,' by David. Save me, O God, for come have waters unto the soul.

2 I have sunk in deep mire, And there is no standing, I have come into the depths of the waters, And a flood hath overflown me.

3 I have been wearied with my calling, Burnt hath been my throat, Consumed have been mine eyes, waiting for my God.

4 Those hating me without cause Have been more than the hairs of my head, Mighty have been my destroyers, My lying enemies, That which I took not away--I bring back.

5 O God, Thou--Thou hast known Concerning my overturn, And my desolations from Thee have not been hid.

6 Let not those waiting on Thee be ashamed because of me, O Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, Let not those seeking Thee Blush because of me, O God of Israel.

7 For because of Thee I have borne reproach, Shame hath covered my face.

8 A stranger I have been to my brother, And a foreigner to sons of my mother.

9 For zeal for Thy house hath consumed me, And the reproaches of Thy reproachers Have fallen upon me.

10 And I weep in the fasting of my soul, And it is for a reproach to me.

11 And I make my clothing sackcloth, And I am to them for a simile.

12 Those sitting at the gate meditate concerning me, And those drinking strong drink, Play on instruments.

13 And I--my prayer [is] to Thee, O Jehovah, A time of good pleasure, O God, In the abundance of Thy kindness, Answer me in the truth of Thy salvation.

14 Deliver me from the mire, and let me not sink, Let me be delivered from those hating me, And from deep places of waters.

15 Let not a flood of waters overflow me, Nor let the deep swallow me up, Nor let the pit shut her mouth upon me.

16 Answer me, O Jehovah, for good [is] Thy kindness, According to the abundance Of Thy mercies turn Thou unto me,

17 And hide not Thy face from Thy servant, For I am in distress--haste, answer me.

18 Be near unto my soul--redeem it, Because of mine enemies ransom me.

19 Thou--Thou hast known my reproach, And my shame, and my blushing, Before Thee [are] all mine adversaries.

20 Reproach hath broken my heart, and I am sick, And I look for a bemoaner, and there is none, And for comforters, and I have found none.

21 And they give for my food gall, And for my thirst cause me to drink vinegar.

22 Their table before them is for a snare, And for a recompence--for a trap.

23 Darkened are their eyes from seeing, And their loins continually shake Thou.

24 Pour upon them Thine indignation, And the fierceness of Thine anger doth seize them.

25 Their tower is desolated, In their tents there is no dweller.

26 For they have pursued him Thou hast smitten, And recount of the pain of Thy pierced ones.

27 Give punishment for their iniquity, And they enter not into Thy righteousness.

28 They are blotted out of the book of life, And with the righteous are not written.

29 And I [am] afflicted and pained, Thy salvation, O God, doth set me on high.

30 I praise the name of God with a song, And I magnify Him with thanksgiving,

31 And it is better to Jehovah than an ox, A bullock--horned--hoofed.

32 The humble have seen--they rejoice, Ye who seek God--and your heart liveth.

33 For Jehovah hearkeneth unto the needy, And His bound ones He hath not despised.

34 The heavens and earth do praise Him, Seas, and every moving thing in them.

35 For God doth save Zion, And doth build the cities of Judah, And they have dwelt there, and possess it.

36 And the seed of His servants inherit it, And those loving His name dwell in it!

Psalms 71

1 In Thee, O Jehovah, I have trusted, Let me not be ashamed to the age.

2 In Thy righteousness Thou dost deliver me, And dost cause me to escape, Incline unto me Thine ear, and save me.

3 Be to me for a rock--a habitation, To go in continually, Thou hast given command to save me, For my rock and my bulwark [art] Thou.

4 O my God, cause me to escape From the hand of the wicked, From the hand of the perverse and violent.

5 For Thou [art] my hope, O Lord Jehovah, My trust from my youth.

6 By Thee I have been supported from the womb, From my mother's bowels Thou dost cut me out, In Thee [is] my praise continually.

7 As a wonder I have been to many, And Thou [art] my strong refuge.

8 Filled is my mouth [with] Thy praise, All the day [with] Thy beauty.

9 Cast me not off at the time of old age, According to the consumption of my power forsake me not.

10 For mine enemies have spoken against me, And those watching my soul have taken counsel together,

11 Saying, `God hath forsaken him, Pursue and catch him, for there is no deliverer.'

12 O God, be not far from me, O my God, for my help make haste.

13 They are ashamed, they are consumed, Who are opposing my soul, They are covered [with] reproach and blushing, Who are seeking my evil,

14 And I continually do wait with hope, And have added unto all Thy praise.

15 My mouth recounteth Thy righteousness, All the day Thy salvation, For I have not known the numbers.

16 I come in the might of the Lord Jehovah, I mention Thy righteousness--Thine only.

17 God, Thou hast taught me from my youth, And hitherto I declare Thy wonders.

18 And also unto old age and grey hairs, O God, forsake me not, Till I declare Thy strength to a generation, To every one that cometh Thy might.

19 And Thy righteousness, O God, [is] unto the heights, Because Thou hast done great things, O God, who [is] like Thee?

20 Because Thou hast showed me many and sad distresses, Thou turnest back--Thou revivest me, And from the depths of the earth, Thou turnest back--Thou bringest me up.

21 Thou dost increase my greatness, And Thou surroundest--Thou comfortest me,

22 I also thank Thee with a vessel of psaltery, Thy truth, O my God, I sing to Thee with a harp, O Holy One of Israel,

23 My lips cry aloud when I sing praise to Thee, And my soul that Thou hast redeemed,

24 My tongue also all the day uttereth Thy righteousness, Because ashamed--because confounded, Have been those seeking my evil!

Psalms 72

1 By Solomon. O God, Thy judgments to the king give, And Thy righteousness to the king's son.

2 He judgeth Thy people with righteousness, And Thy poor with judgment.

3 The mountains bear peace to the people, And the heights by righteousness.

4 He judgeth the poor of the people, Giveth deliverance to the sons of the needy, And bruiseth the oppressor.

5 They fear Thee with the sun, and before the moon, Generation--generations.

6 He cometh down as rain on mown grass, As showers--sprinkling the earth.

7 Flourish in his days doth the righteous, And abundance of peace till the moon is not.

8 And he ruleth from sea unto sea, And from the river unto the ends of earth.

9 Before him bow do the inhabitants of the dry places, And his enemies lick the dust.

10 Kings of Tarshish and of the isles send back a present. Kings of Sheba and Seba a reward bring near.

11 And all kings do bow themselves to him, All nations do serve him,

12 For he delivereth the needy who crieth, And the poor when he hath no helper,

13 He hath pity on the poor and needy, And the souls of the needy he saveth,

14 From fraud and from violence he redeemeth their soul, And precious is their blood in his eyes.

15 And he liveth, and giveth to him of the gold of Sheba, And prayeth for him continually, All the day he doth bless him.

16 There is a handful of corn in the earth, On the top of mountains, Shake like Lebanon doth its fruit, And they flourish out of the city as the herb of the earth.

17 His name is to the age, Before the sun is his name continued, And they bless themselves in him, All nations do pronounce him happy.

18 Blessed is Jehovah God, God of Israel, He alone is doing wonders,

19 And blessed [is] the Name of His honour to the age, And the whole earth is filled [with] His honour. Amen, and amen!

20 The prayers of David son of Jesse have been ended.

Psalms 73

1 A Psalm of Asaph. Only--good to Israel [is] God, to the clean of heart. And I--as a little thing, My feet have been turned aside,

2 As nothing, have my steps slipped, For I have been envious of the boastful,

3 The peace of the wicked I see, That there are no bands at their death,

4 And their might [is] firm.

5 In the misery of mortals they are not, And with common men they are not plagued.

6 Therefore hath pride encircled them, Violence covereth them as a dress.

7 Their eye hath come out from fat. The imaginations of the heart transgressed;

8 They do corruptly, And they speak in the wickedness of oppression, From on high they speak.

9 They have set in the heavens their mouth, And their tongue walketh in the earth.

10 Therefore do His people return hither, And waters of fulness are wrung out to them.

11 And they have said, `How hath God known? And is there knowledge in the Most High?'

12 Lo, these [are] the wicked and easy ones of the age, They have increased strength.

13 Only--a vain thing! I have purified my heart, And I wash in innocency my hands,

14 And I am plagued all the day, And my reproof [is] every morning.

15 If I have said, `I recount thus,' Lo, a generation of Thy sons I have deceived.

16 And I think to know this, Perverseness it [is] in mine eyes,

17 Till I come in to the sanctuaries of God, I attend to their latter end.

18 Only, in slippery places Thou dost set them, Thou hast caused them to fall to desolations.

19 How have they become a desolation as in a moment, They have been ended-- consumed from terrors.

20 As a dream from awakening, O Lord, In awaking, their image Thou despisest.

21 For my heart doth show itself violent, And my reins prick themselves,

22 And I am brutish, and do not know. A beast I have been with Thee.

23 And I [am] continually with Thee, Thou hast laid hold on my right hand.

24 With Thy counsel Thou dost lead me, And after honour dost receive me.

25 Whom have I in the heavens? And with Thee none I have desired in earth.

26 Consumed hath been my flesh and my heart, The rock of my heart and my portion [is] God to the age.

27 For, lo, those far from Thee do perish, Thou hast cut off every one, Who is going a whoring from Thee.

28 And I--nearness of God to me [is] good, I have placed in the Lord Jehovah my refuge, To recount all Thy works!

Psalms 74

1 An Instruction of Asaph. Why, O God, hast Thou cast off for ever? Thine anger smoketh against the flock of Thy pasture.

2 Remember Thy company. Thou didst purchase of old, Thou didst redeem the rod of Thy inheritance, This mount Zion--Thou didst dwell in it.

3 Lift up Thy steps to the perpetual desolations, Everything the enemy did wickedly in the sanctuary.

4 Roared have thine adversaries, In the midst of Thy meeting-places, They have set their ensigns as ensigns.

5 He is known as one bringing in on high Against a thicket of wood--axes.

6 And now, its carvings together With axe and hatchet they break down,

7 They have sent into fire Thy sanctuary, to the earth they polluted the tabernacle of Thy name,

8 They said in their hearts, `Let us oppress them together,' They did burn all the meeting-places of God in the land.

9 Our ensigns we have not seen, There is no more a prophet, Nor with us is one knowing how long.

10 Till when, O God, doth an adversary reproach? Doth an enemy despise thy name for ever?

11 Why dost Thou turn back Thy hand, Even Thy right hand? From the midst of Thy bosom remove [it].

12 And God [is] my king of old, Working salvation in the midst of the earth.

13 Thou hast broken by Thy strength a sea -[monster], Thou hast shivered Heads of dragons by the waters,

14 Thou hast broken the heads of leviathan, Thou makest him food, For the people of the dry places.

15 Thou hast cleaved a fountain and a stream, Thou hast dried up perennial flowings.

16 Thine [is] the day, also Thine [is] the night, Thou hast prepared a light giver--the sun.

17 Thou hast set up all the borders of earth, Summer and winter Thou hast formed them.

18 Remember this--an enemy reproached Jehovah, And a foolish people have despised Thy name.

19 Give not up to a company, The soul of Thy turtle-dove, The company of Thy poor ones forget not for ever.

20 Look attentively to the covenant, For the dark places of earth, Have been full of habitations of violence.

21 Let not the oppressed turn back ashamed, Let the poor and needy praise Thy name,

22 Arise, O God, plead Thy plea, Remember Thy reproach from a fool all the day.

23 Forget not the voice of Thine adversaries, The noise of Thy withstanders is going up continually!

Psalms 77

1 To the Overseer, for Jeduthun. --A Psalm of Asaph. My voice [is] to God, and I cry, my voice [is] to God, And He hath given ear unto me.

2 In a day of my distress the Lord I sought, My hand by night hath been spread out, And it doth not cease, My soul hath refused to be comforted.

3 I remember God, and make a noise, I meditate, and feeble is my spirit. Selah.

4 Thou hast taken hold of the watches of mine eyes, I have been moved, and I speak not.

5 I have reckoned the days of old, The years of the ages.

6 I remember my music in the night, With my heart I meditate, and my spirit doth search diligently:

7 To the ages doth the Lord cast off? Doth He add to be pleased no more?

8 Hath His kindness ceased for ever? The saying failed to all generations?

9 Hath God forgotten [His] favours? Hath He shut up in anger His mercies? Selah.

10 And I say: `My weakness is, The changes of the right hand of the Most High.'

11 I mention the doings of Jah, For I remember of old Thy wonders,

12 And I have meditated on all Thy working, And I talk concerning Thy doings.

13 O God, in holiness [is] Thy way, Who [is] a great god like God?

14 Thou [art] the God doing wonders. Thou hast made known among the peoples Thy strength,

15 Thou hast redeemed with strength Thy people, The sons of Jacob and Joseph. Selah.

16 The waters have seen Thee, O God, The waters have seen Thee, They are afraid-- also depths are troubled.

17 Poured out waters have thick clouds, The skies have given forth a noise, Also--Thine arrows go up and down.

18 The voice of Thy thunder [is] in the spheres, Lightnings have lightened the world, The earth hath trembled, yea, it shaketh.

19 In the sea [is] Thy way, And Thy paths [are] in many waters, And Thy tracks have not been known.

20 Thou hast led as a flock Thy people, By the hand of Moses and Aaron!

Psalms 78

1 An Instruction of Asaph. Give ear, O my people, to my law, Incline your ear to sayings of my mouth.

2 I open with a simile my mouth, I bring forth hidden things of old,

3 That we have heard and do know, And our fathers have recounted to us.

4 We do not hide from their sons, To a later generation recounting praises of Jehovah, And His strength, and His wonders that He hath done.

5 And He raiseth up a testimony in Jacob, And a law hath placed in Israel, That He commanded our fathers, To make them known to their sons.

6 So that a later generation doth know, Sons who are born, do rise and recount to their sons,

7 And place in God their confidence, And forget not the doings of God, But keep His commands.

8 And they are not like their fathers, A generation apostate and rebellious, A generation! it hath not prepared its heart, Nor stedfast with God [is] its spirit.

9 Sons of Ephraim--armed bearers of bow, Have turned in a day of conflict.

10 They have not kept the covenant of God, And in His law they have refused to walk,

11 And they forget His doings, And His wonders that He shewed them.

12 Before their fathers He hath done wonders, In the land of Egypt--the field of Zoan.

13 He cleft a sea, and causeth them to pass over, Yea, He causeth waters to stand as a heap.

14 And leadeth them with a cloud by day, And all the night with a light of fire.

15 He cleaveth rocks in a wilderness, And giveth drink--as the great deep.

16 And bringeth out streams from a rock, And causeth waters to come down as rivers.

17 And they add still to sin against Him, To provoke the Most High in the dry place.

18 And they try God in their heart, To ask food for their lust.

19 And they speak against God--they said: `Is God able to array a table in a wilderness?'

20 Lo, He hath smitten a rock, And waters flow, yea, streams overflow. `Also--bread [is] He able to give? Doth He prepare flesh for His people?'

21 Therefore hath Jehovah heard, And He sheweth Himself wroth, And fire hath been kindled against Jacob, And anger also hath gone up against Israel,

22 For they have not believed in God, Nor have they trusted in His salvation.

23 And He commandeth clouds from above, Yea, doors of the heavens He hath opened.

24 And He raineth on them manna to eat, Yea, corn of heaven He hath given to them.

25 Food of the mighty hath each eaten, Venison He sent to them to satiety.

26 He causeth an east wind to journey in the heavens, And leadeth by His strength a south wind,

27 And He raineth on them flesh as dust, And as sand of the seas--winged fowl,

28 And causeth [it] to fall in the midst of His camp, Round about His tabernacles.

29 And they eat, and are greatly satisfied, And their desire He bringeth to them.

30 They have not been estranged from their desire, Yet [is] their food in their mouth,

31 And the anger of God hath gone up against them, And He slayeth among their fat ones, And youths of Israel He caused to bend.

32 With all this they have sinned again, And have not believed in His wonders.

33 And He consumeth in vanity their days, And their years in trouble.

34 If He slew them, then they sought Him, And turned back, and sought God earnestly,

35 And they remember that God [is] their rock, And God Most High their redeemer.

36 And--they deceive Him with their mouth, And with their tongue do lie to Him,

37 And their heart hath not been right with Him, And they have not been stedfast in His covenant.

38 And He--the Merciful One, Pardoneth iniquity, and destroyeth not, And hath often turned back His anger, And waketh not up all His fury.

39 And He remembereth that they [are] flesh, A wind going on--and it returneth not.

40 How often do they provoke Him in the wilderness, Grieve Him in the desolate place?

41 Yea, they turn back, and try God, And the Holy One of Israel have limited.

42 They have not remembered His hand The day He ransomed them from the adversary.

43 When He set His signs in Egypt, And His wonders in the field of Zoan,

44 And He turneth to blood their streams, And their floods they drink not.

45 He sendeth among them the beetle, and it consumeth them, And the frog, and it destroyeth them,

46 And giveth to the caterpillar their increase, And their labour to the locust.

47 He destroyeth with hail their vine, And their sycamores with frost,

48 And delivereth up to the hail their beasts, And their cattle to the burning flames.

49 He sendeth on them the fury of His anger, Wrath, and indignation, and distress--A discharge of evil messengers.

50 He pondereth a path for His anger, He kept not back their soul from death, Yea, their life to the pestilence He delivered up.

51 And He smiteth every first-born in Egypt, The first-fruit of the strong in tents of Ham.

52 And causeth His people to journey as a flock, And guideth them as a drove in a wilderness,

53 And He leadeth them confidently, And they have not been afraid, And their enemies hath the sea covered.

54 And He bringeth them in unto the border of His sanctuary, This mountain His right hand had got,

55 And casteth out nations from before them, And causeth them to fall in the line of inheritance, And causeth the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents,

56 And they tempt and provoke God Most High, And His testimonies have not kept.

57 And they turn back, And deal treacherously like their fathers, They have been turned like a deceitful bow,

58 And make Him angry with their high places, And with their graven images make Him zealous,

59 God hath heard, and sheweth Himself wroth. And kicketh exceedingly against Israel.

60 And He leaveth the tabernacle of Shiloh, The tent He had placed among men,

61 And He giveth His strength to captivity, And His beauty into the hand of an adversary,

62 And delivereth up to the sword His people, And with His inheritance shewed Himself angry.

63 His young men hath fire consumed, And His virgins have not been praised.

64 His priests by the sword have fallen, And their widows weep not.

65 And the Lord waketh as a sleeper, As a mighty one crying aloud from wine.

66 And He smiteth His adversaries backward, A reproach age-during He hath put on them,

67 And He kicketh against the tent of Joseph, And on the tribe of Ephraim hath not fixed.

68 And He chooseth the tribe of Judah, With mount Zion that He loved,

69 And buildeth His sanctuary as a high place, Like the earth, He founded it to the age.

70 And He fixeth on David His servant, And taketh him from the folds of a flock,

71 From behind suckling ones He hath brought him in, To rule over Jacob His people, And over Israel His inheritance.

72 And he ruleth them according to the integrity of his heart, And by the skilfulness of his hands leadeth them!

Psalms 79

1 A Psalm of Asaph. O God, nations have come into Thy inheritance, They have defiled Thy holy temple, They made Jerusalem become heaps,

2 They gave the dead bodies of Thy servants Food for the fowls of the heavens, The flesh of Thy saints For the wild beast of the earth.

3 They have shed their blood As water round about Jerusalem, And there is none burying.

4 We have been a reproach to our neighbours, A scorn and a derision to our surrounders.

5 Till when, O Jehovah? art Thou angry for ever? Thy jealousy doth burn as fire.

6 Pour Thy fury on the nations who have not known Thee, And on kingdoms that have not called in Thy name.

7 For [one] hath devoured Jacob, And his habitation they have made desolate.

8 Remember not for us the iniquities of forefathers, Haste, let Thy mercies go before us, For we have been very weak.

9 Help us, O God of our salvation, Because of the honour of Thy name, And deliver us, and cover over our sins, For Thy name's sake.

10 Why do the nations say, `Where [is] their God?' Let be known among the nations before our eyes, The vengeance of the blood of Thy servants that is shed.

11 Let the groaning of the prisoner come in before Thee, According to the greatness of Thine arm, Leave Thou the sons of death.

12 And turn Thou back to our neighbours, Sevenfold unto their bosom, their reproach, Wherewith they reproached Thee, O Lord.

13 And we, Thy people, and the flock of Thy pasture, We give thanks to Thee to the age, To all generations we recount Thy praise!

Psalms 80

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Lilies.' A testimony of Asaph. --A Psalm. Shepherd of Israel, give ear, Leading Joseph as a flock, Inhabiting the cherubs--shine forth,

2 Before Ephraim, and Benjamin, and Manasseh, Wake up Thy might, and come for our salvation.

3 O God, cause us to turn back, And cause Thy face to shine, and we are saved.

4 Jehovah, God of Hosts, till when? Thou hast burned against the prayer of Thy people.

5 Thou hast caused them to eat bread of tears, And causest them to drink With tears a third time.

6 Thou makest us a strife to our neighbours, And our enemies mock at it.

7 God of Hosts, turn us back, And cause Thy face to shine, and we are saved.

8 A vine out of Egypt Thou dost bring, Thou dost cast out nations, and plantest it.

9 Thou hast looked before it, and dost root it, And it filleth the land,

10 Covered have been hills [with] its shadow, And its boughs [are] cedars of God.

11 It sendeth forth its branches unto the sea, And unto the river its sucklings.

12 Why hast Thou broken down its hedges, And all passing by the way have plucked it?

13 A boar out of the forest doth waste it, And a wild beast of the fields consumeth it.

14 God of Hosts, turn back, we beseech Thee, Look from heaven, and see, and inspect this vine,

15 And the root that Thy right hand planted, And the branch Thou madest strong for Thee,

16 Burnt with fire--cut down, From the rebuke of Thy face they perish.

17 Let Thy hand be on the man of Thy right hand, On the son of man Thou hast strengthened for Thyself.

18 And we do not go back from Thee, Thou dost revive us, and in Thy name we call.

19 O Jehovah, God of Hosts, turn us back, Cause Thy face to shine, and we are saved!

Psalms 81

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Gittith.' By Asaph. Cry aloud to God our strength, Shout to the God of Jacob.

2 Lift up a song, and give out a timbrel, A pleasant harp with psaltery.

3 Blow in the month a trumpet, In the new moon, at the day of our festival,

4 For a statute to Israel it [is], An ordinance of the God of Jacob.

5 A testimony on Joseph He hath placed it, In his going forth over the land of Egypt. A lip, I have not known--I hear.

6 From the burden his shoulder I turned aside, His hands from the basket pass over.

7 In distress thou hast called and I deliver thee, I answer thee in the secret place of thunder, I try thee by the waters of Meribah. Selah.

8 Hear, O My people, and I testify to thee, O Israel, if thou dost hearken to me:

9 There is not in thee a strange god, And thou bowest not thyself to a strange god.

10 I [am] Jehovah thy God, Who bringeth thee up out of the land of Egypt. Enlarge thy mouth, and I fill it.

11 But, My people hearkened not to My voice, And Israel hath not consented to Me.

12 And I send them away in the enmity of their heart, They walk in their own counsels.

13 O that My people were hearkening to Me, Israel in My ways would walk.

14 As a little thing their enemies I cause to bow, And against their adversaries I turn back My hand,

15 Those hating Jehovah feign obedience to Him, But their time is--to the age.

16 He causeth him to eat of the fat of wheat, And [with] honey from a rock I satisfy thee!

Psalms 83

1 A Song, --A Psalm of Asaph. O God, let there be no silence to Thee, Be not silent, nor be quiet, O God.

2 For, lo, Thine enemies do roar, And those hating Thee have lifted up the head,

3 Against Thy people they take crafty counsel, And consult against Thy hidden ones.

4 They have said, `Come, And we cut them off from [being] a nation, And the name of Israel is not remembered any more.'

5 For they consulted in heart together, Against Thee a covenant they make,

6 Tents of Edom, and Ishmaelites, Moab, and the Hagarenes,

7 Gebal, and Ammon, and Amalek, Philistia with inhabitants of Tyre,

8 Asshur also is joined with them, They have been an arm to sons of Lot. Selah.

9 Do to them as [to] Midian, As [to] Sisera, as [to] Jabin, at the stream Kishon.

10 They were destroyed at Endor, They were dung for the ground!

11 Make their nobles as Oreb and as Zeeb, And as Zebah and Zalmunna all their princes,

12 Who have said, `Let us occupy for ourselves The comely places of God.'

13 O my God, make them as a rolling thing, As stubble before wind.

14 As a fire doth burn a forest, And as a flame setteth hills on fire,

15 So dost Thou pursue them with Thy whirlwind, And with Thy hurricane troublest them.

16 Fill their faces [with] shame, And they seek Thy name, O Jehovah.

17 They are ashamed and troubled for ever, Yea, they are confounded and lost.

18 And they know that Thou--(Thy name [is] Jehovah--by Thyself,) [Art] the Most High over all the earth!

Psalms 84

1 To the Overseer. --`On the Gittith By sons of Korah.' --A Psalm. How beloved Thy tabernacles, Jehovah of Hosts!

2 My soul desired, yea, it hath also been consumed, For the courts of Jehovah, My heart and my flesh cry aloud unto the living God,

3 (Even a sparrow hath found a house, And a swallow a nest for herself, Where she hath placed her brood,) Thine altars, O Jehovah of Hosts, My king and my God.

4 O the happiness of those inhabiting Thy house, Yet do they praise Thee. Selah.

5 O the happiness of a man whose strength is in Thee, Highways [are] in their heart.

6 Those passing through a valley of weeping, A fountain do make it, Blessings also cover the director.

7 They go from strength unto strength, He appeareth unto God in Zion.

8 O Jehovah, God of Hosts, hear my prayer, Give ear, O God of Jacob. Selah.

9 Our shield, see, O God, And behold the face of Thine anointed,

10 For good [is] a day in Thy courts, O Teacher! I have chosen rather to be at the threshold, In the house of my God, Than to dwell in tents of wickedness.

11 For a sun and a shield [is] Jehovah God, Grace and honour doth Jehovah give. He withholdeth not good To those walking in uprightness.

12 Jehovah of Hosts! O the happiness of a man trusting in Thee.

Psalms 85

1 To the Overseer. --By sons of Korah. A Psalm. Thou hast accepted, O Jehovah, Thy land, Thou hast turned [to] the captivity of Jacob.

2 Thou hast borne away the iniquity of Thy people, Thou hast covered all their sin. Selah.

3 Thou hast gathered up all Thy wrath, Thou hast turned back from the fierceness of Thine anger.

4 Turn back [to] us, O God of our salvation, And make void Thine anger with us.

5 To the age art Thou angry against us? Dost Thou draw out Thine anger To generation and generation?

6 Dost Thou not turn back? Thou revivest us, And Thy people do rejoice in Thee.

7 Show us, O Jehovah, thy kindness, And Thy salvation Thou dost give to us.

8 I hear what God Jehovah speaketh, For He speaketh peace unto His people, And unto His saints, and they turn not back to folly.

9 Only, near to those fearing Him [is] His salvation, That honour may dwell in our land.

10 Kindness and truth have met, Righteousness and peace have kissed,

11 Truth from the earth springeth up, And righteousness from heaven looketh out,

12 Jehovah also giveth that which is good, And our land doth give its increase.

13 Righteousness before Him goeth, And maketh His footsteps for a way!

Psalms 86

1 A Prayer of David. Incline, O Jehovah, Thine ear, Answer me, for I [am] poor and needy.

2 Keep my soul, for I [am] pious, Save Thy servant--who is trusting to Thee, O Thou, my God.

3 Favour me, O Lord, for to Thee I call all the day.

4 Rejoice the soul of Thy servant, For unto Thee, O Lord, my soul I lift up.

5 For Thou, Lord, [art] good and forgiving. And abundant in kindness to all calling Thee.

6 Hear, O Jehovah, my prayer, And attend to the voice of my supplications.

7 In a day of my distress I call Thee, For Thou dost answer me.

8 There is none like Thee among the gods, O Lord, And like Thy works there are none.

9 All nations that Thou hast made Come and bow themselves before Thee, O Lord, And give honour to Thy name.

10 For great [art] Thou, and doing wonders, Thou [art] God Thyself alone.

11 Show me, O Jehovah, Thy way, I walk in Thy truth, My heart doth rejoice to fear Thy name.

12 I confess Thee, O Lord my God, with all my heart, And I honour Thy name to the age.

13 For Thy kindness [is] great toward me, And Thou hast delivered my soul from the lowest Sheol.

14 O God, the proud have risen up against me, And a company of the terrible sought my soul, And have not placed Thee before them,

15 And Thou, O Lord, [art] God, merciful and gracious, Slow to anger, and abundant in kindness and truth.

16 Look unto me, and favour me, Give Thy strength to Thy servant, And give salvation to a son of Thine handmaid.

17 Do with me a sign for good, And those hating me see and are ashamed, For Thou, O Jehovah, hast helped me, Yea, Thou hast comforted me!

Psalms 88

1 A Song, a Psalm, by sons of Korah, to the Overseer, `Concerning the Sickness of Afflictions.' --An instruction, by Heman the Ezrahite. O Jehovah, God of my salvation, Daily I have cried, nightly before Thee,

2 My prayer cometh in before Thee, Incline Thine ear to my loud cry,

3 For my soul hath been full of evils, And my life hath come to Sheol.

4 I have been reckoned with those going down [to] the pit, I have been as a man without strength.

5 Among the dead--free, As pierced ones lying in the grave, Whom Thou hast not remembered any more, Yea, they by Thy hand have been cut off.

6 Thou hast put me in the lowest pit, In dark places, in depths.

7 Upon me hath Thy fury lain, And [with] all Thy breakers Thou hast afflicted. Selah.

8 Thou hast put mine acquaintance far from me, Thou hast made me an abomination to them, Shut up--I go not forth.

9 Mine eye hath grieved because of affliction, I called Thee, O Jehovah, all the day, I have spread out unto Thee my hands.

10 To the dead dost Thou do wonders? Do Rephaim rise? do they thank Thee? Selah.

11 Is Thy kindness recounted in the grave? Thy faithfulness in destruction?

12 Are Thy wonders known in the darkness? And Thy righteousness in the land of forgetfulness?

13 And I, unto Thee, O Jehovah, I have cried, And in the morning doth my prayer come before Thee.

14 Why, O Jehovah, castest Thou off my soul? Thou hidest Thy face from me.

15 I [am] afflicted, and expiring from youth, I have borne Thy terrors--I pine away.

16 Over me hath Thy wrath passed, Thy terrors have cut me off,

17 They have surrounded me as waters all the day, They have gone round against me together,

18 Thou hast put far from me lover and friend, Mine acquaintance [is] the place of darkness!

Psalms 89

1 An instruction, by Ethan the Ezrahite. Of the kind acts of Jehovah, to the age I sing, To all generations I make known Thy faithfulness with my mouth,

2 For I said, `To the age is kindness built, The heavens! Thou dost establish Thy faithfulness in them.'

3 I have made a covenant for My chosen, I have sworn to David My servant:

4 `Even to the age do I establish thy seed, And have built to generation and generation thy throne. Selah.

5 and the heavens confess Thy wonders, O Jehovah, Thy faithfulness also [is] in an assembly of holy ones.

6 For who in the sky, Compareth himself to Jehovah? Is like to Jehovah among sons of the mighty?

7 God is very terrible, In the secret counsel of His holy ones, And fearful over all surrounding Him.

8 O Jehovah, God of Hosts, Who [is] like Thee--a strong Jah? And Thy faithfulness [is] round about Thee.

9 Thou [art] ruler over the pride of the sea, In the lifting up of its billows Thou dost restrain them.

10 Thou hast bruised Rahab, as one wounded. With the arm of Thy strength Thou hast scattered Thine enemies.

11 Thine [are] the heavens--the earth also [is] Thine, The habitable world and its fulness, Thou hast founded them.

12 North and south Thou hast appointed them, Tabor and Hermon in Thy name do sing.

13 Thou hast an arm with might, Strong is Thy hand--high Thy right hand.

14 Righteousness and judgment [Are] the fixed place of Thy throne, Kindness and truth go before Thy face.

15 O the happiness of the people knowing the shout, O Jehovah, in the light of Thy face they walk habitually.

16 In Thy name they rejoice all the day, And in Thy righteousness they are exalted,

17 For the beauty of their strength [art] Thou, And in Thy good will is our horn exalted,

18 For of Jehovah [is] our shield, And of the Holy One of Israel our king.

19 Then Thou hast spoken in vision, To Thy saint, yea, Thou sayest, I have placed help upon a mighty one, Exalted a chosen one out of the people,

20 I have found David My servant, With My holy oil I have anointed him.

21 With whom My hand is established, My arm also doth strengthen him.

22 An enemy exacteth not upon him, And a son of perverseness afflicteth him not.

23 And I have beaten down before him his adversaries, And those hating him I plague,

24 And My faithfulness and kindness [are] with him, And in My name is his horn exalted.

25 And I have set on the sea his hand, And on the rivers his right hand.

26 He proclaimeth me: `Thou [art] my Father, My God, and the rock of my salvation.'

27 I also first-born do appoint him, Highest of the kings of the earth.

28 To the age I keep for him My kindness, And My covenant [is] stedfast with him.

29 And I have set his seed for ever, And his throne as the days of the heavens.

30 If his sons forsake My law, And in My judgments do not walk;

31 If My statutes they pollute, And My commands do not keep,

32 I have looked after with a rod their transgression, And with strokes their iniquity,

33 And My kindness I break not from him, Nor do I deal falsely in My faithfulness.

34 I profane not My covenant, And that which is going forth from My lips I change not.

35 Once I have sworn by My holiness, I lie not to David,

36 His seed is to the age, And his throne [is] as the sun before Me,

37 As the moon it is established--to the age, And the witness in the sky is stedfast. Selah.

38 And Thou, Thou hast cast off, and dost reject, Thou hast shown Thyself wroth With Thine anointed,

39 Hast rejected the covenant of Thy servant, Thou hast polluted to the earth his crown,

40 Thou hast broken down all his hedges, Thou hast made his fenced places a ruin.

41 Spoiled him have all passing by the way, He hath been a reproach to his neighbours,

42 Thou hast exalted the right hand of his adversaries, Thou hast caused all his enemies to rejoice.

43 Also--Thou turnest back the sharpness of his sword, And hast not established him in battle,

44 Hast caused [him] to cease from his brightness, And his throne to the earth hast cast down.

45 Thou hast shortened the days of his youth, Hast covered him over [with] shame. Selah.

46 Till when, O Jehovah, art Thou hidden? For ever doth Thy fury burn as fire?

47 Remember, I pray Thee, what [is] life-time? Wherefore in vain hast Thou created All the sons of men?

48 Who [is] the man that liveth, and doth not see death? He delivereth his soul from the hand of Sheol. Selah.

49 Where [are] Thy former kindnesses, O Lord. Thou hast sworn to David in Thy faithfulness,

50 Remember, O Lord, the reproach of Thy servants, I have borne in my bosom all the strivings of the peoples,

51 Wherewith Thine enemies reproached, O Jehovah, Wherewith they have reproached The steps of Thine anointed.

52 Blessed [is] Jehovah to the age. Amen, and amen!

Psalms 90

1 A Prayer of Moses, the man of God. Lord, a habitation Thou--Thou hast been, To us- -in generation and generation,

2 Before mountains were brought forth, And Thou dost form the earth and the world, Even from age unto age Thou [art] God.

3 Thou turnest man unto a bruised thing, And sayest, Turn back, ye sons of men.

4 For a thousand years in Thine eyes [are] as yesterday, For it passeth on, yea, a watch by night.

5 Thou hast inundated them, they are asleep, In the morning as grass he changeth.

6 In the morning it flourisheth, and hath changed, At evening it is cut down, and hath withered.

7 For we were consumed in Thine anger, And in Thy fury we have been troubled.

8 Thou hast set our iniquities before Thee, Our hidden things at the light of Thy face,

9 For all our days pined away in Thy wrath, We consumed our years as a meditation.

10 Days of our years, in them [are] seventy years, And if, by reason of might, eighty years, Yet [is] their enlargement labour and vanity, For it hath been cut off hastily, and we fly away.

11 Who knoweth the power of Thine anger? And according to Thy fear--Thy wrath?

12 To number our days aright let [us] know, And we bring the heart to wisdom.

13 Turn back, O Jehovah, till when? And repent concerning Thy servants.

14 Satisfy us at morn [with] Thy kindness, And we sing and rejoice all our days.

15 Cause us to rejoice according to the days Wherein Thou hast afflicted us, The years we have seen evil.

16 Let Thy work appear unto Thy servants, And Thine honour on their sons.

17 And let the pleasantness of Jehovah our God be upon us, And the work of our hands establish on us, Yea, the work of our hands establish it!

Psalms 91

1 He who is dwelling In the secret place of the Most High, In the shade of the Mighty lodgeth habitually,

2 He is saying of Jehovah, `My refuge, and my bulwark, my God, I trust in Him,'

3 For He delivereth thee from the snare of a fowler, From a calamitous pestilence.

4 With His pinion He covereth thee over, And under His wings thou dost trust, A shield and buckler [is] His truth.

5 Thou art not afraid of fear by night, Of arrow that flieth by day,

6 Of pestilence in thick darkness that walketh, Of destruction that destroyeth at noon,

7 There fall at thy side a thousand, And a myriad at thy right hand, Unto thee it cometh not nigh.

8 But with thine eyes thou lookest, And the reward of the wicked thou seest,

9 (For Thou, O Jehovah, [art] my refuge,) The Most High thou madest thy habitation.

10 Evil happeneth not unto thee, And a plague cometh not near thy tent,

11 For His messengers He chargeth for thee, To keep thee in all thy ways,

12 On the hands they bear thee up, Lest thou smite against a stone thy foot.

13 On lion and asp thou treadest, Thou trampest young lion and dragon.

14 Because in Me he hath delighted, I also deliver him--I set him on high, Because he hath known My name.

15 He doth call Me, and I answer him, I [am] with him in distress, I deliver him, and honour him.

16 With length of days I satisfy him, And I cause him to look on My salvation!

Psalms 92

1 A Psalm. --A Song for the sabbath-day. Good to give thanks to Jehovah, And to sing praises to Thy name, O Most High,

2 To declare in the morning Thy kindness, And Thy faithfulness in the nights.

3 On ten strings and on psaltery, On higgaion, with harp.

4 For Thou hast caused me to rejoice, O Jehovah, in Thy work, Concerning the works of Thy hands I sing.

5 How great have been Thy works, O Jehovah, Very deep have been Thy thoughts.

6 A brutish man doth not know, And a fool understandeth not this; --

7 When the wicked flourish as a herb, And blossom do all workers of iniquity--For their being destroyed for ever and ever!

8 And Thou [art] high to the age, O Jehovah.

9 For, lo, Thine enemies, O Jehovah, For, lo, Thine enemies, do perish, Separate themselves do all workers of iniquity.

10 And Thou exaltest as a reem my horn, I have been anointed with fresh oil.

11 And mine eye looketh on mine enemies, Of those rising up against me, The evil doers, do mine ears hear.

12 The righteous as a palm-tree flourisheth, As a cedar in Lebanon he groweth.

13 Those planted in the house of Jehovah, In the courts of our God do flourish.

14 Still they bring forth in old age, Fat and flourishing are they,

15 To declare that upright [is] Jehovah my rock, And there is no perverseness in Him!

Psalms 94

1 God of vengeance--Jehovah! God of vengeance, shine forth.

2 Be lifted up, O Judge of the earth, Send back a recompence on the proud.

3 Till when [do] the wicked, O Jehovah? Till when do the wicked exult?

4 They utter--they speak an old saw, All working iniquity do boast themselves.

5 Thy people, O Jehovah, they bruise, And Thine inheritance they afflict.

6 Widow and sojourner they slay, And fatherless ones they murder.

7 And they say, `Jehovah doth not see, And the God of Jacob doth not consider.'

8 Consider, ye brutish among the people, And ye foolish, when do ye act wisely?

9 He who planteth the ear doth He not hear? He who formeth the eye doth He not see?

10 He who is instructing nations, Doth He not reprove? He who is teaching man knowledge [is] Jehovah.

11 He knoweth the thoughts of man, that they [are] vanity.

12 O the happiness of the man Whom Thou instructest, O Jah, And out of Thy law teachest him,

13 To give rest to him from days of evil, While a pit is digged for the wicked.

14 For Jehovah leaveth not His people, And His inheritance forsaketh not.

15 For to righteousness judgment turneth back, And after it all the upright of heart,

16 Who riseth up for me with evil doers? Who stationeth himself for me with workers of iniquity?

17 Unless Jehovah [were] a help to me, My soul had almost inhabited silence.

18 If I have said, `My foot hath slipped,' Thy kindness, O Jehovah, supporteth me.

19 In the abundance of my thoughts within me, Thy comforts delight my soul.

20 Is a throne of mischief joined [with] Thee? A framer of perverseness by statute?

21 They decree against the soul of the righteous, And innocent blood declare wicked.

22 And Jehovah is for a high place to me, And my God [is] for a rock--my refuge,

23 And turneth back on them their iniquity, And in their wickedness cutteth them off; Jehovah our God doth cut them off!

Psalms 96

1 Sing to Jehovah a new song, Sing to Jehovah all the earth.

2 Sing to Jehovah, bless His name, Proclaim from day to day His salvation.

3 Declare among nations His honour, Among all the peoples His wonders.

4 For great [is] Jehovah, and praised greatly, Fearful He [is] over all gods.

5 For all the gods of the peoples [are] nought, And Jehovah made the heavens.

6 Honour and majesty [are] before Him, Strength and beauty in His sanctuary.

7 Ascribe to Jehovah, O families of the peoples, Ascribe to Jehovah honour and strength.

8 Ascribe to Jehovah the honour of His name, Lift up a present and come in to His courts.

9 Bow yourselves to Jehovah, In the honour of holiness, Be afraid of His presence, all the earth.

10 Say among nations, `Jehovah hath reigned, Also--established is the world, unmoved, He judgeth the peoples in uprightness.'

11 The heavens joy, and the earth is joyful, The sea and its fulness roar.

12 The field exulteth, and all that [is] in it, Then sing do all trees of the forest,

13 Before Jehovah, for He hath come, For He hath come to judge the earth. He judgeth the world in righteousness, And the peoples in His faithfulness!

Psalms 97

1 Jehovah hath reigned, The earth is joyful, many isles rejoice.

2 Cloud and darkness [are] round about Him, Righteousness and judgment the basis of His throne.

3 Fire before Him goeth, And burneth round about His adversaries.

4 Lightened have His lightnings the world, The earth hath seen, and is pained.

5 Hills, like wax, melted before Jehovah, Before the Lord of all the earth.

6 The heavens declared His righteousness, And all the peoples have seen His honour.

7 Ashamed are all servants of a graven image, Those boasting themselves in idols, Bow yourselves to him, all ye gods.

8 Zion hath heard and rejoiceth, And daughters of Judah are joyful, Because of Thy judgments, O Jehovah.

9 For Thou, Jehovah, [art] Most High over all the earth, Greatly Thou hast been exalted over all gods.

10 Ye who love Jehovah, hate evil, He is keeping the souls of His saints, From the hand of the wicked he delivereth them.

11 Light [is] sown for the righteous, And for the upright of heart--joy.

12 Rejoice, ye righteous, in Jehovah, And give thanks at the remembrance of his holiness!

Psalms 102

1 A Prayer of the afflicted when he is feeble, and before Jehovah poureth out his plaint. O Jehovah, hear my prayer, yea, my cry to Thee cometh.

2 Hide not Thou Thy face from me, In a day of mine adversity, Incline unto me Thine ear, In the day I call, haste, answer me.

3 For consumed in smoke have been my days, And my bones as a fire-brand have burned.

4 Smitten as the herb, and withered, is my heart, For I have forgotten to eat my bread.

5 From the voice of my sighing Hath my bone cleaved to my flesh.

6 I have been like to a pelican of the wilderness, I have been as an owl of the dry places.

7 I have watched, and I am As a bird alone on the roof.

8 All the day mine enemies reproached me, Those mad at me have sworn against me.

9 Because ashes as bread I have eaten, And my drink with weeping have mingled,

10 From Thine indignation and Thy wrath, For Thou hast lifted me up, And dost cast me down.

11 My days as a shadow [are] stretched out, And I--as the herb I am withered.

12 And Thou, O Jehovah, to the age abidest, And Thy memorial to all generations.

13 Thou--Thou risest--Thou pitiest Zion, For the time to favour her, For the appointed time hath come.

14 For Thy servants have been pleased with her stones, And her dust they favour.

15 And nations fear the name of Jehovah, And all kings of the earth Thine honour,

16 For Jehovah hath builded Zion, He hath been seen in His honour,

17 He turned unto the prayer of the destitute, And He hath not despised their prayer.

18 This is written for a later generation, And the people created do praise Jah.

19 For He hath looked From the high place of His sanctuary. Jehovah from heaven unto earth looked attentively,

20 To hear the groan of the prisoner, To loose sons of death,

21 To declare in Zion the name of Jehovah, And His praise in Jerusalem,

22 In the peoples being gathered together, And the kingdoms--to serve Jehovah.

23 He hath humbled in the way my power, He hath shortened my days.

24 I say, `My God, take me not up in the midst of my days,' Through all generations [are] Thine years.

25 Beforetime the earth Thou didst found, And the work of Thy hands [are] the heavens.

26 They--They perish, and Thou remainest, And all of them as a garment become old, As clothing Thou changest them, And they are changed.

27 And Thou [art] the same, and Thine years are not finished.

28 The sons of Thy servants do continue, And their seed before Thee is established!

Psalms 103

1 By David. Bless, O my soul, Jehovah, And all my inward parts--His Holy Name.

2 Bless, O my soul, Jehovah, And forget not all His benefits,

3 Who is forgiving all thine iniquities, Who is healing all thy diseases,

4 Who is redeeming from destruction thy life, Who is crowning thee--kindness and mercies,

5 Who is satisfying with good thy desire, Renew itself as an eagle doth thy youth.

6 Jehovah is doing righteousness and judgments For all the oppressed.

7 He maketh known His ways to Moses, To the sons of Israel His acts.

8 Merciful and gracious [is] Jehovah, Slow to anger, and abundant in mercy.

9 Not for ever doth He strive, Nor to the age doth He watch.

10 Not according to our sins hath He done to us, Nor according to our iniquities Hath He conferred benefits upon us.

11 For, as the height of the heavens [is] above the earth, His kindness hath been mighty over those fearing Him.

12 As the distance of east from west He hath put far from us our transgressions.

13 As a father hath mercy on sons, Jehovah hath mercy on those fearing Him.

14 For He hath known our frame, Remembering that we [are] dust.

15 Mortal man! as grass [are] his days, As a flower of the field so he flourisheth;

16 For a wind hath passed over it, and it is not, And its place doth not discern it any more.

17 And the kindness of Jehovah [Is] from age even unto age on those fearing Him, And His righteousness to sons' sons,

18 To those keeping His covenant, And to those remembering His precepts to do them.

19 Jehovah in the heavens Hath established His throne, And His kingdom over all hath ruled.

20 Bless Jehovah, ye His messengers, Mighty in power--doing His word, To hearken to the voice of His Word.

21 Bless Jehovah, all ye His hosts, His ministers--doing His pleasure.

22 Bless Jehovah, all ye His works, In all places of His dominion. Bless, O my soul, Jehovah!

Psalms 104

1 Bless, O my soul, Jehovah! Jehovah, my God, Thou hast been very great, Honour and majesty Thou hast put on.

2 Covering himself [with] light as a garment, Stretching out the heavens as a curtain,

3 Who is laying the beam of His upper chambers in the waters, Who is making thick clouds His chariot, Who is walking on wings of wind,

4 Making His messengers--the winds, His ministers--the flaming fire.

5 He hath founded earth on its bases, It is not moved to the age and for ever.

6 The abyss! as with clothing Thou hast covered it, Above hills do waters stand.

7 From Thy rebuke they flee, From the voice of Thy thunder haste away.

8 They go up hills--they go down valleys, Unto a place Thou hast founded for them.

9 A border Thou hast set, they pass not over, They turn not back to cover the earth.

10 Who is sending forth fountains in valleys, Between hills they go on.

11 They water every beast of the field, Wild asses break their thirst.

12 By them the fowl of the heavens doth dwell, From between the branches They give forth the voice.

13 Watering hills from His upper chambers, From the fruit of Thy works is the earth satisfied.

14 Causing grass to spring up for cattle, And herb for the service of man, To bring forth bread from the earth,

15 And wine--it rejoiceth the heart of man, To cause the face to shine from oil, And bread--the heart of man it supporteth.

16 Satisfied [are] the trees of Jehovah, Cedars of Lebanon that He hath planted,

17 Where birds do make nests, The stork--the firs [are] her house.

18 The high hills [are] for wild goats, Rocks [are] a refuge for conies,

19 He made the moon for seasons, The sun hath known his place of entrance.

20 Thou settest darkness, and it is night, In it doth every beast of the forest creep.

21 The young lions are roaring for prey, And to seek from God their food.

22 The sun riseth, they are gathered, And in their dens they crouch.

23 Man goeth forth to his work, And to his service--till evening.

24 How many have been Thy works, O Jehovah, All of them in wisdom Thou hast made, Full is the earth of thy possessions.

25 This, the sea, great and broad of sides, There [are] moving things--innumerable, Living creatures--small with great.

26 There do ships go: leviathan, That Thou hast formed to play in it.

27 All of them unto Thee do look, To give their food in its season.

28 Thou dost give to them--they gather, Thou dost open Thy hand--they [are] satisfied [with] good.

29 Thou hidest Thy face--they are troubled, Thou gatherest their spirit--they expire, And unto their dust they turn back.

30 Thou sendest out Thy Spirit, they are created, And Thou renewest the face of the ground.

31 The honour of Jehovah is to the age, Jehovah rejoiceth in His works,

32 Who is looking to earth, and it trembleth, He cometh against hills, and they smoke.

33 I sing to Jehovah during my life, I sing praise to my God while I exist.

34 Sweet is my meditation on Him, I--I do rejoice in Jehovah.

35 Consumed are sinners from the earth, And the wicked are no more. Bless, O my soul, Jehovah. Praise ye Jehovah!

Psalms 105

1 Give ye thanks to Jehovah--call ye in His name, Make known among the peoples His acts.

2 Sing ye to Him--sing praise to Him, Meditate ye on all His wonders.

3 Boast yourselves in His Holy Name, The heart of those seeking Jehovah rejoiceth.

4 Seek ye Jehovah and His strength, Seek ye His face continually.

5 Remember His wonders that He did, His signs and the judgments of His mouth.

6 O seed of Abraham, His servant, O sons of Jacob, His chosen ones.

7 He [is] Jehovah our God, In all the earth [are] His judgments.

8 He hath remembered to the age His covenant, The word He commanded to a thousand generations,

9 That He hath made with Abraham, And His oath to Isaac,

10 And doth establish it to Jacob for a statute, To Israel--a covenant age-during,

11 Saying, `To thee I give the land of Canaan, The portion of your inheritance,'

12 In their being few in number, But a few, and sojourners in it.

13 And they go up and down, from nation unto nation, From a kingdom unto another people.

14 He hath not suffered any to oppress them And He reproveth for their sakes kings.

15 `Strike not against Mine anointed, And to My prophets do not evil.'

16 And He calleth a famine on the land, The whole staff of bread He hath broken.

17 He hath sent before them a man, For a servant hath Joseph been sold.

18 They have afflicted with fetters his feet, Iron hath entered his soul,

19 Till the time of the coming of His word The saying of Jehovah hath tried him.

20 The king hath sent, and looseth him, The ruler of the peoples, and draweth him out.

21 He hath made him lord of his house, And ruler over all his possessions.

22 To bind his chiefs at his pleasure, And his elders he maketh wise.

23 And Israel cometh in to Egypt, And Jacob hath sojourned in the land of Ham.

24 And He maketh His people very fruitful, And maketh it mightier than its adversaries.

25 He turned their heart to hate His people, To conspire against His servants.

26 He hath sent Moses His servant, Aaron whom He had fixed on.

27 They have set among them the matters of His signs, And wonders in the land of Ham.

28 He hath sent darkness, and it is dark, And they have not provoked His word.

29 He hath turned their waters to blood, And putteth to death their fish.

30 Teemed hath their land [with] frogs, In the inner chambers of their kings.

31 He hath said, and the beetle cometh, Lice into all their border.

32 He hath made their showers hail, A flaming fire [is] in their land.

33 And He smiteth their vine and their fig, And shivereth the trees of their border.

34 He hath said, and the locust cometh, And the cankerworm--innumerable,

35 And it consumeth every herb in their land, And it consumeth the fruit of their ground.

36 And He smiteth every first-born in their land, The first-fruit of all their strength,

37 And bringeth them out with silver and gold, And there is not in its tribes a feeble one.

38 Rejoiced hath Egypt in their going forth, For their fear had fallen upon them.

39 He hath spread a cloud for a covering, And fire to enlighten the night.

40 They have asked, and He bringeth quails, And [with] bread of heaven satisfieth them.

41 He hath opened a rock, and waters issue, They have gone on in dry places--a river.

42 For He hath remembered His holy word, With Abraham His servant,

43 And He bringeth forth His people with joy, With singing His chosen ones.

44 And He giveth to them the lands of nations, And the labour of peoples they possess,

45 That they may observe His statutes, And His laws may keep. Praise ye Jehovah!

Psalms 106

1 Praise ye Jah, give thanks to Jehovah, For good, for to the age, [is] His kindness.

2 Who doth utter the mighty acts of Jehovah? Soundeth all His praise?

3 O the happiness of those keeping judgment, Doing righteousness at all times.

4 Remember me, O Jehovah, With the favour of Thy people, Look after me in Thy salvation.

5 To look on the good of Thy chosen ones, To rejoice in the joy of Thy nation, To boast myself with Thine inheritance.

6 We have sinned with our fathers, We have done perversely, we have done wickedly.

7 Our fathers in Egypt, Have not considered wisely Thy wonders, They have not remembered The abundance of Thy kind acts, And provoke by the sea, at the sea of Suph.

8 And He saveth them for His name's sake, To make known His might,

9 And rebuketh the sea of Suph, and it is dried up, And causeth them to go Through depths as a wilderness.

10 And He saveth them from the hand Of him who is hating, And redeemeth them from the hand of the enemy.

11 And waters cover their adversaries, One of them hath not been left.

12 And they believe in His words, they sing His praise,

13 They have hasted--forgotten His works, They have not waited for His counsel.

14 And they lust greatly in a wilderness, And try God in a desert.

15 And He giveth to them their request, And sendeth leanness into their soul.

16 And they are envious of Moses in the camp, Of Aaron, Jehovah's holy one.

17 Earth openeth, and swalloweth up Dathan, And covereth over the company of Abiram.

18 And fire burneth among their company, A flame setteth on fire the wicked.

19 They make a calf in Horeb, And bow themselves to a molten image,

20 And change their Honour Into the form of an ox eating herbs.

21 They have forgotten God their saviour, The doer of great things in Egypt,

22 Of wonderful things in the land of Ham, Of fearful things by the sea of Suph.

23 And He saith to destroy them, Unless Moses, His chosen one, Had stood in the breach before Him, To turn back His wrath from destroying.

24 And they kick against the desirable land, They have not given credence to His word.

25 And they murmur in their tents, They have not hearkened to the voice of Jehovah.

26 And He lifteth up His hand to them, To cause them to fall in a wilderness,

27 And to cause their seed to fall among nations, And to scatter them through lands.

28 And they are coupled to Baal-Peor, And eat the sacrifices of the dead,

29 And they provoke to anger by their actions, And a plague breaketh forth upon them,

30 And Phinehas standeth, and executeth judgment, And the plague is restrained,

31 And it is reckoned to him to righteousness, To all generations--unto the age.

32 And they cause wrath by the waters of Meribah, And it is evil to Moses for their sakes,

33 For they have provoked his spirit, And he speaketh wrongfully with his lips.

34 They have not destroyed the peoples, As Jehovah had said to them,

35 And mix themselves among nations, and learn their works,

36 And serve their idols, And they are to them for a snare.

37 And they sacrifice their sons And their daughters to destroyers,

38 And they shed innocent blood--Blood of their sons and of their daughters, Whom they have sacrificed to idols of Canaan, And the land is profaned with blood.

39 And they are defiled with their works, And commit whoredom in their habitual doings.

40 And the anger of Jehovah Is kindled against His people, And He doth abominate His inheritance.

41 And giveth them into the hand of nations, And those hating them rule over them,

42 And their enemies oppress them, And they are humbled under their hand.

43 Many times He doth deliver them, And they rebel in their counsel, And they are brought low in their iniquity.

44 And He looketh on their distress When He heareth their cry,

45 And remembereth for them His covenant, And is comforted, According to the abundance of His kindness.

46 And He appointeth them for mercies Before all their captors.

47 Save us, O Jehovah our God, and gather us from the nations, To give thanks to Thy holy name, To glory in Thy praise.

48 Blessed [is] Jehovah, God of Israel, From the age even unto the age. And all the people said, `Amen, praise Jah!'

Psalms 107

1 `Give ye thanks to Jehovah, For good, for to the age [is] His kindness:'

2 Let the redeemed of Jehovah say, Whom He redeemed from the hand of an adversary.

3 And from the lands hath gathered them, From east and from west, From north, and from the sea.

4 They wandered in a wilderness, in a desert by the way, A city of habitation they have not found.

5 Hungry--yea--thirsty, Their soul in them becometh feeble,

6 And they cry unto Jehovah in their adversity, From their distress He delivereth them,

7 And causeth them to tread in a right way, To go unto a city of habitation.

8 They confess to Jehovah His kindness, And His wonders to the sons of men.

9 For He hath satisfied a longing soul, And a hungry soul hath filled [with] goodness.

10 Inhabitants of dark places and death-shade, Prisoners of affliction and of iron,

11 Because they changed the saying of God, And the counsel of the Most High despised.

12 And He humbleth with labour their heart, They have been feeble, and there is no helper.

13 And they cry unto Jehovah in their adversity, From their distresses He saveth them.

14 He bringeth them out from the dark place, And death-shade, And their bands He draweth away.

15 They confess to Jehovah His kindness, And His wonders to the sons of men.

16 For He hath broken doors of brass, And bars of iron He hath cut.

17 Fools, by means of their transgression, And by their iniquities, afflict themselves.

18 All food doth their soul abominate, And they come nigh unto the gates of death,

19 And cry unto Jehovah in their adversity, From their distresses He saveth them,

20 He sendeth His word and healeth them, And delivereth from their destructions.

21 They confess to Jehovah His kindness, And His wonders to the sons of men,

22 And they sacrifice sacrifices of thanksgiving, And recount His works with singing.

23 Those going down [to] the sea in ships, Doing business in many waters,

24 They have seen the works of Jehovah, And His wonders in the deep.

25 And He saith, and appointeth a tempest, And it lifteth up its billows,

26 They go up [to] the heavens, they go down [to] the depths, Their soul in evil is melted.

27 They reel to and fro, and move as a drunkard, And all their wisdom is swallowed up.

28 And they cry to Jehovah in their adversity, And from their distresses He bringeth them out.

29 He establisheth a whirlwind to a calm, And hushed are their billows.

30 And they rejoice because they are quiet, And He leadeth them to the haven of their desire.

31 They confess to Jehovah His kindness, And His wonders to the sons of men,

32 And they exalt Him in the assembly of the people, And in the seat of the elders praise Him.

33 He maketh rivers become a wilderness, And fountains of waters become dry land.

34 A fruitful land becometh a barren place, For the wickedness of its inhabitants.

35 He maketh a wilderness become a pool of water, And a dry land become fountains of waters.

36 And He causeth the hungry to dwell there, And they prepare a city of habitation.

37 And they sow fields, and plant vineyards, And they make fruits of increase.

38 And He blesseth them, and they multiply exceedingly, And their cattle He doth not diminish.

39 And they are diminished, and bow down, By restraint, evil, and sorrow.

40 He is pouring contempt upon nobles, And causeth them to wander in vacancy--no way.

41 And setteth on high the needy from affliction, And placeth families as a flock.

42 The upright do see and rejoice, And all perversity hath shut her mouth.

43 Who [is] wise, and observeth these? They understand the kind acts of Jehovah!

Psalms 109

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. O God of my praise, be not silent,

2 For the mouth of wickedness, and the mouth of deceit, Against me they have opened, They have spoken with me--A tongue of falsehood, and words of hatred!

3 They have compassed me about, And they fight me without cause.

4 For my love they oppose me, and I--prayer!

5 And they set against me evil for good, And hatred for my love.

6 Appoint Thou over him the wicked, And an adversary standeth at his right hand.

7 In his being judged, he goeth forth wicked, And his prayer is for sin.

8 His days are few, his oversight another taketh,

9 His sons are fatherless, and his wife a widow.

10 And wander continually do his sons, Yea, they have begged, And have sought out of their dry places.

11 An exactor layeth a snare for all that he hath, And strangers spoil his labour.

12 He hath none to extend kindness, Nor is there one showing favour to his orphans.

13 His posterity is for cutting off, In another generation is their name blotted out.

14 The iniquity of his fathers Is remembered unto Jehovah, And the sin of his mother is not blotted out.

15 They are before Jehovah continually, And He cutteth off from earth their memorial.

16 Because that he hath not remembered to do kindness, And pursueth the poor man and needy, And the smitten of heart--to slay,

17 And he loveth reviling, and it meeteth him, And he hath not delighted in blessing, And it is far from him.

18 And he putteth on reviling as his robe, And it cometh in as water into his midst, And as oil into his bones.

19 It is to him as apparel--he covereth himself, And for a continual girdle he girdeth it on.

20 This [is] the wage of mine accusers from Jehovah, And of those speaking evil against my soul.

21 And Thou, O Jehovah Lord, Deal with me for Thy name's sake, Because Thy kindness [is] good, deliver me.

22 For I [am] poor and needy, And my heart hath been pierced in my midst.

23 As a shadow when it is stretched out I have gone, I have been driven away as a locust.

24 My knees have been feeble from fasting, And my flesh hath failed of fatness.

25 And I--I have been a reproach to them, They see me, they shake their head.

26 Help me, O Jehovah my God, Save me, according to Thy kindness.

27 And they know that this [is] Thy hand, Thou, O Jehovah, Thou hast done it.

28 They revile, and Thou dost bless, They have risen, and are ashamed, And Thy servant doth rejoice.

29 Mine accusers put on blushing, and are covered, As an upper robe [is] their shame.

30 I thank Jehovah greatly with my mouth, And in the midst of many I praise Him,

31 For He standeth at the right hand of the needy, To save from those judging his soul.

Psalms 115

1 Not to us, O Jehovah, not to us, But to Thy name give honour, For Thy kindness, for Thy truth.

2 Why do the nations say, `Where, pray, [is] their God.

3 And our God [is] in the heavens, All that He hath pleased He hath done.

4 Their idols [are] silver and gold, work of man's hands,

5 A mouth they have, and they speak not, Eyes they have, and they see not,

6 Ears they have, and they hear not, A nose they have, and they smell not,

7 Their hands, but they handle not, Their feet, and they walk not;

8 Nor do they mutter through their throat, Like them are their makers, Every one who is trusting in them.

9 O Israel, trust in Jehovah, `Their help and their shield [is] He.'

10 O house of Aaron, trust in Jehovah, `Their help and their shield [is] He.'

11 Ye fearing Jehovah, trust in Jehovah, `Their help and their shield [is] He.'

12 Jehovah hath remembered us, He blesseth, He blesseth the house of Israel, He blesseth the house of Aaron,

13 He blesseth those fearing Jehovah, The small with the great.

14 Jehovah addeth to you, to you, and to your sons.

15 Blessed [are] ye of Jehovah, maker of heaven and earth,

16 The heavens--the heavens [are] Jehovah's, And the earth He hath given to sons of men,

17 The dead praise not Jah, Nor any going down to silence.

18 And we, we bless Jah, From henceforth, and unto the age. Praise ye Jah!

Psalms 116

1 I have loved, because Jehovah heareth My voice, my supplication,

2 Because He hath inclined His ear to me, And during my days I call.

3 Compassed me have cords of death, And straits of Sheol have found me, Distress and sorrow I find.

4 And in the name of Jehovah I call: I pray Thee, O Jehovah, deliver my soul,

5 Gracious [is] Jehovah, and righteous, Yea, our God [is] merciful,

6 A preserver of the simple [is] Jehovah, I was low, and to me He giveth salvation.

7 Turn back, O my soul, to thy rest, For Jehovah hath conferred benefits on thee.

8 For Thou hast delivered my soul from death, My eyes from tears, my feet from overthrowing.

9 I walk habitually before Jehovah In the lands of the living.

10 I have believed, for I speak, I--I have been afflicted greatly.

11 I said in my haste, `Every man [is] a liar.'

12 What do I return to Jehovah? All His benefits [are] upon me.

13 The cup of salvation I lift up, And in the name of Jehovah I call.

14 My vows to Jehovah let me complete, I pray you, before all His people.

15 Precious in the eyes of Jehovah [is] the death for His saints.

16 Cause [it] to come, O Jehovah, for I [am] Thy servant. I [am] Thy servant, son of Thy handmaid, Thou hast opened my bonds.

17 To Thee I sacrifice a sacrifice of thanks, And in the name of Jehovah I call.

18 My vows to Jehovah let me complete, I pray you, before all His people,

19 In the courts of the house of Jehovah, In thy midst, O Jerusalem, praise ye Jah!

Psalms 118

1 Give ye thanks to Jehovah, For good, for to the age [is] His kindness.

2 I pray you, let Israel say, That, to the age [is] His kindness.

3 I pray you, let the house of Aaron say, That, to the age [is] His kindness.

4 I pray you, let those fearing Jehovah say, That, to the age [is] His kindness.

5 From the straitness I called Jah, Jah answered me in a broad place.

6 Jehovah [is] for me, I do not fear what man doth to me.

7 Jehovah [is] for me among my helpers, And I--I look on those hating me.

8 Better to take refuge in Jehovah than to trust in man,

9 Better to take refuge in Jehovah, Than to trust in princes.

10 All nations have compassed me about, In the name of Jehovah I surely cut them off.

11 They have compassed me about, Yea, they have compassed me about, In the name of Jehovah I surely cut them off.

12 They compassed me about as bees, They have been extinguished as a fire of thorns, In the name of Jehovah I surely cut them off.

13 Thou hast sorely thrust me to fall, And Jehovah hath helped me.

14 My strength and song [is] Jah, And He is to me for salvation.

15 A voice of singing and salvation, [Is] in the tents of the righteous, The right hand of Jehovah is doing valiantly.

16 The right hand of Jehovah is exalted, The right hand of Jehovah is doing valiantly.

17 I do not die, but live, And recount the works of Jah,

18 Jah hath sorely chastened me, And to death hath not given me up.

19 Open ye to me gates of righteousness, I enter into them--I thank Jah.

20 This [is] the gate to Jehovah, The righteous enter into it.

21 I thank Thee, for Thou hast answered me, And art to me for salvation.

22 A stone the builders refused Hath become head of a corner.

23 From Jehovah hath this been, It [is] wonderful in our eyes,

24 This [is] the day Jehovah hath made, We rejoice and are glad in it.

25 I beseech Thee, O Jehovah, save, I pray Thee, I beseech Thee, O Jehovah, prosper, I pray Thee.

26 Blessed [is] he who is coming In the name of Jehovah, We blessed you from the house of Jehovah,

27 God [is] Jehovah, and He giveth to us light, Direct ye the festal-sacrifice with cords, Unto the horns of the altar.

28 My God Thou [art], and I confess Thee, My God, I exalt Thee.

29 Give ye thanks to Jehovah, For good, for to the age, [is] His kindness!

Psalms 119

1 [Aleph.] O the happiness of those perfect in the way, They are walking in the law of Jehovah,

2 O the happiness of those keeping His testimonies, With the whole heart they seek Him.

3 Yea, they have not done iniquity, In His ways they have walked.

4 Thou hast commanded us Thy precepts to keep diligently,

5 O that my ways were prepared to keep Thy statutes,

6 Then I am not ashamed In my looking unto all Thy commands.

7 I confess Thee with uprightness of heart, In my learning the judgments of Thy righteousness.

8 Thy statutes I keep, leave me not utterly!

9 [Beth.] With what doth a young man purify his path? To observe--according to Thy word.

10 With all my heart I have sought Thee, Let me not err from Thy commands.

11 In my heart I have hid Thy saying, That I sin not before Thee.

12 Blessed [art] Thou, O Jehovah, teach me Thy statutes.

13 With my lips I have recounted All the judgments of Thy mouth.

14 In the way of Thy testimonies I have joyed, As over all wealth.

15 In Thy precepts I meditate, And I behold attentively Thy paths.

16 In Thy statutes I delight myself, I do not forget Thy word.

17 [Gimel.] Confer benefits on Thy servant, I live, and I keep Thy word.

18 Uncover mine eyes, and I behold wonders out of Thy law.

19 A sojourner I [am] on earth, Hide not from me Thy commands.

20 Broken hath my soul for desire Unto Thy judgments at all times.

21 Thou hast rebuked the cursed proud, Who are erring from Thy commands.

22 Remove from me reproach and contempt, For Thy testimonies I have kept.

23 Princes also sat--against me they spoke, Thy servant doth meditate in Thy statutes,

24 Thy testimonies also [are] my delight, The men of my counsel!

25 [Daleth.] Cleaved to the dust hath my soul, Quicken me according to Thy word.

26 My ways I have recounted, And Thou answerest me, teach me Thy statutes,

27 The way of Thy precepts cause me to understand, And I meditate in Thy wonders.

28 My soul hath dropped from affliction, Establish me according to Thy word.

29 The way of falsehood turn aside from me And with Thy law favour me.

30 The way of faithfulness I have chosen, Thy judgments I have compared,

31 I have adhered to Thy testimonies, O Jehovah, put me not to shame.

32 The way of Thy commands I run, For Thou dost enlarge my heart!

33 [He.] Show me, O Jehovah, the way of Thy statutes, And I keep it--[to] the end.

34 Cause me to understand, and I keep Thy law, And observe it with the whole heart.

35 Cause me to tread in the path of Thy commands, For in it I have delighted.

36 Incline my heart unto Thy testimonies, And not unto dishonest gain.

37 Remove mine eyes from seeing vanity, In Thy way quicken Thou me.

38 Establish to Thy servant Thy saying, That [is] concerning Thy fear.

39 Remove my reproach that I have feared, For Thy judgments [are] good.

40 Lo, I have longed for Thy precepts, In Thy righteousness quicken Thou me,

41 [Waw.] And meet me doth Thy kindness, O Jehovah, Thy salvation according to Thy saying.

42 And I answer him who is reproaching me a word, For I have trusted in Thy word.

43 And Thou takest not utterly away From my mouth the word of truth, Because for Thy judgment I have hoped.

44 And I keep Thy law continually, To the age and for ever.

45 And I walk habitually in a broad place, For Thy precepts I have sought.

46 And I speak of Thy testimonies before kings, And I am not ashamed.

47 And I delight myself in Thy commands, That I have loved,

48 And I lift up my hands unto Thy commands, That I have loved, And I do meditate on Thy statutes!

49 [Zain.] Remember the word to Thy servant, On which Thou hast caused me to hope.

50 This [is] my comfort in mine affliction, That Thy saying hath quickened me.

51 The proud have utterly scorned me, From Thy law I have not turned aside.

52 I remembered Thy judgments of old, O Jehovah, And I comfort myself.

53 Horror hath seized me, Because of the wicked forsaking Thy law.

54 Songs have been to me Thy statutes, In the house of my sojournings.

55 I have remembered in the night Thy name, O Jehovah, And I do keep Thy law.

56 This hath been to me, That Thy precepts I have kept!

57 [Cheth.] My portion [is] Jehovah; I have said--to keep Thy words,

58 I appeased Thy face with the whole heart, Favour me according to Thy saying.

59 I have reckoned my ways, And turn back my feet unto Thy testimonies.

60 I have made haste, And delayed not, to keep Thy commands.

61 Cords of the wicked have surrounded me, Thy law I have not forgotten.

62 At midnight I rise to give thanks to Thee, For the judgments of Thy righteousness.

63 A companion I [am] to all who fear Thee, And to those keeping Thy precepts.

64 Of Thy kindness, O Jehovah, the earth is full, Thy statutes teach Thou me!

65 [Teth.] Good Thou didst with Thy servant, O Jehovah, According to Thy word.

66 The goodness of reason and knowledge teach me, For in Thy commands I have believed.

67 Before I am afflicted, I--I am erring, And now Thy saying I have kept.

68 Good Thou [art], and doing good, Teach me Thy statutes.

69 Forged against me falsehood have the proud, I with the whole heart keep Thy precepts.

70 Insensate as fat hath been their heart, I--in Thy law I have delighted.

71 Good for me that I have been afflicted, That I might learn Thy statutes.

72 Better to me [is] the law of Thy mouth Than thousands of gold and silver!

73 [Yod.] Thy hands made me and establish me, Cause me to understand, and I learn Thy commands.

74 Those fearing Thee see me and rejoice, Because for Thy word I have hoped.

75 I have known, O Jehovah, That righteous [are] Thy judgments, And [in] faithfulness Thou hast afflicted me.

76 Let, I pray Thee, Thy kindness be to comfort me, According to Thy saying to Thy servant.

77 Meet me do Thy mercies, and I live, For Thy law [is] my delight.

78 Ashamed are the proud, For [with] falsehood they dealt perversely with me. I meditate in Thy precepts.

79 Those fearing Thee turn back to me, And those knowing Thy testimonies.

80 My heart is perfect in Thy statutes, So that I am not ashamed.

81 [Kaph.] Consumed for Thy salvation hath been my soul, For Thy word I have hoped.

82 Consumed have been mine eyes for Thy word, Saying, `When doth it comfort me?'

83 For I have been as a bottle in smoke, Thy statutes I have not forgotten.

84 How many [are] the days of Thy servant? When dost Thou execute Against my pursuers judgment?

85 The proud have digged for me pits, That [are] not according to Thy law.

86 All Thy commands [are] faithfulness, [With] falsehood they have pursued me, Help Thou me.

87 Almost consumed me on earth have they, And I--I have not forsaken Thy precepts.

88 According to Thy kindness quicken Thou me, And I keep the testimony of Thy mouth!

89 [Lamed.] To the age, O Jehovah, Thy word is set up in the heavens.

90 To all generations Thy faithfulness, Thou didst establish earth, and it standeth.

91 According to Thine ordinances They have stood this day, for the whole [are] Thy servants.

92 Unless Thy law [were] my delights, Then had I perished in mine affliction.

93 To the age I forget not Thy precepts, For by them Thou hast quickened me.

94 I [am] Thine, save Thou me, For Thy precepts I have sought.

95 Thy wicked waited for me to destroy me, Thy testimonies I understand.

96 Of all perfection I have seen an end, Broad [is] Thy command--exceedingly!

97 [Mem.] O how I have loved Thy law! All the day it [is] my meditation.

98 Than mine enemies Thy command maketh me wiser, For it [is] before me to the age.

99 Above all my teachers I have acted wisely. For Thy testimonies [are] my meditation.

100 Above elders I understand more, For Thy precepts I have kept.

101 From every evil path I restrained my feet, So that I keep Thy word.

102 From Thy judgments I turned not aside, For Thou--Thou hast directed me.

103 How sweet to my palate hath been Thy saying, Above honey to my mouth.

104 From Thy precepts I have understanding, Therefore I have hated every false path!

105 [Nun.] A lamp to my foot [is] Thy word, And a light to my path.

106 I have sworn, and I confirm [it], To keep the judgments of Thy righteousness.

107 I have been afflicted very much, O Jehovah, quicken me, according to Thy word.

108 Free-will-offerings of my mouth, Accept, I pray Thee, O Jehovah, And Thy judgments teach Thou me.

109 My soul [is] in my hand continually, And Thy law I have not forgotten.

110 The wicked have laid a snare for me, And from thy precepts I wandered not.

111 I have inherited Thy testimonies to the age, For the joy of my heart [are] they.

112 I have inclined my heart To do Thy statutes, to the age--[to] the end!

113 [Samech.] Doubting ones I have hated, And Thy law I have loved.

114 My hiding place and my shield [art] Thou, For Thy word I have hoped.

115 Turn aside from me, ye evil-doers, And I keep the commands of my God.

116 Sustain me according to Thy saying, And I live, and Thou puttest me not to shame Because of my hope.

117 Support Thou me, and I am saved, And I look on Thy statutes continually.

118 Thou hast trodden down All going astray from Thy statutes, For falsehood [is] their deceit.

119 Dross! Thou hast caused to cease All the wicked of the earth; Therefore I have loved Thy testimonies.

120 Trembled from Thy fear hath my flesh, And from Thy judgments I have been afraid!

121 [Ain.] I have done judgment and righteousness, Leave me not to mine oppressors.

122 Make sure Thy servant for good, Let not the proud oppress me.

123 Mine eyes have been consumed for Thy salvation. And for the saying of Thy righteousness.

124 Do with Thy servant according to Thy kindness. And Thy statutes teach Thou me.

125 Thy servant [am] I--cause me to understand, And I know Thy testimonies.

126 Time for Jehovah to work! they have made void Thy law.

127 Therefore I have loved Thy commands Above gold--even fine gold.

128 Therefore all my appointments I have declared wholly right, Every path of falsehood I have hated!

129 [Pe.] Wonderful [are] Thy testimonies, Therefore hath my soul kept them.

130 The opening of Thy words enlighteneth, Instructing the simple.

131 My mouth I have opened, yea, I pant, For, for Thy commands I have longed.

132 Look unto me, and favour me, As customary to those loving Thy name.

133 My steps establish by Thy saying, And any iniquity doth not rule over me.

134 Ransom me from the oppression of man, And I observe Thy precepts,

135 Thy face cause to shine on Thy servant, And teach me Thy statutes.

136 Rivulets of waters have come down mine eyes, Because they have not kept Thy law!

137 [Tzade.] Righteous [art] Thou, O Jehovah, And upright [are] Thy judgments.

138 Thou hast appointed Thy testimonies, Righteous and exceeding faithful,

139 Cut me off hath my zeal, For mine adversaries forgot Thy words.

140 Tried [is] thy saying exceedingly, And Thy servant hath loved it.

141 Small I [am], and despised, Thy precepts I have not forgotten.

142 Thy righteousness [is] righteousness to the age, And Thy law [is] truth.

143 Adversity and distress have found me, Thy commands [are] my delights.

144 The righteousness of Thy testimonies [is] to Cause me to understand, and I live!

145 [Koph.] I have called with the whole heart, Answer me, O Jehovah, Thy statutes I keep,

146 I have called Thee, save Thou me, And I do keep Thy testimonies.

147 I have gone forward in the dawn, and I cry, For Thy word I have hoped.

148 Mine eyes have gone before the watches, To meditate in Thy saying.

149 My voice hear, according to Thy kindness, Jehovah, according to Thy judgment quicken me.

150 Near have been my wicked pursuers, From Thy law they have been far off.

151 Near [art] Thou, O Jehovah, And all Thy commands [are] truth.

152 Of old I have known Thy testimonies, That to the age Thou hast founded them!

153 [Resh.] See my affliction, and deliver Thou me, For Thy law I have not forgotten.

154 Plead my plea, and redeem me, According to Thy saying quicken me.

155 Far from the wicked [is] salvation, For Thy statutes they have not sought.

156 Thy mercies [are] many, O Jehovah, According to Thy judgments quicken me.

157 Many [are] my pursuers, and adversaries, From Thy testimonies I have not turned aside.

158 I have seen treacherous ones, And grieve myself, Because Thy saying they have not kept.

159 See, for thy precepts I have loved, Jehovah, According to Thy kindness quicken me.

160 The sum of Thy word [is] truth, And to the age [is] every judgment of Thy righteousness!

161 [Shin.] Princes have pursued me without cause, And because of Thy words was my heart afraid.

162 I do rejoice concerning Thy saying, As one finding abundant spoil.

163 Falsehood I have hated, yea I abominate [it], Thy law I have loved.

164 Seven [times] in a day I have praised Thee, Because of the judgments of Thy righteousness.

165 Abundant peace have those loving Thy law, And they have no stumbling-block.

166 I have waited for Thy salvation, O Jehovah, And Thy commands I have done.

167 Kept hath my soul Thy testimonies, And I do love them exceedingly.

168 I have kept Thy precepts and Thy testimonies, For all my ways are before Thee!

169 [Taw.] My loud cry cometh near before Thee, O Jehovah; According to Thy word cause me to understand.

170 My supplication cometh in before Thee, According to Thy saying deliver Thou me.

171 My lips do utter praise, For Thou dost teach me Thy statutes.

172 My tongue doth sing of Thy saying, For all Thy commands [are] righteous.

173 Thy hand is for a help to me, For Thy commands I have chosen.

174 I have longed for Thy salvation, O Jehovah, And Thy law [is] my delight.

175 My soul liveth, and it doth praise Thee, And Thy judgments do help me.

176 I wandered as a lost sheep, seek Thy servant, For Thy precepts I have not forgotten!